<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0013">
   <teiHeader type="w">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Journal of a tour from Clapton through North Wales to Ireland
               <date>1802</date></title>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Edited with an introduction by Elizabeth Edwards</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                  <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                  <idno>MS 22190B</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <ab>
                            <locus/>
                        </ab>
               </msContents>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <!-- delete as appropriate -->
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <fw>f. iir</fw>
            <p>The following journal of a tour through <placeName ref="pl1221">North
                  Wales</placeName> taken in the Spring of 1802 was written by my [page torn]
                  <persName ref="pe2030">Mary Anne</persName>, &amp; was intended for the amusement
               of her sister Elinor.<note type="editorial">Possibly a variant of ‘Eliza’, given as
                  Eade’s sister’s name in the following paragraph.</note> Alas! How little we can
               count upon happiness in this world! How rich in comfort was I at the period when
               these pages were written! How different is my present condition. Death! Thou hast
               made a void, thou hast inflicted a wound, which neither time can fill, nor physician
               heal. Of the short period which it pleased God to <sic>alot</sic> for my union in
               this world with one of the most perfect of his creatures, I reflect upon no portion
               with more satisfaction, than the few weeks which occupy this tour. I was happy in
               being her instant companion, in the opportunity which it afforded of observing in her
               new traits of character, in discovering fresh beauties of mind, &amp; in the
               certainty of the pleasure which she derived from it – It now appears </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. iiv</fw>
            <p>like a pleasing vision, impress’d indeed strongly upon the imagination, but without
               reality – – – This Book is in right the property of my sister-in-law <persName ref="pe2062">Eliza Vaux</persName>, but a conversation which occur’d relative to
               it a few evenings before the melancholy decease of my beloved Wife, added to the
               particular interest I feel in it, from having participated <sic>the pleasures</sic>
               it recites, had so endear’d it to me, that she will I am sure pardon me that I do not
                  <sic>yeild</sic> it to her – I beg that after my death it may be deliver’d to her
               – </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="underline">March 1803</hi>
               <hi rend="underline">
                        <persName ref="pe2063">William Eade</persName>
                    </hi>
            </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 1r</fw>
            <p>Journal of our Excursion to <placeName ref="pl1673">Dublin</placeName> 1802 </p>
            <p>
                    <hi rend="superscript">Set out from <placeName ref="pl2863">Clapton</placeName> 14
                  May</hi>
                </p>
            <p>
                    <hi rend="superscript">returned – 19 June</hi>
                </p>
            <p>In addressing this following little journal of our intended tour my dearest <persName ref="pe2062">Eliza</persName>, to you, I shall but follow your example, in the
               very entertaining one, you dedicated to me when you visited <placeName ref="pl1827">Swansea</placeName>.<note type="editorial">Eliza Vaux’s tour of Wales remains
                  untraced, but mention of it here offers evidence of the manuscript tour format as
                  part of a system of exchange within small coteries.</note> I despair indeed of
               rendering mine as delightful as I found yours to be, yet it will now fall to my lot
               to explore the other division of that beautiful principality with which you were so
               much charmed. I trust you will find some pleasure in contrasting my account of the
               wild grandeur of its northern mountains with the more softened graces of its southern
               beauties. In writing this account </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 1v</fw>
            <p>the idea of my beloved <persName ref="pe2062">Eliza</persName> will give spirit to my
               employment, &amp; I shall not merely excuse it, as a task for which the reward must
               be future, when by its aid I shall retrace those lovely scenes which else would fade
               from my remembrance, but as one from which I shall receiv<del>ed</del> immediate
               gratification &amp; as I relate every effect of sublimity &amp; describe every touch
               of beauty, the idea of affording amusement &amp; pleasure to my darling sister, will
               I hope give as much animation to my language as it will delight to my heart: &amp; if
               you, my inspiring goddess fail to answer my invocation, the blame of my defects must
               lay upon yourself; the powerless muse, &amp; not the suppliant </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 2r</fw>
            <p>writer must be censured – </p>
            <p>Alas! my dear <persName ref="pe2062">Eliza</persName> &amp; is it thus then, is it
               merely in imagination that you can <hi rend="superscript">now</hi> be my companion in
               that loved time for ever fled when our hours of bliss &amp; mornings of sorrow were
               mutually enjoyed or mutually soothed – and is it I who lament, who was the cause of
               our <sic>seperation</sic> – how strangely are our feelings mixt since I can at the
               same time sorrow at our <sic>seperation</sic>, &amp; yet rejoice in its cause; at
               least my <persName ref="pe2062">Eliza</persName> believe that the memory of our happy
               early hours will never be effaced from my recollection, nor the strong tie of
               affection which they formed be torn from my heart. But I forget it was not to tell
               you how I love you that I took up my </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 2v</fw>
            <p>pen; it was to relate that of which you are ignorant, not to remind you of what you
               know: I quit therefore this seducing theme &amp; begin a less attractive one my
               journal.</p>
            <p> This morning then friday the 14 of May, with heavy hearts we quitted <placeName ref="pl2863">Clapton</placeName> at a quarter past nine. The expected pleasures of
               our journey so often anticipated with delight, were at this morning anticipated no
               more, for all idea of future gratification was lost in the acuter feelings of regret
               with which both <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> &amp; myself bade a long
               farewell to our darling <persName ref="pe2064">boy</persName> – But we had not much
               time for the indulgence of melancholy, [illegible] a si<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>gular adventure, which promised but a disastrous commencement to our
               journey</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 3r</fw>
            <p>forcibly diverted our thoughts. We had passed the <placeName ref="pl2864">Stamford
                  Hill turnpike</placeName> &amp; had proceeded some way down the first lane leading
               to <placeName ref="pl2865">Hornsey</placeName> where we perceived that we were not
               followed by Benjamin; we had left him paying the toll, &amp; therefore supposing he
               was detained at the gate we waited quietly enough some time for his appearance – but
               he did not appear. We now remembered that our <sic>rout</sic> had not been
               particularly mentioned to him, &amp; with some alarm hastened back to the high road,
               here as we did not see him we became conscious he must have pursued it, &amp; hoping
               he would return on finding he did not overtake us we rode slowly on to meet him; this
               however</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 3v</fw>
            <p>proved a fruitless hope, &amp; on hearing he had been seen two miles further on
               galloping full speed to <placeName ref="pl2866">Edmonton</placeName>, we gave up all
               idea of meeting him again for this day, even if we had the good fortune to see him
               before we reached <placeName ref="pl1018">Holyhead</placeName>. We returned therefore
               to the turnpike &amp; left our <sic>rout</sic> with the man there, &amp; then again
               pursued our way down the lane sometimes laughing at our own folly in omitting to give
               him a direction &amp; at others deploring its provoking consequences – Fortunately
               however his spruce appearance at a distance made the laugh predominant; for not being
               able to learn any thing of us he had <sic>turnd</sic> down one of the other lanes to
               extend his search of us as now in</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 4r</fw>
            <p>despair returning in hopes of information to the turnpike. Thus again a united party
               we proceeded with reviving spirits, but shivering limbs, for the morning which at
               first was cold, &amp; only cheered by an uncertain sun, now became more &amp; more
               gloomy; &amp; soon after we had ascended <sic>
                        <placeName ref="pl2867">Muzzle-hill</placeName>
                    </sic> our evil genius again <sic>assaild</sic> us in
               form of a fall of snow: </p>
            <p>“And we poor souls! with small delight”</p>
            <p>“Beheld the strange unusual sight.” </p>
            <note type="editorial"> The source of this quotation remains unclear, however these
               lines may be slightly misquoted from a contemporary riddle ('And she, poor soul, with
               small delight / Beheld the strange unusual sight'). See <hi rend="italic">The
                  Masquerade. A Collection of New Enigmas, Logogriphs, Charades, Rebusses, Queries
                  and Transpositions</hi> (Southampton and London: T. Baker, G. &amp; T. Wilkie and
               J. Bell, 1797), p. 60.</note>
            <p>most strange indeed and most unusual in the middle of the month of May. Happily we
               were resolved to be pleased, &amp; this resolution has in itself half the sources of
               pleasure, &amp; therefore by its aid we contrived to find a good share of it in our
               ride thro <placeName ref="pl2868">Highgate</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl2869">Finchly</placeName> to </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 4v</fw>
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="pl2870">Watford</placeName>, in spite of the snow which fell at
               intervals all the morning. A part of this ride brought our <placeName ref="pl2871">Cambridge</placeName> expedition &amp; my dear <persName ref="pe2062">Eliza</persName> to my mind: the scene seemed <hi rend="superscript">to</hi>
               mourn your absence with me, for nothing could form a much stronger contrast with its
               former appearance than what it now wore. In vain I sought for <hi rend="superscript">the</hi> glowing radiance, which a cloudless sky had cast around when we last
               visited it, in vain I wished for one cheering ray, of that bright sun, that then cast
               his hottest beams upon us; the pitiless storms, wrapt half the beauties of the
               country in obscurity; &amp; the “bitter piercing air”<note type="editorial">Possibly
                  a reference to John Aikin, ‘A Winter’s Piece’; see <hi rend="italic">Poems, by J.
                     Aikin</hi> (London: J. Johnson, 1791), p. 21. </note> numbed our every feeling;
               &amp; nothing but our before mention’d resolution could have brought us</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 5r</fw>
            <p>in good spirits to <placeName ref="pl2870">Watford</placeName> where we waited. The
               day somewhat improved on us when we left this place, from whence to [?Hunton] Bridge
               the country continues to be very pretty, as you pass <placeName ref="pl2872">Cashiobury</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl2873">Grove Parks</placeName> the
               two beautiful seats of the Earls of <persName ref="pe2065">Essex</persName> &amp;
                  <persName ref="pe2066">Clarendon</persName>, opposite the latter is Russel Farm, a
               sweet place belonging to Lady Keppel<note type="editorial">Possibly a reference to
                  Anne Miller (d. 1824), widow of George Keppel, 3rd Earl of Albemarle
                  (1724-72).</note> – From <placeName ref="pl2875">Hunton Bridge</placeName> thro’
                  <placeName ref="pl2874">King’s Langley</placeName> to <sic>
                        <placeName ref="pl2876">Berk Hempstead</placeName>
                    </sic> the ride is flat and uninteresting, running
               along the Grand Junction <sic>channell</sic>, which carries all the works of industry
               from Manchester to <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>. At <placeName ref="pl2876">Berk Hampstead</placeName> ended our first day’s journey, for there
               we took a late dinner &amp; slept; the place was not very pretty in itself, but the
               country around it has all the peculiar features of the Hertfordshire</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 5v</fw>
            <p>scenery, &amp; of course therefore is very pretty; between dinner &amp; tea we took a
               walk down a <sic>shaddy</sic> lane, which as the evening was now clear, &amp; the
               setting sun, gave us a “farewell sweet,” ere he sunk to rest; was sufficiently
               inviting: from thence we got into some cornfields, &amp; at the expence of a little
               trespass found our way back to our Inn <placeName ref="pl2879">The King’s
                  Arms</placeName>. At this Inn which is small, but tolerably clean &amp;
               comfortable, we were shewn the method of plaiting the split straw, which is, a
               simple, &amp; very profitable manufacture.</p>
            <p>Saturday the 15. We were awoke this morning by the sunbeams peeping into our room
               &amp; inviting us to pursue our plan of taking an early stage by the cheering promise
               of their exhilarating company; we obeyed the summons, &amp; were well repaid by</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 6r</fw>
            <p>
                    <hi rend="superscript">a</hi> sweet ride, as far as <placeName ref="pl2877">Aston
                  Clinton</placeName>; we went as far indeed to <placeName ref="pl2878">Aylesbury</placeName> to breakfast but the beauty of the ride did not extend
               beyond this village – till within about two miles of it, the road is delightful,
               &amp; adorned with several sweet parks of which <placeName ref="pl2880">Tring
                  Park</placeName> the seat of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
               <persName ref="pe2067">Drummond Smith</persName> appears to most advantage from the
               road. About the above mentioned distance from <placeName ref="pl2877">Aston
                  Clinton</placeName> the face of the country entirely changed; the sweet enclosures
               of Hertfordshire, its gently swelling hills, its beautiful hedges, its luxuriant
               cultivation &amp; the frequent tho’ small woods that every where give variety as to
               its scenes; entirely disappeared; &amp; were succeeded by open &amp; extensive
               prospects, which could boast of little richness or interest; this village in itself
               is extremely pretty</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 6v</fw>
            <p>&amp; the situation &amp; appearance of the Inn is so very inviting we regretted that
               we had not slept there; it was at this village we entered Buckinghamshire. We
               breakfasted at <placeName ref="pl2883">the George</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl2878">Aylesbury</placeName>, which appeared to be a very good Inn. It was
               market day which gave the town a cheerful animation, which lent it some attraction,
               of which at other times it does not seem to possess much. The market seemed to be
               chiefly a poultry one of which we saw great quantities, particularly ducks for which
               we were told they were famous; they are very successful in rearing the early broods,
               &amp; as the <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> markets are principally
               supplied with them from this <hi rend="superscript">place</hi>, the price was
               extravagant.</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 7r</fw>
            <p>Nothing of consequence occurred between <placeName ref="pl2878">Aylesbury</placeName>
               and <placeName ref="pl2882">Buckingham</placeName> the country was open &amp;
                  <sic>great part</sic> of it was heath, tho’ in many places they were inclosing for
               arable land; &amp; planting it with hedges, which in this part of the country <add place="above">are scarce</add>, the division of property being <sic>merly</sic>
               straight lines of grass, as in the <placeName ref="">isle of Thanet</placeName>. On
               entering the <placeName ref="pl2884">Cobham arms</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl2882">Buckingham</placeName> we ordered dinner &amp; a post chaise, in
               which while the former was preparing we went to see <placeName ref="pl2821">Stowe</placeName>, the seat of the <persName ref="pe0784">Marquis of
                  Buckingham</persName>; we were however obliged to content ourselves with seeing
               the gardens to-day, as we had not much time &amp; <add place="above">as</add> the
                  weather<del>ed</del> seemed fair <del>&amp;</del> we doubted if we delayed walking
               over them now, what the morrow </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 7v</fw>
            <p>would bring forth. These justly celebrated Gardens pleased me extremely, &amp; I was
               astonished how human art could produce so many beauties: to nature they were indebted
               for nothing but space, &amp; one large level was formerly the sum of their
               attractions. But <persName ref="">Capability Brown</persName> appeared &amp; at his
               word, the gentle eminences were bid to swell; the waters were called forth from their
               hidden caverns &amp; forced to flow in one beautiful expanse; while all the fair
               variety of vegetation “from the lofty cedar, to the lowliest herb were shown their
               proper station &amp; there taught to flourish. I doubt not my dear <persName ref="pe2062">Eliza</persName> that there are many gardens more beautiful than
               those of <placeName ref="pl2821">Stowe</placeName>
                </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 8r</fw>
            <p>but I think the number must be small <sic>were</sic> nature has done so little, &amp;
               art so much. Throughout the whole grounds numerous edifices are erected in situations
                  <sic>were</sic> their effect will be most <sic>stricking</sic>; those which
               pleased me most were the <placeName ref="pl2885">Gothic Temple of the
                  Pillar</placeName> erected to the memory of <persName ref="pe2077">L<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>: Cobham</persName> both which we ascended the latter
               is 115 feet high; &amp; the view from the top is well worth seeing, as it commands
               the whole of the gardens. A heavy shower of rain, which unexpectedly overtook us,
               obliged us to hasten our return to the <del>
                        <placeName ref="pl2883">George</placeName>
                    </del>
               <add place="above">
                        <placeName ref="pl2884">Cobham Arms</placeName>
                    </add> (an
               excellent Inn) <sic>were</sic> we quietly remained for the rest of the day.
                  <placeName ref="">Buckingham</placeName> appears to be a clean pleasant town,
               without any thing very <sic>stricking</sic>; the situation </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 8v</fw>
            <p>of the church is singular it is built on a hill in the midst of the town, the summit
               of which is but a little higher than the tops of the houses that nearly encircle it;
               this summit forms a square church-yard, part of which is a public promenade, where we
               &amp; the rest of the congregation walked the next morning before service began: thus
               passed our third wedding-day!</p>
            <p>Sunday the 16. We went as soon as we had breakfasted to the Church, were [sic] we
               heard the prayers very badly read, &amp; then listened to a sermon on the Conversion
               of S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Paul, as different my dear <persName ref="pe2062">Eliza</persName> to the one we were once so very delighted with, as you can well
               imagine. After it was concluded we again went to <placeName ref="pl2821">Stowe</placeName> to see the house: It is a </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 9r</fw>
            <p>most noble structure, &amp; conveys an idea of magnificence worthy of the rank of its
               owner; I was extremely struck with it yesterday when I had merely seen the external
               of the building, &amp; I was glad to find the interior grandeur did not disgrace it:
               the entrance into a most elegant saloon is <sic>strickingly</sic> beautiful, &amp;
               pleased me beyond any thing of the kind I had ever seen: the roof which is
               exquisitely carved is supported by beautiful [?composition] pillars, in the recesses
               between which are statues of the Apollo, <sic>Antinuos</sic>, Venus &amp;c: which
               unfortunately are now partly mutilated, &amp; in others are elegant braziers, by
               which the saloon is heated.<note type="editorial">For modern photographs of the
                  saloon at Stowe, see <ref type="http" target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Saloon_dome,_2_of_2_-_Stowe_House_-_Buckinghamshire,_England_-_DSC07186.jpg">here</ref> and <ref type="http" target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Saloon_-_Stowe_House_-_Buckinghamshire,_England_-_DSC07180.jpg">here</ref>
                    </note> None of the other apartments pleased me as much as this, yet
               there are many of them</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 9v</fw>
            <p>truly splendid particularly the music room<note type="editorial">For a modern
                  photograph of the music room at Stowe, see <ref type="http" target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Music_Room_-_Stowe_House_-_Buckinghamshire,_England_-_DSC07146.jpg ">here</ref>
                    </note> which is painted with great taste &amp; enriched with a
               great deal of fine <sic>guilding</sic>: the room called the white apartment from the
               furniture which is white <sic>Sattin</sic>, is entirely hung with lady Buckingham’s
               paintings; &amp; many of them are delightfully executed; in <del>the</del> one of the
                  drawing<del>s</del>
               <add place="above">rooms</add> also were some extremely fine pictures by the ancient
               masters, some of which I admired extremely. It is impossible to particularize all the
               apartments, those hung with tapestry were very rich, &amp; the state bed-room also is
               very splendid, &amp; has in it two small light closets one hung with some charming
               cabinet pictures, &amp; the other decorated with Chinese</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 10r</fw>
            <p>rareties of all sorts, all these apartments including the library form one grand
               suite, &amp; the effect when all the doors are thrown open is uncommonly magnificent,
               extending the whole length of the building which is 170 feet. Unfortunately we saw it
               to its great disadvantage as the house is undergoing some alterations, &amp; the
               furniture was all [?down]. After all that I have said of <placeName ref="pl2821">Stowe</placeName>, you will be surprized to hear that it is a place I never wish
               to see again, the labour of decoration &amp; the wish to astonish, seems every where
               (tho’ infinitely less so in the house than in the grounds) so evident, that tho’ the
               eye is gratified, the mind is dissatisfied, &amp; wishes for a something beyond what
               it finds; that something which the un[illegible] graces of nature would instantly
               have</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 10v</fw>
            <p>afforded, here the power &amp; the poorness of art seem both fully displayed; you are
               astonished it can do so much, yet you sigh that it can do no more.</p>
            <p>From <placeName ref="pl2821">Stowe</placeName> we went on to <placeName ref="pl2886">Banbury</placeName> a market town in Oxfordshire, &amp; passed in a ride of
               fifteen miles and a half thro’ three different counties Bucks: Northampton: &amp;
               Oxon; yet we saw but little variety in the country, excepting that the last six miles
               were rather more enclosed &amp; woody &amp; consequently pleasanter: however the
               comparative warmth of the evening made us enjoy our ride very much. <placeName ref="pl2886">Banbury</placeName> is a place of much trade, &amp; tho’ <add place="above">rather</add> large there is not <sic>a person it</sic> who lives on
               his fortune; <add place="above">they are all traders manufacturers or farmers</add>
               our landlord of the <placeName ref="pl2887">Red Lion</placeName> (a tolerable Inn)
               has himself a farm of 1000 acres</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 11r</fw>
            <p>&amp; is a miller, or a maltster, a brewer, &amp; a large importer &amp; vendor of
               foreign wines. <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> liked the place, &amp; the
               church, I thought them both dull, the latter is built of a dark colored stone which
               was very ugly in my eyes, but I believe that I took a sort of prejudice against the
               place tho’ I don’t know wherefore; the only thing I saw in <del>the place</del> that
               I liked, was a mortal man called Cap<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>: Hill<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note> of the Oxford Blues; the sight of whom
               called so pleasant a train of recollection to my mind, that they communicated a
               degree of bienveillance to himself, what they were your own memory dear Ely will tell
               you, with more distinctness than I could name them.</p>
            <p>Monday 17 After breakfasting at <placeName ref="pl2886">Banbury</placeName> we
               proceeded thro’ Gaydon Inn to <placeName ref="pl0543">Warwick</placeName>
                </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 11v</fw>
            <p>our ride had nothing very pleasant to boast of; the country for the most part flat
               &amp; insipid, &amp; violent hail storms with accompanying cold northerly winds,
               rendered it still more disagreeable; we had now entered Warwickshire, for some miles
               for the first place in it is Warmington Church about five miles from <placeName ref="pl2886">Banbury</placeName>, but we found no change in the scenery till we
               approached <placeName ref="pl0543">Warwick</placeName> itself, towards which as we
               advanced our country &amp; our weather gradually improved, till the beautiful grounds
               of <placeName ref="pl1558">Warwick castle</placeName> opened on our left, &amp;
               conducted us over a fine bridge on the Avon; to the town. Nothing can be more
               beautiful or more <sic>stricking</sic> than the entrance to <placeName ref="pl0543">Warwick</placeName>; the noble castle <note type="editorial">The stone-built
                  Warwick Castle dates from the thirteenth century. By the early nineteenth century
                  it was the family home of the Greville family. The earliest known inventory of the
                  collection at Warwick Castle was made by Thomas Pennant in 1774: see <ref type="http" target="http://www.ourwarwickshire.org.uk/content/article/connoisseur-collector-george-greville-2nd-earl-warwick">here</ref>
                    </note> (the seat of the <persName ref="pe0930">Earl of
                  Warwick</persName>) first meets the eye on the left raising its frowning
               battlements, &amp;</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 12r</fw>
            <p>ivy-crowned turrets in venerable majesty, &amp; almost in the same moment the
               charming spires of St Mary’s Church, of the Free school &amp; the Priory becomes
               conspicuous &amp; form an assemblage of fine objects, which filled us with still
               greater delight, as it was quite unexpected; the town on entering it we found also a
               very pretty one.<note type="editorial">For a late eighteenth-/early
                  nineteenth-century view of Warwick, by Henry Edridge, see <ref type="http" target="https://collections.britishart.yale.edu/vufind/Record/3646425">here</ref>
                    </note> As we intended dining here we filled up the interval of
               preparation, by a nearer view of the object of our distant admiration, the fine old
                  <placeName ref="pl1558">Castle</placeName>: nothing can my dear <persName ref="pe2062">Eliza</persName> inspire more delightful sensations than the
               examination of these beautiful remains of ancient magnificence; its present lord has
               considerably embellished &amp; improved it, attending strictly in all he has done to
               it, to the preservation of that imposing air of age &amp; grandeur</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 12v</fw>
            <p>which is its distinguishing characteristic: Yet the apartments tho’ retaining all
               their ancient magnificence are not devoid of modern cheerfulness; the floors &amp;
                  <sic>wainscoats</sic> are of inlaid &amp; carved oak; &amp; many of the rooms are
               decorated with delightful pictures by the most celebrated masters of the various
               schools of Europe; many of these I longed for you to see, as I am sure you would have
               been charmed with them. When you were tired of gazing on these admirable
               representations of nature, I would have led you to the window, &amp; there shown you
               a scene where the “mighty mother” herself as if in mockery of her finest
                  <sic>copiists</sic>, made a lavish display of her inimitable graces; The beautiful
               Avon rolls its silvery tide at the foot of the <placeName ref="pl1558">Castle</placeName>, &amp; just under the window there is a kind of fall,
               where</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 13r</fw>
            <p>the remains of the ancient drawbridge are still to be seen; which adds to the beauty
               of the scene &amp; beyond is a rich &amp; charming view. With reluctance we left it
               to see the armoury, where all the arms of the valiant now uselessly repose; I was
               astonished how their massive weight could ever have been supported; but early habit
               undoubtedly made them comparatively light. <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName>
               as he viewed them felt an heroic ardour seize him, &amp; wished himself a hero of
               those times, or the redoubtable Guy himself; &amp; I half fancied myself one of those
               noble dames, whose slightest <sic>favor</sic> was held by those unconquered
                  <sic>heros</sic>, dear almost as the <sic>honor’s</sic> of knight-hood; &amp; we
               both envied the illustrious descendants of this illustrious time; how can the
               successors of names long famed, disgrace the noble ancestry</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 13v</fw>
            <p>they claim! From the sort of reverie we were thus thrown into we were soon recalled,
               by the vulgar op<del>p</del>eration of eating dinner, after which we visited a scene
               of a very different nature a manufactory of Worsted yarn: one of the partners in it,
               a M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crumpton,<note type="editorial">Probably a reference
                  to William Crompton (dates unknown), a partner in the Warwick textile firm Parkes,
                  Brookhouse and Crompton (established 1796), which folded in 1822.</note> was a
               schoolfellow of <persName ref="pe2063">Williams</persName> &amp; very politely showed
               it us himself. It is a manufactory on the same principal as the cotton ones performed
               in part by spinning Jennys;<note type="editorial"> The Spinning Jenny was a machine
                  for spinning thread onto multiple spindles, patented in 1770, which transformed
                  the process of cotton manufacturing; see <ref type="http" target="http://www.bl.uk/learning/timeline/item107855.html">here</ref>
               </note> the whole (or very nearly so) from the first washing of the wool as it comes
               from the sheep, to the last winding of the worsted on the bobbins is performed by a
               most curious &amp; complicated machinery all worked by a steam engine: I was
               extremely pleased by it, but regretted very much my entire ignorance of the mechanic
               powers, which made it leave a confus<del>s</del>ion in my head, which I found
               some</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 14r</fw>
            <p>difficulty in reducing to order. Seeing this manufactory took <sic>us up</sic> so
               long a time, we could not reach <placeName ref="pl1293">Birmingham</placeName> as we
               intended tonight but were obliged to content ourselves with the best accommodations
               we could meet with at the poor village of <placeName ref="pl2889">Knowle</placeName>;
               those we found at the <placeName ref="pl2888">Mermaid Inn</placeName> were just
               tolerable, but no more. </p>
            <p>Tuesday 18 We arose early &amp; got to <placeName ref="pl1293">Birmingham</placeName>
               to breakfast before nine o’ clock, I was rather better pleased with this town than I
               expected, tho’ certainly it is a vile dirty place; but I spent so pleasant a day
               here, I was inclined to be pleased with every thing. <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> was acquainted with a young merchant here, of the name of
                  <persName ref="pe2078">Hunt</persName>; who came to us the moment he heard of our
               arrival, &amp; with the greatest kindness &amp; attention gave up the whole day to
                  <sic>shewing</sic> us the curiosities of the town. </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 14v</fw>
            <p>Thro’ his assistance we saw the Whip, the Pin &amp; Clay’s Manufactory<note type="editorial">George Nicholson’s The Cambrian Traveller’s Guide (1813; 2nd
                  edition), lists ‘Clark and Ashmore’s whip Manufactory’ at the Bullring, ‘Phipson’s
                  pin-manufactory’ on New Street and ‘Clay’s japan manufactory and show-room’ on
                  Newhall Street as ‘Objects worthy of notice’ for visitors to Birmingham (p.
                  134).</note> with all of which we were extremely entertained, the <add place="above">two</add> former I think you saw at Gloucester, &amp; know therefore
               how simple yet curious they are; the latter you can easily imagine for after the
               paper has once acquired the thickness required which is often that of an inch, &amp;
               which is merely performed by pasting one sheet upon another &amp; drying them well;
               the rest is exactly the same, as the shop of a cabinet maker as it will bear to be
               used in the same manner as wood <del>entirely</del>. After satisfying our curiosity
               at these places we walked to Soho, which is some distance from the town, hoping to
               see M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
               <persName ref="pe2079">Bolton’s</persName> various works,<note type="editorial">A
                  reference to Matthew Boulton’s Soho Foundry, Soho Manufactory and Soho Mint, which
                  employed steam power as part of the new mechanisation of the manufacturing
                  process.</note> unfortunately the men were all at dinner when we arrived, tho’ we
               had hastened ourselves on their account; however M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 15r</fw>
            <p>
                    <persName ref="pe2078">Hunt</persName> assured us we lost very little, as they have
               at this time <del>very</del> little employment, &amp; consequently there is not much
               to be seen; the workmen are also chiefly employed on the Steam Engine patent which I
               think I understood was not shown. We were however amply repaid for our walk, by a
               sight of <persName ref="pe2080">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Egerton’s</persName>
               paintings on glass,<note type="editorial">Francis Eginton worked for Matthew Boulton
                  at his Soho Manufactory in the 1760s and 70s, before later setting up his own
                  glass painting business.</note> which are infinitely more beautiful than any thing
               of the kind I had any idea of; it is a totally different art from the old one, &amp;
               in my opinion far superior to it; it has not indeed that matchless richness of
                  <sic>coloring</sic> possess’d by its predecessors, but the beauties of softness,
               &amp; the charming effects of light &amp; shade, more than compensate for that; of
               these the old paintings possessed nothing; &amp; instead of those “shapes which shape
               had none,”<note type="editorial">A reference to John Milton, <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>, II: 667.</note> which their art produced all the elegance
               of grecian <sic>symetry</sic>
            </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 15v</fw>
            <p>&amp; costume are <hi rend="superscript">here</hi> displayed with as much grace as on
               canvas. This art was quite new to me, &amp; therefore struck me exceedingly, but you
               may have an idea of it, as <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> informs <hi rend="superscript">me</hi> the celebrated window in <placeName ref="">New College
                  Chapel</placeName> which you have seen, is in the same <sic>stile</sic> &amp; that
                  <persName ref="pe2080">Egerton</persName> is even surpassed by <persName ref="pe0927">Jarvis</persName>, but this ’till I see I cannot help doubting. From
               hence we all returned to the <placeName ref="pl2985">Swan Inn</placeName> to dinner,
               this is mentioned by Cary as the first Inn,<note type="editorial">This precise
                  reference remains unidentified, but probably alludes to the widely-used guidebook
                  John Cary published in 1798 as <hi rend="italic"> Cary's New Itinerary; or, an
                     accurate delineation of the great roads, both direct and cross, throughout
                     England and Wales</hi>.</note> but we were sorry that we had follow’d him in
               coming to it, as we found both <placeName ref="pl2986">Lloyd’s Hotel</placeName>,
               &amp; ‘The Hotel’<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note> were far superior to it,
               as our <sic>accodations</sic> were certainly not more than pretty good, by no means
               first rate. <persName ref="pe2078">Harry Hunt</persName> dined with us, he is very
               lively agreeable young man &amp; made our meal a very pleasant one; We drank tea at
               his <sic>mother</sic> on the Crescent: &amp; found her a </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 16r</fw>
            <p>most captivating woman; I must use that expression, altho she can no longer boast the
               bloom or the graces of youth, for neither will sufficiently describe the charm of her
               manners. I scarcely ever was more pleased with any one at first sight, or spent a
               pleasanter evening; her sister who lives with them is also a very agreeable woman,
               tho’ much inferior to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Hunt, of whom to give you some
               idea I need only say she reminded me of the dear M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                  LeMesurier;<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note> they were all extremely
               friendly &amp; pressed us very much to lengthen our stay with them, which we refused
               with reluctance: &amp; took leave of them after a sociable supper: the pleasures of
               this day were much encreased by good news of our treasure at home.</p>
            <p>Wednesday 19. We had a post chaise this morning to the <placeName ref="pl2890">Brades</placeName>, where we went to breakfast at</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 16v</fw>
            <p>an uncle of <sic>
                        <persName ref="pe2078">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                     Hunts</persName>
                    </sic>, who has some large Ironworks here which he offered to
               show us;<note type="editorial">The Brades Ironworks (a steelworks and tool
                  manufactory from the early nineteenth century), at Oldbury just outside
                  Birmingham, was owned by William Hunt (dates unknown).</note> the <placeName ref="pl2890">Brades</placeName> are <del>at</del> some miles distant from
                  <placeName ref="pl1293">Birmingham</placeName>, &amp; nearer to <placeName ref="pl2891">Dudley</placeName>. Here we were received with the same hospitable
               kindness we yesterday met with both by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>s Hunt &amp; a young lady who was on a visit there went
               with us over the works. The sight of them was truly astonishing, but I must own they
               filled me with as much terror as wonder: the deafening noise occasioned by the
               stupendous wheels, which worked the still more formidable hammers, the bars of
               red-hot iron which the men were continuously running to and fro with in all
               directions, &amp; the innumerable sparks that flew all round, made the scene
               perfectly horrific; it is not in my power to give you</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 17r</fw>
            <p>an idea of the magnitude of these works, the thing for which they are most celebrated
               is cast steel for which M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hunt has a patent. Nothing can
               convey so adequate an idea of the surprizing force of steam <del>there</del> as the
               sight of them for they are all set in motion by a Steam Engine of great magnitude
               &amp; power. When we had taken leave of this friendly family we went on thro
                  <placeName ref="pl2891">Dudley</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl2892">Wolverhampton</placeName>
               <sic>were</sic> we met Benjamin &amp; the horses who had been sent there over night:
               it was fortunate for us our morning ride was in a <sic>close</sic> carriage for it
               was the worst we have had; the rain <del>had</del> fell heavily all the way to the
                  <placeName ref="pl2890">Brades</placeName> but such was the excessive cold it was
               not able to melt the snow which had fallen in the night &amp; which in some places
               was full three inches thick; towards noon however the sun showed his
                  <sic>resplendant</sic> visage, &amp; clouds</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 17v</fw>
            <p>&amp; coldness fled before his powerful influence, &amp; thus cheered we
                  <sic>agained</sic> placed ourselves in the chair, &amp; had a sweet ride to the
               Iron Bridge Colebro<add place="above">o</add>k<del>e</del> Dale. The country which
               from the time we left <placeName ref="pl2892">Wolverhampton</placeName> had been
               extremely pretty, grew more &amp; more so as we approached the beautiful Dale, which
               fully deserves its celebrity: in the Iron bridge<note type="editorial">The Iron
                  Bridge at Ironbridge, built by Abraham Darby and completed in 1779, was the first
                  bridge to be made out of cast-iron. See <ref type="http" target="https://historicengland.org.uk/services-skills/education/educational-images/the-iron-bridge-ironbridge-4242">here</ref>
                    </note> I was rather disappointed, I had heard too much of it, or
               this would not have been the case; for had my ideas been rather more moderate they
               would have been gratified for certainly it is very handsome. Here we saw the smelting
               of the iron the first process it undergoes; it is in this state M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hunt receives it, &amp; every other process to its
               formation into implements of husbandry &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>. we had
               seen there. After dinner we took a delightful stroll thro’ some beautiful public
               walks the property of <persName ref="pe2081">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                  Reynolds</persName>, who keeps them</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 18r</fw>
            <p>in order pro <add place="above">bono</add> public, the evening was sweet &amp; we
               fully enjoyed it, &amp; tired ourselves sufficiently to enjoy “tired nature’s sweet
               restorer,” <note type="editorial">Eade is quoting the opening of Edward Young’s <hi rend="italic">The Complaint: or, Night-thoughts on Life, Death &amp;
                     Immortality</hi> (London: R. Dodsley, 1742).</note> at the <placeName ref="pl2893">Tontine Inn</placeName> which is, a very nice one. </p>
            <p>Thursday 21 We breakfasted at the Iron Bridge as <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> wished to descend one of the neighbouring Coal
                  <sic>Pitts</sic>, the one he went down was 400 feet deep but his descriptions of
               it on his return did not make me regret its being one of the things I could not see,
               indeed he owned it is one of those that it is pleasanter to have seen that to see. We
               set off after breakfast with a warm &amp; promising morning, tho’ the mists that hung
               on the hills obscured the prospect &amp; made us a little doubtful of the issue of
               the day, we had not however present cause to complain of it; at Colebrook is another
               iron bridge, of a later structure, I <sic>prefered</sic> it to the</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 18v</fw>
            <p>old one as being lighter, more simple &amp; more elegant, &amp; a little beyond are
               the ruins of an old <placeName ref="pl2822">Abbey</placeName> which are very
               beautiful: our ride from hence to <placeName ref="pl0740">Shrewsbury</placeName> was
               the <sic>lovliest</sic> we have had; the charming hills of this beautiful country,
               finely wooded &amp; rich in cultivation, crowned by the majestic <placeName ref="pl2823">Rekin</placeName>, the highest of them all formed a noble back ground
               to the various views, while all the way the winding <placeName ref="pl1226">Severn</placeName> &amp; the humbler <placeName ref="pl2894">Tern</placeName>
               adorned the nearer ground. On the right of Atcham we passed <placeName ref="pl2825">Attingham House</placeName> the noble seat of <persName ref="pe2031">L<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. Berwick</persName>, &amp; a little further the more
               modest <placeName ref="pl2826">residence</placeName> of <persName ref="pe2082">Robert
                  Burton Jun<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    </persName>: Esqr: one of the sweetest
               spots I ever saw, &amp; the one I preferred to all we passed tho’ this country is
               full of them. At <placeName ref="pl0740">Shrewsbury</placeName> we stopped to wait at
                  <placeName ref="pl1610">the Lion</placeName> which seemed to be a good Inn, &amp;
               here <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> was tempted to purchase “the </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 19r</fw>
            <p>sweetest &amp; cheapest mare in all England,” with which bargain he filled up his
               time in <placeName ref="pl0740">Shrewsbury</placeName>, of which town I saw very
               little as it began to rain immediately on our arrival &amp; consequently I was
                  <del>but</del> confined to the Inn, it appeared however to be large ancient, &amp;
               indifferent pleasant. We had a rainy ride from hence to <placeName ref="pl1260">Oswestry</placeName>, but my oil-silk so <sic>compleatly</sic> defended me from
               any ill effects of it, that I greatly enjoyed the reviving freshness it diffused, as
               well as the lovely country thro which we passed, which however was rather less
               beautiful than what we had seen in the morning. Thro’ all my ride to-day poor
                  Bennet<note type="editorial">Unidentified, but possibly a servant to Eade.</note>
               has been constantly in my thoughts; <placeName ref="pl1021">Shropshire</placeName>
               the beloved spot of her nativity was I think often the theme of her praises, &amp; I
               am sure she had cause to remember its charming </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 19v</fw>
            <p>scenes with admiration.</p>
            <p>At <placeName ref="pl1260">Oswestry</placeName> we took up our quarters at the
                  <placeName ref="pl2827">Sir Watkin Williams Wynne’s Arms</placeName> a new &amp;
               most excellent Inn, one of the best indeed I ever saw; &amp; here while satisfying
               our appetites with two delicate roast chickens, our ears were saluted by the sweet
               tones of the Welch Harp; my raptures at its first soft chords was extreme for
               independent of its own charms, I was in <sic>extasies</sic> at the certainty it gave
               me that <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>, that land of wonders I had so long
               wished without hope to contemplate, was actually within a few miles of us: think
                  <persName ref="pe2062">Eliza</persName> of your feelings on a like occasion, &amp;
               judge of mine! <placeName ref="pl1260">Oswestry</placeName> is a very poor town the
               last in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>, but the dress &amp; language of
               the people are more than half welch; &amp; here on the borders of another country,
               tho’ not another island; at the distance of 183 miles.</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 20r</fw>
            <p>from the objects of my tenderest love, do you not think you were all present to my
               recollection? the dear remembrance of you added sweets to my repose, &amp; my dear
                  <persName ref="pe2062">Eliza</persName> may be sure she was not the least thought
               of, tho’ the smiling image of my darling <persName ref="pe2064">boy</persName> might
               dispute her claim to preeminence in my reverie.</p>
            <p>Friday 21.<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> We left our comfortable inn this morning
               before breakfast, &amp; I anticipated with delight our entrance into <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>, I had indeed awoken with one of
                  <sic>Margarett’s</sic> happy feels which <sic>encreased</sic> upon me as we
               advanced every moment nearer &amp; nearer to this beautiful principality: at the
               village of Chirk we entered it, &amp; the scene that immediately opened on our view
               gave me a faint idea of its charms; the hills on every side enclosed the sweet valley
               of <sic>Ceriog</sic>, which tho’ not very extensive, is delightful <del>pretty</del>
               a pretty [illegible] is</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 20v</fw>
            <p>thrown across it which struck me the more as it was the first I had ever seen: soon
               after we had passed thro’ the valley we turned out of the high road to see <placeName ref="pl1256">Chirk Castle</placeName>, the seat of <persName ref="pe2032">Col:<hi rend="superscript">l</hi> Middleton</persName>, it is a fine old <placeName ref="pl1256">Castle</placeName> &amp; very well kept up, but after seeing
                  <placeName ref="pl1558">Warwick</placeName> it disappointed me; but the ride thro’
               the park was delightful, &amp; the view from the castle rich, romantic, &amp;
               extensive it is said that seventeen counties may be seen from it. It is astonishing
               how soon the country changes on leaving <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>;
               I yesterday considered the hills of <placeName ref="pl1021">Shropshire</placeName> as
               lofty &amp; gazed on the rich country with ardent admiration, yet compared even with
               this entrance into <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>, the hills seem
               insignificant, &amp; the country insipid. Soon after we regained the high road, we
               saw the </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 21r</fw>
            <p>immense <placeName ref="pl1609">aqueduct</placeName> which is building over the Vale
               of Llangollen from the Ellesmere canal, when <sic>compleat</sic> it will be a very
               noble work, at present it is in a very unfinished state. Since I have mentioned this
               celebrated valley, you will imagine my dear <persName ref="pe2062">Eliza</persName>,
               that all the magic of Welch scenery was now fast opening on our view; but no
               imagination can form an idea half so exquisite as the prospects which continually
               encreased in beauty as we approached the poor village of <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName>, poor in itself but rich in the charms of its situation.
               You might well tell me I could not possibly raise my expectations to a pitch
               suffering [?by] elevated, in thinking of <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>
               for though can never reach to half its beauties. The lofty mountains on each side
               this </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 21v</fw>
            <p>exquisite valley are richly tufted with wood to the edge of the romantic <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName>, which in this part gently murmurs over a pebbly
               bottom, frequently it can scarcely be seen to glitter thro’ the trees that overshadow
               its banks, &amp; only its soothing music reveals its situation. The mountains on each
               side occasionally assumed a bolder character, &amp; as if in disdain of ornament,
               show their rugged sides, covered only with their native rocks. Never did the heavens
               illuminate a lovelier morning than this, it seems sent on purpose to
                  <sic>heighthen</sic> the charms of the scene; not one was lost on me, &amp; no
               words “can paint the rapture of my soul” the whole way, I powerfully felt, that
               “These scenes would work my soul's eternal health,”</p>
            <p>“And love, &amp; gentleness, &amp; joy impart”</p>
            <note type="editorial">A quotation from Book 1 of James Beattie's <hi rend="italic">The
                  Minstrel; or, The Progres of Genius</hi> (1771): ‘These charms shall work thy
               soul’s eternal health, / And love, and gentleness, and joy, impart’ (p. 7).</note>
            <p>At length we arrived at <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName>
                </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 22r</fw>
            <p>to breakfast at the <placeName ref="pl2828">Hand Inn</placeName>, which gave us an
               agreeable foretaste of Welch accommodation, however tho’ the rooms were small &amp;
               not delicately clean, the people were very civil; but of all the characters least
               likely to be met with in this retired part of the world, what do you think of a
               french valet of the old stamp? figure to yourself a being that seemed never to have
               been fed with more fattening provision than soup meagre, with his long chin enveloped
               in neck cloth, three under waistcoats, one of which was of dirty pink
                  <sic>sattin</sic>, a frill which extended far beyond them all, &amp; a coat of
               green mist silk more dirty if possible than any part of his attire &amp; you will if
               you add to all this bows every sixth word; &amp; smiles at every second <del>you
                  will</del>
               <hi rend="superscript">have some</hi> idea of our waiter at <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName>; a more risible character I never beheld, &amp; as I soon
               found to look at him &amp; not laugh was beyond “all power of face” I did<note type="editorial">A quotation from Alexander Pope, <hi rend="italic">An Epistle
                     from Mr. Pope, to Dr. Arbuthnot</hi> (London: J. Wright, 1734), p.
               3.</note>
                </p>
            <p> </p>
            <p>f. 22v</p>
            <p>not make the attempt: I only wish you could have seen him when <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> asked if he was a welchman as with the most self complacent
               voice &amp; manner he answered “Oh no Sir, this not <hi rend="underline">my</hi>
               country”: indeed it was impossible to mistake his accent, his countenance, or his
               gestures. After the necessary recruit of a good breakfast we set forth on a ramble
               thro’ this lovely valley, we staid for some time to admire the very pretty <placeName ref="pl1954">bridge</placeName> in this town over the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName>, which here dashes over a more rugged bed, &amp; from hence it
               foams over large masses of rock, which adds considerably to its romantic beauty,
               unfortunately the long continuance of dry weather, had at this time diminished its
               waters extremely. From the bridge we went on to <placeName ref="pl0785">Valle Crucis
                  abbey</placeName> of which there are some very elegant remains, part of the old
               abbey is now converted into a farm house</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 23r</fw>
            <p>but the ruins that remain in their “time decayed” state are extremely beautiful,
               consisting chiefly of gothic arches in many parts quite perfect, &amp; a large &amp;
               elegant carved &amp; decorated window which reaches to the ground; the situation
               amidst woods &amp; mountains of this fine old abbey adds greatly to the effect of its
               ruins &amp; forms a scene that is altogether lovely.<note type="editorial">For an
                  eighteenth-centuty view of Valle Crucis, by Moses Griffith, see <ref type="http" target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Valle_Crucis_Abbey03017.jpg">here</ref>
                    </note> Near it is a very pretty summer house belonging to one of
               the neighbouring gentlemen, sweetly situated where dinner parties are often made.
               After a walk of five miles <sic>in</sic> a very hot day I was too tired to attempt
               climbing the steep mountain on which the ruins of <placeName ref="pl0794">Castell
                  Dinas Brân</placeName> stand; but as <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName>
               wished to see them, it was agreed that I should follow a path that seemed to lead
               round the foot of the mountain while he scaled its heights: we parted accordingly but
               I soon</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 23v</fw>
            <p>found that my path did not go far round the mountain, but as it was a very
                  <sic>beatten</sic> road I concluded it led to the town, I also imagined <hi rend="superscript">that</hi>
               <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> must see the course of it from the mountain
               top &amp; would not therefore be uneasy about me, so I resolved on pursing it; &amp;
               soon found myself safe at the bridge, where I found full amusement in watching <hi rend="superscript">the</hi> glistening waters as they dashed along, &amp; admiring
               the bewitching scenery around me. Long before I expected his return I perceived
                  <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> coming down the last hill, but hastening
               to meet him I perceived his countenance to be so heated, I might say so inflamed I
               was terrified ere I heard him speak but much more so, when I heard his thick hurried
               accents; it was however some relief to me to find no accident had actually befallen
               him, &amp; that I was the unconscious cause of his agitation. From the </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 24r</fw>
            <p>top of the mountain he had fancied he saw me running with swiftness from the pursuit
               of a shepherds dog; &amp; knowing my terror of these animals, &amp; that flight would
               only make an imaginary danger a real one; he immediately left the view unseen, &amp;
               the ruins unexplored that he had just with difficulty gained, &amp; precipitately
               flew down the mountain, regardless of its nearly perpendicular height, &amp; bounding
               two or three yards at a step, till happily he reached the bottom unhurt: here I was
               not to be found, so without stopping he ran round the mountain &amp; back to the
               place where he left me, shaping unknown horrors in his imagination, &amp; calling me,
               till quite exhausted, he could call no longer. The people whom he met could seldom
               understand his language &amp; those that did had not seen me; at length: when he was
               a little </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 24v</fw>
            <p>recovered tho’ he thinks he had run nearly three miles, he was going to set off again
               when a woman fortunately came in sight who gave him the desired information that she
               had seen me safe in <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName>. Relieved from his
               fright he returned to the town in sea<add place="above">r</add>ch of me, but you have
               no idea how shocking he looked when I met him, his whole face was of the deepest
               scarlet, his eyes seemed starting from his head, &amp; he appeared scarcely able to
               stand: I really thought his agitation of mind &amp; fatigue of body would throw him
               into a fever; but thank God! a tumbler of port wine &amp; a <hi rend="superscript">change of</hi> linen entirely refreshed him, &amp; a little lameness is all the
               bad consequence that has ensued: Whatever occasion’d this mistake I not know, for
               tho’ I passed a dog of this description I am not aware of having been followed by it:
               this incident will perhaps make you smile when you read it; but it really was rather </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 25r</fw>
            <p>frightful at first, &amp; abated the sensations of delight I had experienced in the
               morning for some time; they revived again however when once more seated in our chaise
               we continued our ride thro’ the remainder of the Vale of Llangollen. Sweet as our
               mornings ride had been it now only served as a point of comparison, from which we
               might <hi rend="superscript">note</hi> what “passed that passing sweet”<note type="editorial">Probably adapted or misquoted from William Cowper’s ‘Retirement’
                  (‘How, sweet, how passing sweet is solitude!’). See <hi rend="italic">Poems by
                     William Cowper</hi> (London: J. Johnson, 1782), p. 295.</note>: so exquisite is
               the rest of the valley, so rich the mountains, so bewitching the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName>, that it was impossible to express our admiration of
               one view, ere “Some lovely wonder had usurp’d its place” “Chac’d by a charm still
                  <sic>lovlier</sic> than the last.”<note type="editorial">A quotation from William
                  Mason’s ‘Elegy on the Death of Lady Coventry’; see <hi rend="italic">Elegies. By
                     William Mason</hi> (London: Robert Horsfield, 1763), p. 16.</note> This
               enchanting valley extends full ten miles, &amp; when with sorrow we quitted it, we
               passed thro’ country that at any other time we should have thought charming, the
               darting <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName> still accompanying us to <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName>. Here we <sic>eat</sic> our first Welch dinner at
               the New Inn, &amp; a capital one</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 25v</fw>
            <p>it was, consisting of welch mutton, which is perfectly delicious <add place="above">&amp; trout</add> just caught in the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName>; our
               landlady a most worthy old soul doing all she could to please us: we had also a most
               excellent Harper, who played the whole evening, &amp; indeed some time after we were
               in bed, with a taste &amp; feeling not to be surpassed. Between dinner &amp; tea we
               walked forth to see a little of <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName> &amp; its
               environs, it is a very poor place, but the situation is pretty enough; on our return,
               the good woman came with great joy to tell us <del>some</del>
               <hi rend="superscript">a fine</hi> fiddler was just arrived, &amp; that he &amp; Ned
               the blind harper <hi rend="superscript">above</hi> mentioned were playing together:
               at first I thought this information rather unpleasant than otherwise, but I soon
               found, that this itinerant fiddler played in a <sic>stile</sic> far different from
               what our poor scraping fellows in the street do: he accompanied the harp with such
               uncommon </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 26r</fw>
            <p>
                    <sic>delicasy</sic> as never to over power it, &amp; as our friend Ned had a soul in
               unison with his own, they played their native airs together with such exquisite
               pathos I could have listened to them for ever. Our nights lodgings were so dirty
               &amp; comfortless they required something to compensate for them, but after such a
               day as this we looked on them as the price of pleasure &amp; paid it willingly. </p>
            <p>Saturday 22 – We breakfasted at <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName>, &amp; had
               as different <del>fr</del> a ride from that of yesterday as can well be imagined, the
               first few miles indeed are the prettiest, &amp; at 5 ½ miles from <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName> is a sweetly romantic spot called <placeName ref="pl2829">Pont y Glyn</placeName>; the bridge itself is rudely simple according
               well with the wild scenery in which it stands; there is a small deep glen down which
               a fine cascade very beautifully falls, but at present it has very little water;
               excepting this small glen</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 26v</fw>
            <p>all was bleak; barren &amp; cheerless, the mountains are not high enough, tho’ they
               rose on all sides to merit the praise of sublimity, &amp; were almost as devoid of
               verdure as of cultivation. I pitied the miserable inhabitants of the wretched hovels
               thinly scattered in different parts of them, but blame mingled with my pity, for
               industry might even here strew some flowers in their way. Thro’ this dreary region we
               rode to <placeName ref="pl1576">
                        <sic>Kernioge Mawr</sic>
                    </placeName>, <sic>were</sic>
               we waited; this is merely a posting Inn, &amp; has very few cottages near it; I found
               little to tempt me from it, &amp; therefore spent the time we waited in writing to
               Louisa, and <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> who went climbing about the
               mountains found nothing but the pleasure of exercise to repay him. From hence to
               within about four miles of <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName> we saw no
               improvement in the scene; ’till suddenly the boldest &amp; most noble mountains burst
               upon our view, which rising one above another </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 27r</fw>
            <p>almost hid their lofty heads in the clouds; &amp; soon a rich &amp; fertile valley
               opened at their feet; about half way up the mountains the road is cut commanding the
               full view of the valley as at <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName>, you
               descend the mountains to enter <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>, down the
               last of which is more than three miles. This exquisite prospect had a still more
                  <sic>stricking</sic> effect from being thus [illegible], but of itself nothing can
               be more grand; the <placeName ref="pl2384">Conway</placeName> flows along the bottom
               of the valley, at first in a small stream, which ere it reaches <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanwrst</placeName> swells into a broad &amp; beautiful river. The
               vale of Llanrwst is considerably wider than that of Llangollen &amp; the mountains
               that bound it are of a more majestic height; the infinite <add place="above">variety</add> of their forms &amp; appearance, some remarkable only for wild
               sublimity, others softened into beauty by the fine woods that covered them</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 27v</fw>
            <p>their broad shadows sweeping across the valley giving it a [?nice] grace from the
               ever-changing tints, &amp; varying effects of light &amp; shade, produced a scene,
               which gave me higher delight than any I have yet seen. This mountainous valley is
               interspersed every where with gentlemen’s seats, &amp; exhibits a picture of
               cultivation uncommon in <add place="above">
                        <placeName ref="pl1221">North
                     Wales</placeName>
                    </add>, in the midst of it is the town from whence it takes
               its name: upon the whole we agreed it had more of grandeur, but less of romantic
               sweetness than <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName>. The entrance into
                  <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName> is very beautiful, the simple but
               pretty <placeName ref="pl1531">bridge</placeName> built by <persName ref="pe1159">Inigo Jones</persName> in <sic>honor</sic> of his native town, over the
                  <placeName ref="pl2384">Conway</placeName> first presents itself to view, &amp;
               behind the town wearing an air of neatness &amp; comfort superior to most in
                  <placeName ref="pl1221">North Wales</placeName> has a charming appearance: on
               entering it we found that industry had here received its usual reward </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 28r</fw>
            <p>in the encreased population &amp; comfort of the place. We dined and slept at the
                  <placeName ref="pl2090">Eagles</placeName>, &amp; found our accommodation
               excellent. While our dinner was making ready we <sic>stroled</sic> into the sweetest
               little church yard in the world, here &amp; in several other places we saw many of
               the graves adorned in the Welch fashion<note type="editorial">On the Welsh practice
                  of decorating graves with flower, see <ref type="http" target="https://sublimewales.wordpress.com/material-culture/buildings/churchyards/flowers-on-graves/">here</ref>
                    </note> with boughs of trees, flowers &amp;c. but I cannot say the
               effect produced was at all similar to that described by Pratt<note type="editorial">A
                  reference to Samuel Jackson Pratt, <hi rend="italic">Gleanings Through Wales,
                     Holland and Westphalia</hi> (London: T. N. Longman and L. B. Seeley, 1795), p.
                  114 (‘Amongst the customs that had peculiar attractions for me, was the tender
                  veneration paid, externally at least to the dead … I have seen graves so
                  diligently cultured, as every week to have been planted with the choicest flowers
                  of the season’).</note>; the neat borders of blooming flowers so carefully tended,
               so sedulously replenished, if every they existed exist, at least in these parts, no
               more; what we have seen when first strewn over the new-made grave may have a very
               pleasing effect, but in the faded state they are suffered to remain they do not add
               either neatness or ornament to the church yards. While admiring the smoothly gliding
                  <placeName ref="pl2384">Conway</placeName>, which washes</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 28v</fw>
            <p>one side of that I am describing we noticed two little laughing girls, who were half
               slyly, half bashfully approaching us, afraid to utter the <sic>sentance</sic>, that
               we knew hung on their lips of “Pray give me a penny” – the archness of their smiles,
               &amp; the recollection that it was here he had first heard this petition
                  <sic>profered</sic> four years ago, drew the unasked boon from <persName ref="pe2063">William’s</persName> pocket, &amp; sent them away with a few
               additional dimples. This phraze comprehends the whole compass of the knowledge these
               little urchins have of English, &amp; you cannot meet either girl or boy, throughout
                  <placeName ref="pl1221">North Wales</placeName>, that does not accost you with it,
               so that your pockets should be well supplied to answer all their demands. After
               dinner we again walked out, &amp; crossing the bridge, were shewn the effect said to
               be produced by shaking the center on one side, namely that the corresponding part of
               the other</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 29r</fw>
            <p>is affected in the same manner; there certainly was a slight vibration but I did not
               feel it very sensibly. <persName ref="pe2063">William’s</persName> lameness prevented
               our attempting to climb the mountains, but we had a very pleasant walk ’till dusk
               along the banks of the <placeName ref="pl2384">Conway</placeName>. </p>
            <p>Sunday 23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>. It was in vain attempting to attend any
               place of Worship to-day, as the service is every where performed in Welch; we thought
               therefore of going to see some Waterfalls in this neighbourhood; but we found on
               enquiry they would scarcely at present repay us for visiting them as the continued
               dry weather had nearly deprived them of water; in consequence of which we had no
               choice but continuing our journey. Our ride was extremely sweet &amp; beautiful,
               thro’ mountain scenery which every instant wore a new aspect as we perused the
               charming course of the <placeName ref="pl2384">Conway</placeName>
                </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 29v</fw>
            <p>where unruffled waters flowed on our right; unfortunately the lowness of the tide
               robbed of its chief beauty one of the most admired spots in this isle; it is where
               the closing mountains so nearly encircle this fine river, as to prevent the eye from
               tracing its entire course, &amp; gives it the appearance <hi rend="superscript">of
                  a</hi> wide &amp; noble lake; but the retiring tide had left little more water
               than covered its muddy bottom, &amp; the deserted river now afforded only another
               proof of the determined ill-fortune that had attended all our hopes of gratification
               from water views, since we left home. A high mountain on our <del>left</del>
                    <hi rend="superscript">right</hi> whose ascent seemed rather less formidable than the
               rest, while its height promised to repay our labour by an extensive prospect tempted
               us a few miles before</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 30r</fw>
            <p>we reached <placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName> to alight from the chair, &amp;
               climb its rugged sides; <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> reached its summit
               without much difficulty, but about twenty yards below it, the ascent became so
               entirely perpendicular &amp; the footsteps so slippery, while the huge stones that
               alone could have afforded any assistance appeared to have so unstable a foundation;
               that I found neither agility nor strength nor I must add courage equal to the
               attempt; &amp; I was obliged to defer the sight of the ocean till evening, while
                  <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> enjoyed from his station on the
               mountain’s top a view of its “multitudinous waves,” &amp; a scene in other respects
               truly delightful. Soon after we entered the singular &amp; picturesque town of
                  <placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName>; which is I believe <sic>a unique</sic>
               in our island, from being regularly</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 30v</fw>
            <p>fortified, surrounded by a turreted wall, &amp; further protected by a noble old
               castle which once no doubt frowned proud defiance upon our invaders, &amp; held the
               surrounding country in awe, tho’ now its strong towers of defence, even if perfect,
               could not protect it from one half hour’s modern cannonade. Thro’ its mouldering
               ruins we <sic>stroled</sic> for half an hour, &amp; as we viewed with admiration
               these beautiful remains of antiquity, our conversation naturally reverted to those
               “bygone” times when its now falling battlements, stuck terror into its enemies; &amp;
               its <hi rend="superscript">now</hi> ruined desolate halls, invited with hospitable
                  <sic>splendor</sic> the guest to revel or the traveller to repose, or resounding
               with the sprightly notes of minstrel music called them to join in the </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 31r</fw>
            <p>dance or the song. It is now <sic>compleatly</sic> in ruins, &amp; does not, nor
               indeed cannot afford shelter to one human being, &amp; we could not but regret that
               the destroying hand of time had <del>so</del> left so little by which we could judge
               of its former interior, tho’ perhaps it is in some respects more beautiful in decay,
               than it was in days of renown: from one part of the wall we had a charming view of
               the <placeName ref="pl2384">Conway</placeName>, &amp; the old arched gateway, whence
               the ferry boats depart. We had an excellent dinner at the Harp, a very comfortable
               Inn, &amp; fortified ourselves by it, for the fatigues of the awe-inspiring stage on
               which we entered on concluding it, the stage which leads from hence to <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName>. Scarcely had we</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 31v</fw>
            <p>left <placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName> ere we began the descent of an
               enormous mountain, great part of which we were obliged to walk down to ease the
               horses who could with difficulty keep their feet, &amp; I could not survey without
               some terror, the frightful precipice on our left, which in many places was most
               dangerously left without either wall or bank; but its dangers &amp; its grandeur were
               soon forgotten as we approached the foot of the tremendous <placeName ref="pl1338">Penmaen Mawr</placeName>, the passage of this mountain was <add place="above">formerly</add>
               <sic>iminently</sic> dangerous, as it had then no protection from the horrific
               precipice that hangs immediately over the <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai
                  Straits</placeName>, but a strong wall is now built along it, which effectively
               guards the traveller from its </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 32r</fw>
            <p>dangers, &amp; he has now only to dread those that threaten him from the overhanging
               stones on the other side. The road is cut along this stupendous mountain about a
               third of the h<add place="above">e</add>ight from its base, above it a mass of <add place="above">huge</add> stones seem to hang on the side of the mountain, scarcely
               supported by the sand to which they cling, &amp; of which the fall of the smallest
               would be sufficient to crush the horse &amp; his rider for ever, below it is the
               precipice above mentioned, on which hang in like manner vast stones that from time to
               time have fallen from the fearful <sic>heigths</sic> above; at the bottom the lovely
                  <placeName ref="pl1564">straits of Menai</placeName> flowed gently along, &amp;
               formed a beautiful contrast, to the <sic>aweful</sic> sublime scene,
                  <sic>pourtrayed</sic> by the majestic mountains </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 32v</fw>
            <p>that here frown along its shores. Soon after leaving <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName> at the small village of <placeName ref="pl2895">Trefriew</placeName> we had entered Carnarvonshire &amp; were therefore less
               astonished at the loftiness of these <sic>mountain</sic> for this is the most grand
               of all the welch counties; from <placeName ref="pl1338">Penmawn Mawr</placeName>
               however the road <del>is road</del> itself is nearly level but still a noble chain of
               mountains on our left with the mighty <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>
               himself faintly discovered towering above the rest, his summit still covered with
               snow; gave sublimity to the scene, while the fine straits on our right continued to
               lend to it the softer touches of beauty: Arrived <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName> &amp; hence to the Ferry two miles beyond are several pretty
               houses &amp; seats, among which that of <persName ref="pe0420">Lord
                  Penrhyn</persName>, &amp; in a humbler <sic>stile</sic> the sweet retreat of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wyatt<note type="editorial">Probably a reference to
                  Benjamin Wyatt (1745-1818), land agent and engineer, who became chief agent at the
                  Penrhyn Estate in the mid-1780s. His house was Lime Grove, an eighteenth-century
                  villa; for an early nineteenth-century illustration see <ref type="http" target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Lime_Grove_near_Bangor,_North_Wales.jpeg">here</ref>
                    </note> pleased us most. The Inn at Bangor ferry where we took </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 33r</fw>
            <p>up <add place="above">our</add> lodgings for the night is sweetly situated on the
               border of the <placeName ref="pl1564">Straits</placeName>, from which a pleasant
               garden alone separates it; the room we had commanded a charming view of them: their
               waves on this lovely evening murmured with the gentleness of a river, &amp; as the
               sun was now setting, the distance &amp; obscurity gave to the view of the hilly
                     <sic>
                        <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesea</placeName>
                    </sic> a softness &amp;
               attractiveness it might otherwise have wanted; I could not but regret that its being
               Sunday prevented our having the Harp whose soft chords would so have accorded with
               the scene. Unhappily the calm without did not enter the Inn for we found the people
               uncivil &amp; the attendance very bad, besides our bed room’s being close, dirty
               &amp; altogether disagreeable. </p>
            <p>Monday 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> – We found on awaking that the wind was so
               directly favourable for <placeName ref="pl1673">Dublin</placeName>, that we</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 33v</fw>
            <p>agreed it was wisest not to defer sailing till the next day; as our first intention
               had been, purposing to see the <placeName ref="pl1719">Paris Mine</placeName> on this
               day; while we were waiting for the ferry boat I was delighted by a harp as sweet,
               played by a hand almost as <sic>skillful</sic> as the one at <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName>, &amp; listened with particular interest to one tune so
               feeling and so pathetic I know not how to describe it effects on me; I was alone, for
                  <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> was gone to see after the ferrymen &amp;
               my mind during this interval naturally dwelt on all those dear friends from whom the
               boundless ocean was so soon to separate me, to separate me indeed for but a very
               short time, but the idea of having the rolling sea between us was so new &amp; so
               strange as to appear to me quite frightful; with this idea in my head I fa<add place="above">n</add>cied the air in </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 34r</fw>
            <p>question seemed to correspond with my feelings, &amp; that it lamented the pain of an
               approaching exile; I was induced to ask the harper the name of it, &amp; found by his
               answer that the music had spoken truly, for it was a song made on the commencement of
               a long journey &amp; began with a farewell to the friends whom the traveller was
               about to leave. I quitted the harp and the Inn with regret to enter the ferry boat
               which soon carried us to the opposite shores of <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesea</placeName>; in the boat were several other passengers going by the
                  pacquet<note type="editorial">Medium-sized sailing ship used for transporting
                  passengers and freight.</note> of tonight to <placeName ref="pl1673">Dublin</placeName> &amp; I learnt that our resolution of sailing in it was the
               more necessary as no pacquet leaves the <placeName ref="pl1018">Head</placeName> on
               tuesdays a circumstance of which we were before ignorant. On landing we put both the
               horses in harness, &amp; made what expedition we could, &amp; reached <placeName ref="pl1018">Holy head</placeName>
                </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 34v</fw>
            <p>a distance of three &amp; twenty miles in three hours &amp; a half; this ride thro’
                  <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesea</placeName> had nothing to interest the island is
               rocky &amp; barren, &amp; tho’ unequal in its surface the hills are by no means high,
               &amp; there is very little wood, or any kind of cultivation throughout it, &amp; the
               population appeared to be <sic>proportionably</sic> scanty. <placeName ref="pl1018">Holyhead</placeName> is a vile town &amp; our Inn the <placeName ref="pl2830">Eagle &amp; Child</placeName> still viler; it is large but dull, dirty, &amp; ill
               attended; &amp; I was glad to escape from <add place="above">it</add> to go aboard
               the pacquet, the <sic>Besborough</sic>
                    <note type="editorial">One of a number of
                  vessels (see also the ‘Hillsborough’, below) providing a daily service between
                  Holyhead and Dublin, six days a week, in the later eighteenth century. See Justin
                  Merrigan and Ian Collard, <hi rend="italic">Holyhead to Ireland: Stena and its
                     Welsh Heritage</hi> (Stroud: Amberley Publishing, 2010), 16.</note>
               <persName ref="pe2083">Capt Goddard</persName>. We weighted anchor at twenty minutes
               before eight, &amp; I remained on deck for about an hour, tho’ <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> soon went down to his <sic>birth</sic>, when I went to take
               possession of mine I was surprized to find it so comfortable and slept in it for some
               hours very soundly; at a little after four in the morning the information that we
               were entering the bay of <placeName ref="pl1673">Dublin</placeName> urged me to get
               up; on going on deck</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 35r</fw>
            <p>I was surprized &amp; delighted by the sight of this fine &amp; truly beautiful bay,
               &amp; the still more glorious sight of the rising Sun; our vessel however made its
               way so rapidly that it was scarcely light enough to give us a full view of the shores
               &amp; at twenty minutes before five we found ourselves on irish ground, were soon
               after safe in the land pacquet a sort of long coach which conveyed us to <placeName ref="pl1673">Dublin</placeName> &amp; at six o’clock on the morning of
                  <sic>Teusday</sic> 25 we arrived without incident at M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wilkinson’s<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note> in <placeName ref="pl2900">Dawson Street</placeName>!, in a new country (at least to me) &amp;
               far away from my darling <persName ref="pe2064">boy</persName> &amp; you, my ten
               times dear <persName ref="pe2062">Eliza</persName>. I shall pass over, my dear
                  <persName ref="pe2062">Eliza</persName>, those days in which I have passed in
                  <placeName ref="pl0889">Ireland</placeName>, either at <placeName ref="pl2831">Bushy Park</placeName> or <placeName ref="pl2832">Terenure</placeName> in family
               circles or small parties, which you may suppose are pretty much</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 35v</fw>
            <p>the same as in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>: as my design is to paint
               nature’s varieties, or the performances of art, in their inanimate productions, &amp;
               not to trace the nice distinctions which mark the various features of men &amp;
               manners, &amp; which in countries so nearly connected cannot be very dissimilar:
               these therefore it would be contrary to my plan even were it within the scope of my
               abilities (which certainly it is not) to delineate. What however you would not wish
               me to omit, &amp; without which indeed my journal would be <sic>incompleat</sic> is
               the remarks I have made on those parts of our now united kingdom<note type="editorial">The Acts of Union between Britain and Ireland came into effect on
                  1 January 1801.</note> which I have had an opportunity of contemplating.
                  <placeName ref="pl1673">Dublin</placeName> itself as the capital city, as well as
               the first place I saw, claims to be first noticed: its situation as you must have
               heard is delightful, commanding in many parts a view of the</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 36r</fw>
            <p>enchanting bay,<note type="editorial">For contemporary views of Dublin, including the
                  bay, see Finola O’Kane, ‘The City of Dublin’, <ref type="http" target="https://www.bl.uk/picturing-places/articles/the-city-of-dublin">here</ref>
                    </note> that bears its name, &amp; every where surrounded by
               charming country: it is not however built as you may imagine, &amp; as I fully
               expected, immediately on the bay, if it were the beauty would be much heightened.
               Independently of its situation; I must own myself not much pleased with this capital:
               the best streets are far inferior to ours, &amp; the few squares do not merit
               comparison with those in <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> – <placeName ref="pl2833">Sackville Street</placeName> indeed is as wide; I think it is even
               wider than any we have, but it is not nearly so long, nor has it the grand &amp;
               striking appearance of <placeName ref="pl0961">Portland Place</placeName> &amp; some
               others. <placeName ref="pl2835">St Stephen’s Green</placeName> is the largest of the
               squares &amp; in point of extent is a very noble one; but the houses are not well
               built &amp; the inside is nothing but a large field with a walk round it – <placeName ref="pl2834">Merrion Square</placeName> is the</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 36v</fw>
            <p>most admired situation in <placeName ref="pl1673">Dublin</placeName>, &amp; from some
               of the houses you have a fine view of the bay, but the houses have not a handsome
               appearance on the outside, &amp; the middle of the square is also a sort of field.
               The new Square, as far as I could judge in its present unfinished state, were it in a
               better part of the town I should greatly prefer; it called <placeName ref="pl2836">Mountjoy Square</placeName>, the houses are better &amp; more regularly built,
               &amp; I was told the spacious inside was intended to be prettily planted. The great
               fault of all the Streets &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>: in <placeName ref="pl1673">Dublin</placeName> is the want of regularity in the <sic>heigth</sic>
               &amp; size of the houses &amp; a shabbiness in their external appearance which I do
               not know how to describe: this I am the more surprized at as the beauty of many of
               the public buildings show that the irish know &amp; can</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 37r</fw>
            <p>employ the beauties of Architecture. Of these admired buildings, of which they are
               very proud, I can make but a brief mention, as I had very little opportunity of
               contemplating them, &amp; saw them in so horrid a manner, as to bring home a very
               imperfect idea of them. The <placeName ref="pl2837">Lying <sic>Inn</sic>
                  Hospital</placeName> in Rutland Square is a very handsome one; one part of it is
               called the Rotunda which consists of one noble Saloon &amp; a set of fine apartments,
               elegantly fitted up, for almost every species of public amusement, like our Pantheon,
               but the profits are far more nobly applied to the support of the hospital: here
               masquerades are frequently given, of which the irish seem very fond.</p>
            <p>In <placeName ref="pl2838">
                        <sic>Colledge</sic> Green</placeName> Stands the
                  <sic>Colledges</sic> to which it owes its name, a building very
                  <sic>incompleat</sic> in <hi rend="superscript">its</hi> architecture &amp;
               design, having been often been added <sic>too</sic> &amp; altered</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 37v</fw>
            <p>since its erection by its foundress <persName ref="pe0357">Queen
                  Elizabeth</persName>
                    <note type="editorial">Trinity College Dublin obtained its
                  charter from Elizabeth I in 1592. For a contemporary view of the College, see <ref type="http" target="http://www.dublincity.ie/image/libraries/dg25b-trinity-college-dublin">here</ref>
                    </note>: upon the whole it pleased me extremely, tho probably my
               ignorance of architecture made many of its defects less offensive to my eyes than
               they would have been to more <sic>skillful</sic> ones. The appearance from the street
               is very noble to which the Provosts house adjoining it, which is a handsome stone
               building, adds very much: on passing thro the gateway you enter the first square,
               built principally of stone, in which are the Museum, Dining Hall Chapel &amp;
               Lecturing Hall; we however first examined the second square to which you pass from
               the first, this also is principally faced with stone &amp; consists of the students
               apartments, &amp; the Library;<note type="editorial">For a modern photograph of the
                  interior of the Long Room at Trinity College Library, see <ref type="http" target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Long_Room_Interior,_Trinity_College_Dublin,_Ireland_-_Diliff.jpg">here</ref>
                    </note> the latter is very handsome &amp; is supported by a
               colonnade of pillars: the </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 38r</fw>
            <p>inside is of great length floored with oak, of which wood the partitions for the
               books &amp; a handsome gallery above are made both of which are richly carved; the
               form &amp; stile of it are not very unlike Trinity Library at Cambridge;<note type="editorial">For a modern photograph of the Wren Library at Trinity College,
                  Cambridge, see <ref type="http" target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:WrenLibraryInterior.jpg">here</ref>
                    </note> but whether from the force of first impressions or any real
               inferiority of beauty it did not please me so much; &amp; the “learned dust” that
               every <add place="above">where</add> hung around it quite disgusted me. The
                  Chapel<note type="editorial">For a modern photograph of the chapel at Trinity
                  College, see <ref type="http" target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Trinity_College_Chapel,_Dublin.jpg">here</ref>
                    </note> was the next building we entered, it has been newly erected,
               &amp; is built opposite the Lecturing Hall, exactly on the same plan, with an elegant
               portico at the entrance: the inside is very beautiful, of a long shape &amp; about
               eighty feet high: opposite the entrance is the communion table &amp; immediately
               before it, a very pretty pulpit of carved oak, the pews, &amp; a gallery opposite</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 38v</fw>
            <p>the communion table are also of oak richly carved, the execution of which is more
               beautiful than any modern workmanship of the sort I have seen. Over the alter and the
               pews on one side are the windows over <add place="above">those on</add> the other are
               corresponding <sic>nitches</sic> of <sic>plaister</sic>, as for some reason I cannot
               they could not have windows all round; the bad effect however of these
                  <sic>plaister</sic>
               <sic>nitches</sic> is much lessened by a light festoon of crimson curtains very
               prettily hung over them, as well as over the real windows: the <sic>cieling</sic> is
               of <sic>plaister</sic> very richly &amp; handsomely ornamented. Immediately over the
               entrance is the gallery I before mentioned, in the middle of which is the organ the
                  <sic>cieling</sic> over the passage that leads to them is greatly admired for its
               elegance and simplicity: I scarcely ever saw so small a building that pleased me so
               much, as this Chapel, unless I except that at Greenwich,<note type="editorial">A
                  reference to the Chapel of St Peter and St Paul, Royal Naval College, Greenwich;
                  see <ref type="http" target="https://www.ornc.org/chapel#ck6Wo0qlpXzKexoU.97">here</ref>
                    </note> it is however a pleasing</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 39r</fw>
            <p>not a grand edifice. The Lecturing Hall<note type="editorial">A reference to the
                  Examination Hall at Trinity College, Dublin, built in the late eighteenth century.
                  For a modern photograph of the interior, see <ref type="http" target="https://www.tcd.ie/about/trinity/campus/image06.php">here</ref>
                    </note>
               opposite which we next visited is not worthy of any particular description, the
               inside is neat, &amp; hung with pictures of those who have been the benfactors or
               ornaments of the <sic>Colledge</sic>, among which is one of its founders in which I
               fancy the vanity of the “Virgin Queen,” was consulted rather than the productions of
               a strong likeness; it certainly has the <sic>stile</sic> of countenance that
               distinguishes all her pictures, but it appears to be the portrait of a much handsomer
               woman, than she is recorded to have been. The Dining Hall is a plain Apartment, not
               very much worth seeing hung also with portraits of those students, whose matured
               talents have reflected honor, on their education: tho’ we saw the kitchen below it, I
               do not think it necessary to describe the seven large stoves it contains, the spits
               that turned before them or the cooks that attended them.</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 39v</fw>
            <p>I must also be silent respecting the last object of our curiosity the Museum<note type="editorial">The present Museum at Trinity College, Dublin, dates from the
                  mid-nineteenth century. The museum as visited by Eade was located at Regent House;
                  for an early nineteenth-century view of the interior, see <ref type="http" target="The present Museum at Trinity College, Dublin, dates from the mid-nineteenth century. The museum as visited by Eade was located at Regent House; for an early  nineteenth-century view of the interior, see http://onlinecollection.nationalgallery.ie/objects/1854/the-old-museum-regent-house-trinity-college-dublin">here</ref>
                    </note>; for such was the poverty, &amp; <hi rend="underline">commonness</hi> of its <sic>relicks</sic> I could scarcely refrain from laughing
               at the care with which they were preserved: here however the dust did not offend me,
               for tho’ nothing in itself could be worse, it seemed not unwise to throw over their
               glasses a veil sufficiently thick to prevent too minute an examination of their
               contents. The whole <sic>Colledge</sic> was shown us with great attention &amp;
               politeness, by a friend of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wilkinson’s, <persName ref="pe2033">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Magee</persName>, one of the
                  <sic>Proffesors</sic>.</p>
            <p>The <placeName ref="pl2842">Parliament House</placeName> is nearly opposite the
               Colledge: I think you must have heard of the uncommon beauty of this elegant
               building, it is indeed truly admirable; that part which was the house of Commons,
               along which runs a lofty &amp; most noble colonnade is the most worthy of admiration;
               the House of Lords a circular</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 40r</fw>
            <p>edifice was added after its first erection, at one end of it, &amp; tho’ handsome in
               itself rather injures than improves the effect of the building as a whole. As I
               walked thro’ the magnificent suit of apartments which composed both &amp; saw the
               costly furniture, &amp; rich hangings [?torn] from them; I could not wonder at the
               regret many of the irish feel, on beholding this stately edifice, where once their
               chartered rights were guarded, &amp; their interests defended; dismantling of all
               that can reveal its former use &amp; splendour, &amp; converting into a National
               Bank: even those whose judgements approve the measures that decreed this change, may
               find their feelings &amp; their prejudices, turn in sorrow from the spectacle. </p>
            <p>The <placeName ref="pl2843">Four Courts</placeName>, (as it is called, for here the
               four courts of justice are held) is the last public building I shall mention, as I
               had no opportunity of seeing the <placeName ref="pl2844">Custom House</placeName>
               which I greatly regretted this is </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 40v</fw>
            <p>also an admired, &amp; handsome building, &amp; one that pleased me exceedingly, tho’
               it has, I think, one great defect, namely that the dome which crowns the center is
               much too low &amp; insignificant &amp; seems quite lost between the noble wings on
               either side – I cannot conclude this account of <placeName ref="pl1673">Dublin</placeName> without mentioning first its extent which is above two miles
               long &amp; one &amp; a half wide, or about a fourth part of <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> – &amp; secondly its river the <sic>
                        <placeName ref="pl2840">Liffy</placeName>
                    </sic>, which did it not run thro’ a capital city would
               surely have been of little note; nothing can be less deserving of the epithet of
                     “<sic>
                        <placeName ref="pl2840">Liffy’s</placeName>
                    </sic> limpid stream,”<note type="editorial">A quotation from Thomas Tickell’s narrative ballad ‘Lucy and
                  Colin’, published by the mid-1720s at least but reprinted throughout the
                  eighteenth century. See <hi rend="italic">Lucy and Colin, A Song</hi> (Dublin:
                  Pressick Rider and Thomas Harbin, 1725).</note> for ’tis narrow, sluggish &amp;
               muddy, &amp; scarcely merits to be called a river; the Canal is a much finer object.
               I do not expect my dear <persName ref="pe2062">Eliza</persName>, that all this will
               be very interesting to you &amp; I have written it rather to assist my own memory in
               future, than to amuse you; what, however, I have</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 41r</fw>
            <p>now to relate of a little tour into the county of <placeName ref="pl2841">Wicklow</placeName> is of a different nature, &amp; it so delighted me that I
               cannot but hope I shall be able to impart some of my pleasure to you even in
               recital.</p>
            <p>We left <placeName ref="pl2831">Bushy Park</placeName> about seven o’clock on Monday
               the 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> of May, our party consisting of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; Miss Wilkinson in a post chaise, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> [illegible] &amp; myself in a curricle, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ponsey Shaw his brother<note type="editorial">Probably a
                  reference to Ponsonby Shaw (1784-1871).</note>, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
               <sic>Burnard</sic> Shaw, his cousin<note type="editorial">Probably a reference to
                  Bernard Shaw (d. c. 1808).</note>, &amp; <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName>
               on horseback. We first ro<del>a</del>de thro’ some sweet country in which we had a
               number of charming Sea Views to the <placeName ref="pl2845">Scalp</placeName>, a most
               remarkable pass between two rocky mountains which appear to have been violently rent
               asunder; but whether by art or nature, or whether they were at their creation what
               they now are, is uncertain: the vulgar believe it the violent work of some outraged
               giant (for the belief of the former existence of these gigantic beings is universal
               among the poor in <placeName ref="pl0889">Ireland</placeName>) the learned dispute
               about it, &amp; leave the truth as deeply hidden as ever – On each side the mountains
               are covered with huge loose overhanging </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 41v</fw>
            <p>stones as at <placeName ref="pl1338">Penmaen Mawr</placeName>, but their height is so
               much inferior not so great (it appears to me) as a third that they are not nearly so
               tremendous. This singular pass conducts the road to the hills over which you must
               journey to the villages of <placeName ref="pl2896">Inneskerry</placeName>, where at
               an Inn not one whit superior to those in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>,
               tho’ so near <placeName ref="pl1673">Dublin</placeName>, we breakfasted: but tho’ our
               accommodation was poor, the bread &amp; butter was excellent, &amp; as we were pretty
               hungry we enjoyed it greatly. After this welcome meal was ended we took leave of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; Miss Wilkinson who went quietly on to <placeName ref="pl2897">Bray</placeName>, &amp; proceeded to <placeName ref="pl2846">Powerscourt</placeName>, the noble domain of <persName ref="pe2034">Lord
                  Powerscourt</persName>: here thro’ its beautiful walks we <sic>stroled</sic> for
               near an hour, uncertain whether to prefer those w<add place="above">h</add>ere the
               close imbowring shades shut out every sunbeam, or those which opened to the rich
               &amp; various prospects around; on one of these our choice at last rested; one path
               opened on a sweetly wooded glen &amp; caught a charming view of the <placeName ref="pl2847">Dargle</placeName>, a more exquisite spot can hardly be imagined.</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 42r</fw>
            <p>After a long ramble we obtained leave to see the house, but soon found its noble <add place="pl2847">exterior</add> had raised much too high our idea of its internal
               magnificence: its furniture &amp; decorations are quite unworthy of so fine a seat,
               &amp; there is but one fine apartment; the entrance Hall is indeed tolerably handsome
               but not sufficiently lofty; above it is the saloon which certainly is in itself a
               noble room &amp; fitted up with great taste, but it is the only one, the rest of the
               mansion is nothing more than a cheerful gentleman like house. From hence we had a
               lovely ride of about three miles to the celebrated Waterfall, called <placeName ref="pl2848">Powerscourt Waterfall</placeName>, which is part of the domain. this
               is believed to be one of the highest falls of water in the world it is precipitated
               from a <sic>heigth</sic> of 350 feet, &amp; must be very grand indeed when there is a
               good supply of water, the quantity to-day was very scanty, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Shaw said he had never seen so little; but in spite of this disadvantage I
               was delighted with it, &amp; could hardly prevail on myself to leave it; tho’ we
               passed </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 42v</fw>
            <p>a good while at its feet, allaying our again raised hunger from our basket of
               provisions &amp; our thirst from its pure streams. But with still greater regret did
               I afterwards quit the romantic <placeName ref="pl2847">Dargle</placeName> to which we
               next proceeded: this is a lovely glen which runs between two mountains wooded on each
               side entirely from their summits to where their roots sink in the river which runs
               along its bottom; this is the river which first falls from Powerscourt &amp; here
               finds a rocky bed, similar to that of the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName>:
               the woods on either side are almost wholly of oak, excepting a few ashes that seem to
               grow out immediately from the solid rocks, round which their roots twine in a manner
               altogether curious &amp; singular, yet far from wanting variety from being so nearly
               of oak <add place="above">it</add> has a richness, roundness &amp; incomparable
               beauty, that I know not how to describe, it reminded me of our favorite Green’s
               [?touches], but what pencil can produce the <sic>beautious</sic> forms, &amp;
               exquisite colouring of </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 43r</fw>
            <p>nature in scenes like this? here while my eye wandered over the lovely wood or
               watched the shining <del>waters</del> river forming innumerable little cascading
               falls, as its crystal waters dashed from rock to rock, or gleamed gently over the
               sometimes level bed; while my ear listened to its soothing music, &amp; my heart felt
               its every feeling open to delight, how could I not but wish my once
                  <sic>inseperable</sic> companion were enjoying <add place="above">it</add> with
               me, &amp; regret this lovely scene was one you would probably never see. Thro’ this
               sweet place we had walked as it is scarcely passable for any but horsemen or foot
               passengers, on leaving it we had an agreeable but short ride to the town of
                  <placeName ref="pl2897">Bray</placeName>, a pleasant clean place, consisting
               principally of white cabins (so the cottages here are called) &amp; some good
               gentleman’s houses – Here we rejoined M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; Miss
               Wilkinson, dined, &amp; spent a sociable evening, &amp; at night had comfortable
               lodgings.</p>
            <p>The next morning June 1.st the same party, namely <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName>, Myself, &amp; Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Robert,
               Ponsy, &amp; Burnard Shaw again set off in quest of new beauties. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wilkinson being too unwell to </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 43v</fw>
            <p>bear us company remained at the Inn with his sister. We had a sweet ride as far as
                  <placeName ref="pl2849">New town Mount Kennedy</placeName> to breakfast; this is a
               charming little village &amp; seemed formed to be the abode of quiet enjoyment, but
               its serenity was destroyed in the late rebellion by a desperate battle’s being fought
               within it.<note type="editorial">The Battle of NewtownMountKennedy, which formed part
                  of the 1798 United Irish uprising, took place on 30 May 1798.</note> After
               breakfast we proceeded immediately to the beautiful Glyn of the Downs belonging to
                  M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
               <persName ref="pe2084">Peter Le Touch</persName> who has a handsome <placeName ref="pl2898">house</placeName> at one end of the hill which commands a full view
               of the valley: the <sic>stile</sic> of this glen is similar to the <placeName ref="pl2847">Dargle</placeName>, but inferior in beauty the woods on each side
               being less rich in foliage, &amp; above all it wants the grand ornament of the river,
               the place of which is supplied by the high road; we had not time to enter the domain
               which M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Shaw told us was well worth seeing, but were
               obliged to content ourselves with the view of its beauties as</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 44r</fw>
            <p>present themselves to the road; these however [?few] wished conversation till the
               noble domain of Dunran, richly wooded, &amp; diversified with fine hills from which
               several extensive, variegated &amp; magnificent views are on one side presented;
               claimed our undivided admiration.<note type="editorial">For an approximate
                  illustration of the scene, at the Dunran estate in Wicklow, being described by
                  Eade in this passage, see <ref type="http" target="http://catalogue.nli.ie/Record/vtls000551046">here</ref>
                    </note> The sea
               which at every opening forms one <sic>of finest</sic> features of the scenery
               throughout the country of <placeName ref="pl2841">Wicklow</placeName> adds grandeur
               &amp; majesty to all the views from Dunran; but the sweetest prospect we had of it
               was from the window of an elegant little cottage orné<note type="editorial">A house
                  built in a rural setting to a consciously picturesque or rustic design, typically
                  with some decorative features such as ornate woodwork (OED).</note>, <add place="above">in</add> which we rested <sic>in</sic> for a short time, as we had
               walked over the domain; thro’ this arched window the sea formed the boundary of a
               most lovely prospect, &amp; is <del>of</del> itself bounded by the Welch Mountains
               which of a clear evening are distinctly seen; these sort of cottages are common on
               all the <add place="above">irish</add> seats, &amp; are in general fitted up with
               great taste; yet an english eye could</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 44v</fw>
            <p>not but observe, &amp; an english heart not but regret, that these were merely
               ornamental, &amp; that the obscure residences of the poor only disgrace, by their
               meanness &amp; misery those spots which on the estates of our nobles they would
               adorn, by imparting an air of cheerfulness, &amp; an idea of plenty &amp; content.
               When our time forbade a further stay at Dunran we continued our way to the <placeName ref="pl2899">Devil’s Glyn</placeName> the extent of our progress thro’ <placeName ref="pl2841">Wicklow</placeName>. This was one of the most admired spots in the
               county, &amp; was by many preferred to the <placeName ref="pl2847">Dargle</placeName>: it is a valley of the same sort running between a chain of woody
               mountains divided by a rocky &amp; impetuous stream; but it is longer, wilder, more
               various, &amp; is terminated by a fine water-fall, from which the river descends in
               one body more or less tremendous according to the supply of water; at this time it
               was very small.</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 45r</fw>
            <p>At present its beauty is under an eclipse, as most of the trees on one side have been
               cut down, &amp; those on the other much injured during the rebellion, it is said that
               age would shortly have produced as great a desolation, but it is to be regretted that
               they were not removed more gradually, as younger ones could be reared to supply their
               places as it must now be some years before its beauty can be recovered we saw it
               under an additional disadvantage resulting from the severity of the season, which had
               cut off many of the young shoots &amp; prevented the ashes in particular from putting
               forth their leaves, &amp; thus rendered the foliage of the remaining trees less
               luxuriant than it would otherwise have been; yet still it was a most delightful spot.
               As our morning’s entertainment had made us both hot &amp; tired (for we had walked
               thro’ the <placeName ref="pl2899">Devil’s Glyn</placeName>, as well as at Dunran) we
               found ourselves</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 45v</fw>
            <p>desirous of refreshment before we set our faces forward towards <placeName ref="pl2897">Bray</placeName>: we therefore seated ourselves on some rocks in the
               midst of the river (which is more rapid &amp; bold than the one in the <placeName ref="pl2847">Dargle</placeName>) to which we <sic>scambled</sic>, &amp; opened our
               basket of stores – Among these a bottle of port-wine, wore rather an inviting
               appearance to “thirsty souls,” but alas! we could find no glass to drink it from,
               &amp; to quaff it from the bottle was in many respects objectionable, particularly as
               being all men, save myself, some fears were felt least the last drinker should find
               his portion the reverse of Benjamin’s mess<note type="editorial">Biblical reference
                  (see Genesis 43:34) meaning the largest share or portion of something.</note>; but
               as no other scheme could be thought of, we should have fixed on this, but the
               gentlemen thinking it would be better if cooler plunged it into the stream for this
               purpose: in this operation the luckless bottle got a crack which the blushing water
               soon discovered, &amp; on examination so</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 46r</fw>
            <p>large a fracture was perceived that the danger of splinters obliged us to give up all
               idea of sipping from the broken vessel: in this emergency necessity that far-famed
               mother of invention suggested an expedient to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Shaw
               which I would give you seventy guesses to discover without the same instructress:
               this was no other than <persName ref="pe2063">William’s</persName> snuff box; as it
               was tortoise shell it was soon completely purified, &amp; all parties agreed that the
               wine tasted excellently from it: this little incident excited much mirth &amp; never
               was a merrier or pleasanter morning enjoyed. </p>
            <p>We returned nearly by the same <sic>rout</sic> as we had come, some of which with
               restive horses or an <sic>unskillful</sic> driver, would not have been without
               dangers, as I was situated I was not at all alarmed as I had full reliance on M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Shaw’s coachmanship, but I suspect my Aunt Hannah would
               have thought</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 46v</fw>
            <p>that we went not only “near enough,” but also too near some unguarded precipices.
               Near <placeName ref="pl2849">Newtown Mount Kennedy</placeName> we altered our
                  <sic>rout</sic> a little to see a very pretty house &amp; grounds called the
               Hermitage, it now belongs to two old bachelors<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note> which I was quite provoked at for how could they feel one
               half of the delights so sweet a place could call forth? ’tis a small wild glen where
               if art has interfered at all, it is impossible to distinguish her footsteps from
               those of nature; at the end of it is a sweetly pretty fall of water from three
               different rocks, which appears like three distinct cascades; I cannot describe to you
               half the graces of this romantic little spot, &amp; I hated to think that perhaps its
               owners might visit it only as a scene <sic>calculate</sic> “to lull the weary to
               profound repose,”<note type="editorial">A quotation from Book II of Beattie’s, The
                  Minstrel (1774); see II: 10.</note> when it might “bid all the fine attuned
               emotions live,”<note type="editorial">Probably quoted from Ann Radcliffe, <hi rend="italic">The Romance of the Forest</hi> (1791); see <hi rend="italic">The
                     Romance of the Forest</hi>, ed. Chloe Chard (Oxford: Oxford University Press,
                  1986), p. 262.</note> &amp; call forth the best </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 47r</fw>
            <p>feelings of the heart – It was now so late that we were forced to hurry home without
               seeing any other of the curiosities of the place, but with all the haste we could
               make we found on arrival at <placeName ref="pl2897">Bray</placeName> that we had kept
                  M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wilkinson waiting an hour &amp; a half for his
               dinner, for which we were very sorry; here we had as famous fare &amp; the same
               comfortable lodgings as the day before.</p>
            <p>On Wednesday morning June 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> we returned to <placeName ref="pl2831">Bushy Park</placeName> by the town of Old Connaught, from a hill
               behind which we had <add place="above">a</add> lovely sea view; we turned a little
               out of the high road to breakfast with M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> John Lees who
               married the eldest Miss Shaw, at a pretty little hired cottage, which they have for a
               summer residence. After passing an hour or two pleasantly with them, we went on
               quietly to <placeName ref="pl2831">Bushy</placeName> where I heard with great joy ,
               that on our <sic>outsett</sic> we had narrowly escaped <hi rend="superscript">seeing</hi> the dual<note type="editorial">The dual concerned Catholic
                  Emancipation, which Jones supported and Musgrave opposed. See <hi rend="italic">Authentic Detail of an Affair of Honour between William Todd Jones, esq., and
                     Sir Richard Musgrave</hi> (Dublin, 1802).</note> fought between <persName ref="pe2035">Sir Richard Musgrave</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe2036">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Jones</persName>; imagine </p>
            <p> </p>
            <p>f. 47v</p>
            <p>what would have been my horror had we passed <persName ref="pe2037">L.<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Ely</persName>’s at the morning of its taking
                  place,<note type="editorial">Probably a reference to Rathfarnham Castle, a
                  sixteenth-century castle in South Dubin, remodelled in the eighteenth century; see
                     <ref type="http" target="http://www.heritageireland.ie/en/dublin/rathfarnhamcastle/">here</ref>
                    </note> instead of ten minutes before it as we did.</p>
            <p>Thus my dear <persName ref="pe2062">Eliza</persName> ends all I have to relate
               concerning our séjour in <placeName ref="pl0889">Ireland</placeName>, as the short
               time we staid after this, was spent like the former part of our visit, in home
               circles or sociable parties, &amp; we saw nothing more of the country.</p>
            <p>On Friday evening the 4th of June after dining &amp; supping in <placeName ref="pl2900">Dawson Street</placeName>, we took leave of the kind M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>s Wilkinson from whom I parted with regret; at twelve
               o’clock, we entered the land Pacquet &amp; in about an hour found ourselves on board
               the water one: the <sic>Hilsborough</sic>
                    <note type="editorial">One of a number of
                  vessels (see also the ‘Bessborough’, above) providing a daily service between
                  Holyhead and Dublin, six days a week, in the later eighteenth century. Merrigan
                  and Collard, p. 16.</note> Capt.<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> Shaw<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note> had the honor of receiving us as passengers,
               which got <sic>under weigh</sic> about half past one. We immediately took possession
               of our <sic>births</sic> in which we slept very comfortably for some hours &amp; left
               them for the deck at nine the next morning. </p>
            <p>Saturday 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> June. The wind was</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 48r</fw>
            <p>low, &amp; the sea calm, so that we made but little way, &amp; we might have enjoyed
               the softness of the morning greatly but for those <sic>disaigree</sic> feelings which
               in a greater or less degree attend most young sailors: fortunately a refreshing
               breeze in the right point sprung up about half past eleven which greatly improved our
               situation in all respects, both as to bodily ills (which indeed we had but slightly
               suffered from) &amp; as to our prospect of approaching land; soon after the
                  <placeName ref="pl1018">Head</placeName> faintly appeared in the horizon, &amp; we
               visibly gained upon <add place="above">it</add> ’till a little after three, when as
               we were joyfully anticipating a speedy landing a sudden crash over our heads
               fearfully reminded <add place="above">us</add> we were not yet secure of obtaining
               it: this proceeded from the fall of our topmast, which a sudden squall took
                  <sic>compleatly</sic> in half, happily the rigging prevented its falling quite
               down, or probably my head would have received it</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 48v</fw>
            <p>&amp; my dear little <persName ref="pe2064">boy</persName> been obliged to find in
               you a mother, as well as an aunt, for I was immediately under it: from this however
               as from all other perils I was preserved I hope to worthy ends. This accident
               retarded us a little, but at half past four we landed, after a passage of fifteen
               hours, &amp; most happy did I feel, in reflecting that the sea no longer divided me
               from the objects of my fondest affection [.] At the horrid Inn of the <placeName ref="pl2830">Eagle &amp; Child</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl1018">Holyhead</placeName> we were obliged to remain ’till morning, but the company of
               one of our fellow passengers, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lewis<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note>, a friend of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
               Wilkinson’s amused some of our otherwise weary hours.</p>
            <p>Sunday 6 June – We breakfasted at <placeName ref="pl1018">Holyhead</placeName>, &amp;
               afterwards proceeded by our former road to <placeName ref="pl2850">
                        <sic>Gwyndw</sic>
                    </placeName>, a good deal of rain had fallen during the night
               &amp; the morning was refreshing &amp; pleasant, but in</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 49r</fw>
            <p>the country I found as much singularity &amp; as few charms as before – <placeName ref="pl2850">Gwyndw</placeName> has no other house than the Inn which we found
               very clean &amp; nice &amp; kept by very civil people – Our accommodations indeed
               were not splendid as we were obliged to content ourselves with a bed-chamber as our
               drawing-room scarcely larger than a good light closet. Even for this we were indebted
               to the civility of S<hi rend="superscript">ir</hi> John Corden<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note>, who had bespoken it for us the night before for the house
               was <sic>compleatly</sic> full of company – Here we meant to have passed the rest of
               the day, knowing we could not see the <placeName ref="pl1719">Paris mine</placeName>,
               one object of our curiosity, ’till the morrow: but our landlady strongly advised our
               proceeding to <placeName ref="pl1967">Amlwch</placeName> a village about a mile
               beyond the mines &amp; as they said ten from <placeName ref="pl2850">Gwyndw</placeName> but we thought it not more than eight. This advice after
               dining at <placeName ref="pl2850">Gwyndw</placeName> we resolved on following &amp;
               thought the country for the first </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 49v</fw>
            <p>few miles rather better cultivated &amp; prettier than any we had seen in
                     <sic>
                        <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesea</placeName>
                    </sic> , but as we approached
               the mine <del>all</del> this quite disappeared &amp; it soon became a scene of entire
               desolation, for the sulphuric smoke from the kilns entirely destroys vegetation
               wherever its baleful influence reaches. This ill effect is now much lessened by a
               method discovered within these few years of confining the smoke which becomes
               valuable from turning into flour of brimstone. <placeName ref="pl1967">Amlwch</placeName> is a wretched place inhabited solely by miners, &amp; the Inn
               tho’ called Ty Mawr (or the great house) is a mighty poor place but as we got a
               tolerable bed we were not disposed to complain. </p>
            <p>Monday June 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> – We procured a person at <placeName ref="pl1967">Amlwch</placeName> to shew them to us, &amp; went immediately after
               breakfast to see the celebrated copper mines of Paris &amp; Mona: it is a curious
               &amp; interesting sight but one that I cannot at all </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 50r</fw>
            <p>describe, &amp; must therefore refer you to some of the clear &amp; scientific
               accounts that have been published of them; we were unfortunate in our day of visiting
                  <add place="above">them</add> for it was a holiday (Whit Monday) and there was not
               one man at work, which is the most entertaining part of the whole to see; however we
               were made to understand the manner of working them very clearly. We spent an hour
               &amp; a half in exploring the various wonders of the place, &amp; then returned to
                  <placeName ref="pl2850">Gwyndw</placeName> where however we only took a
                  nooning<note type="editorial">I.e. rest taken around noon.</note> &amp; then
               retraced our way to <placeName ref="pl1563">Bangor Ferry</placeName>. The first part
               of our ride appeared quite as uninteresting as we had before thought it, excepting
               that a number of holiday makers whom we met in all parts gave it a good deal of
               animation – nothing can be more <sic>drole</sic> than to see a number of Welch people
               on such occasions whose utmost finery never exceeds a bed-gown of lindsey
                  <sic>wolsey</sic>
                    <note type="editorial">Linsey-woolsey, a textile material woven
                  from a mixture of wool and flax.</note> of a </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 50v</fw>
            <p>deeper blue than ordinary or an immense beaver hat of a more glossy appearance. As we
               drew nearer to the Ferry our ride became extremely beautiful, for tho’ our
               fore-ground acquired no new charms a most noble mountain scene opened in the
               distance, as travelling this way the Carnavonshire mountains rise in unspeakable
               grandeur before you – the summits of these lofty mountains were many of them lost in
               the clouds &amp; nothing could surpass the beauty of their appearance, as their
               majestic heads now burst upon our view, &amp; now shrouded themselves again in
               obscurity; I recognized among them my old friend <placeName ref="pl1338">Penmaen
                  Mawr</placeName> with great pleasure. At <placeName ref="pl1563">Bangor
                  Ferry</placeName> we dined, &amp; while that meal was preparing, I took a
                  <sic>strole</sic> into the Inn garden to admire the fine <placeName ref="pl1564">Straits of Menai</placeName>, which I thought still more lovely than when I saw
               them before, &amp; I was sorry to leave the contemplation</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 51r</fw>
            <p>of them for the miserable bed room where our dinner was prepared, this Inn also being
               full of company. After dinner we proceeded towards <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> &amp; had for the first mile &amp; half the same fine
               mountain scenery as in the morning, but when we turned off into the Caernarvon road,
               the prospects entirely changed; the inspiring mountains that proudly swelled beyond
               the clouds &amp; seemed like Satan to be boldly venturing “not far off Heaven, in the
               precincts of light,”<note type="editorial">A quotation from John Milton, <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>, III: 88.</note> sank suddenly away, &amp; a
               scene of sweetness, softness &amp; beauty succeeded that I want words to describe. On
               our right the setting Sun shed a glowing radiance over the island of <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName> (which here seemed well wooded, for we looked on
                     <sic>
                        <placeName ref="pl1965">Plâs Newyd</placeName>
                    </sic> the seat of the
                  <persName ref="pe1230">Earl of Uxbridge</persName>) &amp; over the lovely
                  <placeName ref="pl1564">straits of Menai</placeName> which flowed with a calmness
               so exquisitely soft as to inspire feelings almost heavenly throughout the whole ride
               they were alternately seen in all their</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 51v</fw>
            <p>gently beauty or <hi rend="superscript">obscured</hi> with ever-varying
                  <sic>lovliness</sic> by the woods that grow on their banks; on our left a gentle
               ascent covered with the richest cultivation, or the most enchanting woods
                  <sic>compleated</sic> a scene more bewitchingly sweet than any my imagination had
               ever formed, &amp; to add one more charm to the ride the evening <sic>odeurs</sic>
               heightened by some lately fallen rain gave out their most fragrant perfumes. This
               captivating ride was terminated by our arrival at the Hotel at <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>, an inn of the very first order for
               cleanliness &amp; civility, &amp; even superb accommodations, I was never at a better
               any where.</p>
            <p>Tuesday June 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> – We took a post chaise to the lakes of
                  <sic>Llanberris</sic> about five miles from <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>, <del>but</del> the road is very bad, &amp; I scarcely
               think our horses could have gone <hi rend="superscript">it</hi>, at least not without
               hazards. for a little way on our first setting out, the country was cultivated &amp;
               pretty, but soon a rough unadorned </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 52r</fw>
            <p>boldness became its chief characteristic, as we approached the lake this character
               became more marked &amp; nothing could exceed the ruggedness &amp; barrenness of the
               craggy &amp; towering mountains whose summits now rose with most awful grandeur “yet
               even in a scene thus desolate &amp; rude,”<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note>
               the hand of industry had fertilised a few small spots which smiled indeed as “gardens
               in the wilderness”. When we alighted from the chaise the lake of <sic>
                        <placeName ref="pl1527">Llanberris</placeName>
                    </sic> was at our feet,<note type="editorial">For a contemporary view of Llanberis Lake, by J.M.W. Turner, see
                     <ref type="http" target="https://www.tate.org.uk/art/artworks/turner-view-across-llanberis-lake-towards-snowdon-d04180">here</ref>
                    </note> a turn in the road had hid it from us till that moment, the
               spot was wild &amp; rude in the extreme, yet not without a savage nobleness, which
               charmed even from its apparent disdain of charming; a few wretched huts compiled of
               stones laid one on another without any cement &amp; some even, as far as I could see,
               without any windows, <sic>where</sic> scattered on the edge of the lake, which in
               this first part is narrow, &amp; shallow: here we waited for some time expecting the
               arrival of the boat that was to row us down the stream; surrounded by all the women
               &amp; children in the neighbourhood who all seemed </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 52v</fw>
            <p>merry &amp; happy notwithstanding their extreme poverty. The boat at length arrived,
               but we still waited some time for its unloading, for it was a miserable crazy thing
               employed to bring down slates from the quarries in the mountains: a woman &amp;
               afterwards a boy whom we took in from a hut a little further up the lake rowed us
               &amp; our postilion accompanied us as interpreter &amp; guide. The first or Lower
               Lake they told us was two miles and a half long but there seemed to be great
                  confu<del>s</del>sion in their accounts of it &amp; we thought it more: we could
               not learn its breadth <del>as</del> but we thought it in parts nearly three quarters
               of a mile, but this as it winds among the mountains is very various,
                  <del>sometimes</del> contrasting or expanding as they approach to, or recede from
               each other: The mountains called the Snowdon chain rises from the very edge of the
               lake on each side, heaped one above another in every possible form &amp; of every
               description: some with savage suddenness displaying their rugged sides without a
               trace </p>
            <p> </p>
            <p>f. 53r</p>
            <p>of vegetation, others (&amp; these the most numerous) not less wild, but rather less
               rugged, covering themselves with a scanty verdure; &amp; a few; tho’ but a few,
               adorning themselves with small tufted woods: on our right the tremendous <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName> himself reared his awful head far above the rest,
               &amp; in unrivalled sublimity showed himself lord of the surrounding country: This,
               like many of the welch scenes, so wholly surpasses not description only, but even
               imagination, that I despair of giving you the faintest idea of it. As we rowed up the
               lake, the clouds rested on the heads of the mountains &amp; threatened us with rain,
               but happily they gradually rolled away &amp; we had a heavenly day. At <placeName ref="pl1309">Dolbadarn castle</placeName>, some ruins of which still remain, &amp;
               which stands near the spot where the upper &amp; lower lakes, mingle their
               transparent waters; we landed to see the Waterfall called Pennant Mawr, &amp; had a
               very pleasant walk to it: an opening in the mountains leave in this place some meadow </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 53v</fw>
            <p>land, on which cattle w<del>h</del>ere grazing, &amp; the ascent to the fall was by
               no means tremendous. Pennant Mawr (or the great hollow) is an extremely pretty fall,
               &amp; amply repaid our exertions to see it: at times it must be very beautiful but as
               we saw it the water tho’ swelled by the late rains, was not plenteous enough to make
               it a grand fall, &amp; we were told, that a few days before it had been nearly dry.
               After rambling with much delight for near an hour, we returned to our boat, but
               determined not to row up the upper lake, which is much the shorter of the two, as our
               time was becoming precious &amp; we could see the whole extent of it from our landing
               place. <persName ref="pe2085">Bingley</persName> in his tour mentions a very
               remarkable spot near the village of <sic>
                        <placeName ref="pl1527">Llanberris</placeName>
                    </sic> (which stands at the head of the upper lake)
               which he calls the Devil’s <sic>Kitchin</sic>,<note type="editorial">See William
                  Bingley, <hi rend="italic">A Tour round North Wales, performed during the summer
                     of 1798</hi> (London, 1800): ‘Amongst the rocks, at the bottom, I observed a
                  number of circular holes of different sizes, from a few inches in diameter to two
                  feet or upwards, which have been formed by the eddy of the torrent from above.
                  These hollows are frequently called by the Welsh people, Devil’s pots, and from
                  this circumstance, the place itself is sometimes called the Devil’s kitchen.’ (I,
                  211).</note> could we have attain’d any information concerning it, we should have
               proceeded up the Lake, but our postboy, &amp; rowers knew of no such place, so we
               were obliged to give </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 54r</fw>
            <p>it up, tho in the afternoon we learnt from the man at the <placeName ref="pl1309">Castle</placeName> that we were near it &amp; might have seen it with ease, a
               piece of information which unfortunately came too late to benefit us. In returning
               our views were not quite so grand as they had been before, because in going up the
               lake the mountains <sic>encrease</sic> in loftiness every moment, &amp; of course in
               returning they sink in the same proportion; yet we did not therefore less enjoy our
               row; for the Sun had, by this time dispersed every cloud, &amp; the heads of every
               mountain &amp; that even of the mighty <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>
               were distinctly visible in all the fantastic variety of their forms shooting into the
               pure ether above! Of all the beautiful, the sublime, the astonishing scenery we have
               yet seen, this claims the undoubted pre-eminence, &amp; we returned to <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> almost overpowered by its grandeur.</p>
            <p>After dinner we again went out to examine the curiosities of <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>
                </p>
            <p> </p>
            <p>f. 54v</p>
            <p>which we had not had time to visit before, to the <placeName ref="pl1566">Castle</placeName> the most noted of these we first directed our steps – It is a
               very noble ruin, one of the finest if not the finest in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>; &amp; is in much higher preservation than that of <placeName ref="pl1530">Conway</placeName>: as a ruin it did not please me so much, but it
               conveys higher ideas of feudal magnificence, &amp; is so perfect as to give a
               tolerable idea of the interior of an ancient mansion: we were shown the room in which
               the unfortunate <persName ref="pe2086">Edward the second</persName> first beheld the
               light: it is a chamber in what is called the <placeName ref="pl2387">eagle’s
                  tower</placeName>, to the top of which we ascended &amp; had a fine view of the
               surrounding country. The old man who shewed it to us was a most venerable figure well
               suited to be its inhabitant, he explained &amp; expatiated on the remains with great
               pride &amp; shewed a great deal of intelligence not only in this but in the
               information he gave us respecting the surrounding country, he was formerly a guide up
                  <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>. Returning </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 55r</fw>
            <p>home we walked along the Quay<note type="editorial">For a contemporary image of
                  Caernarfon castle in its quayside setting, by Thomas Rowlandson see <ref type="http" target="http://interactive.britishart.yale.edu/art-in-focus-wales/165/caernarfon-castle">here</ref>
                    </note> which is built at the foot of the Castle, &amp; seems to be
               the “boulevards” of the place. <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> is a
               fine old town, &amp; has several pleasant houses; its situation on the lovely
                  <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai Straits</placeName> renders it truly delightful –
               &amp; its admirable Inn the <placeName ref="pl1567">Hotel</placeName> certainly
               recommends it still further to travellers; with this Inn I have only one fault to
               find, it has a very bad harper. </p>
            <p>Wednesday 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> – If you had never been in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> my dear <persName ref="pe2062">Eliza</persName>,
               &amp; had never contemplated the rich varieties of its beauties, I should fear you
               would not credit what I have to relate of this day; would never believe after all I
               have said of <placeName ref="pl1527">Llanberris</placeName>, that the ride between
                  <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> &amp; <sic>
                        <placeName ref="pl1518">Begglelert</placeName>
                    </sic> (pronounced Bethgelert) surpassed even that in
               its wonderful sublimity; yet it is true that all we have seen does not equal what our
               wondering eyes have this day beheld – The road is cut thro’ the mountains, <add place="above">&amp; is</add> generally good, but as a great part is at the foot of
               them, I think it must sometimes be </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 55v</fw>
            <p>impassable from the overflowing waters; it runs thro’ the heart of Caernarvonshire,
               the noblest country of <placeName ref="pl1221">North Wales</placeName>, &amp;
               presents scenes of such surpassing grandeur as no pencil could <sic>pourtray</sic>,
               no tongue describe, no imagination combine. Stupendous mountains rose on all sides of
               us, of every form, tint, &amp; variety, &amp; with <del>as</del>
               <hi rend="superscript">such</hi> endless profusion as to mock all description; while
               in the meantime we were riding thro’ a deluge of rain, which tho’ it gave us some
               personal inconveniences, added considerably to the sublimity of the scene; for from
               every hollow &amp; from every rocky passage where it could find a channel, it poured
               its resistless waters, in foaming torrents down the mountain’s sides, forming
               innumerable waterfalls of unthought of beauty. At [?Nantmillill]about six
                  <sic>mile</sic> &amp; a half from <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>
               we passed a very pretty cascade which the rain had now made really </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 56r</fw>
            <p>beautiful, &amp; soon after what appeared to us a fine lake, tho’ as <persName ref="pe2085">Bingley</persName> calls it a pool, it is probable the same cause had
               swelled it much beyond its usual extent.</p>
            <p>When we arrived at <sic>
                        <placeName ref="pl1518">Begglelert</placeName>
                    </sic> I was
                  <sic>compleatly</sic> wet through; &amp; the Inn was so full we could scarcely
               procure a room to shelter ourselves in, &amp; found a bed was a thing quite
               unattainable, tho’ to proceed any further was impossible; to stay at the inn was
               therefore a case of necessity, &amp; we resolved to lodge as we could. We regretted
               the rain on one account extremely as it effectually prevented <persName ref="pe2063">William’s</persName> ascending <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>, which
               he meant to have done from this place; instead of which we were obliged to remain in
               a miserable dark little room in which we could scarcely accommodate ourselves &amp;
               luggage, &amp; be half poisoned with a smoky chimney, &amp; a villainous turf fire;
               yet here the bitter was not without the sweet, for we had a most capital dinner. When
               this meal was ended we perceived </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 56v</fw>
            <p>that the skies had shut their flood-gates for the present, &amp; we took advantage of
               this circumstance to walk down to <placeName ref="pl1525">
                        <sic>Pont
                     Aberglasllyn</sic>
                    </placeName> about 1 ½ <sic>mile</sic> distant. Nothing could
               be finer than this walk along the Banks of the <sic>
                        <placeName ref="pl1518">Begglelert</placeName>
                    </sic> river, which foamed &amp; dashed along from rock
               to rock, with the most resistless impetuosity: this was the finest sight of the sort
               we had seen for tho’ these rocky mountain streams are <del>to be seen</del>
               <hi rend="superscript">frequent</hi> in all parts of <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>, all we had before passed were so shrunk with the long drought,
               as to be quite insignificant when compared to this in its present agitated state. The
                  <placeName ref="pl1525">pont Aberglasllyn</placeName> is a most romantic bridge
               thrown over the river where it forms the noted salmon leap, &amp; the situation
               between ridges of majestic mountains, &amp; over this beautiful stream is uncommonly
               striking: with the salmon leap we were both disappointed: it is formed by a
               semicircular ridge of rocks that run across the bed of the river </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 57r</fw>
            <p>which falls perpendicularly down them for several feet – but it has so great a
               regularity as to make you fancy it, rather a work of art, than a sport of Nature:
               here I could not but envy the superior strength &amp; agility of my dear companion
               who climbed one of the noble mountains that rise at the foot of the bridge, while I
               was obliged to remain contentedly at the bottom; &amp; to give you some idea of their
                  <sic>heigth</sic> when he was so far above me as scarcely to be discernible he
               appeared to himself hardly to be on high ground so much more lofty were the mountains
               above him.</p>
            <p>On our return to the Inn we found that the departure of a lady &amp; gentleman, who
               were making a walking tour had left a very nice sitting room &amp; a bedroom at
               liberty for us; to the latter we soon retired but I <del>soon</del>
               <hi rend="superscript">quickly</hi> found it could not be called a place of rest; for
               nothing could be more disgustingly dirty, smaller or more <sic>compleatly</sic>
               comfortless; which together with the roaring </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 57v</fw>
            <p>of the wind as it swept between the mountains, &amp; of the pelting of the rain which
               soon began with its former fury kept me awake nearly all night: I find my dear
                  <persName ref="pe2062">Eliza</persName> I am not a thorough traveller yet.</p>
            <p>Thursday 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> – The rain still continuing this morning we
               were reluctantly obliged to give up our intention of visiting the <placeName ref="pl2901">
                        <sic>Vale of Gwynnant</sic>
                    </placeName>, which is impassable for
               carriages; &amp; pursue our homeward journey. The first part of our road was
               extremely bad, &amp; in parts dangerous; but as we drew near <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan-y-Bwlch</placeName> it greatly improv’d as it is new making: this a little
               diverted our attention from the contemplation of scenes of grandeur &amp;
               magnificence equal to those of yesterday, in one of which we though we had quite bid
               adieu to. We were now travelling again in Merionethshire having come over <placeName ref="pl1525">Pont Aberglasllyn</placeName> (or <add place="above">the</add> Devils
               Bridge) which separates</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 58r</fw>
            <p>this county &amp; Caernarvonshire; &amp; as we advanced farther into it, the
               mountains became less tremendous &amp; lost a part of their savage wildness &amp;
               woody glens thro’ which romantic streams generally flowed over beds of rocks, gave
               variety of beauty to our ride. <placeName ref="pl2903">Tan-y-Bwlch Inn</placeName>
               <sic>were</sic> we dined is situated in the beautiful Vale of Festiniog near a fine
               seat of <persName ref="pe0939">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Oakley</persName>’s
               called <placeName ref="pl1570">Tan-y-Bwlch Hall</placeName> – After dinner the heavy
               showers that had fallen at intervals during the whole morning were dispersed &amp; we
               ventured to explore the country in a walk. From the roads we had chosen we perceived
               on a woody eminence above us what appeared to be a pretty fall of water, &amp; having
               scrambled to it, found it to be one of those temporary streams which the rain
               occasioned to fall from the over hanging mountains; &amp; which ran glittering down
               among the wood in a very sweet manner in numberless cascades; from thence we
               discerned a very good </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 58v</fw>
            <p>path <add place="above">thro the wood</add> which led us back again nearly to our
               Inn. From hence to <placeName ref="pl1517">
                        <sic>Dolgelle</sic>
                    </placeName>, our next
               stage, the ride was far inferior in grandeur &amp; beauty of every sort, the
               mountains decreased in magnitude considerably &amp; were barren without the rude
               wildness &amp; sublimity to which we had lately been accustomed; but one noble sight
               made amends for this – About 5 miles from <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelle</placeName> at a bridge built over one of the finest of the mountain
               rivers we had passed; having been previously instructed by our landlord at <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan-y-Bwlch</placeName>; we got out of the chair &amp; having with
               some difficulty &amp; after numerous unsuccessful applications, found a wooden
                  <sic>leged</sic> Welchman who understood enough of English to comprehend the
               object of our enquiries, &amp; who undertook to be our guide; We proceeded with him
               to see the noble cataract <sic>
                        <placeName ref="pl1572">Doly Myllyn</placeName>
                    </sic>
               about ½ a mile from the road on the right. Our walk to it was the most </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 59r</fw>
            <p>romantic that can well be imagined, thro’ a wild wood &amp; along the foaming stream
               that after falling magnificently down, the cataract, rushes along ’till it reaches
               the bridge on the road &amp; passes under that to the bed of the river before
               mentioned; forming all the way cascades of such variety &amp; grandeur that I mistook
               some of them for the <sic>
                        <placeName ref="pl1572">Doly Myllin</placeName>
                    </sic>
               itself. Greatly superior to them all did I, however, find it when we arrived at its
               feet; the situation is most delightful &amp; the surrounding scenery the most
               appropriate that fancy could desire; the water forms a sort of double cataract, &amp;
               falls in two perpendicular sheets of great width, &amp; from considerable
                  <sic>heigths</sic>; the lovely cascades that are formed by it as it dashes in
               sparkling columns from one of these stupendous falls to the other might alone have
               gratified our curiosity: &amp; upon the whole the magnificence &amp; the variety of
               the fall &amp; the beauty </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 59v</fw>
            <p>of the situation made us prefer the cataract of <placeName ref="pl1572">Doly
                  Myllin</placeName> to all the wonders of this kind we had seen; seeing it too as
               we did with a more than ordinary supply of water. The rest of our evening ride had
               little remarkable in it, excepting the dangers that we ran in passing for some miles
               along the precipice that hung over the river on our left, but our horses were now
               accustomed to Welch scenes, &amp; as the road is wide &amp; very excellently kept,
               they brought us all safely to the Golden Lion at <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelle</placeName>: a pretty good Inn for <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>.</p>
            <p>Friday 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> – We held a consultation whether we should
               visit <sic>Pistil</sic> y [?bain] the most noted cataract of <placeName ref="pl1221">North Wales</placeName>, or whether <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName>
               should ascend <placeName ref="pl1866">Cader Idris</placeName> the second in magnitude
               of its mountains; we could not spare time for both: as he had been disappointed of
               realising the summit of <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>, &amp; we had
               seen so many interesting falls</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 60r</fw>
            <p>of water, the latter was agreed on; &amp; in spite of a high wind &amp; clouded sky
               he set out as soon as we had breakfasted, on a little welch pony provided by his
               guide. This guide <persName ref="pe2089">Robert Edwards</persName> by name, a spare
               [?“Tantony- Bobus-”] like figure of seventy nine years old, gave us a curious paper
               specifying all <del>t</del>his titles &amp; employments in which among others he
               stiles himself “Guide General &amp; Grand Expositor of all the curiosities of
                  <placeName ref="pl1221">North Wales</placeName>; &amp; Knight of the most
               eccentric (&amp; perhaps happy) Order of Thoughtless Inexplicable”. His humble
               manners, however, accorded better with his appearance, than with these sonorous
               titles – During <persName ref="pe2063">William’s</persName> absence I employed myself
               in writing, &amp; regretted extremely that a harp stood unused in my
                  <sic>parlor</sic>, but I could get no one who could call forth its power of
               “discoursing most eloquent music;” this I was the more sorry for as I had not heard
               it, since its chords had been so miserably struck at <sic>
                        <placeName ref="pl1565">Carnarvon</placeName>
                    </sic>; since we had left that city, our</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 60v</fw>
            <p>journeying had been thro’ roads too little frequently to repay any harper for
               constant attendance at the Inns, &amp; our near approach to <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> made it improbable we should be much oftener regaled by them;
               but as I could not awaken its melody myself I was obliged to be contented with its
               silence.</p>
            <p>
                    <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> returned sooner than I expected having had
               a very cold ride, &amp; but indifferent success in seeing the prospects for the
               clouds usually hung so heavy in the sides of the mountain as to obscure the whole
               scenery below, this together with the high wind which scarcely permitted them or
               their <sic>poneys</sic> to keep their feet, obliged him to give up ascending the
               highest point of the mountain which is sixteen yards above that which he gained: the
               sun before they descended kindly dispersed the clouds for few minutes, &amp; opened
               to their view the extensive &amp; various scenery below, bounded in one</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 61r</fw>
            <p>part by the sea, which with the pretty village of <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName> seems immediately at their feet; but the gathering mists
               soon closed again upon them, &amp; they were forced to return home without any
               further gratifications. At half past four o’clock we resumed our journey by ascending
               a long &amp; steep mountain commanding a view of the pretty &amp; well cultivated
               valley in which <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelle</placeName> is built; of this we
               soon lost sight, &amp; entered on a bleak &amp; barren scene, which in its turn
                  <del>yeilded</del>
               <hi rend="superscript">gave place</hi> to mountains covered with fine verdure, which
                  <sic>yeilded</sic> pasture to numberless flocks. Here the road lies between two
               ridges of high mountains &amp; is cut <del>along</del>
               <hi rend="superscript">thro’</hi> the sides of one of them, running for a long way
               along the edge of a precipice that is really frightful: I do not know which is the
               worst, this or that we passed last night for neither have the slightest guard, not
               even a bush to make the danger less startling; but this promises a safer fall on the </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 61v</fw>
            <p>green herbage beneath, while that would have plunged us into the rough &amp; dashing
               current of a rocky river. We were both rather glad when from this mountain pass we
               descended <add place="above">again</add> into the vallies which continue with little
               variation to <sic>
                        <placeName ref="pl1513">Dinasmouthy</placeName>
                    </sic> a poor city,
               where we had been recommended not to stop, as we should meet with very indifferent
               accommodations, we had reason (judging by appearances) to think this advice was good,
               &amp; therefore left this town, the last in Merionithshire, &amp; entering
               Montgomoryshire proceeded a mile &amp; a half farther to the <placeName ref="pl1512">Cross Foxes</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl1515">Mallwyd</placeName>; this Inn
               stands a little out of the high road &amp; we missed the turning to it, but did not
               lose much time as we soon met with a man who put us in the right way; it is indeed
               easily found as there is a direction post at its entrance which says to “Mallwyd,”
               but we were ignorant that the </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 62r</fw>
            <p>village was so called. We had had several showers during our ride, &amp; a very heavy
               one fell as we were at tea, this I was very sorry for as the <placeName ref="pl1512">Cross Foxes</placeName> stands in so sweet a valley I longed to take a
                  <sic>strole</sic> in it but as we were forced to remain within it was some
               consolation that the Inn tho’ small was very clean, &amp; in all respects extremely
               comfortable. </p>
            <p>Saturday 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. We intended to have taken a stage before
               breakfast but the heavy rain with which the morning opened determined us to wait an
               hour or two in hopes of more <sic>favorable</sic> skies; soon after our breakfast we
               found their appearance less threatening; but we had a showery ride the whole of the
               morning – At an Inn called <placeName ref="pl1511">Cannon’s Office</placeName> about
               12 miles from <placeName ref="pl1515">Mallwyd</placeName> we were obliged to take a
               nooning while Boyo had a shoe fastened which had become loose: to this place &amp;
               from hence to <placeName ref="pl1514">Llanfair</placeName>, &amp; <placeName ref="pl0741">
                        <sic>Welch Pool</sic>
                    </placeName> our rout was <sic>intirely</sic>
               among pleasant vallies which succeeded each other</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 62v</fw>
            <p>the whole way; these for the most part boast a considerable share of beauty, &amp;
               some fertility &amp; cultivation &amp; the verdant mountains that surround them
               appear to afford such excellent pasture to the sheep, as proclaims a richness of
               soil, that would well repay the industry that further improved it: but husbandry does
               not appear to be a <sic>favorite</sic> employment of the welch, who seem to possess
               but little activity. When we passed thro’ <placeName ref="pl1514">Llanfair</placeName> (a small town) we found it was market day, the first welch
               market we had ever seen: it was not a scene of much animation for the buyers &amp;
               sellers were both looking on with the carelessness of uninterested spectators, &amp;
               tho’ it was nearly two o’clock we met many people with articles for sale only then
               going to it. From <placeName ref="pl1514">Llanfair</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0741">Welch Pool</placeName> the road is in most miserable order, &amp;
                  <add place="above">we</add> thought ourselves lucky in reaching the latter place
               without accident; indeed the man whom we sent for to examine the chair</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 63r</fw>
            <p>told us it was a piece of good fortune by no measure common. <placeName ref="pl0741">Welch Pool</placeName> is rather a large town, but a place of no business &amp;
               apparently very dull: we dined at The <placeName ref="pl1510">Royal Oak
                  Inn</placeName>, in a large room which I thought dirty &amp; disagreeable, &amp; I
               was not sorry to leave it, &amp; pursue our journey to <placeName ref="pl2917">
                        <sic>Montgomory</sic>
                    </placeName>, to which place we had a sweet ride
               proceeding equally from the charms of the country, &amp; the beauty of the evening.
               As we advanced nearer to <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> the sinking
               mountains gradually lost their sublimity, &amp; around <placeName ref="pl2917">Montgomory</placeName> they can only rank as very high hills; but a richer soil,
               &amp; more fertile fields, repay the inhabitants of these lower lands for the loss of
               the magnificent, but unprofitable beauties of <sic>
                        <placeName ref="pl1565">Carnarvon</placeName>
                    </sic> and <sic>Merionith</sic> shires. The approach to
                  <placeName ref="pl2917">Montgomory</placeName> on this side is very
                  <sic>stricking</sic>, the shattered ruins of the old <placeName ref="pl2920">Castle</placeName> picturesquely situated on a rugged rock forms the fore-ground
               on the right, relieved by a wooded hill behind it, in the middle but less </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 63v</fw>
            <p>forward to the view is the town &amp; on the left appears the <sic>steple</sic> of
               the <placeName ref="pl2922">parish church</placeName> surrounded by trees: the town
               disappoints you on entering, for its first appearance promises more beauty, than it
               possesses; &amp; the <placeName ref="pl2921">Dragon Inn</placeName> presents us with
               nothing more inviting than we had left at <placeName ref="pl0741">Welch
                  Pool</placeName>. At this town English becomes became again familiar to our ears,
               &amp; very little welch is spoken. </p>
            <p>Sunday 13. We were now so near <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>, which we
               entered about six miles &amp; a half beyond <placeName ref="pl2917">Montgomory</placeName>, that <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> began to
               suppose his journey at an end &amp; to think so much of home &amp; his boy, I could
               not prevail on him to delay our journey of this day ’till after morning service, a
               circumstance my dear <persName ref="pe2062">Eliza</persName> that you may be sure I
               greatly regretted: yet I own it was soon <sic>forgotton</sic> when we set off after
               breakfast with a cloudless sky, &amp; brilliant sunshine, which illumined our lovely
               ride to <placeName ref="pl2918">Bishop’s Castle</placeName>, the scene of beauty
               &amp; plenty</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 64r</fw>
            <p>however were fully calculated to call forth the warmest sentiments of gratitude &amp;
               devotion, &amp; my heart fervently felt them. Nothing could form a stronger contrast
               than the country thro’ which we past this morning &amp; that we had contemplated
               during the middle of the last week – there all was wild, <sic>aweful</sic>, &amp;
               sublime, here all was fertile, soft, &amp; beautiful. The encircling hills that still
               rose in every side of us were rich in cultivation, adorned with majestic woods, or
               decked with verdant pastures, which afforded a delicious herbage to the numerous
               flocks, that enlivened them; below the “vallies thick with wavy corn”<note type="editorial">Slightly misquoted from Matthew Prior’s long poem ‘Carmen
                  Seculare, for the Year 1700’; see <hi rend="italic">Poems on Several
                     Occasions</hi> (1709), p. 156.</note> smiled with more luxuriant fertility; not
               one barren spot, tho’ ever so small deformed the prospect, but as far as the eye
               could reach on all sides, riches &amp; abundance met its view; while the sweeping
               shadows of the hills diversified the prospect. Unfortunately the bad conditions of
               the roads, deprived <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> of </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 64v</fw>
            <p>half the pleasures of this ride, for he was obliged to keep his eyes so fixt on the
               horse, he scarcely dared raise them to behold the beauties that surrounded him. At
               the <placeName ref="pl2923">Castle</placeName>, at <placeName ref="pl2918">Bishop’s
                  Castle</placeName> (a neat, pleasant Inn) we had the cheapest “snack” (an irish
               word) possible cold lamb, <sic>sallad</sic>, bread, cheese, butter &amp; ale, with a
               supply of hay &amp; corn for the horses for three &amp; ninepence: after which we
               continued our way to <placeName ref="pl1706">Ludlow</placeName>, thro what we were
               told was the best road, tho’ without this information we might have mistaken it for
               the worst either in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> or <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>; this is the more shameful, as there is no natural
               impediment to its being excellent, &amp; it might be rendered such at a trifling
               expense, &amp; without much <sic>labor</sic>. This again deprived <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> of the pleasure of contemplating the rich country
               thro’ which we passed, which exhibited the whole way the same enchanting features of
               luxuriant beauty as that I had so much admired in the former part of the morning. On
               our arrival at <placeName ref="pl1706">Ludlow</placeName>, <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> was so fatigued with driving, &amp; I with jotting that </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 65r</fw>
            <p>we could not move ’till after dining when we <sic>stroled</sic> thro’ the town which
               we admired very much, as it is remarkably clean, neat, &amp; built very prettily: I
               remembered its being a <sic>favorite</sic> town of mama’s, &amp; therefore expected
               to be <del>as</del> much pleased with it, &amp; I was not at all disappointed. The
                  <placeName ref="pl1611">Castle</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl1859">Church</placeName> are both objects of curiosity; the former like that at
                  <placeName ref="pl2917">Montgomory</placeName>, is situated on a rock, &amp; is a
               handsome ruin, at the foot of it are some pleasant public walks commanding a view of
               the river <placeName ref="pl2924">Teme</placeName>, a clear but not very beautiful
               stream. The <placeName ref="pl1859">Church</placeName> is a handsome gothic
               structure, worthy both in its exterior &amp; interior of admiration, but we both
                  <sic>prefered</sic> the former. After seeing them we returned to our Inn the
                  <placeName ref="pl2925">Angel</placeName> where we remained the rest of the
               evening: it is a very good Inn, &amp; after our late accommodations appeared even
               elegant.</p>
            <p>Monday 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. We left <placeName ref="pl1706">Ludlow</placeName>, before breakfast, the morning was very fine, &amp; we had a
               delightful ride to <placeName ref="pl2919">Tenbury</placeName>, tho’ the country lost
               by degrees, the extended prospects</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 65v</fw>
            <p>&amp; commanding hills that had adorned our journey of yesterday: on leaving
                  <placeName ref="pl1706">Ludlow</placeName> we entered <placeName ref="pl1653">Herefordshire</placeName>, just crossed <placeName ref="pl1021">Shropshire</placeName> again at <placeName ref="pl2926">Burford</placeName>,
               &amp; then made our entrée into <placeName ref="pl1284">Worcestershire</placeName>,
               in which county is <placeName ref="pl2919">Tenbury</placeName> where at the
               remarkably pretty Inn of the <placeName ref="pl2927">Swan</placeName> we enjoyed a
               capital breakfast. Here I took a pleasant little walk by myself as <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> was engaged with the horses; after this we
               proceeded to the <placeName ref="pl2928">Hundred House Inn</placeName> a most
                  <del>ap</del>
                    <hi rend="superscript">un</hi>pleasant <del>Inn</del>
               <hi rend="superscript">place</hi> where we waited the country having become more
               &amp; more <sic>inclosed</sic> every mile &amp; soon offering nothing to the view but
               orchards &amp; small Hop-grounds – Leaving this ugly Inn we went on to <placeName ref="pl0806">Worcester</placeName>, &amp; found the road as we approached this
               city grew flat &amp; insipid to the greatest degree our eyes so long accustomed to
               scenes of sublimity &amp; grandeur could scarcely look on the <placeName ref="pl2929">Malvern Hills</placeName> with complacency, those hills which my father &amp;
                  M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>s. [?Bell]<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note> climbed with so much pride appeared so low &amp;
               insignificant</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 66r</fw>
            <p>that I felt angry at their presumption in assuming any celebrity; yet their outline
               is in truth bold &amp; irregular &amp; travelling this way into <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> instead of out of it, we should probably have
               joined our voices in their praise: the “river <placeName ref="pl1226">Severn</placeName>” also, noted for its silvery stream appeared to our eyes, from
               which the picture of the mountain torrents had not yet faded, to flow in a sluggish
               &amp; thick current; &amp; we agreed that it would be necessary for us to visit
                  <placeName ref="pl0806">Worcester</placeName> again before we could speak with
               impartial justice of its environs. In spite of warning <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> would go to the <placeName ref="pl2930">Hop Pole
                  Inn</placeName>; to whisper the truth in your ear my dear <persName ref="pe2062">Eliza</persName>, I suspect his curiosity led him thither against his judgement;
               as he had a floating idea that the guests were waited on by lasses in livery instead
               of the most awkward manikins; he was however disappointed &amp; punish’d for this was
               not the case, tho’ I believe it is true of one of the other Inns, &amp; we found our
               accommodations </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 66v</fw>
            <p>comfortless, &amp; the attendance “le derniere détestable.” After dinner we
                  <sic>stroled</sic> about the town with which we were much pleased it is large,
               clean, cheerful &amp; in all respects well built: here for the first &amp; only time
               we heard some military music, &amp; the town was full of soldiers, a sight which tho’
               a few months ago so common, is already growing rare: before our return to the
                  <placeName ref="pl2930">Inn</placeName> we visited the <placeName ref="pl2931">Cathedral</placeName> with the outside of which I was not much pleased, but the
               interior is very beautiful consisting of several isles of the most perfect gothic
               arches; there is also a very pretty <placeName ref="pl2932">Chapel</placeName> called
               Prince Alfred’s, &amp; in it, as well as throughout the Cathedral are numerous fine
               old monuments many of which are admired; but <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> had so great a horror of them I was afraid he would quite
               affront the poor verger, who ran over their histories ’till he was </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 67r</fw>
            <p>nearly out of breath, yet spite of all his rapid <sic>eloquotion</sic> found his
               tongue less nimble than his auditor’s feet: as I have no passion for reverend
               archbishops in stones, or noble barons with their seven brave sons &amp; as many of
               our daughters who formed of the same durable materials have knelt in constant prayer
               for the last eight hundred years; I own I was not sorry to escape from them also.</p>
            <p>On Tuesday 15 As soon as we had breakfasted we went to <persName ref="pe2093">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Burslem</persName>’s at <placeName ref="pl2933">Hanbury</placeName> about [blank space] miles from <placeName ref="pl0806">Worcester</placeName>. <persName ref="pe2093">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                  Burslem</persName>’s <placeName ref="pl2934">Parsonage</placeName> is a very
               pretty white house, pleasantly situated; &amp; from it is a walk sheltered by trees,
               up a number of steps to the <placeName ref="pl2935">church</placeName>; which is very
               handsome &amp; built on a hill where it appears to great advantage; the inside has
               been newly repaired, &amp; correspondents in neatness &amp; even in ornament to the
               out; it is certainly the prettiest &amp; most </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 67v</fw>
            <p>handsome country church I ever saw, &amp; its pastor is not a little proud of it:
               with him &amp; his family we passed a very pleasant day, &amp; slept under their
               “hospitable roof” with great comfort after being so long lodged at Inns. </p>
            <p>Wednesday 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.We took a long walk with M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>s Burslem before our
               return to <placeName ref="pl0806">Worcester</placeName> &amp; went over <placeName ref="pl2936">Hanbury Hall</placeName>, a seat of <persName ref="pe2094">L:<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Exeter</persName>’s with them: it is an old place
               belonging to the family of his first wife, but is now much in decay as he has not
               inhabited <add place="above">it</add> for some years when in good order it must have
               been a pretty place enough, but would never have been very <sic>stricking</sic>.
               Leaving our kind hosts at <placeName ref="pl2933">Hanbury</placeName> we returned to
                  <placeName ref="pl0806">Worcester</placeName> in time to see [?Fl/H]eight &amp;
               Bar’s Pottery before dinner; this is a simple but very amusing manufactory, the only
               art of </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 68r</fw>
            <p>which consists in mixing the clay, which is always done by one of the partners: their
               porcelain is clear &amp; good but I think I have seen finer even of English
               production, &amp; their patterns want taste &amp; variety. After dinner we gladly
               bade farewell to the <placeName ref="pl2930">Hop-Pole</placeName> &amp; had a sweet
               ride to the village of <placeName ref="pl2937">Broadway</placeName>: the country
               indeed was only “indifferent pretty;” but the evening was extremely fine, &amp; the
               bean-fields in full blossom, flung the most exquisite perfume around us all
                  <sic>they</sic> way. We slept at the <placeName ref="pl2938">White Hart
                  Inn</placeName>, which is exceedingly clean &amp; comfortable, &amp; w<add place="above">h</add>ere we had excellent attendance. </p>
            <p>Thursday 17. When we awoke this morning the idea of our near approach to <placeName ref="pl1613">Blenheim</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl1347">Oxford</placeName>
               those objects of universal admiration scarcely entered our minds, we were within a
               hundred miles of home a distance now appearing almost </p>
            <p> </p>
            <p>f. 68v</p>
            <p>nothing, within a hundred miles of all we loved, &amp; of our sweet <persName ref="pe2064">boy</persName>; Oh! how at this recollection did every other sink
               away! how exquisite must <add place="above">have</add> been the charms of any object,
               that after so long an absence, apparently doubles in length by the extent of country
               we had travelled, could <add place="above">have</add> allured us willingly to
                  <del>stop</del>
               <hi rend="superscript">retard</hi> our return for an hour! Happily for <del>the</del>
               <hi rend="superscript">our</hi> future feelings, which would no doubt have been those
               of regret if we passed these far-famed spots without notice; (of mine at least, for
                  <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> had seen them before) our horses could
               not travel as fleetly as our minds to them a hundred miles was of some consequence,
               was a distance that would require long intervals of rest in journeying over; &amp; as
               we were obliged to consult their convenience, we went quietly on an early stage to
                  <placeName ref="pl2939">Moreton</placeName> to breakfast,</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 69r</fw>
            <p>at the <placeName ref="pl2940">White Hart</placeName>, apparently a passable good
               Inn. Neither this stage nor the next to <placeName ref="pl1943">Woodstock</placeName>
               offered much to interest us, &amp; as soon as we arrived at the <placeName ref="pl2941">Bear</placeName> at the latter we ordered a phaeton to visit
                  <placeName ref="">Blenheim</placeName>: these carriages are kept for this express
               purpose here &amp; I suppose at the other Inns. The entrance to this noble Park is
               magnificent, &amp; the whole ride thro’ it, presents scenes of continual beauty &amp;
               majesty: even to my eyes (now spoilt for all that art, or even nature except in her
               highest walks can offer) they appeared worthy of all their celebrity, &amp; far
               surpassed every other similar scene I have seen. After we had rode over the Park we
               walked thro’ the gardens which quite delighted me, &amp; which I <sic>prefered</sic>
               beyond comparison to those at <placeName ref="pl2821">Stowe</placeName>. The house is
               rather a heavy</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 69v</fw>
            <p>pile of building, but has a stately appearance; of its interior magnificence I could
               not judge, for <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> had seen it before; &amp;
               assured me it was not worth the trouble of going over it: whether he was right or
               wrong I know not, but I found not difficulty in <sic>yeilding</sic> to his wishes of
               non-inspection as fine furniture &amp; fine apartments never afford me much pleasure.
               On our return to the <placeName ref="pl2941">Bear</placeName> we had an excellent
               dinner, &amp; afterwards <sic>stroled</sic> about <placeName ref="pl1943">Woodstock</placeName>, &amp; admired the [?cullery] ’till we were quite fatigued;
               the glove trade seemed less flourishing than usual, for we found great difficulty in
               procuring the small supply we wished for – It was nearly dusk when we came in to tea
               soon after which, we sought &amp; obtained the calm blessing of repose. </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 70r</fw>
            <p>As I have hitherto been particular in mentioning the counties we have touched on, I
               must not forget to say that on leaving <placeName ref="pl2937">Broadway</placeName>
               we entered Gloucestershire &amp; at the Four Shire Stone about ten miles beyond we
               quitted it for Oxfordshire.</p>
            <p>Friday 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> – We had a pleasant ride this morning (which
               was remarkably fine) to <placeName ref="pl1347">Oxford</placeName> before breakfast,
               &amp; took this first meal very comfortably at the <placeName ref="pl1555">Star</placeName> which seemed to be an excellent Inn; &amp; when we had finished
               it we took <sic>took</sic> a man from the Inn to shew us the most remarkable
                  <sic>colledges</sic> &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>: The first we visited was
                  <placeName ref="pl1549">Christ Church</placeName> w<add place="above">h</add>ere
               there is a large gallery of fine pictures by the ancient masters<note type="editorial">A reference to Christ Church Picture Gallery, which holds an
                  important collection of Old Masters; see <ref type="http" target="https://www.chch.ox.ac.uk/picture-gallery/christ-church-picture-gallery">here</ref>
                    </note>; many of these I should liked to bestow a much longer time
               on, than our <sic>liesure</sic> would allow &amp; I reluctantly left them to follow
               our conductor to the hall, which is large &amp; handsome &amp; hung round (as is
               often the case) with</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 70v</fw>
            <p>portraits of eminent men who have sprung from the colledge. We then ascended to the
               library which is also <del>a</del> large <del>one</del>, consisting of two stories
               &amp; built of Norway oak which has a solid &amp; venerable appearance: this
                  <sic>colledge</sic> is an ancient &amp; fine one, but I saw little in it to
               please, altho I traversed it with interest from considering it was here our dear
                  <persName ref="pe2064">William</persName> would probably acquire all the “academic
               lore” he will one day I hope possess. From hence we passed to the <placeName ref="pl1547">Radcliffe Library</placeName> an elegant circular building with which
               I was greatly pleased: we exhibited ourselves “selon l’usage” on the leads, &amp; had
               from them a very fine view of this beautiful city, which gratified my extremely –
               With the <placeName ref="pl1553">Bodleian Library</placeName> I was much disappointed
               having somehow acquired an idea of its being a very beautiful as well as large</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 71r</fw>
            <p>repository of the works of the learned; I suppose I was mistaken in imagining it to
               be esteemed such, at least it appeared to me quite the reverse, &amp; the old ceiling
               painted all over with the arms of the University I thought positively ugly; its size
               was also inferior to my expectations &amp; I was surprized how its 200,000 volumes
               could all find places; particularly as so much space is occupied by the pictures, of
               which I admired some very much, but was most struck by a noble statue in brass<note type="editorial">For a modern photograph of the bronze statue of William Herbert
                  at the Bodleian Library, see <ref type="http" target="https://www.geograph.org.uk/photo/5810633">here</ref>
                    </note> of
                  <persName ref="pe2095">William Earl of Pembroke</persName> the graceful ease of
               which cannot be surpassed. We next, I believe, visited <placeName ref="pl2943">
                        <sic>Magdelen</sic> Chapel</placeName> with which I was delighted: the
               entrance is lighted only by painted glass windows, the greater part of which have
               been lately executed by <persName ref="pe2080">Egerton</persName>, in one
                  <sic>color</sic> a dark brown; they are extremely beautiful &amp; cast a chastened
               gloom over the chapel which adds an inexpressible awe to the inexplicable
               feelings</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 71v</fw>
            <p>of mingled gratitude, devotion &amp; piety which it is impossible not to experience
               while gazing on the exquisite picture by Guida [?] over the communion table; of our
               Saviour bearing his cross; the patient anguish, the dignified resignation, the
               “something not of this earth,” that seemed breathed over the whole figure, made it
               appear “no work of mortal hand;” a more touching performance imagination cannot
               conceive. The <placeName ref="pl2942">New <sic>Colledge</sic> Chapel</placeName> was
               the last object of our curiosity; it is I think in all respects well worthy of
               admiration but the celebrated window painted by <persName ref="pe0927">Jervais</persName> from a design of <persName ref="pe1162">Sir Joshua
                  Reynolds</persName>, is certainly its most beautiful ornament. the upper part
               represents the Nativity &amp; the lower (divided into seven compartments) the
               christian &amp; cardinal virtues; I <sic>prefered</sic> the figures designed for the
               christian graces, but could not decide in</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 72r</fw>
            <p>my own mind, whether the group so sweetly figuring Charity, or the enchanting
               personification of Hope delighted me most.<note type="editorial">For modern
                  photographs depicting the West Window of the chapel at New College, see <ref type="http" target="http://www.therosewindow.com/pilot/Oxford-new-col/Ww-Frame.htm">here</ref>
                    </note> After seeing this window I no longer hesitated to allow the
               superiority of <persName ref="pe0927">Jervais</persName> to Girton, but perhaps he
               owes it more to the noble design from which he copied than to his own excellence. We
               just passed thro’ the <placeName ref="pl1549">Christ Church</placeName> &amp;
                     <sic>
                        <placeName ref="pl1554">Magdelen</placeName>
                    </sic> Walks, which are pretty
               enough, but not equal to <placeName ref="pl2944">Clare Hall Piece</placeName> at
                  <placeName ref="pl2871">Cambridge</placeName> nor did any single thing at
                  <placeName ref="pl1347">Oxford</placeName>
               <add place="above">delight me as much</add> as The <placeName ref="pl2945">Kings
                     <sic>Colledge</sic> Chapel</placeName> &amp; Trinity Library there, yet as a
               whole I infinitely prefer this to its sister University, its <sic>colledges</sic> are
               altogether much handsomer, &amp; more advantageously situated; indeed I can imagine
               nothing finer in its kind than the High Street where so many of them stand. I felt
               some regret at not entering <placeName ref="pl2946">University
                  <sic>Colledge</sic>
                    </placeName>, tho’ assumed it contained nothing worthy of
               notice, but age &amp; my veneration for its</p>
            <p> </p>
            <p>f. 72v</p>
            <p>founder, the noble Alfred,<note type="editorial">University College was long thought
                  to have been founded by King Alfred in the 870s. In reality it was founded as a
                  result of a bequest left by William of Durham (d. 1249).</note> would have made it
               an object of curiosity to me, &amp; I could not look at it without interest. After
               seeing all this variety of objects I returned to our Inn, with my head in
                  <sic>compleat</sic> confusion, which I could not get rid of while eating an
               excellent nooning of which some pretty good ice formed a part; not till we arrived,
               after a pleasant ride thro “mediocre” country to <placeName ref="pl2947">Dorchester</placeName> where at the quiet, comfortable, but unassuming Inn of the
                  <placeName ref="pl2948">White Hart</placeName> we <sic>stoped</sic> &amp; dined.
               From hence to <placeName ref="pl2949">Henley on Thames</placeName> the country is
               very pretty, particularly <add place="above">the</add> latter part of the stage: I
               was rather disappointed in <placeName ref="pl2949">Henley</placeName> as I had heard
               much of its beauties; but with <hi rend="underline">
                        <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> eyes</hi> it would probably have pleased me more. We had a
               very dull room at the <placeName ref="pl2950">Red Lion</placeName>, tho it must have
               many <add place="above">that are</add> pleasant as it fronts the <placeName ref="pl1389">Thames</placeName>; our windows indeed looked on the river, but we
               were on the ground floor, &amp; had also to complain of very indifferent</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 73r</fw>
            <p>attendance, ascribable probably to our humble equipage as we were now in courtly
               regions. As the evening was fine we walked after ten along <placeName ref="pl1389">Thames</placeName>’s “flower-<sic>enameled</sic> meads” till it was nearly dark
               watching the waters stealing down their waveless current in undisturbed tranquillity:
               with feelings far different from those called forth by the roaring torrents of the
                     <sic>
                        <placeName ref="pl1518">Begglelert</placeName>
                    </sic> river – where our
               minds <hi rend="superscript">experienced</hi> the highest elevation as “looking above, below,
               around us, we saw that all was great, yet felt within us that <sic>interlectual</sic>
               principle that was greater still;” <note type="editorial">Probably a reference to
                  Harriet and Sophia Lee’s <hi rend="italic">Canterbury Tales</hi>; see ‘The
                  Officer’s Tale’, <hi rend="italic">Canterbury Tales. Volume the Third</hi>
                  (London: G. G. and J. Robinson, 1797), p. 40.</note> that noble principle that
               from contemplating the most magnificent of nature’s works, could ascend still higher
               to the adoration of its Almighty Author. Here indeed <sic>reflexion</sic> taught us,
               all that made this far-famed river the merited subject of british Song, the just
               object of british enthusiasm; but these immediate <sic>feeling</sic> explained all
               that made it, the <sic>sourse</sic> of admiration.</p>
            <p>Saturday June 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> – This morning we left <placeName ref="pl2949">Henley</placeName> early, &amp; breakfasted at </p>
            <p> </p>
            <p>f. 73v</p>
            <p>The <placeName ref="pl2951">King’s Arms</placeName>, Maidenhead Bridge: an Inn most
               sweetly situated on the banks of the <placeName ref="pl1389">Thames</placeName>: the
               morning was fine &amp; we enjoyed our ride exceedingly, for the country is extremely
               pretty the whole of this stage: We were not disposed to give the same report of the
               next to <placeName ref="pl2952">Hounslow</placeName>, as every mile grew
                  <sic>flater</sic> &amp; more dusty: on arriving there we immediately ordered a
               post chaise, &amp; hastened on to <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>; to our
               impatient fancies the miles of this last stage seemed to lengthen as we advanced; the
               thoughts of near-approaching <add place="above">home</add> filled our hearts, &amp;
               the country offered no charms to our view that could for a moment divide our
               attention: At length we arrived at [illegible], &amp; from thence, I in his chair
               with him, &amp; <persName ref="pe2063">William</persName> on horse-back soon found
                  our<del>selves</del>
               <hi rend="superscript">way</hi> to <placeName ref="pl2863">Clapton</placeName>, &amp; once more
               embraced our dear <persName ref="pe2064">boy</persName>! the feeling of that moment
               you must, my <persName ref="pe2062">Eliza</persName>, fancy, for I cannot
               describe!</p>
            <p> </p>
            <p>f. 74</p>
            <p>And now my most beloved Sister farewell, I finish my little journal of a most
               delightful tour with regret because in finishing it I conclude a long imaginary
               conversation with you; which has possessed many charms for me – May you find some few
               in it also, assured that to contribute to your slightest pleasures is always among
               the first of mine.</p>
            <p>
               <persName ref="pe2030">Mary Anne Eade</persName>
                </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>