<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0023">
    <teiHeader type="w">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Anne Lister's diary, tour of North Wales 11-27 July 1822
                    <date>1822</date></title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Transcribed with an Introduction by Kirsty McHugh and edited by Elizabeth
                        Edwards</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement/>
                        <repository/>
                        <idno/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>

                <p>
                    <pb n="42"/>
                    <fw>[f. 42]</fw> Saturday 13 July<lb/> [Code: Two kisses last night, one almost
                    immediately after the other, before we went to sleep and one just before getting
                    up this morning I felt better, but was so shockingly low last night I cried
                    bitterly but smothered it so that <persName ref="pe2175">M–</persName> scarcely
                    knew of it. At any rate, she took no notice, wisely enough. I told <persName ref="pe2175">M–</persName> before we got up of my <hi rend="superscript">proper</hi> regard for and correspondence with <persName ref="pe2176">Miss
                        MacLean</persName> and <persName ref="pe2175">M–</persName> told me of the
                    gentlemanliness &amp; agreeableness of Mr Powis who, it seems, might interest
                        <persName ref="pe2175">M–</persName> more than duly had her heart no object
                    but <persName ref="pe2177">C–</persName>, with whom she has had no connection
                    these four months.] Not down to breakfast till 11 – settling 1 thing or other –
                        <persName ref="pe2175">M–</persName> went with me to the stables to see
                    Percy &amp; the gig &amp; we then (leaving my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName>) went to inquire about servants – walked a little on the
                    walls <hi rend="superscript">&amp;</hi> up &amp; down the <placeName ref="pl1537">rows</placeName> &amp; did not come in till 1 \({40\over 60}\)
                    – then, perhaps luckily for us, all in a bustle &amp; <persName ref="pe2175">M–</persName> off at 2 \({1\over 4}\).<note type="authorial"><persName ref="pe2175">M</persName> gave me fifteen pounds to place to her
                            <unclear>aunt</unclear></note> &amp; We were off in \({1\over 2}\) hour
                    &amp; got here (the <placeName ref="pl3086">King's Head</placeName>, new hotel,
                        <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> patronized by <persName ref="pe0954">Lady Eleanor Butler</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe0957">Miss Ponsonby</persName>) in 4 \({1\over 2}\) hours <hi rend="superscript">about 7</hi> including the \({1\over 2}\) hour we stopped at the church
                    gate at <placeName ref="pl0792">Wrexham</placeName> to <hi rend="superscript">see</hi> that beautiful <placeName ref="pl1983">church</placeName> which is
                    kept with the greatest possible neatness – Beautiful drive from <placeName ref="pl0002">Chester</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0792">Wrexham</placeName>. It was market day &amp; the town seemed very busy.
                    Beautiful drive also from <placeName ref="pl0792">Wrexham</placeName> here but I
                    was perhaps disappointed with the first couple of miles of the vale of
                    Llangollen – the hills naked of wood &amp; the <hi rend="superscript">white</hi>
                    limestone quarries on our left certainly not picturesque. About 3 miles from
                        <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName>,<note type="authorial">Ruabon, 6 miles from Llangolen, they pronounce as if spelt Rawbon
                        (anglice)</note> when <placeName ref="pl0794">Castle Dinas Bran</placeName>
                    came in sight, we were satisfied of the beauties of the valley but the sun was
                    setting on the castle, &amp; so dazzled our eyes we could scarce look that way.
                    The inn (kept by <persName ref="pe2179">Elizabeth Davies</persName>) is close to
                    the <placeName ref="pl1954">bridge</placeName> &amp; washed by the <placeName ref="pl1138">River Dee</placeName>, we are much taken with our hostess &amp;
                    with the place – have had an excellent roast leg of mutton, &amp; trout &amp;
                        <hi rend="superscript">very fine port wine</hi> with every possible
                    attention – I should like to spend a few days here – It is from here the
                        Saltmarshes<note type="editorial">Christopher Saltmarshe of Saltmarshe Hall
                        in the East Riding of Yorkshire (1784-1852) and his wife Emma (née Rawson)
                        of Stoney Royd, Halifax (d.1834). Lister asked the Saltmarshes for advice on
                        visiting Wales.</note> had the mutton sent – 5d per lb &amp; the carriage
                    might be about 1 \({1\over 2}\) per lb making it in all 6 \({1\over 2}\) a lb.
                    The waiter said we had come on the wrong side of the water – we should have
                    crossed by a bridge on our left over the canal (the <placeName ref="pl3088">Ellesmere</placeName>) &amp; turned along the <placeName ref="pl1609">aqueduct</placeName> – we sat down to dinner at 8 \({1\over 2}\), having
                    previously strolled thro' the town to <persName ref="pe0954">Lady E–
                        B–</persName>'s &amp; <persName ref="pe0957">Miss Ponsonby</persName>'s
                        <placeName ref="pl1614">place</placeName> – there is a public road close to
                    the house, thro' the grounds, &amp; along this we passed &amp; repassed
                    [deletions] standing to look at the house (cottage) which is really very pretty
                    – a great many of the people touched their hats to us on passing &amp; we are
                    much struck with their universal civility. A little [girl] seeing us apparently
                    standing to consider our way, shewed us the road to <placeName ref="pl1614">Plâs
                            <sic>Newyd</sic></placeName> (<persName ref="pe0954">Lady E.
                        B–</persName>'s &amp; <persName ref="pe0957">Miss P–</persName>'s), followed
                    &amp; answered our several questions very civilly. A little boy then came &amp;
                    we gave each of them all our halfpences, 2d each – After dinner (the people of
                    the house took it at 10), wrote the following note <hi rend="superscript">to the
                        Right Honourable <persName ref="pe0954">Lady Eleanor Butler</persName> &amp;
                            <persName ref="pe0957">Miss Ponsonby</persName> – Plasnewydd</hi> Mrs
                    &amp; Miss Lister take the liberty of presenting their compliments to <persName ref="pe0954">Lady Eleanor Butler</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe0957">Miss Ponsonby</persName>, &amp; of asking permission to see their grounds
                    at <placeName ref="pl1614">Plâs <sic>Newyd</sic></placeName> in the course of
                    tomorrow morning – Miss L–,<note type="editorial">Anne Lister</note> at the
                    suggestion of Mr Banks,<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note> had intended
                    herself the honour of calling on <hi rend="superscript">her</hi>
                    <persName ref="pe0954">ladyship</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe0957">Miss
                        Ponsonby</persName>, &amp; hopes she may be allowed to express her very
                    great regret at hearing of her <persName ref="pe0954">ladyship</persName>'s
                    indisposition – <placeName ref="pl3086">King's Head Hotel</placeName> – Saturday
                    evening 13 July. The message returned was that we should see the grounds at 12
                    tomorrow – this will prevent our going to church, which begins at 11 &amp; will
                    not be over till after 1 – the service is principally in Welsh except the lesson
                    &amp; sermon every 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> Sunday &amp; tomorrow is the
                    English day – <persName ref="pe0954">Lady E.B.</persName> has been couched – she
                    ventured out too soon &amp; caught cold – her medical man (Mr Lloyd Jones of
                        <placeName ref="pl1246">Ruthin</placeName>)<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note> positively refuses her seeing anyone – her cousin,
                    Lady Mary Ponsonby,<note type="editorial">Possibly either Mary Elizabeth
                        Ponsonby (1776-1861), who married Charles Grey, 2nd Earl Grey, in 1794, or
                        Mary Ponsonby (née Butler; dates unknown), wife of the Irish Whig George
                        Ponsonby (1755-1817).</note> passed thro' not long ago &amp; did not see her
                    – wrote the above of today &amp; the last 16 lines of yesterday from 10
                    \({1\over 2}\) to 12 \({1\over 2}\) after dinner – It struck 12 before I came up
                    to bed &amp; I wrote \({1\over 2}\) hour afterwards – Very fine day – merely a
                    beam or 2 of sun, &amp; no dust – consequence of late rain – they have had
                    scarcely any rain here till last day or 2 – they were burnt up before – market
                    day here – beef 6d per lb, veal 3d-3 \({1\over 2}\), mutton 4d to 5d – [code: a
                    good deal of discharge both today &amp; yesterday]<note type="editorial">Lister
                        makes brief references to ‘discharge' in encoded passages throughout her
                        tour. She is thought to have contracted a veneral disease from Mariana
                        Belcombe around 1820, who had in turn been infected by her husband.</note>
                    –</p>
                <p>
                    <pb n="43"/>
                    <fw>[f. 43]</fw> Sunday 14 July<lb/> My <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName>
                    and I off at 8 \({1\over 2}\) to <placeName ref="pl0794">Castel Dinas
                        Bran</placeName> (bran, crow i.e. crow castle)<note type="authorial">Tuesday
                        20 August 1822, improperly called crowcastle –</note> &amp; got back again
                    at 10 \({10\over 60}\)– 36 minutes in ascending to the summit – a boy, the
                    underwaiter at the inn, went with us as guide, and led us by the way <hi rend="superscript">thro</hi> the little garden of Evan Parry whose son, a
                    boy of 12 or 13 accompanied us with 2 sticks pronged with iron – my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> used hers, but I had no need of one – the way
                    is perfectly good and considering the steepness of the ascent &amp; the dryness
                    of the ground not at all slippery <hi rend="superscript">for I never slipped
                        once even with my bright iron-heeled boots on</hi> – little steps cut which
                    obviate whatever difficulty there might otherwise be – there was a light blue
                    mist over the mountains which impeded our view – &amp; after reading <persName ref="pe2085">Bingley</persName>'s description<note type="editorial">See
                        William Bingley, <hi rend="italic">A Tour Round North Wales, performed
                            during the Summer of 1798</hi> (London, 1800), II: 128: ‘The view from
                        Castell Dinas Brân are, upon the whole, so very extensive and beautiful,
                        that to any person who has not had an opportunity of ascending Snowdon, or
                        Cader Idris, this will be found a tolerable compensation.' Lister had
                        borrowed several works on Wales from the Halifax Circulating Library
                        including Bingley's <hi rend="italic">Tour</hi> before they set off for
                        Wales.</note> &amp; that ascending <placeName ref="pl0794">Dinas
                        Bran</placeName> might be a substitute to those who had not ascended
                        <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>. I was disappointed we could not
                    see near to the end of the Vale of Llangollen – nor distinguish anything of
                        <placeName ref="pl0785"><sic>Vale</sic> Crucis Abbey</placeName> – the hills
                    immediately around bounded our view very narrowly – the remains are very small –
                    Mr …. (not Middleton) of Chirk to whom the <placeName ref="pl0794">castle</placeName> belongs is going to build a sort of gothic <hi rend="superscript">cottage or</hi> summer house at the top of the hill (the
                    shell nearly completed) the <placeName ref="pl0794">castle</placeName> is to be
                    walled round with an upper &amp; lower wall, &amp; the rest of the ascencottat
                    pleasant all round – this will be a very great improvement – the waiter seemed
                    to know something of the <hi rend="superscript">underground</hi> communications
                    with the <placeName ref="pl0794">castle</placeName> mentioned but disbelieved by
                        <persName ref="pe2085">Bingley</persName><note type="editorial">See Bingley,
                        II: 127-8: ‘The inhabitants of Llangollen say, that somewhere about this
                        rock [Craig Eglwyseg] is an opening, from whence there is a long arched
                        passage under ground, supposed to lead to the castle. I scarcely gave any
                        credit to this report, for I could not, upon enquiry, hear of any person who
                        had seen it, or could tell whereabouts it was.'</note> – he (the waiter)
                    said it was somewhere towards the north end of the <placeName ref="pl0794">castle</placeName> now filled up with stones – In descending we gave the
                    boy 1/ – for going with us and taking the sticks &amp; went into his father's
                    cottage – very neat – his wife and youngest daughter there very neat looking
                    healthy people – a very nice old man – a slater by trade and slated "that grand
                    house" the <placeName ref="pl3086">King's Head</placeName> – He had been reading
                    the "English physician" an old physic book<note type="editorial">Probably a
                        reference to Nicholas Culpeper's astrological and herbalist medical work <hi rend="italic">The English Physitian</hi> (1652).</note> – we asked him
                    to read us a little of the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> chapter of St John in
                    Welsh – he did &amp; I tried to read after with tolerable success – the
                    pronunciation is very gutteral, but I think I could get the language in a few
                    months so as to make myself pretty well understood – Had breakfast as soon as we
                    got back – excellent bread &amp; butter, hot home-made rolls, &amp;c &amp; good
                    coffee – At 11 \({3\over 4}\) my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> &amp; I,
                    accompanied by Boots<note type="editorial">I.e. the boot boy from the
                        hotel.</note> to introduce us, walked to <placeName ref="pl1614">Plâs
                        Newydd</placeName> – the gardener in waiting – we talked to him a good deal
                    – he seemed a good sort of intelligent man much attached to his mistresses after
                    having lived with them 30 years – he had walked about the country with them many
                    miles when they were young – they were about 20 when they 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> came there &amp; had now been there 43 years<note type="editorial">Butler and Ponsonby settled in Llangollen in 1778, when
                        they were around 39 and 23 respectively.</note> – they kept no horses but
                    milked 6 cows – said I, "Can they use the milk of 6 cows?" "Oh! they never mind
                    the milk – it is the cream" – he said <persName ref="pe0954">Lady
                        E.B.</persName> was a good deal better – He remembered Mr Banks – has been
                    there 4 or 5 times – I told him I had longed to see the place for the last dozen
                    years, &amp; we have expressed our great admiration of the place – In <placeName ref="pl1999">St <sic>Gothens</sic></placeName> (for I know not how else to
                    spell it &amp; which we most particularly admired) was a little bookcase of 30
                    or 40 volumes, chiefly poetry, Spenser, Chaucer, Pope, Cowper, Homer,
                    Shakespeare, &amp;c – I quite agreed with <persName ref="pe2175">M–</persName>
                    (vide her letter), the place "is a beautiful little bijou" shewing excellent
                    taste – much to the credit of the ladies who have done it entirely
                        themselves.<note type="editorial">Lister recorded rereading Mariana's
                        letters written from her 1817 tour of Wales in a diary entry for 28 July
                        1828.</note> The gardener said, "they were always reading" – the dairy is
                    very pretty, close to the house, &amp; particularly the pump Gothic iron-work
                    from <placeName ref="pl0740">Shrewsbury</placeName> (<placeName ref="pl3102">Colebrookdale</placeName> perhaps originally) – the well 7 yards deep – It
                    is an interesting place – my expectations were more than realized &amp; it
                    excited in me, from a variety of circumstances, a sort of particular interest
                    tinged with melancholy – I could have mused for hours &amp; dreampt <hi rend="superscript">dreams</hi> of happiness, conjured up many a vision of
                    [illegible] hope – In our return we strolled thro' the church yard – I shall
                    copy the epitaph to <persName ref="pe0954">Lady E. B–</persName>'s &amp;
                        <persName ref="pe0957">Miss P–</persName>'s favourite old servant, Mrs
                        <persName ref="pe2184">Mary Clark</persName>, who died in 1809, when we go
                        back<note type="authorial">‘omitted copying the epitaph as I intended –
                        sorry –'</note> – Just peeped into the church stood in the porch – the
                    service not concluded – for the benefit of the distressed Irish<note type="editorial">The poor potato crop of 1821 resulted in severe food
                        shortages in Ireland in 1822, especially in the southern and western
                        counties.</note> – got back to the inn at 1 \({1\over 4}\) and off to
                        <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName> at 1 \({3\over 4}\) and get here
                        <hi rend="superscript">(<placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName>)</hi> in
                    exactly 1 \({40\over 60}\) hours at 3 \({35\over 60}\) – (<hi rend="superscript">dated at</hi> Cernioge 8 \({1\over 2}\) p.m.) Very fine drive (10 miles
                    vid. Carey p. 235)<note type="editorial">A reference to John Cary: <hi rend="italic">Cary's New Itinerary; or, An Accurate Delineation of the
                            Great Roads, Both Direct and Cross, Throughout England and Wales</hi>
                        (London, 1798).</note> from <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName>
                    to <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName>, the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName> within a short distance on our right all the way – the
                    banks shaded by rather large trees – perhaps chiefly alders – the valley narrow
                    the hills on each side bold and beautiful and picturesque – this road like a
                    bowling green – one of the best I ever travelled – <lb/>
                    <pb n="44"/><fw>[f. 44]</fw> Government have lately taken this road (the whole
                    way for <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1018">Holyhead</placeName>) into their own hands,<note type="editorial">The first
                        of a series of Parliamentary Acts relating to the London-Holyhead road was
                        passed in 1815, which provided for the improvement of the route, following a
                        report by Thomas Telford in 1811.</note> &amp; tho' the tolls are much
                    heavier in consequence thereto vast improvements have been made in the road
                    &amp; are <hi rend="superscript">now</hi> going on in different parts of the
                    line of it – <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName> is a small
                    limestone-built <hi rend="superscript">post</hi> town, like a neat village – a
                    small <placeName ref="pl1665">church</placeName> on a rising ground on the left
                    just after our entrance of the town – stopt 1 \({10\over 60}\) hours at the inn
                    &amp; bait the horses – the <placeName ref="pl3113">Owen Glendwr</placeName>
                    apparently a very comfortable inn – a good place to sleep at if one was not
                    anxious to get on further – Left <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName> at 4
                    \({35\over 60}\) &amp; got here (<placeName ref="pl1576">Cerniog
                        Mawr</placeName>) in 3 hours at 7 \({35\over 60}\) – the road very pretty
                    for about 6 miles to Lundyforth (according to the pronunciation)<note type="editorial">Probably a reference to Pont Glyn-diffwys, near Llangwm;
                        see <ref type="http" target="https://britishlistedbuildings.co.uk/300019583-pont-glyn-diffwys-llangwm">here</ref>. For an 1808 sketch of this scene by Turner, see <ref type="http" target="https://www.tate.org.uk/art/artworks/turner-the-corwen-betws-y-coed-road-near-glyn-diffwys-looking-towards-pont-y-glyn-d06880">here</ref>.</note>
                    <hi rend="superscript">(Pontyglyn or Pont Llyn Dyffws vid. Nicholson's guide
                        p.353)</hi> bridge romantically situated over the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName> which foamed in a <hi rend="superscript">tolerably broad
                        but</hi> shallow stream over its broken rocky bed below – we stopt &amp; got
                    out of the gig for a minute to view it – the road (to the right of it) cut thro'
                    the rock to a considerable depth – from here, however, the beauty of the road
                    begins to decline, &amp; the last 3 miles from <sic><placeName ref="pl3129">Cerig y Drudion</placeName></sic>. (Cherrig ch pronounced like ch in
                    church, y Drudyon) plain &amp; dreary – the land poor &amp; peaty, the hills
                    quite bare – a little before <placeName ref="pl3129">Cerig y
                    Drudion</placeName>, we observed a conical hill, having the appearance of 2
                    mounds or tumels as at <placeName ref="pl0794">Dinas Bran</placeName>, &amp;
                    which <hi rend="superscript">we took for</hi> the citadel of Caractacus<note type="editorial">British king or chieftain in the first century AD.</note>
                    mentioned by Cary<note type="editorial">See Cary, p. 167: ‘Within \({1\over 2}\)
                        a Mile of Cerrig y Drudion on r. is the famous Citadel of the Druids, where
                        Caractacus retired to after his Defeat at Caer Caradoc.'</note> – it seemed
                    something like an old stonework remain on the side towards <placeName ref="pl3129">Cerig y Drudion</placeName> – the last 2 or 3 miles of the road
                    almost in a straight line before us &amp; <placeName ref="pl1576">Cerniog
                        Mawr</placeName> tho' a very neat looking whitewashed house stands by itself
                    in the midst of hills so bare of people &amp; trees my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> &amp; I agreed we should not like to stay there longer than
                    necessary – there is a turnpike bar very near the gate (there are two such
                    between <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName>) such as I had never seen before, struck us
                    exceedingly – [sketch inserted] ten iron radii about 1 inch broad &amp;
                    \({1\over 4}\) inch thick, spring at equal distances from the circumference of
                    the 2 little quadrants [deletions] of circles placed in the corners of the foot
                        <hi rend="superscript">and top</hi> of the hanging side – a very slight iron
                    post is fastened to the stone posts &amp; upon the top of this small iron post
                    finished off to admit it, the gates are hung by a [drawing] swinging on the top
                    of the posts – Sat down to dinner here <hi rend="superscript">about 8</hi>
                    <placeName ref="pl1576">Kernioge Mawr Inn</placeName> as the man of the inn
                    spells it – Trout, mutton chops &amp; gooseberry tart &amp; cream – very good –
                    settled everything paid the bill &amp;c &amp; came to bed at 9 \({1\over 2}\) to
                    be in readiness in the morning to start at 7 for <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel
                        Curig</placeName> – wrote the last 9 lines of today [code: after having
                    curled my hair] feel so very heavy &amp; sleepy I can write no more – I wonder
                    what success I shall have about <persName ref="pe0954">Lady E.B.</persName>
                    &amp; <persName ref="pe0957">Miss Ponsonby</persName>
                    <hi rend="superscript"><persName ref="pe2179">Mrs Davies</persName> thought they
                        would be pleased with my note</hi> but I can't write more now than that we
                    have had delightful weather today &amp; travelled on most comfortably – I am
                    more than \({1\over 2}\) asleep &amp; must make the best of my way to bed – 'Tis
                    now 11 \({1\over 2}\) [code: a good deal of discharge] I have heard the wind
                    whistle here 2 or 3 times – what a dreary place it must be in Winter!<lb/>
                </p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Monday 15 July <lb/> Off at 7 \({1\over 2}\) to <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel
                        Curig</placeName> – detained talking to <persName ref="pe2197">Mr
                        Weaver</persName> the landlord about our route, &amp; bought of him
                    Nicholson's Cambrian Traveller's guide,<note type="editorial">George Nicholson's
                            <hi rend="italic">The Cambrian Traveller's Guide, and Pocket
                            Companion</hi>, a compendium-style guidebook drawing on the work of
                        earlier Welsh travel writers such as (among others) Thomas Pennant, William
                        Bingley, Arthur Aikin and William Warner, was first published in 1808. The
                        second edition, which Lister bought at Cernioge, was an expanded version,
                        published in 1813 as <hi rend="italic">The Cambrian Traveller's Guide, in
                            Every Direction</hi>.</note> London 1813, 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>
                    edition 1 vol. large 8vo price 18/) From the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>
                    turnpike (about 3 miles from <placeName ref="pl1576">Cernioge</placeName>) the
                    road loses all its naked dreariness &amp; begins to be wooded &amp; beautiful –
                    we stopt according to <persName ref="pe2197">Mr W–</persName>'s directions about
                    6 miles or rather more from <placeName ref="pl1576">Cernioge</placeName> &amp;
                    turned down a footpath on our left to see the beautiful <placeName ref="pl2852">fall of Penmachno</placeName> – this took us altogether about 25 minutes
                    &amp; waiting 10 minutes for <persName ref="pe2198">George</persName> to see it,
                    we were delayed 35 minutes.<note type="authorial">Perhaps a couple of miles
                        beyond the <placeName ref="pl2852">fall of Penmachno</placeName> passed the
                            <placeName ref="pl3133">Wellington iron bridge</placeName> – a very
                        beautiful one, the finishing at each end wrought into the rose the thistle
                        and shamrock very prettily done</note> Notwithstanding this we reached here,
                        <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel Curig</placeName>, at 10 \({1\over 2}\) a
                    distance of 15 miles – meant to have breakfasted at <placeName ref="pl3132">Bettws</placeName> but passed on by mistake. [deletion] Stood up in the gig
                    to see the fall of the Rhyddol<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note> &amp;
                    got out to look at the bridge built <hi rend="superscript">over the river</hi>
                    on rocks [deletions] sublime scenery for the last 11 or 12 miles – <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName> very majestic – completely cloud-capt – Had
                    breakfast at 11 – then walked into the garden whence a fine view of this king of
                    mountains &amp; a couple of small lakes just beyond the garden – [deletions]
                    about 12 the day cleared so much we intended to ascend – all agreed with the
                    guide &amp; to be off in \({1\over 2}\) hour (at 2) – the house, planned by
                    Wyatt has a handsome exterior &amp; some capital rooms – but the attendance
                    &amp; <hi rend="superscript">breakfast are</hi> the worst we have had so
                        far<note type="editorial">A reference to the Royal Hotel at Capel Curig,
                        built by Lord Penrhyn in 1803. Lister is drawing her information from
                        Nicholson's <hi rend="italic">Guide</hi> (see p. 175 in the 1813
                        edition).</note> – <lb/><note type="authorial">vid. line 5 from the bottom
                        of the next page</note><lb/>
                    <pb n="45"/>
                    <fw>[f. 45]</fw> (<placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName> Tuesday 8 p.m.) Off
                    to Snowden at 2p.m. went in the gig (the guide mounted behind us) as far as we
                    had to go on the <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName> road i.e. 4
                    \({1\over 4}\) miles, &amp; sent <persName ref="pe2198">George</persName> back
                    with the horses – Began the ascent on foot at 3, &amp; gained the highest point
                    of the highest summit <placeName ref="pl2862"><sic>Wydfa</sic></placeName>. (a
                    distance of 5 miles) in 3 \({40\over 60}\) hours – we had hoped to see the sun
                    set but this was prevented by intervening clouds – we saw however a magnificent
                    prospect – seven lakes immediately among the Snowdonian mountains – the
                        <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai Straights</placeName> – the bays of Cardigan
                    &amp; Caemawr, <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesea</placeName> &amp;c. &amp;c. the
                    ascent was much easier than I expected – no danger attending it, &amp; the
                    exertion required more on account of the length of the way than anything else –
                    our last part of the ascent for a considerable distance (just above the Glas-Lyn
                    lake) &amp; passing by the <placeName ref="pl3134">copper works</placeName>
                    which have killed the fish &amp; turned green the waters of the lake) was along
                    an artificial path 5 feet wide, cut in traverses, which brought us up to the
                    ridge, as it were, on which stands <hi rend="superscript">the pointed
                        summit</hi>
                    <placeName ref="pl2862">Wydfa</placeName> – the first view is certainly most
                    striking and altogether we thought ourselves well repaid for our trouble.
                    Neither the guide (<persName ref="pe2200">Evan Jones</persName>) nor I expected
                    my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> to go to the top, &amp; therefore took
                    a boy with us to conduct her to <placeName ref="pl1527">Llanberis</placeName> –
                    as we went along in the gig we had perceived 2 men on horseback after us – they
                    rode to the <placeName ref="pl3135">pass of Llanberis</placeName>, sent their
                    horses to the village &amp; we soon found them at our heels going up the
                    mountain – they continued to join us for the benefit of our guide to which I
                    should have objected but one of them was the son of <hi rend="superscript">our</hi> innkeeper &amp; the other's <hi rend="superscript">(a Mr Reid, an
                        attorney)</hi> arm was taken by my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName>
                    &amp; he helped her up the mountain &amp; was in fact the means of enabling her
                    to get up to the top – arrived there, we looked about a few minutes, &amp; then
                    foolishly sat down in the little hut on the stone benches &amp; were some
                    minutes. All the party felt chilled and took a little bread &amp; brandy
                    excluding myself – Indeed the 2 gents drank almost all the two pint bottles of
                    brandy <hi rend="superscript">our guide had taken</hi> at 3 or 4 different times
                    of halt – the guide meant to have taken us to <placeName ref="pl1527">Llanberis</placeName> by <placeName ref="pl1309">Dolbadarn
                        Castle</placeName> a route of 7 miles – but fancying that by going a shorter
                    we might return to sleep at <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel Curig</placeName> we
                    ventured down a very steep &amp; difficult pass just above <placeName ref="pl1527">Llanberis</placeName> – had I had an idea what it was I should
                    not have thought of doing it – However, by dint of patient labour &amp; constant
                    hold of the guide she got down – frightened as she was yet appearing less so
                    than Mr Reid – yet tho' we saved three miles of distance we were 2 \({20\over
                    60}\) hours in descending, &amp; did not reach the little inn at <placeName ref="pl1527">Llanberis</placeName> till 9 \({40\over 60}\), too late to
                    think of leaving it – the gents. returned to <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel
                        Curig</placeName> – we remained – had boiled milk &amp; bread &amp; butter
                    for supper &amp; went to bed – having nothing with us I only took off my pelisse
                    &amp; neck handkerchief &amp; lay down in the rest of my clothes at 11 – to be
                    called at 4 – For fear of damp sheets I wrapt my plaid round me – I know not
                    that I was ever more heated – I had scarcely a dry thing about me – we had
                    walked about 5 \({1\over 2}\) miles of ascent and about 4 of descent 10 times
                    more fatiguing than anything which I had done before – my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName>'s bowels very painful – doubtless for sitting in the cold
                    hut &amp; taking sheer brandy – I tasted nothing &amp; felt no inconvenience –
                    Very fine day – cool &amp; pleasant &amp; tolerably clear notwithstanding the
                    clouds that shaded the setting sun –<lb/></p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Tuesday 16 July<lb/> Out in \({1\over 2}\) hour the guide &amp; I walked to
                        <placeName ref="pl1309">Dolbadarn castle</placeName> &amp; thence to the
                    waterfall of <sic><placeName ref="pl1308">Conant Mawr</placeName></sic> – a
                    distance altogether going &amp; returning about 5 miles – (about 2 miles from
                    the inn to the castle &amp; thence about mile to the waterfall) – at 6 \({3\over
                    4}\) after paying our little bill at the <placeName ref="pl3137">Vaenol
                        Arms</placeName> – <placeName ref="pl3104">Vaenol</placeName> the name of
                    the seat of <persName ref="pe0944">Mr Ashton Smith</persName> to whom the little
                    inn kept by <persName ref="pe2201">Robert Closs</persName> belongs together with
                    extensive property in the neighbourhood – 2 \({20\over 60}\) hours walking to
                    where the gig left us yesterday that is 4 long miles along the <placeName ref="pl3135">pass of Llanberis</placeName> so narrow as to seem almost like
                    a <hi rend="superscript">tremendous</hi> fissure in the mountains – just before
                    getting into the gig looked down the vale &amp; upon the <placeName ref="pl3136">lake of Quinant</placeName> – we <hi rend="superscript">were</hi> only 7
                    \({3\over 4}\) miles from <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName>, for
                    the whole distance from <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel Curig</placeName> is only
                    12 miles – we <hi rend="superscript">were</hi> back to breakfast about 10 and
                    off to <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName> about 12 – about 2 miles
                    from <placeName ref="pl3132">Bettws</placeName> stopt &amp; walked down<note type="authorial">vid. lines 5 and 6 from the bottom of the last page</note>
                    to see the <placeName ref="pl2851">Rhaidr y Wennol</placeName> waterfall –
                    turned over the curved <placeName ref="pl3143">bridge</placeName> at Bettws (it
                    is built on rocks in the river) &amp; got to <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>
                    <hi rend="superscript">(nine miles)</hi> about 2 – beautiful drive all the way –
                    the town busy &amp; full of people it being market day – walked about, saw the
                    church &amp; got 2 men to shake the bridge for us – when they set their backs
                    and pushed against the one centre stone we certainly [missing word] the motion
                    at the other centre stone – walked down almost to <placeName ref="pl1532">Gwydir
                        Castle</placeName> to take a look at it – stopt at the Eagles Inn<note type="editorial">Eighteenth-century hotel in Llanrwst; see <ref type="http" target="http://coflein.gov.uk/en/site/27123/details/eagles-hotel">here</ref>.</note> – seemingly a pretty good one, where one might sleep
                    comfortably – the drive from <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName> here<lb/>
                    <pb n="46"/><fw>[f. 46]</fw> called 12 miles (about 11 \({1\over 2}\) by the
                    mile-posts) beautiful &amp; fine – we were much struck with it in spite of the
                    rain which began very soon after our leaving <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName> – By the way, we had just got into the gig when Mr
                    Reid came up &amp; inquired after us – he was thrown down somehow or other by
                    his horse last night &amp; they did not get home till 1 – Our approach to <hi rend="superscript">&amp; first sight of</hi>
                    <placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName> remarkably fine – a very hill stage,
                    &amp; bad road so much of it set with boulder stones very slippery to the horses
                    feet – the road too very narrow – one could scarce think it 7 or 8 years <hi rend="superscript">ago</hi> the great high <hi rend="superscript">road</hi>
                    from <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> thro' <placeName ref="pl0740">Shrewsbury</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl1018">Holyhead</placeName> –
                    stopt at the <placeName ref="pl3124">Harp Inn</placeName> – my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> unwell in her bowels all the day, &amp; had tea
                    this evening just before I had dinner – a shoulder of a sheep that was killed
                    this morning yet the meat was well flavoured tho' rather tough – we <hi rend="superscript">left <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName> at 4
                        and</hi> got here in 4 \({10\over 60}\) hours determined not to press Percy
                    – he has brought us today 39 miles &amp; came in as fresh as if he had done
                    nothing – we have seen not one goat yet – they are all destroyed on
                            <sic><persName ref="pe2202">Lord Gwedyr</persName>'s</sic> estate – on
                    account of <hi rend="superscript">them</hi> hurting his plantations, he about 7
                    years ago sent an order that every tenant should get rid of all he had by
                    Llanrwst fair (in September) – this was giving them too little time, &amp;
                    caused them great loss which could have been remedied by giving them till
                    Christmas instead of September –for goat's flesh is not good without salting
                    &amp; should be killed at Christmas – <hi rend="superscript">very</hi> fine
                    morning – rain from about 4 \({1\over 2}\) to 7 \({1\over 2}\) p.m. 'Tis now
                    about 10 \({3\over 4}\) – I am so sleepy I can write no more [code: more
                    discharge today and yesterday than I almost ever had before]<lb/>
                </p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Wednesday 17 July <lb/> [code: about two hours dressing putting on clean things
                    &amp; <unclear>siding</unclear> my imperial &amp;c] Went out to see the
                        <placeName ref="pl1530">castle</placeName> about 10 \({3\over 4}\). Had
                    scarcely got there before it began to rain pretty heavily &amp; continued the
                    whole while that we <hi rend="superscript">were</hi> obliged to return [code:
                    Gave the man two shillings for shewing the castle. I think one would have done.
                    The art of travelling requires an apprenticeship. Surely I shall improve in
                    time. I have given many a sixpence that might have been spare. Always take in
                    your hand what you mean to give before you go.] The <placeName ref="pl1530">castle</placeName> is a most beautiful &amp; surprisingly perfect remain
                    all things considered – but we have seen it to great disadvantage in consequence
                    of the rain could not see <hi rend="superscript">the</hi> interior of the keep
                    tower – the boys of the town sometimes climb into it – <hi rend="superscript">but hardly anyone else</hi> – it adjoins the great hall – <sic><placeName ref="pl3144">Diganwy</placeName></sic> is just across the river about a
                    mile from the ferry-house – the passage is 1 shilling each person – <placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName> seems a poor sort of town of 2 or 3 streets
                    – we have been comfortable here – good, clean beds, tho' very small rooms – no
                    window – curtains, no wash-stand – the pitcher &amp; basin on the toilet table –
                    good breakfast &amp; great attention – the people seem clean, tho' the house
                    looks dirtyish <hi rend="superscript">&amp; second-rate</hi> because, perhaps,
                    it is old &amp; not easily made to look clean <hi rend="superscript">or kept
                        clean</hi> – But, on going out I see it is evidently not the first-rate
                    house – the <placeName ref="pl3145">White Lion</placeName>, a little <hi rend="superscript">few doors</hi> lower down the street appears a neat, new
                    building &amp;, as we passed, a gentleman's landau <hi rend="superscript">(hansom)</hi> with his own post-boy &amp; horses was at the door. [Code: We
                    do not cut a figure in travelling equal to our expenses. My <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> is shabbily dressed &amp; does not quite
                    understand the thorough manners of a gentlewoman – for instance, taking the
                    man's arm so readily to <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName> &amp;c
                    &amp;c. Indescribable. <persName ref="pe2198">George</persName> too is a clown
                    of a servant – too simple in the manners of the world. But we are not known. I
                    will try to learn &amp; improve in travelling matters &amp;, by thought &amp;
                    observation, may turn all this to future advantage. But I feel very low. Somehow
                    or other seeing <persName ref="pe2175">M–</persName> has been no comfort to me
                    when I asked her how long she thought it might be before we got together &amp;
                    she seemed to fight off answering. On pressing farther she said she felt some
                    delicacy in this subject &amp; did not like to talk openly of it even to
                    ourselves for tho she did not love him yet kindness &amp; obligation made her
                    feel a wish to avoid calculating the time or thinking of except in general terms
                    – I promised not to press her on the subject again. All this has made a great
                    impression on me &amp; I know not how it is I cannot shake it off. She never did
                    so before but talked [illegible] of so many – five or ten for instance – years
                    as I did. She seemed fond of me as ever yet all the night when I was almost
                    convulsed with smothering my sobs she took no notice nor was affected at all
                    apparently. The <pb n="47"/><fw>[f. 47]</fw> next morning her eyes filled at
                    parting. I know not how it is but she as it were deceived me once &amp; I feel
                    that it is miserable to doubt. My <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName>
                    observed that she did not seem so fond of me as I was of her. I wish I did not
                    think quite so much of all this but alas I cannot help – surely I shall be
                    better by &amp; by. I feel miserably low. I remember too what she said of Mr
                    Powis that if her heart was not engaged as it is to me she might be in danger of
                    very undesirable &amp; uncomfortable feelings of interest towards him. I might
                    have written her a few lines but feel as if I had not resolution. Were I fit for
                    another world how gladly would I go there.] <lb/>
                </p>
                <lb/>
                <p> Just finished the above of today at 12 \({1\over 4}\) – then read <persName ref="pe2085">Bingley</persName> &amp; the Cambrian Directory &amp;
                    Nicholson's Cambrian Guide – and afterwards wrote<note type="authorial">Aber 12
                        p.o.</note> 1 \({1\over 2}\) pages small &amp; close, giving an account of
                    our journey to <persName ref="pe2175">M–</persName> to be sent from <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> – It continued to rain all the day &amp;
                    we <unclear>ordered</unclear> dinner at 6, a boiled neck of mutton &amp; caper
                    sauce – nothing else – about 5 the rain began to abate &amp; it being quite fair
                    by 6 we determined to go a stage, besides we found the room in which we sat so
                    very damp, it gave my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> the rheumatism
                    &amp; we had dinner in a little sitting room upstairs – on looking <hi rend="superscript">more</hi> about us the house did seem dirty &amp;
                    uncomfortable &amp; in spite of the civility of the people we wanted to change
                    our quarters – the <placeName ref="pl3145">White Lion</placeName> is the inn to
                    go to – we were off at 7 \({24\over 60}\) and reached here (<placeName ref="pl1595">Aber</placeName>, Black Bull) in exactly 2 \({10\over 60}\)
                    hours between 9 &amp; 10 miles – the first part of the road very hilly &amp;
                    walking up <sic><placeName ref="pl1338">Penman-Mawr</placeName></sic> took some
                    time – the first view of the sea <hi rend="superscript">we lost sight of course
                        immediately</hi> after passing a fine defile <hi rend="superscript">is most
                        striking fine</hi> – the road cut out of the one side <hi rend="superscript">of the <unclear>hill</unclear></hi> with a low wall <hi rend="superscript">[illegible]</hi> deep precipice beneath and <hi rend="superscript">then on
                        the other side</hi> (on the right) a tremendous mountain with an excavation
                    in it perhaps a copper mine <hi rend="superscript">my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> got out &amp; walked to the bottom of the road</hi>
                    soon afterwards we came to <placeName ref="pl1338">Penman Mawr</placeName> which
                    is tremendously fine – the sea was smooth as glass – the sun setting over it
                    most beautifully. It was indeed altogether a magnificent sight – such scenery I
                    never saw before – the drive from <placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName>
                    here exceeds all we have met with hitherto – It was darkish before we got here –
                    It seems a comfortable house, &amp; our beds look comfortable – sat up reading
                    Nicholson's guide – did not come upstairs till 11 \({40\over 60}\) – then wrote
                    the last 13 lines of today – Fine all the way we came not a drop of rain –
                    passed the mail just before we came to the Penman Mawr turnpike – [code: a great
                    deal of discharge tho I have hitherto used two syringe-fulls of water night
                    &amp; morning] <lb/>
                </p>
                <lb/>
                <p> Thursday 18 July <lb/> At 8 \({1\over 4}\) my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> &amp; I set off (a <hi rend="superscript">cunning</hi>
                    little girl our guide – picked her up in the village) to see the cataract
                        <placeName ref="pl3146">Rhiader Mawr</placeName> – the girl pronounced
                    Rhiader as tho' pronounced adder – going &amp; returning took us 1 <hi rend="superscript">49/60</hi> hours. Rained all the time more or less, but
                    gently &amp; not so as to wet one much – my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> thought the cataract not worth the trouble we had had –
                    Breakfasted – the milk in the house all sour – desired the waiter to get some
                    elsewhere – nobody kept any cows or even goats &amp; no milk to be had – sent
                    for the mistress (<persName ref="pe2203">Mrs Lewis</persName>) she was very
                    civil, said it was a shame to live in the country &amp; have no milk &amp; she
                    sent somewhere, borrowed a pint, &amp; I had at last, coffee au lait as usual,
                    &amp; a good breakfast. In paying the bill they gave me, in change 2 Irish
                    tenpennys, but valued them only at 9d. I gave the waiter 1 of them and 2d, &amp;
                    the chamber[maid] the other (i.e. 9d) not giving her anything for my bed,
                    because the sheets were certainly not clean of which I took care to tell both
                    her &amp; her mistress – as they told we could get nothing for the horses at the
                    slate quarries we took 2 feeds of corn (16d) with us wrapt up in the plaid – the
                    clouds looked very threatening – Left <placeName ref="pl1595">Aber</placeName>
                    at 11 \({10\over 60}\), and <hi rend="superscript">in \({1\over 2}\)</hi> at 12
                    \({40\over 60}\), on account of the heavy shower stopt [at] a <hi rend="superscript">neat</hi> looking small house by the wayside (<persName ref="pe2204">Mr Jones</persName>'s the <sic><placeName ref="pl3147">Tin y
                            mins Inn</placeName></sic>, as the chambermaid spelt it, 7 miles from
                        <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName> &amp; 8 from <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel Curig</placeName> – Detained here 1 \({1\over 2}\) hours
                    it rained almost all the while &amp; besides Percy had his near hind shoe
                    fastened on – the Vale of <sic><placeName ref="pl1529">Nant
                        Frayon</placeName></sic> begins about a mile from <placeName ref="pl3147">Tin y mins Inn</placeName> with the <placeName ref="pl1578">slate
                        quarries</placeName> – Drove forwards about 3 \({1\over 2}\) miles to within
                    4 or 5 miles of <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel Curig</placeName>, a good way
                    beyond the end of <placeName ref="pl3148">Ogwen Pool</placeName> – the scenery,
                    the tremendous mountains on each side all the way, particularly bordering the
                    lake, sublime &amp; savagely grand – It was about 3 hours from our leaving
                        <placeName ref="pl3147">Tin y mins</placeName> to our going into the slate
                    quarry which we entered at 4 \({1\over 4}\) &amp; stood \({1\over 2}\) hour – it
                    rained very heavily all the while &amp; afterwards <lb/>
                    <pb n="48"/><fw>[f. 48]</fw> till we got back to <placeName ref="pl3149">Llandegai</placeName> (2 miles from here, <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName>) where we turned to our left this morning to <placeName ref="pl1529">Nant Frayon</placeName> – we turned off to the slate quarries
                    to the left as we returned from <placeName ref="pl3148">Ogwen Pool</placeName>
                    at the last turnpike before <placeName ref="pl3149">Llandegai</placeName> –
                    owing to some men standing by we took a round in going &amp; were 20 minutes
                    from the high road to the quarries – we returned another way in 10 minutes – the
                    quarries very well worth seeing – shewn us by an overlooker John Hughes. A
                    better sort of workman allowed 14/- a week – 8 hundred &amp; 2 or 3 men employed
                    in all the quarries (belonging <hi rend="superscript">now</hi> to <persName ref="pe2205">Mr Pennant</persName> who succeeded to the estates of the late
                        <persName ref="pe0420">Lord Penryn</persName>, &amp; who, <persName ref="pe2200">Evan Jones</persName> the <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName> guide told <hi rend="superscript">us</hi> had 28, 000 a
                    year clearing 18, 000 by the quarries – we saw the largest quarries 450 men
                    employed in it – they were pulling down huge masses of slate with ropes – or
                    rather the ropes were fastened to or about the rock for the men to climb up by,
                    &amp; split or rend off the masses with large iron wedges – others were blasting
                    the rock with gunpowder – this so lacerates the rock they only do it when other
                    means fail – we went thro' a longish tunnel from one quarry to another 60 yards
                    deep – slates different sizes – the largest £7 a thousand<note type="authorial">Perhaps the smallest size may be about 8 inches long by 6 inches
                        broad</note>
                    <hi rend="superscript">delivered</hi> at Port Penrhyn (close to <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName>) the smallest 4/6 a thousand – good workmen
                    can earn £2 a month – each one pays 4/- a month towards clearing away the waste
                    made in getting &amp; dressing the slates – &amp; what more is required is paid
                    by <persName ref="pe2205">Mr Pennant</persName> – the refuse is carted out along
                    the side of the hill &amp; has a striking effect (like so many pit-hills as we
                    call them) at a distance<note type="authorial">In returning just as we passed
                        the bridge from the quarries &amp; got back to the turnpike close to it, a
                        flash of vivid lightening came across us immediately followed by a loud peal
                        of thunder, &amp; the rain which had begun just before we got to the
                        quarries, continued till within a couple of miles of <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName> vid. line 10 from the top of p. 49</note> – we
                    particularly <hi rend="superscript">admired</hi> the small <hi rend="superscript">scattered</hi> town &amp; very neat-looking church of
                        <placeName ref="pl1971">Llandegai</placeName>, &amp; should have liked to
                    visit <placeName ref="pl1650">Penryn castle</placeName> at a short distance from
                    it on the right (going from <placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName>
                    <hi rend="italic">to <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName></hi>) had we had
                    time &amp;c – The <placeName ref="pl1650">castle</placeName> is approached from
                        <placeName ref="pl3149">Llandegai</placeName> by a fine gothic gateway under
                    a handsome dog-toothed Saxon church-like arch – this, however, struck me as
                    rather inconsistent with a regular castle gate – not quite finished – got out at
                    the <placeName ref="pl3150">Castle Inn</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName> (at the back of the <placeName ref="pl2025">cathedral</placeName>) at 6 – drove down to the <placeName ref="pl2026">bishop's palace</placeName> (I suppose it is) at first, &amp; thence
                    directed to <placeName ref="pl3150">the castle</placeName> – It is the best inn
                    in the place, but bad enough &amp; dirty enough – quite full – 2 very small hot
                    uncomfortable looking rooms at the top of the house – and a sitting room on the
                    left of the entrance on the ground floor next to the street &amp; even about
                    this we had some difficulty, finding other company when we returned from the
                        <placeName ref="pl2025">cathedral</placeName> &amp; obliged to civily turn
                    them out, tho' here before us –a <hi rend="superscript">reverend</hi> Mr &amp;
                    his daughter Miss Jones from <placeName ref="pl1246">Ruthin</placeName> – walked
                    out before dinner – a very poor little town &amp; very paltry <placeName ref="pl2025">cathedral</placeName> – a great long sword upon a flat table in
                    a niche bespoke the tomb of <sic>Owen Glendwr</sic><note type="editorial">A
                        reference not to Owain Glyndŵr but to the tomb of Owain Gwynedd (c.
                        1100-70), king of Gwynedd in the twelfth century. For a modern photograph of
                        the tomb, see <ref type="http" target="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/66/Y_Gadeirlan_Bangor_Cathedral_Church%2C_Gwynedd_North_Wales_55.JPG">here</ref>.</note> – suspecting that we ought to have gone to the
                        <placeName ref="pl3151">Penrhyn Arms</placeName> at Port Penrhyn close upon
                        <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName>, perhaps \({1\over 2}\) mile off
                    – I walked to see &amp; be convinced – this is a dirty bustling coach-house –
                        <hi rend="superscript">Perhaps</hi>
                    <placeName ref="pl1563">Bangor Ferry</placeName> would have suited us much
                    better, but Mr <persName ref="pe2206">W.H. Rawson</persName> said "avoid
                        <placeName ref="pl1563">Bangor Ferry</placeName>" – we shall see it tomorrow
                    – I wish I had not minded this – however, we mean to be off at 7 in the morning
                    &amp; breakfast at the hotel at <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> –
                    we had mullet to dinner (sat down at 7 \({1\over 2}\)) well dressed &amp; good –
                    a large too-short-a-time-kept leg of mutton &amp; a goodish currant tart (pie) –
                    settled the accounts &amp; wrote this journal of today after dinner – It seems
                    to have been fair all the evening – Finished this at 10 \({1\over 2}\) &amp;
                    then went upstairs to bed – </p>

                <p>Friday 19 July<lb/>Rain all the night &amp; prevented our setting off this
                    morning till 7 \({3\over 4}\) instead of 7 – Drove to <placeName ref="pl1563">Bangor Ferry</placeName> (the front towards our road like that of a common
                    ale-house, but a longish neatly white washed front towards the <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai</placeName> that there may be tolerably good
                    accommodation – <hi rend="superscript">but</hi> the house we hear here
                    (Caernarvon Hotel or Marquess of Anglesea's Arms) is quite full – got out at the
                    bridge over the straights<note type="editorial">Thomas Telford's Menai Bridge
                        would not be completed and operational until 1826.</note> of which the 4
                    small arches on the <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesea</placeName> side &amp; the
                    3 on this side are finished – I have just finished my letter to <persName ref="pe2175">M–</persName> (begun on Wednesday at <placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName>, having written the latter the \({1\over 2}\) 3d page
                    &amp; the ends small &amp; close) &amp; have said "the span left for the iron
                    arch look tremendous &amp; the work when completed will deserve <lb/>
                    <pb n="49"/><fw>[f. 49]</fw> a high place among the wonders of our land – In
                    point of strength it is Egyptian – in point of lightness &amp; proportion
                    Grecian – I am delighted with it &amp; think it so far the germ of the finest
                    thing I ever saw – <sic>"..."</sic> After a rainy day on Wednesday the evening
                    was fine: it was high water, &amp; so fine a drive as the 9 miles from
                        <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1595">Aber</placeName> (6 miles from <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName>,
                    &amp; where we slept) cannot surely be surpassed throughout the kingdom or
                    perhaps the world – The winding down the chasm before <placeName ref="pl1338">Penman Mawr</placeName>; the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> view of the
                    sea bounded by <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesea</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl1959">Puffin Island</placeName>; the sun setting most gloriously; the
                    road cut out of the rock about 50 yards<note type="authorial">should be 50 feet
                        or about 20 yards</note> from the foot of <placeName ref="pl1338">Penman
                        Mawr</placeName>, the waves or rather water smooth as glass just murmuring
                    below, formed altogether so fine, so sublimely beautiful a scene as I shall not
                    hastily forget – the shades of evening ushered us into <placeName ref="pl1595">Aber</placeName>, where we slept &amp; breakfasted the next morning
                    comfortably, after walking about 3 miles <hi rend="superscript">there and
                        back</hi> to see the Rhiader vawr, a somewhat noted cataract – we left
                        <placeName ref="pl1595">Aber</placeName> a little after 11 (rain prevented
                    our setting off sooner) turned along the <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel
                        Curig</placeName> road at <placeName ref="pl3149">Llandegai</placeName>,
                    &amp; made a diversion of nearly 2 miles to see the whole of the celebrated vale
                    of <placeName ref="pl1529">Nant Frayon</placeName> &amp; the <placeName ref="pl1578">Penrhyn slate quarries</placeName> – our expectations more than
                    equalled in both respects,<note type="editorial">The Lister's Halifax neighbour
                        William Henry Rawson advised them to see the slate quarries. His letter,
                        received 4 July 1822, is retained in the Shibden Hall papers at
                        WYC:1525/6/5/2.</note> &amp; got to <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName> about 6, in time to see surely the most paltry city
                    &amp; <placeName ref="pl2025">cathedral</placeName> in his majesty's dominions –
                    yet the situation of <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName> is beautiful
                    &amp; had the inn (<placeName ref="pl3120">The Castle</placeName> – the best)
                    been better we might have enjoyed ourselves more." – Beautiful drive from
                        <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName> here – got here in 2 \({1\over
                    4}\) hours at 10 \({1\over 4}\) – It is a large handsome looking <placeName ref="pl3112">house</placeName>, built by the present <persName ref="pe2196">Marquess</persName> – we have a sitting-room, about 11 yards by 6, lighted
                    by 3 large sashes – I should think it about 14ft high or perhaps more – have had
                    a good breakfast &amp; are very comfortable more especially after such inns as
                    the <placeName ref="pl3124">Harp</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName> &amp; far worse <hi rend="superscript">as to sleeping
                        rooms</hi> the <placeName ref="pl3120">Castle</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName> – there was not even a chair in my room last
                    night – in fact, the place was too small to hold me – it was very close, &amp;
                    the whole house had a smell of dirtyness &amp; meat kept too long – <persName ref="pe2198">George</persName> too was very uncomfortable – yet I slept well
                    not withstanding – 'Tis now 3 \({1\over 4}\) – the sun has been getting out for
                    the last \({1\over 4}\) hour, &amp; it is fair &amp; fine – It began to rain
                    while I was on <hi rend="superscript">one of</hi> the walls of the bridge over
                    the <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai</placeName> (I got out to go upon it &amp;
                    view this stupendous work) &amp; rained <hi rend="superscript">all</hi> the rest
                    of our way home – sometimes very heavily, &amp; did not begin to clear at all
                    till about 1 – Between the tops of the arches there are strong walls built all
                    down the middle of the bridge <hi rend="superscript">longitudinally</hi> &amp;
                    the other walls meet there at right angles the spaces between &amp; arches
                    across the bridge – The post leaves here at 5, but the letters must be in the
                    office at 4 – sent my letter to <persName ref="pe2175">M–</persName> at 3
                    \({3\over 4}\) – my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> &amp; I walked out at
                    4 – went to the <placeName ref="pl1566">castle</placeName>, walked all round it
                    &amp; then had the <hi rend="superscript">daughter of the</hi> woman whose
                    province it is to shew it – went up to the top of the <placeName ref="pl2387">Eagle-Tower</placeName> – fine view – Nicholson's guide says the interior
                    was divided into 2 parts, an outer &amp; inner part – vid. p. 284<note type="editorial">See Nicholson, p. 286: ‘The area within is irregularly
                        oblong, formerly divided into 2 parts, forming an outer and inner
                        court.'</note> the woman said it was divided into 3 courts, &amp; I thought
                    I saw traces of this triple division – we were 50 minutes there – perfectly
                    delighted with this castle. Much larger than <placeName ref="pl1530">Conway
                        Castle</placeName> &amp; not such a perfect skeleton – A fine gallery
                    (Nicholson says 70 yards long) quite entire – the dungeon is very much filled
                    up, but seemed small altogether as far as I could judge from the outside – for
                    tho on the brink of the interior it was too dark to see anything of it without a
                    candle – the <placeName ref="pl1566">castle</placeName> is very irregular, but
                    very imposing, &amp; surely one of the most perfect specimens of castle
                    architecture now remaining – I think <persName ref="pe2205">Mr
                        Pennant</persName> would have done well to have taken the arch of the great
                    entrance as a model for the arch of his <hi rend="superscript">new</hi> gateway
                    at <placeName ref="pl1650">Penrhyn Castle</placeName> – He would thus have
                    avoided the seeming confusion of <hi rend="superscript">the</hi> ecclesiastical
                    &amp; castle style – we returned home immediately – it had begun to rain again
                    &amp; we just got in before it came on heavily &amp; continued with little
                    intermission more or less the rest of the evening – Dinner at 6 \({1\over 4}\) –
                    salmon &amp; a roasted leg of mutton, 7 or 8lbs &amp; very good – it was, the
                    waiter said, the common size – He mentioned <persName ref="pe2207">Mr
                        Roberts</persName>, the harper, who won the silver medal (a small silver
                    harp) at the Eisteddfod in 1821 at <placeName ref="pl0792">Wrexham</placeName><note type="editorial">The Wrexham Eisteddfod at which
                        Roberts won the silver harp was held in 1820 rather than 1821.</note> – we
                    asked what we should give him – the waiter said people seldom gave him less than
                    \({1\over 2}\) crown, &amp; if he made a charge, he would charge \({1\over 2}\)
                    crown an hour for he was not a common harper but a sort of teacher &amp; master
                    bard among them. He came at 9 &amp; played \({15\over 60}\) hours in our room,
                    for which we gave him 3/. He seemed satisfied – played us several Welsh airs,
                        <persName ref="pe2208">Handel</persName>'s 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>
                    concerto &amp;c. &amp; is certainly a fine performer with great execution &amp;
                    taste – He had<note type="authorial">no unnecessary quavering with his hands but
                        held them steadily parallel with the strings – he played us what he played
                        first at Wrexham "Sweet Richard" with good &amp; very difficult variations –
                        from us he went to the party in the next room that we still had the benefit
                        of him. [‘Sweet Richard' was a well-known Welsh air in the period, which had
                        been included in numerous musical collections (see, for example, Edward
                        Jones's <hi rend="italic">Musical and Poetical Relicks</hi> (1784)). The air
                        was closely associated with Roberts after his Eisteddfod win, and was
                        published in London in 1821 under the title <hi rend="italic">Sweet Richard:
                            performed at the Congress of Welsh Bards at Wrexham by Richard Roberts
                            of Carnarvon, who gained the Silver Harp, with variations by John
                            Parry</hi> (London: J. Power, 1821).]</note>
                    <lb/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <pb n="50"/><fw>[f. 50]</fw>
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>Saturday 20 July<note type="authorial">written at Beddgelert</note>
                    <lb/> My <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> called me at 6 \({10\over 60}\)
                    – got up immediately – all quite ready for being off after breakfast – my
                        <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> &amp; I went out a few minutes before
                    8 – walked to the top of the hill behind the hotel – The view is certainly very
                    fine – high water – very hot &amp; close portending rain – returned to the
                    house, turned down a narrow sort of grassy lane to the shore of the <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai</placeName>, thence along the fashionable walk of the
                    town (a sort of rampart-walk, broad &amp; neatly gravelled) at the foot of the
                    town-wall along the <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai</placeName> – round the
                        <placeName ref="pl1566">castle</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl3127">Queen
                        Eleanor's gate</placeName> – here <hi rend="superscript">(at 9 \({10\over
                        60}\))</hi> my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> (being a little
                    rheumatic) left me &amp; returned home – I pursued the stream of <hi rend="superscript">or rather road along</hi> the <placeName ref="pl3128">Seiont</placeName> in pursuit of traces of old <placeName ref="pl2023">Segontium</placeName> – passed a little square remain – came to a bridge of
                    2 or 3 arches across the river (beautifully wooded for a considerable distance
                    on the opposite bank) a neat white washed house or 2, a turnpike &amp; 2 roads
                    on the other side, &amp; little cascade just on this side of the bridge &amp;
                    very pretty view – turned up the hill on my left – an uneven surfaced <hi rend="superscript">stony</hi> grass-grown mound, probably the site of
                    ancient buildings – crossed a field &amp; came into a road – passed close by a
                    farm-house built adjoining the round tower remains of the old Roman
                    fortification – the wall seemed the farm-yard boundary on one side, &amp; so
                    covered with ivy on the other I could make nothing of it – In fact I was
                    uncertain about it entirely (foolishly not having a guide with me) &amp; had no
                    time to loiter strolled thro' the town to the market place – fine mutton 4d a lb
                    veal 3 \({1\over 2}\) – saw no beef. Neat, small, covered market place thence to
                    the Goat Inn – &amp; thence inquired my way to the bank – not open – a young man
                    at the door civilly let me in &amp; gave me 10 sovereigns for a £10 Bank of
                    England &amp; would charge nothing – the Welsh prefer <unclear>country</unclear>
                    notes to Bank of England there are so many forgeries – went direct home by the
                    walk along the <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai</placeName> &amp; sat down to
                    breakfast immediately at 10 \({1\over 4}\) – Very good house – very civil people
                    &amp; we may safely recommend our friends there – It would be a good place for
                    head-quarters – like the town of <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>
                    very much – Fine view of the <placeName ref="pl1566">castle</placeName> this
                    morning a little from the town on the back of the <placeName ref="pl3128">Seiont</placeName> – most beautiful remain of castle architecture –
                        <persName ref="pe2209">Mr Bettiss</persName> of the hotel saw us off, gave
                    us his card, &amp; hoped we had been comfortable – off at 11 \({1\over 4}\) –
                    perhaps \({1\over 2}\) mile on our road (the <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName> road) we came to a cottage forty or fifty yards from
                    a neat white washed church – at this cottage I got out &amp; turned into the
                    field on our right to see the old Roman wall or fort described by <persName ref="pe2085">Bingley</persName> vol. 1 p. 170,<note type="editorial">See
                        Bingley I: 170: ‘Not far from hence is the antient fort which belonged to
                        it; this is also of an oblong figure, and contains about an acre of ground.
                        The walls are at present about eleven feet high and six in thickness, and at
                        each corner there has formerly been a tower.'</note> et seq. &amp; vid.
                    Nicholson's guide p. 283<note type="editorial">‘Near the Seiont was a strong
                        fort, intended to secure a landing-place at the time of high water. This was
                        of an oblong shape included in an area of about one acre. Two sides of the
                        walls are nearly entire.'</note> – I had seen the opposite extremity before
                    breakfast – stopt \({1\over 4}\) hour – ran along the remain inside &amp; out to
                    find a place free from ivy, or grass, or brushwood – it is almost wholly covered
                    with one or other so as to resemble a bank fence – however, at the extremity of
                    the field next the road there is a bare part which shews the Roman method of
                    building &amp; farther in thro' a gap, I discovered 1 or 2 of the small
                    perforations so much spoken of thro' the wall transversly – vid. King's
                    muniments on the Roman manner of building<note type="editorial">A reference to
                        Edward King's Munimenta Antiqua; or, Observations on Ancient Castles,
                        published in four volumes between 1799 and 1806. King discusses Caernarfon
                        in Volume III (1804).</note> – we reached here <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName> the Jones' Arms<note type="editorial">Probably a
                        reference to the hotel later known as the Royal Goat, built in 1802 by
                        Thomas Jones; see <ref type="http" target="http://www.coflein.gov.uk/en/site/16816/details/royal-goat-hotelbeddgelert-hotel">here</ref>.</note>
                    <hi rend="superscript">at 2 \({35\over 60}\)</hi> (Mr Jones of <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> owner of the new inn, a <hi rend="superscript">neat nice house</hi>, beautifully situated to the right,
                    a little above the village, &amp; across the stream – planted all about &amp;
                        <hi rend="superscript">thus</hi> embosomed in wood – remarkably pretty –
                    very fine drive from <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> here –
                        <placeName ref="pl2855">Bettws Garmon</placeName> only 2 or 3 poor cottages
                    – noticed Nant mill very pretty little cascade – quite close to the road on our
                    right &amp; too little fence to protect us from the stream – noticed also
                    [blank] Williams' – white <hi rend="superscript">or yellow</hi> washed –
                    plantations about the house (larch trees as there are here about the inn) &amp;
                    very pretty – the pass or entrance to <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName> very narrow rugged &amp; singularly fine – on
                    entering it &amp; coming down the hill I could not help saying to my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> this is the prettiest sublime we have seen<note type="editorial">For a contemporary depiction of Beddgelert, including the
                        river, cottages and steep-sided setting, see Mary Smirke, ‘Betgellert
                        Bridge' (c. 1808), <ref type="http" target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Betgellert_bridge,_Carnarvonshire.jpeg">here</ref>.</note> – the village is in as it were a small basin formed
                    by high rough mountains – the rock darkened with heath or moss &amp; finely bare
                    here &amp; there – the bottom of the basin beautifully verdant with here &amp;
                    there trees about the few cottages, &amp; a stream tumbling over its rocky bed
                    thro' the midst – it is [in] fact <hi rend="superscript">far</hi> the most
                    picturesque village we have yet met with – some very heavy showers as we came
                    along – the clouds tremendously black – the top of <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName> quite enveloped – got here in the beginning of a very
                    heavy shower – Just 3 \({35\over 60}\) i.e. an hour since we got in – <lb/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <pb n="51"/><fw>[f. 51]</fw> looking a little at <persName ref="pe2085">Bingley</persName> &amp; Nicholson's Cambrian Guide<note type="authorial">written at Tan y Bwlch Inn 10</note> – at 4 took a little girl to carry the
                    plaid &amp; umbrella &amp; set off to <placeName ref="pl3152">Dinas
                        Emris</placeName>
                    <hi rend="superscript">about 1 ½ mile on the <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel
                            Curig</placeName> road in Cwm Cloch</hi> – we had gone little more than
                    a mile, when the poor child began to cry, &amp; I sent her back again – walked
                    forward 2 miles (i.e. about \({1\over 2}\) mile beyond <placeName ref="pl3152">Dinas Emris</placeName>) a little way along Lake Dinas – small house at the
                    end of it &amp; some green fertile looking fields – a little plantation at the
                    house – I longed to have gone further as far as <placeName ref="pl3136">Lake
                        Gwinant</placeName> – the scenery as far as I did go, very fine – got back
                    at 5 \({10\over 60}\) in the midst of a heavy shower – very hot with walking –
                    Off from <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName> for <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan-y-Bwlch</placeName> at 5 \({35\over 60}\) – the scenery for
                    the first 3 miles terrifically fine – <placeName ref="pl1525">Pont-Aber-Glasyn</placeName> bridge tremendous – the road for a good way
                    down to it narrow &amp; no fence or merely a <hi rend="superscript">single
                        row</hi> of great stones to guard the precipice – there is no great cataract
                    – but the unguardedness of the road, the [deletion] torrent tumbling over rocks
                    below &amp; the perpendicular rock to the height of 2 or 3 hundred feet on the
                    other side form a most impressive scene – there is a turnpike just beyond the
                    bridge thro' which we went up a tremendously steep hill, from which a fine view
                    down an opening upon the <placeName ref="pl1524">Traethmawr</placeName> sands.
                    Indeed the whole stage (they called it 10 miles at <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName>) is tremendously hilly – the scenery is
                    indescribably fine – the first <hi rend="superscript">about</hi> 3 miles &amp;
                    the last about 2 cannot surely be exceeded – but the whole far surpassed
                    anything we had seen – <placeName ref="pl1338">Penman Mawr</placeName> is a
                    different sort of thing <hi rend="superscript">should be excepted</hi> &amp;
                    should not be compared with it – Very fine peeps at <placeName ref="pl2862">Wyddfa</placeName> at intervals, &amp; the <placeName ref="pl3154">Glyder
                        mawr</placeName> – never saw <placeName ref="pl2862">Wyddfa</placeName> to
                    such advantage – In short, no one travelling in Wales should miss the drive from
                        <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan-y-Bwlch</placeName> – the road in many places not at all fenced off
                    from the precipice on one side – my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> sick
                    with fright more than <hi rend="superscript">once</hi> – several heavy showers
                    as we came along, just in our faces, particularly for 50 or 100 yards just after
                    leaving <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName> &amp; for the last
                    \({1\over 2}\) mile – the inn most beautifully situated at the foot of an almost
                    perpendicular steep wooded from top to bottom – tremendous descending the road
                    down it – a most comfortable inn – sat down to dinner at 9 \({1\over 2}\) (got
                    here in 2 \({20\over 60}\) hours at 5 minutes before 8) fryed salmon, a <hi rend="superscript">very</hi> small fish cut in slices – a roast loin of
                    mutton &amp; apple tart &amp; cream – the best potatoes I have tasted in Wales –
                    the mutton most excellent, the best we have had – we have enjoyed our dinner
                    exceedingly &amp; both had a nap since – my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> is just gone to bed – instead of wine, a bottle of very
                    fair cider – they get it from <placeName ref="pl1302">Bristol</placeName> – Did
                    not begin this page till 10 50/60 &amp; it is now 11 \({1\over 2}\) – Very <hi rend="superscript">heavy</hi> showers repeatedly during the day – but tho'
                    we had our coats &amp;c. dried at <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName>
                    &amp; here we escaped getting much wet – 12 miles from <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> to B_ 10 from B_ here – the roads roughish &amp;
                    very hilly <hi rend="superscript">very</hi> particularly this last stage, yet
                    Percy came in not at all tired – He is a capital gig-horse – Went upstairs to
                    bed at 11 \({40\over 60}\) – sat up reading Nicholson's Cambrian Guide article
                    Harlech &amp;c.<note type="editorial">See Nicholson, pp. 573-81.</note> &amp;
                    looked over our accounts – [code: a great deal of discharge yesterday &amp;
                    today &amp; ever since I left home]<lb/>
                </p>
                <lb/>
                <p>Sunday 21 July<lb/>We had found as much as \({1\over 2}\) hour difference in the
                    clocks in a single stage – these a quarter later than those at <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> which latter I go by – Very rainy night
                    &amp; morning – enough to wet one thro' in 2 or 3 minutes – Tis very doubtful
                    whether we can strike out at all today – the weather is so bad &amp; seems so
                    likely to continue so, and besides we are so limited for time, I think we must
                    give up <placeName ref="pl1520">Harlech</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelli</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl1866">Cader Idris</placeName>,
                    nay! Had it been fine perhaps we might have got to <placeName ref="pl1240">Aberystwyth</placeName> &amp; the <placeName ref="pl3155">Devil's
                        Bridge</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl3156">Hafod</placeName> – and we
                    must return by <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName> from here – came
                    downstairs at 9 \({1\over 2}\) quite ready for being off if the weather were
                    better – 12 50/60 after much watching the weather it seemed to clear a little
                    near 1pm, &amp; we determined to go to <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelli</placeName>
                    <hi rend="superscript">(18 miles)</hi> by the high road (<placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> road) vid. Cary p. 243<note type="editorial">Possibly a reference to Cary, pp. 169-71 (rather than p. 243), which lists
                        the Dolgellau-Beddgelert route.</note> – off from <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y Bwlch</placeName> at 1 \({40\over 60}\) &amp; got to <sic><placeName ref="pl3153">Trawsfynidd</placeName></sic>
                    <hi rend="superscript">in</hi> 1 32/60 hours – <hi rend="superscript">at 3
                        12/60</hi> – Trowsfinith pronounced) – a miserable village – perhaps a
                    tolerable town for North Wales – 6 miles from <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y
                        Bwlch</placeName> – <hi rend="superscript">passed</hi> the Highgate Inn, a
                    small pot-house, &amp; drove a little farther to the Cross Foxes Inn<note type="editorial">‘Wednesday 21 August 1822, the arms of William – Sir Watkin
                        Williams Wynne of Wynnstay' [marginal authorial note]. Lister is referring
                        to an inn some four miles outside Dolgellau, set on the junction where the
                        main roads heading north-south and east-west meet.</note> a good <hi rend="superscript">deal</hi> better in appearance than the other this still
                    a very common sort of ale-house the road <hi rend="superscript">here</hi> for
                    the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> \({1\over 2}\) way bad &amp; hilly <lb/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <pb n="52"/><fw>[f. 52]</fw>the latter pretty tolerable – a tremendous hill just
                    out of <placeName ref="pl1522">Maentwrog</placeName> where we passed the neat
                        <hi rend="superscript">looking</hi> little <placeName ref="pl3157">church</placeName> close on our right – In looking down the water saw
                        <placeName ref="pl1570">Tan y Bwlch</placeName> (<persName ref="pe0939">Mr
                        Oakley</persName>'s) embosomed in wood on the right of the declivity as we
                    went down to <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y Bwlch</placeName> last night – &amp;
                    on the same side of the vale about 3 miles from <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y
                        Bwlch</placeName> on the margins of the lake the village of <placeName ref="pl1523">Ffestiniog</placeName> whence the vale is commonly named by
                    tourists – the clock here is 30 minutes <hi rend="superscript">later than</hi>
                    from that at <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y Bwlch</placeName> &amp; \({1\over
                    2}\) hour later than <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> – the clocks
                    at <placeName ref="pl1576">Cernioge</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel Curig</placeName> varied about \({1\over 2}\) hour – a little rain as
                    we set off but rest of the way fair – a shower just as we stopt here – soon lost
                    sight of the Vale of Festiniog which is certainly very beautiful – well
                    cultivated, well wooded, &amp; fertile – the road after leaving it bounded by
                    high rugged mountains more or less distant so distant as scarcely to form what
                    one would call a vale – the high &amp; bleak intervening ground <hi rend="superscript">[illegible] strewed</hi> with large rude masses of stone
                    – passed thro' a little wood of moss-grown oaks up a hill near here –
                        "<placeName ref="pl3153">Trawsfynidd</placeName> a large village" vid.
                    Nicholson's Cambrian Guide p. 795<note type="editorial">‘<hi rend="superscript">Trawsfynydd</hi>, a large village situated in an open barren country,
                        where there is a public-house, but Welsh only is spoken.'</note> "a mean
                    village" vid. p. 1272.<note type="editorial">‘After passing the mean village of
                        Trawsfynydd, mr. Skrine proceeded to view the famous cascade of
                        Dolymleynllyn'.</note>
                    <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelle</placeName> 9 \({5\over 60}\) – arrived here at
                    8 \({5\over 60}\) i.e. twelve miles in 3 \({20\over 60}\) hours having left
                        <placeName ref="pl3153">Trawsfynidd</placeName> at 4 \({3\over 4}\) – the
                    first 4 miles of the road very bad made with stones broken into such large
                    pieces, or paved as it were with them so roughly, we were obliged to walk all
                    the way &amp; still were shocked &amp; jolted – the country too bleak &amp;
                    dreary &amp; uninteresting, the mountains receding too far – yet a few little
                    cottages or poorish little farm houses – almost ricked off the road, when, at
                    the end of the first 4 miles the mountains began to approach each other, the
                        <sic>Mawdach</sic><note type="editorial">River which feeds into the Mawddach
                        Estuary.</note> rushed along its rocky bed on our right, &amp; the scenery
                    became <hi rend="superscript">wooded &amp;</hi> very fine – by &amp; by crossed
                    the river &amp; <hi rend="superscript">then</hi> had it all along on our left –
                    several little streams ruched into the river – one forming a beautiful cascade
                    close on our right &amp; then rushed thro' a bridge under the road – 2 or 3
                    gentlemen's seats – the wood, the water, the stupendous mountain ranges one each
                    side forming a landscape surely not to be surpassed! – the town of
                        <sic>Dolgelle</sic> finely situated &amp; opened upon us beautifully. Indeed
                    the whole of the last eight miles of this road baffles description – we have
                    seen nothing to compare with it – the coming down upon <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName> is very fine, as also thro' <placeName ref="pe0939">Mr Oakley</placeName>'s woods down to <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y
                        Bwlch</placeName>, but I give the preference to the last 8 miles of today
                    &amp; think no one should visit <placeName ref="pl1221">N.W.</placeName> without
                    travelling this road – the approach to &amp; view of <placeName ref="pl1338">Penman Mawr</placeName> (which perhaps struck me the most <hi rend="superscript">at the time</hi>; the tremendous grandeur of the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 3 miles from <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y Bwlch</placeName>
                    including Pont Aberglaslyn &amp; the peep down upon <placeName ref="pl1524">Traithmawr</placeName> Sands – and the savage sublimity of the scenery
                    about <placeName ref="pl3148">Ogwen Pool</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl1529">Nant Frayon</placeName> have together with the last 8 miles of today,
                    impressed me as the best worth seeing things we have met with – <hi rend="superscript">dinner at 6</hi> My <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName>'s bowels not quite well (the cider yesterday might disagree
                    with her) &amp; she had tea immediately on our arrival – I had part of a loin of
                    mutton roasted – very good &amp; tender, a piece of salmon boiled &amp; an apple
                    pie or tart with a bottle of cider, of which I did not quite drink a tumbler
                    glass – wrote the last 14 lines after dinner – had done them at 10 50/60 having
                        1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> settled with <persName ref="pe2198">George</persName>. Very sleepy &amp; went upstairs at 11 [code: my
                        <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> &amp; I for the first time have a
                    double bedded room but I have managed to get a dressing room up in the garret –
                    great deal of discharge] </p>
                <p> Monday 22 July <lb/> Capital lodgings rooms, good bed &amp; slept well –
                    Breakfast at 10 – the worst breakfast I have had because the butter strong &amp;
                    not good &amp; the coffee bad or perhaps the boiled milk a little inclined to be
                    sourish – Rained all the night sometimes very heavily &amp; rainy morning that
                    at once we gave up all thought of going to <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName> or doing anything but make the best of our way home –
                    my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName>'s bowels better this morning but she
                    looks ill – 'Tis now 12 – have been reading Nicholson's guide ever since
                    breakfast – (<placeName ref="pl3158">Drws y Nant Inn</placeName>, ale-house by
                    the road side, W. Jones 8 miles from <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelle</placeName>) stopt here to bait the horses at 2 \({20\over 60}\)
                    having left <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelle</placeName> at 12 \({3\over 4}\) –
                    Beautiful drive as far as here, chiefly thro' wood, the <placeName ref="pl3108">Wnion</placeName><note type="editorial">‘Pronounced as if spelt anglice
                        Winnion' [marginal authorial note].</note> river accompanying us from
                        <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelle</placeName> &amp; foaming on our right – it
                    forms several pretty cascades particularly 1 under a bridge perhaps a mile or 2
                    from here – Just before leaving <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelle</placeName>,
                    for 20 minutes walked round the town – certainly a poor place according to
                    English ideas – the cottages miserable, tho' apparently of the better sort for
                        <placeName ref="pl1221"><hi rend="superscript">North</hi> Wales</placeName>
                    – mud floors – the smell of the peat fires is strong &amp; disagreeable to those
                    not accustomed <lb/>
                    <pb n="53"/><fw>[f. 53]</fw>to it – &amp; the large masses of the dark mountain
                    stone used for building, the unevenness of them in all but the better kind of
                    houses filled up with lesser fragments give the buildings an unusually dark rude
                    appearance which, with broken windows, completes the shabby look of the cottages
                    in <placeName ref="pl1221">North Wales</placeName> – But the fine blue roofing
                    slate very commonly used is remarkably neat, &amp; seems oddly contrasted with
                    the rest – there is a sort of square (market place) at <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelle</placeName> – on one side the <placeName ref="pl3159">Angel
                        Inn</placeName> with a penthouse or covered way in front, facing a row of
                    poor-looking cottages with a covered way also in front – at another side the
                    "Caravansery" or Red Lion Inn,<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note> &amp;
                    opposite to it the <placeName ref="pl3160">Ship Inn</placeName> apparently a new
                    erection &amp; next best inn to the <placeName ref="pl1886">Golden
                        Lion</placeName> close to the church to which you turn to the right on
                    entering the town from <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y Bwlch</placeName> – this
                    inn consists of 2 capital erections (for a Welsh town, where the inns seem
                    generally the best houses) on each side of the street fronting each other – the
                    one to our left as we arrived has the sign – here everything is cooked &amp;
                    carried across the street to the other house in which we were the former being
                    full – but our part had a covered door-way supported on 2 slender pillars &amp;
                    I think cut the best appearance – the people very civil – woman waiter – steady
                    elderly woman who had lived there many years – nice steady elderly chambermaid –
                    stopt a minute at a small stationers shop in the square at <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelle</placeName> – a <unclear>cat</unclear> doctoring book
                    in Welsh &amp; English, <hi rend="superscript">description of</hi>
                    <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelle</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl1866">Cader
                        Idris</placeName> 2/- – English testament – map of <placeName ref="pl1221">North Wales</placeName> in a case – 2 or 3 Welsh pamphlets in the window –
                    as we entered the town, near the bridge on the left a handsomish new erection
                    nearly finished for a town or county hall – In the walls of this as of the
                        <placeName ref="pl1886">Golden Lion</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl3160">Ship Inn</placeName>, the large masses of stone cut regularly
                    &amp; look well enough, tho' dark &amp; heavy – the clouds came over the
                    mountains &amp; we feared a continuance of the rain – we had had only a drop or
                    2 for a moment once or twice, &amp; seem to have left it behind us – yet the
                    clouds have quite hid the highest summits of the mountains, yet we have had no
                    good view of <placeName ref="pl1866">Cadir Idris</placeName> – (<placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName> – <placeName ref="pl3161">White Lion
                        Inn</placeName> – Ellis 8 \({1\over 4}\) p.m.) Left <placeName ref="pl3109">Drws y Nant</placeName> at 3 \({3\over 4}\) &amp; got here at 5 50/60 – all
                    the guide books mention the <placeName ref="pl3162">Bull</placeName> as the best
                    inn; the people at <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelle</placeName> recommended us
                    to the White Lion – Drove thro' the town to compare appearances &amp; stopt at
                    the latter tho' my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> thought the <placeName ref="pl3162">Bull's Head</placeName> rather the better looking of the 2 –
                    However, I think we are right – the landlady is a very nice woman – everything
                    seems very clean &amp; comfortable &amp;, so far, I should certainly recommend
                    the house – my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> had a little mutton broth
                    with a boiled steak or 2 in it – I had a small loin of mutton (very good)
                    roasted, good peas &amp; potatoes, &amp; a very good bilberry tart – no wine –
                    only cold water – Walked a little into the town before dinner (sat down to table
                    about 7) &amp; also afterwards – better town than <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelle</placeName> – we admired it very much as we entered – wide street
                    7 or 8 young elm trees on our left – a neat town-hall opposite our inn <hi rend="superscript">(our inn on the left)</hi> – a neat church<note type="editorial">Probably a reference to the chapel that stood on the site
                        now occupied by the parish church, Christ Church; see <ref type="http" target="http://www.coflein.gov.uk/en/site/43832/details/christ-church-bala-gwynedd">here</ref>.</note> a little farther on the same side as the town hall –
                    the church very neatly pewed (peeped in at the window) &amp; apparently recently
                    built – 3 or 4 little streets besides the main street &amp; I should think
                        <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName> must rank high among the good towns
                    in <placeName ref="pl1221">North Wales</placeName> – The drive from <placeName ref="pl3109">Drws y Nant</placeName> very uninteresting till we came in sight of
                    the <placeName ref="pl2101">Bala lake</placeName> – which we kept close on our
                    right (often no fence to guard the road from it) <hi rend="superscript">up</hi>
                    to the very town at last within a fields' length – a beautiful sheet of water –
                    full when we saw it, its surface curled like the waves of the sea &amp; at this
                    end a little surf – quite as much as we saw at the foot on <placeName ref="pl1338">Penman Mawr</placeName> – the gentlemen's cottages very
                    prettily situated on the East bank of the lake – very fair road all the way –
                    great deal of hay to get in <placeName ref="pl1221">North Wales</placeName>
                    &amp; a good deal to cut – the grass very thin &amp; short, not at all equal to
                    one of our middling pastures – little corn to be seen anywhere &amp; that only,
                    thin short oats or barley. I <hi rend="superscript">have</hi> somewhere seen a
                    little rye, but do not remember any wheat in <placeName ref="pl1221">North
                        Wales</placeName>. Very few cattle &amp; those only the small black breed
                    &amp; occasionally a few brindled red – sheep up &amp; down the mountains, but
                    not so small as I expected. Have only seem 1 <hi rend="superscript">goat a</hi>
                    little tame thing at <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> – I had an
                    idea of pretty grey Welsh ponys but have seen nothing of the sort – Should not
                    have known the horses I have seen from English – the weather improved before we
                    left <placeName ref="pl3109">Drws y Nant</placeName>, &amp; had a pretty fine afternoon. A few drops of rain sent us
                    in about 8 \({1\over 2}\) but it seems [illegible] off again for the present –
                    Settled with <persName ref="pe2198">George</persName> &amp; paid the bill,
                    meaning to be off to <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName> at 7 in the
                    morning – went upstairs at 9 50/60 – [code: Sat up hunting for a frill &amp;
                    adding up my accounts. Find one pound short] In taking out my purse at
                        <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y Bwlch</placeName>, I let fall some sovereigns
                    &amp; surely did not pick them all up – I must have lost one<note type="editorial">‘Wednesday night 21 August 1822 On settling my accounts at
                        home found I had not lost a sovereign – I had ommitted setting down the
                        Cambrian guide bought at Cernioge' [marginal authorial note].</note> [code:
                    great deal of discharge]</p>
                <p>
                    <pb n="54"/><fw>[f. 54]</fw> Tuesday 23 July<lb/> Good bed, very clean &amp;
                    comfortable &amp; slept well – Rainy night &amp; rainy morning – yet no prospect
                    of doing any good by waiting &amp; off from <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName> (the <placeName ref="pl3161">White Lion Inn</placeName>,
                    John Ellis) at 7 \({25\over 60}\) – the upper road to <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName> only ten miles, but had come the lower (14 miles) thro'
                    the <placeName ref="pl3098">Vale of Edeirnion</placeName> on account of the scenery –
                    Beautiful vale – the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName> nearly close on our
                    right most of the way – winds most beautifully, flowing gently between its low
                    banks occasionally prettily wooded – what a contrast to the torrents <hi rend="superscript">which</hi> we have lately been accustomed to a beautiful
                    vale – But it rained all the way to the last of the turnpikes about or near
                    \({1\over 2}\) mile from <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName> &amp; our
                    view was sadly spoilt by the thickening of the weather &amp; the gig – top up –
                    Did not know the town or the inn again – could scarce believe it the same place
                    we stopt at on Sunday-week (p.44) Left <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName>
                    at 7 \({25\over 60}\) &amp; got here in 2 \({20\over 60}\) hours at 9 \({3\over
                    4}\) – Breakfast immediately – (<placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> –
                        <placeName ref="pl3086">King's Head</placeName>, new hotel Mr Davis 2
                    \({3\over 4}\) p.m.) Left <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName> at 11
                    \({35\over 60}\) &amp; got here in 1 \({1\over 2}\) hours (10 miles
                    government-made road, most excellent in spite of having been almost deluged with
                    rain) at 1 \({5\over 60}\) – the Vale of Corwen beautiful certainly, but as I
                    have repeatedly told my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> would be the
                    case, it now seemed tame after the scenery we have seen – yet the <placeName ref="pl3098">Vale of Edeirnion</placeName> pleased us, even in the rain,
                    &amp; we prefer it to that of Corwen which saw more distinctly – as we had the
                    top down all the way – a drop or 2 of rain just after setting off &amp; a shower
                    for about the 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> mile from <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> – heavy rain just after we got in – <persName ref="pe2179">Mrs Davis</persName> received us at the door &amp; came into
                    our rooms to answer our enquiries after <persName ref="pe0954">Lady Eleanor
                        Butler</persName>. <persName ref="pe2179">Mrs Davis</persName> was called up
                    at one last night, &amp; they thought her ladyship would have died – she was,
                    however, rather better this morning – the physician does not seem to apprehend
                    danger, but Mrs D- is alarmed &amp; spoke of it in tears. <persName ref="pe0957">Miss Ponsonby</persName>, too, is alarmed &amp; ill herself, on this
                    account – pain in her side "She is a lady" said Mrs D– "of very strong ideas;
                    but this would grieve her too" – Mrs D– has only known them 13 or 14 years
                    during which time she has lived at this house but had always seen them "so
                    attached, so amiable together" – no two people ever lived more happily – they
                    like all the people about them, are beloved by all &amp; do a great deal of
                    good. <persName ref="pe0954">Lady Eleanor</persName> has the remains of beauty.
                        <persName ref="pe0957">Miss Ponsonby</persName> was a very fine woman.
                        <persName ref="pe0954">Lady E.B.</persName> about 80. <persName ref="pe0957">Miss P–</persName> 10 or 12 years younger. The damp this bad account casts
                    upon my spirits I cannot describe – I am interested about these 2 ladies very
                    much – there is something in their story &amp; in all I have heard about them
                    here that, added to other circumstances, makes a deep impression. Sat musing on
                    the sopha, wotting what to do, inconsolate &amp; moody [code: Thinking of
                        <persName ref="pe2175">M–</persName> Low about her. I cannot shake off the
                    impression of what she said at <placeName ref="pl0002">Chester</placeName> about
                    delicacy in calculating <persName ref="pe2177">C</persName>'s life, Mr Powis,
                    etc. I know not how it is, I am shockingly low altogether.] <persName ref="pe2179">Mrs Davis</persName> being going to enquire after <persName ref="pe0954">Lady E.B.</persName> my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName>
                    &amp; I walked with her to wait for her giving an answer to our inquiries – the
                    physician there – strolled about <hi rend="superscript">for</hi> 10 minutes,
                    &amp; he not being gone &amp; it threatening to rain, returned &amp; only just
                    got in before a tremendously heavy shower – then sat down &amp; wrote the above
                    of today. I feel better for this writing – in fact, come what may, writing my
                    journals – thus, as it were, throwing my mind on paper always does me good.
                        <persName ref="pe2179">Mrs Davis</persName> just returned – brought <hi rend="superscript">a good account of her ladyship and</hi> a message of
                    thanks for our enquiries from <persName ref="pe0957">Miss Ponsonby</persName>
                    who will be glad to see me this evening to thank me in person – shall <hi rend="superscript">go</hi> about 6 \({1\over 2}\) or 7, just after dinner.
                    [code: This is more than I expected. I wonder how I work my way &amp; what she
                    will think of me. <persName ref="pe2179">Mrs Davis</persName> wishes me to give
                    all the comfort, all I can, &amp; not to mention that I know of her having been
                    called up last night] (9 p.m.) Dinner at 6 [code: Before dinner about two hours
                    upstairs and washing, cutting my toenails, putting clean things &amp;c] At 7
                    went to <placeName ref="pl1614">Plas Newydd</placeName> &amp; got back at 8 –
                    just an hour away &amp; surely the walking there &amp; back did not take me more
                    than 20 minutes. Shewn into the room next the library (the breakfast room)
                    waited a minute or 2, &amp; then came <persName ref="pe0957">Miss P–</persName>
                    a large woman <hi rend="superscript">so as to waddle in walking but</hi> tho'
                    not taller than myself – in a blue <hi rend="superscript">shortish waisted
                        cloth</hi> habit, the jacket unbuttoned shewing a plain plaited <hi rend="superscript">frilled</hi> habit shirt – a thick white cravat, rather
                    loosely put on – hair powdered, parted I think down the middle in front, cut a
                    moderate length all round &amp; hanging straight, tolerably thick – the remains
                    of a very fine face – coarsish white cotton stockings – ladies slipper shoes cut
                    low down, the foot hanging a little over – altogether a very odd figure – yet
                    she had no sooner entered into conversation than I forgot all this &amp; my
                    attention was wholly taken by her manners &amp; conversation – <lb/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <pb n="55"/><fw>[f. 55]</fw> The former, perfectly easy, peculiarly attentive
                    &amp; well <hi rend="superscript">bred</hi> &amp; bespeaking a person accustomed
                    to a great deal of good society – mild &amp; gentle, certainly not masculine,
                    &amp; yet there was a je-ne-sais-quoi striking – her conversation shewing a
                    personal acquaintance with most of the literary characters of the day &amp;
                    their works – she seems sanguine about <persName ref="pe0954">Lady
                        Eleanor</persName>'s recovery – poor soul! My heart ached to think how small
                    the chance – she told me that her ladyship had undergone an operation 3 times –
                    the sight of one eye restored! – couching by absorption – I said I believed it
                    was neither a painful nor dangerous operation – she seemed to think <hi rend="superscript">it</hi> both, the one &amp; the other. Mentioned the
                    beauty of the place – the books I had noticed in their rustic library – she said
                        <persName ref="pe0954">Lady E–</persName> read French, Spanish &amp; Italian
                    – had great knowledge of ancient manners &amp; customs, understood the obsolete
                    manners &amp; phrases of Tasso<note type="editorial">A reference to the Italian
                        poet Torquato Tasso (1544-95).</note> remarkably well – had written
                    elucidatory notes on the first 2 (or 4, I think) books of Tasso, but had given
                    away the only copy she ever had. Contrived to ask if they were Classical – "No!"
                    (said she) "Thank God from Latin &amp; Greek I'm free" – Speaking of
                    translations she mentioned La Cerda's<note type="editorial">The Spanish Jesuit
                        scholar Juan Luis de la Cerda's (1558-1643) <hi rend="italic">Commentary on Virgil</hi> was
                        published in 1647.</note> (I think it was) as the best according to some
                    bishop friend of hers, of Virgil &amp; Cary's<note type="editorial">Henry
                        Francis Cary (1772-1844), literary translator best known for his translation
                        of Dante's <hi rend="italic">The Divine Comedy</hi> (1805-14).</note> as being most excellent of
                    Tasso, literal &amp; excellent for a beginner &amp; which she should recommend
                    to anyone wanting assistance. She somehow mentioned Lucretius,<note type="editorial">A reference to the first-century poet and philosopher Titus
                        Lucretius Carus, whose only known work is <hi rend="italic">De Rerum
                            Natura</hi>.</note> but it was "a bad book &amp; she was afraid of
                    reading it" – I asked why – he was a deistical writer – I mentioned Dr John
                    Mason Good's translation,<note type="editorial">English writer and physician
                        (1764-1827), who published his verse translation of Lucretius's <hi rend="italic">De Rerum Natura as The Nature of Things: A Didactic
                            Poem</hi> in 1805.</note> adding that I believed he <hi rend="superscript">Dr Good</hi> was not a high church man. "No! She knew he
                    was heterodox". I observed that <hi rend="superscript">she might think</hi> all
                    the classics objectionable. "Yes! They wanted pruning, but the Delphin
                        Editions<note type="editorial">A reference to the Delphin Classics,
                        published in London by Abraham John Valpy in the early nineteenth
                        century.</note> were very good – as people got older, she said, they were
                    more particular – she was almost afraid of reading Cain,<note type="editorial">Byron's verse drama, <hi rend="italic">Cain: A Mystery</hi>, a reworking of
                        the biblical story of Cain and Abel, was published in 1821.</note> tho'
                        <persName ref="pe2185">Lord B</persName> had been very good in sending them
                    several of his works. I asked if she had read Don Juan<note type="editorial">Byron's unfinished epic satire <hi rend="italic">Don Juan</hi> was published between 1819 and 1824
                        – cantos I-V of the poem had been published by the time of Lister's
                        visit.</note> – she was ashamed to say she had read the 1st canto – she said
                    I had named Mr Bankes – &amp; asked if it was Mr Bankes Cleava<note type="editorial">Possibly a reference to William John Bankes (1786-1855). A
                        note preserved in the Bankes family archive in Dorset History Centre
                        confirms that Bankes visited Plas Newydd in 1805.</note> – I thought not,
                    did not know him, but he was the most particular friend of a friend of mine – it
                    was Mr B– the great Grecian, said to be now the best in England since Mr
                    Parson's death.<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note> She did not think he
                    had ever been there, did not know, did not remember him. She asked if I would
                    walk out – shewed me the kitchen garden – walked round the shrubbery with me –
                    she said she owned to their having been 42 years there. They landed first in
                        <placeName ref="pl1245">South Wales</placeName>, but it did not answer the
                    accounts they had heard of it – they then travelled in <placeName ref="pl1221">North Wales</placeName> &amp;, taken with the beauty of this place, took
                    the cottage for 31 years – but it was a false lease &amp; they had had a great
                    deal of trouble &amp; expense. It was only 4 years since they had bought the
                    place. Dared say I had a much nicer place at home – mentioned its situation,
                    great age, long time in the family, &amp;c. She wished to know where to find an
                    account of it – said it had been their humble endeavour to make the place as old
                    as they could. Spoke like a woman of the world about liking the place where I
                    was born &amp;c – said I was not born there – my father was a younger brother
                    but that I had the expectation of succeeding my <persName ref="pe2186">uncle</persName> – "Ah ,Yes," said she "you will soon be the master &amp;
                    there will be an end of romance" "Never! Never!" said I. I envied their place
                    &amp; the happiness they had had there – dared say, they had never quarrelled –
                    "No!' they had never had a quarrel – little difference of opinion sometimes –
                    life could not go on without it – but only about the planting of a tree – and
                    when they differed in opinion, they took care to let no one see it." At parting
                    she <hi rend="superscript">shook hands with me and</hi> gave me a rose; I said I
                    should keep it for the sake of the place where it grew – <hi rend="superscript">she had before said she should be happy to introduce me some time to
                            <persName ref="pe0954">Lady Eleanor</persName></hi> – I had given my
                        <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName>'s compliments &amp; enquiries – said
                    she would have called with me but feared to intrude &amp; was not quite well
                    this evening – she (<persName ref="pe0957">Miss P–</persName>) gave me a sprig
                    of geranium for my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> with her compliments
                    &amp; thanks for her inquiries. <persName ref="pe0954">Lady E.</persName> was
                    asleep while I was there – <persName ref="pe0957">Miss P–</persName> had been
                    reading to her "Adam Blair"<note type="editorial">A reference to John Gibson
                        Lockhart's 1822 novel <hi rend="italic">Adam Blair</hi>, which
                        controversially depicted a clergyman's affair with a married woman.</note>
                    the little book recommended to me by <persName ref="pe2175">M–</persName> at
                        <placeName ref="pl0002">Chester</placeName>. I had told <persName ref="pe0957">Miss P–</persName> I had first seen an account of them in La
                    Belle Assemblee a dozen years ago,<note type="editorial">A reference to Madame
                        de Genlis's 1804 account of her visit to Butler and Ponsonby, published in
                            <hi rend="italic">La Belle Assemblée; or, Bell's Court and Fashionable
                            Magazine</hi> in 1808 (Vol. 5, 99-102). See Fiona Brideoake, <hi rend="italic">The Ladies of Llangollen: Desire, Indeterminacy, and the
                            Legacies of Criticism</hi> (Bucknell University Press, 2017), p.
                        281.</note> &amp; had longed to see the place ever since. She said some
                    people had been very impertinent, particularly <persName ref="pe2187">Dr
                        Mavor</persName>,<note type="editorial">A reference to William Fordyce
                        Mavor's account of Mary Carryl at Plas Newydd in volume 5 of his 6-volume
                            <hi rend="italic">The British Tourist's, or, Travellers's Pocket
                            Companion</hi> (London, 1809): ‘The cottage in reality deserves its
                        name. Only two rooms are shewn, – the dining-room and the library. Both are
                        adorned with exquisite drawings of scenes in Wales, and round the
                        chimney-pieces are some family miniatures, which were recognised by one of
                        the party, without applying to the old house-keeper who attended us, and who
                        is herself an original at full length' (p. 318).</note> who had in some way
                    displeased (laughed at, or something) their old housekeeper to whose memory they
                    had erected a monument in the church yard – &amp; it seems the ladies have a
                    particular objection to <persName ref="pe2187">Dr M–</persName> but <persName ref="pe0957">Miss P–</persName> appears to have lost her teeth &amp;
                    occasionally mumbles a little that as a stranger I did not always perhaps quite
                    understand <hi rend="superscript">her</hi> It seems 2 of the Cromptons &amp;
                    their brother (of Esholt)<note type="editorial">A reference to the Crompton
                        banking family of Esholt Hall, just north of Bradford. The family comprised
                        of nine siblings: the three mentioned here are Mary, Henrietta and William
                        Rookes Crompton. Henrietta's sketchbook of their 1821 Welsh tour survives in
                        North Yorkshire County Record Office. Lister socialised with the Cromptons
                        in York; for her opinion on the family see <hi rend="italic">The Secret
                            Diaries of Miss Lister</hi>, p. 269. For Henrietta Crompton see also
                            <ref type="http" target="https://collections.britishart.yale.edu/vufind/Record/2036493/Description ">here</ref>.</note> were lately sketching the place. The ladies sent
                    them chairs – went out to speak to them (for they were retiring, fearing they
                    had offended the ladies) – formed an acquaintance &amp;, wanting to know
                    something about the Derwentwater family<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note> which the C–s could get to know – there has been a
                    correspondence. <persName ref="pe0957">Miss P–</persName> said she had not
                    answered their last letter but meant to do it – <persName ref="pe0954">Lady
                        E.B.</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe0957">Miss P–</persName> seem great
                    pedigree people. antiquarians, topographers &amp;c. I came away much pleased
                    with <persName ref="pe0957">Miss P–</persName> &amp; sincerely hoping <persName ref="pe0954">Lady E–</persName> will recover to enjoy a few years more in
                    this world. I know not how it is, I felt low after coming away – a thousand
                    moody reflections occurred, but again, writing has done me good – went <hi rend="superscript">to</hi> &amp; returned from <placeName ref="pl1614">Plas
                        Newydd</placeName> in a gleam – showery afternoon &amp; evening – I mean to
                    dry &amp; keep the rose <persName ref="pe0957">Miss P–</persName> gave me – 'Tis
                    now 10 \({1\over 4}\). Sat talking to my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName>.
                    Came downstairs at 11 \({10\over 60}\) [code: forty minutes
                        <unclear>siding</unclear> my things in the imperial – used the syringe with
                    cold water three times today great deal of discharge]</p>
                <p>
                    <pb n="56"/><fw>[f. 56]</fw>Wednesday 24 July<lb/> Came downstairs at 9
                    \({20\over 60}\) – have just been to the harper to <unclear>tell</unclear> him
                    some of the most melancholy Welsh airs he knows – Have seen <persName ref="pe2179">Mrs Davis</persName> – <persName ref="pe0954">Lady
                        Eleanor</persName> has had a good night (<placeName ref="pl1246">Ruthin</placeName>, <hi rend="superscript">Cross-foxes or</hi> Wynnstay
                    Arms, 4 \({1\over 4}\) p.m.) [deletions] the property of <persName ref="pe0941">Sir Watkin Williams Wynn</persName>, but the <placeName ref="pl3123">White
                        Lion</placeName> is the best inn – as we do not stop except to bait the
                    horses did not go to the <placeName ref="pl3123">White Lion</placeName> because
                    they <hi rend="superscript">rather</hi> ill natured oppose the <placeName ref="pl3086">Kings Head</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> – yet the waiter recommended us to go there – Left
                        <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> at 11 &amp; did not get here
                    till 3 \({5\over 60}\) being 3 50/60 hours in coming 13 miles the old road is 12
                    miles the new 14 to save some tremendous hills – at the 2d turnpike from
                        <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> there were only some little
                    boys &amp; perhaps thro' <persName ref="pe2198">George</persName>'s manner of
                    inquiring (we sent him back to inquire) they sent us the lower way by which we
                    saved 1 mile before we got into the new road again, but were near an hour
                    ascending a most tremendous hill, rendered 10 times worse by the road being
                    furrowed by the rains in all directions – obliged to walk up &amp; got into the
                    gig again to sit during 2 or 3 heavy showers – about 7 miles from <placeName ref="pl1246">Ruthin</placeName> came into the new road at the <hi rend="superscript">3d</hi> turnpike – the road deluged with rain – cut up to
                    the nerve &amp; viler than any travelled road I ever saw – it rained heavily the
                    greatest part of the time &amp; we were obliged to go foot's pace as cautiously
                    as possible &amp; were still jolted exceedingly – For between 2 and 3 miles
                    (perhaps) the road lay at the bottom of a deep ravine following the <hi rend="superscript">course of the</hi> paltry <placeName ref="pl3056">river
                        Clwyd</placeName> (a mere brook quite unequalling the name of river) close
                    on our left – a couple of miles from the town (<placeName ref="pl1246">Ruthin</placeName>) the road good but heavyish with the rain – It seems a
                    nice neat town, but I have felt too unwell ever since getting up this morning to
                    stir out – the acid apple tart I had yesterday disagreed with me. [code: A lax
                    early this morning before I could get washed]. There is a woman, by the way
                    squalling <hi rend="superscript">in the house in a very improper way</hi> &amp;
                    I would not come here again – go to the <placeName ref="pl3123">White
                        Lion</placeName> – Just before breakfast this morning sent <persName ref="pe2198">George</persName>
                    <hi rend="superscript">with compliments to <persName ref="pe0957">Miss
                            Ponsonby</persName></hi> to enquire after <persName ref="pe0954">Lady
                        Eleanor</persName> – the former much obliged to us for sending – the latter
                    has had a good night &amp; was better – went into <persName ref="pe2179">Mrs
                        Davis</persName>'s room &amp; congratulated her &amp; begged her to write me
                    a few lines in about 10 days, to say how <persName ref="pe0954">Lady
                        Eleanor</persName> was – said I was going abroad &amp; should feel anxious
                    to hear – begged her not to name this to <persName ref="pe0957">Miss
                        P–</persName> gave my address &amp; have no doubt <persName ref="pe2179">Mrs
                        Davis</persName> will write. Spoke, too, to the waiter about sending us
                    Welsh mutton – \({1\over 2}\) a sheep will travel better than a less portion on
                    account of the meat being exposed to the air – the surface of the chine-bone
                    protecting the meat – it will be 5d a lb &amp; 1 \({1\over 2}\) d a lb carriage
                    exclusive of one yard of cloth wrapper that will cost a shilling – it will
                    arrive at <placeName ref="pl0481">Halifax</placeName> in 3 days – stopt a minute
                    in passing but did not get out to see <placeName ref="pl0785">Vale Crucis
                        Abbey</placeName> – 1 \({1\over 2}\) miles from <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName>
                    <hi rend="superscript">a field distant from the road</hi> on our right – part of
                    the remains covered in &amp; turned into <hi rend="superscript">part of</hi> a
                    farmstead – the views pretty now &amp; then but almost lost upon us thro' the
                    extreme badness of the road &amp; weather – the <placeName ref="pl1443">Vale of
                        Clwyd</placeName> opens upon us richly. At breakfast in <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> the waiter again brought us the
                    list-of-company-book – wrote in it the following "Wednesday 24 July 1822. Mrs
                    &amp; Miss Lister have spent 2 days here &amp; will take every opportunity of
                    recommending the <placeName ref="pl3086">King's Head</placeName> (<placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName>) the conduct of which great credit to
                        <persName ref="pe2179">Mrs Davis</persName>" - Left <placeName ref="pl1246">Ruthin</placeName> at 5 &amp; got here (<placeName ref="pl3122">The Bull
                        Inn</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1477">Denbigh</placeName>) at 6
                    \({20\over 60}\), that is exactly at the rate of 6 miles an hour, the distance
                    being 8 miles – Now &amp; then a little sun shiny, good road &amp; fine weather
                    all the way till a few drops of rain just as we entered the town – pleasant
                    drive – singular looking town – especially as we drove up the long, steep, wide,
                    pretty-good street to the <placeName ref="pl3122">Bull Inn</placeName> just
                    behind the town-house – Market day &amp; the streets pretty full tho' a small
                    market because it was the fair last week – the house looked full &amp; busy –
                    besides market people there was a rent-day held here, that of <persName ref="pe2192">Miss Middleton</persName> of <placeName ref="pl1256">Chirk</placeName> – the waiter at <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> recommended us to the <placeName ref="pl3114">Crown
                        Inn</placeName>, but the look of it determined me to see the <placeName ref="pl3122">Bull</placeName>, &amp; the latter having much the better
                    appearance of the 2, here we are – an old house – narrow oak staircases that
                    have a dirty look, but very civil, attentive people &amp; we are certainly come
                    to the right house – Ordered dinner in an hour &amp; sat down at 7 \({1\over
                    2}\). My <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName>'s bowels being still far from
                    well, &amp; myself very bilious, we had minced veal (white) &amp; a light batter
                    pudding with a lump of preserved apricot on the top - all very good &amp;, quite
                    contrary to expectation I had some enjoyment of my dinner. During the hour
                    before dinner we walked round the <placeName ref="pl1880">castle</placeName>
                    &amp; the bowling green, remarkably pretty &amp; worth seeing, particularly for
                    the fine bridge there along this fertile, wooded, &amp; therefore beautiful
                        <placeName ref="pl1443">Vale of Clwyd</placeName> – but the scene is merely
                    beautiful &amp; tame to us now with a foaming river &amp; mountain grandeur –
                    the hills are <pb n="57"/><fw>[f. 57]</fw> rounded into curves of beauty without
                    one trace of the sublime – no water – the want is striking – we have a
                    comfortable sitting-room upstairs [code: A double-bedded room adjoining &amp; I
                    have my wash-stand. Dress &amp; undress here in the sitting room]. Got a little
                    out of our way in leaving <placeName ref="pl1246">Ruthin</placeName> &amp;
                    passed the <placeName ref="pl3123">White Lion Inn</placeName> – a very nice,
                    largish-looking house – certainly the place we ought to have gone – <persName ref="pe2198">George</persName> tells me the other was not respectable – the
                    man <hi rend="superscript">landlord</hi> was a horse-dealer &amp; the squalling
                    came from his daughter whom some man was laying hold of. Both my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> &amp; I felt too unwell to stir out again after
                    dinner. 'Tis now 10p.m. when I have just finished writing the latter half of
                    today – [code: At ten, discovered a neighbouring double-bedded room at liberty.
                    Had all moved there &amp; glad to get a place to myself.] Went to my room at 11
                    \({1\over 4}\) [code: great deal of discharge but not quite as much as two days
                    ago this last morning &amp; night or two. I have used three syringes of water
                    instead of two]<lb/></p>
                <lb/>
                <p> Tuesday 25 July<lb/> Went to a glove shop on the same side as the inn a little
                    higher up – <placeName ref="pl1477">Denbigh</placeName> being celebrated for
                    gloves – the shop shut up (only one shop of note) &amp; the gloves in the window
                    damaged &amp; very inferior make &amp; appearance – Mrs Salisbury<note type="editorial">Unidentified but possibly the landlady of the Listers'
                        inn.</note> sent to the glovers' house – he was in his hay field <lb/> &amp;
                    had taken the key of his shop &amp; his wife who came to us was sorry we could
                    not wait – Off immediately at 10 \({3\over 4}\) – an hour in getting <hi rend="superscript">the 4 miles</hi> to <placeName ref="pl1371">St
                        Asaph</placeName> – <hi rend="superscript">walked the horse up</hi> 2 or 3
                    steepish hills which made us so long – Stopt 20 minutes at the cathedral gate
                    while we saw the <placeName ref="pl1561">cathedral</placeName> itself – They are
                    underdrawing in very good <hi rend="superscript">gothic</hi> style the roof of
                    the nave – Messrs Barrett (I think the woman said) &amp; Parry of <placeName ref="pl0740">Shrewsbury</placeName><note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note> – the cathedral very small but very neat and
                    altogether a pretty <hi rend="superscript">little</hi> ecclesiastical bijou –
                    the see worth<note type="editorial">The district under the jurisdiction of a
                        bishop or archbishop; a diocese (<hi rend="italic">OED</hi>).</note> £7000 a
                    year the woman said she knew – one steep street, the White Lion (I think) the
                    only good inn, at the top of it – Left <placeName ref="pl1371">St
                        Asaph</placeName> at 12 \({5\over 60}\) and stopt at the White Horse
                    (Richard Mansell, <placeName ref="pl1251">Holywell</placeName>) at 2 \({25\over
                    60}\), just 2 \({20\over 60}\) hours coming there ten miles – a few steepish
                    hills, &amp; walking slowly up them made us get on slowly – Fine view of the
                    Irish Channel estuary of the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName> about 2
                    miles from here – stopt at the turnpike (one mile distant from the town) close
                    to some mines on our left whence the men gave us some specimens of cubic lead,
                    calamine, &amp; black jack – From the inn my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> &amp; I walked down to <placeName ref="pl1979">St
                        Winifred's well</placeName>, close to the church yard – a woman there at the
                    well – gave each of us a glass of water &amp; a printed sheet of paper account
                    of the spring<note type="editorial">For an illustration of the broadsheet that
                        may have been seen by Lister at St Winifrede's, see <ref target="http://curioustravellers.ac.uk/en/a-fleeting-glimpse-of-c19th-ephemeral-texts/" type="http">here</ref>.</note> for which I gave her 6d &amp; she
                    certainly was not satisfied. Thence my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName>
                    and I walked forwards to the village of Greenfield – in returning my <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> left me a little below <placeName ref="pl1979">St Winifred's well</placeName>, &amp; I turned up a lane on the right to
                    what is called the <placeName ref="pl3121">Holywell level</placeName> – it looks
                    like a common culvert &amp; arch about a yard from the surface of the water.
                    There is a small cottage over it, some people live there to prevent children
                    doing mischief – the culvert or level opens into a small basin where were laid
                    up 3 of the vessels perhaps 1 yard wide &amp; ten long. The level extends 1
                    \({1\over 2}\) miles, the woman at the cottage said there is a communication
                    with it at the mines near the turnpike about one mile from <placeName ref="pl1251">Holywell</placeName>. <persName ref="pe2193">Mr
                        Harrison</persName> chief manager of the mines &amp; level – the woman gave
                    me another specimen or 2. Indeed I had first picked them up there &amp; had got
                    a very good one of black jack from a heap of stones to mend the road with as my
                    aunt &amp; I walked to Greenfield – Left <placeName ref="pl1251">Holywell</placeName> at 4 \({25\over 60}\) – pretty enough for 3 or 4 miles
                    from <placeName ref="pl1251">Holywell</placeName> so long as we had the estuary
                    of the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName> full in view – At the mines<note type="editorial">A reference to the Holywell Level lead mine, opened in
                        1773.</note> near 3 miles from <placeName ref="pl1251">Holywell</placeName>
                    on the right of the road at a small village asked a man if he could give me a
                    specimen of the white ore of lead – he knew nothing of it; but when I asked him
                    for a piece of chat he stooped &amp; picked up a piece from a heap of stones
                    laid by the roadside to mend it with – <placeName ref="pl0703">Northop</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl1534">Hawarden</placeName>
                    niceish little towns with good churches – at the latter town a handsome gothic
                    gateway to Sir Richard Glynn's place<note type="editorial">A reference to the
                        Glynne family of Hawarden, and probably to Sir Stephen Richard Glynne
                        (1807-94), 9th baronet, owner of Hawarden Castle, an eighteenth-century
                        gothic mansion named after the castle in its grounds. See <ref type="http" target="http://www.coflein.gov.uk/en/site/35877/details/hawarden-castle-hawarden">here</ref>.</note> in whose grounds is <hi rend="superscript">the ruin
                        of</hi>
                    <placeName ref="pl0788">Hawarden Castle</placeName>. Stopt here at <placeName ref="pl3125">Willoughby's</placeName>, the Royal hotel <placeName ref="pl0002">Chester</placeName>, at 7 \({1\over 2}\), having got here in 3
                    \({5\over 60}\) hours from <placeName ref="pl1251">Holywell</placeName> – very
                    good road – walked Percy up 3 or 4 hills – were shewn into the same sitting room
                    we had a fortnight ago – asked to have the same lodgings rooms &amp; have got
                    them [code: My <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> went upstairs. I sat
                    musing on <persName ref="pe2175">M–</persName> thinking I wasted my life in vain
                    expectation, hoping for a time which she is too delicate to like to calculate.
                    Somehow I cannot get over this.] Sat down to dinner at 8 ½ – giblet soup –
                    excellent veal cutlets, potatoes, peas, currant tart &amp; a bottle of port
                    wine. My <persName ref="pe2178">aunt</persName> better &amp; I felt as usual
                    again today &amp; have enjoyed my dinner. I have just settled with <persName ref="pe2198">George</persName> &amp; written the last 20 lines of today
                    &amp; it is now 10 \({40\over 60}\) […]<lb/>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>