<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0411">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Donald MacQueen to Thomas Pennant</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP297</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>6</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0069">Donald MacQueen</persName>
                    <date when="1773-11-20"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0742">Kilmuir</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct0412"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct0410"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gd">Gaelic</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="enclosed">
                <fw>p.1<hi rend="superscript">st.</hi></fw>
                <p>Notes –––––</p>
                <p>Two Vessels went from <placeName ref="pl0715">Sky</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl0955">Uist</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl2656">Kintail</placeName> a part of <persName ref="pe0155">Lord
                        Seaford's</persName> Estate on the opposite continent And two more from
                        <placeName ref="pl0712">Lewis</placeName> with men, women &amp; Children to
                        <placeName ref="pl0697">America</placeName>. The Proprietors took the Alarm,
                    reduced their rents And passed from Services &amp; Small taxes to Which their
                    people were formerly bound. <persName ref="pe0155">Lord Seaford</persName> hath
                    Shewn a good disposition but found cause not to dismiss his Factor. This
                    conduct, if persisted in, will Surely break the Spirit of Emigration — some of
                        <persName ref="pe0447">Alexander Macdonald's</persName> people, After
                    signing with the rest, Stoped short but Whether the remains of the former Spirit
                    combined with fears And small disappointments, may not spring up into a flame is
                    still Uncertain, for if there is Any Early attempt made to mend the rent-role,
                    the tumult which is now nearly Laid will rouse itself with greater violence.
                        <persName ref="pe0446">The Laird of MacLeod</persName> a young man under Age
                    So full of good Sense, Humanity &amp; Condescension, that tho he is burdened
                    with an Immense Load of debt, he hath reduced his Rent-role to the abilities of
                    the people And made a full conquest of their hearts. A Numerous Clan Acknowledge
                    him for their friend and Protector, who if he persists in the present Measures,
                    will soon stretch Every Nerve to relieve him from his difficulties. I shall be
                    Extremely glad that you mention him in Some Such Light in your Publication, that
                    he might be Led by it, to preserve the Character he So Early attempts to
                    acquire, And that you may not Suppose that I am guided by any of the partial
                    affections, from which I am intirely free as being on another Estate, <persName ref="pe0073">Dr Samuel Johnson</persName> will, I am Sure, confirm this
                    Truth, for he hath been Much in his company while he remained in <placeName ref="pl0715">Sky</placeName>.</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe0447">Sir Alexander Macdonald of Macdonald</persName>, <persName ref="pe0446">Norman MacLeod of MacLeod</persName>, <persName ref="pe0448">John MacLeod</persName> of <placeName ref="pl0952">Rasay</placeName> and
                        <persName ref="pe1950">Charles Mackinnon of Mackinnon</persName> are the
                    only proprietors in <placeName ref="pl0715">Sky</placeName>. <persName ref="pe0447">Sir Alexander Macdonald</persName> is Lineally descended of the
                    Lords of the Isles, the three Last of Whom were Earls of <placeName ref="pl1142">Ross</placeName>, the Heirs &amp; Successors of <persName ref="pe1951">SumerLed</persName>, the famous Thane or Depute Sovereign of <placeName ref="pl0818">Argyle</placeName>, who <unclear reason="illegible">on</unclear>
                    <pb/><fw>2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></fw> Account of his being marryed to
                        <persName ref="pe1952">a Daughter of Olave King of Man</persName>, assumed
                    the Superiority of the Isles; his power And distance from the Seat of Royalty
                    tempted him as well as Eight or more of his Successors, to Assert something like
                    An Independancy on the Crown of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>,
                    Untill <persName ref="pe1953">John</persName> the Last of them by Entering into
                    a Treaty with <persName ref="pe1954">Edward King of England</persName> against
                    his Rightful Sovereign <persName ref="pe1955">James the 3<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi></persName>, of which there is a Coppy in <persName ref="pe0977">Rimer's</persName>
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0673">fœdera</title></bibl>, forefeited
                    titles And all, When the Earldom of Ross was Unalienably annexed to the Crown in
                    the year 1476. And he at the Mediation of <persName ref="pe1956">the
                        Queen</persName> a Daughter of <placeName ref="pl2709">Denmark's</placeName>, was afterwards restored to the Lordship of the Isles.
                    This <persName ref="pe1953">John</persName> gave to his brother <persName ref="pe1957">Hugh</persName> a Charter of by much the greater part of the
                    Estate now possessed by <persName ref="pe0447">Sir Alexander
                        Macdonald</persName>, dated at <placeName ref="pl0682">Aros</placeName> in
                        <placeName ref="pl0729">Mull</placeName> in the year 1495. And as the Line
                    of <persName ref="pe1953">John Lord of the Isles</persName> is long since
                    Extinct, the descendants of his brother <persName ref="pe1957">Hugh</persName>
                    seem to bid fairest for the Right of Representation.</p>
                <p>The Families of MacLeod of <placeName ref="pl0954">Harris</placeName> and
                        <placeName ref="pl0952">Rasay</placeName> a branch of the Family of the
                    MacLeods of <placeName ref="pl0712">Lewis</placeName> who were very considerable
                    in their day are according to an Uncontradicted Tradition descended of the Kings
                    of <placeName ref="pl0707">Man</placeName>, for when a Cession was made of the
                    Kingdom of the Isles by <persName ref="pe1958">Magnus the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of Norway</persName> to <persName ref="pe1959">Alexander the 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> of
                        Scotland</persName>, a provision <add place="above">was made</add> for
                    Securing the Rights And Possessions of Such of the Norvegian Subjects as
                    inclined to remain where they were. Several made choice of keeping their
                    possession in the Isles, rather than throw themselves Upon the dice of Fortune
                    in <placeName ref="pl0835">Norway</placeName>, whose posterity are now Existing,
                    the many of them have been brought Low, by the revolutions which are frequent
                    Among Military tribes, yet the MacLeods of <placeName ref="pl0954">Harris</placeName> And <placeName ref="pl0952">Rasay</placeName> Also,
                    preserved an honourable rank, without Loseing or Acquiring a Single Acre of
                    ground for time Immemorial And tho <persName ref="pe0446">the present
                        MacLeod's</persName> Situation Seems very distressful his parts firmness
                    &amp; perseverance promise, in time to Extricate Him from Every
                    Incumberance.</p>
                <p>The Clan Mackinnon As well as the Grants &amp; Macgregors call themselves Clan
                    Alpin, that is the descendants of <persName ref="pe1960">Alpin</persName>, who
                    was <add place="above">a</add> King of the Scots <pb/>
                    <fw>3<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi></fw> In the 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                    Century. <persName ref="pe1950">Mackinnon</persName> possesses an Estate in
                        <placeName ref="pl0715">Sky</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl0729">Mull</placeName> down from the time of the Lordship of the Isles.</p>
                <p>Who is Chief of a Highland Clan When it hath been Split into different And
                    independant families before we had Any great knowledge or Letters, is a question
                    of more Curiosity than Use And ill to Solve. The former Importance of the Chief,
                    when his Clan wou'd fly to his banners in the days of Military prowess, is in
                    our days of Peace utterly cancelled. The calmer Arts of Industry And the more
                    violent passion for Money than Renown, have pulled it Up from the roots.
                    Countenance, recommendation And protection from Injuries, Some Shreds of them,
                    in some places <add place="above">is all that</add> remain of the old Spirit And
                    Whoever is most capable &amp; willing to Serve the Clan in these respects, is
                    Chief for the time, While the true Representative According to the present Laws
                    of Succession, May be Lurking Unheeded in a Corner. Among a Variety of Tribes of
                    the same Clan Each have their pretensions which hath frequently given Occassion
                    to Disputes Among themselves. It is now Scarce worth their While, Surely not
                    worth the pains of a disinterested person to Setle the difference, tho the Case
                    were more clear than it is. In a Line Where Every degree is not Ascertained by
                    Charters, Sasines, contracts of Marriage, Untill you Arrive at the first founder
                    of a Family, you are but groping in the dark. Tho' one Assumes the original
                    Motto and a great part of the Arms of a Family More than a Century ago, can this
                    pass for Any proof When all who Lay their Claims have not been called to the
                    Lyon's Office for their Interest? The determination of the question is an
                    Invidious task, And in the Main impossible to Answer.</p>
                <p>The Bag-pipe was known to the Romans (<persName ref="pe1961">Nero</persName> had
                    one) who woud very probably introduce the Use of it into <placeName ref="pl2663">Gaul</placeName>, where it was As Necessary As the pipe or flute was among
                    the Lacedemonians to keep them to a Regular March and Moderate their Ardour
                    &amp; Impetuosity in Batle. It is the Character of the Gauls that in their first
                    onset they were more than men and if the Enemy coud bear their first Impressions
                    they were Less than <pb/><fw>4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></fw> Women, for
                    their wild Unrestrained violence woud Soon Exhaust their Vigour and Spirit. The
                    bag-pipe, then, woud be an Important War-like implement, on account of the
                    Loudness &amp; regularity of it's Music And the Romans cou'd scarce miss to
                    furnish them with it when they took them into their Armies, to keep them to
                    order and discipline. We have had the harp And the pipe from <placeName ref="pl0889">Irland</placeName>, where our Great men too the grand tour of
                    former days when it was the Kingdom of Saints &amp; Geneologies And I find by an
                    Antient Song that they had some of the Belgæ among them perhaps from those of
                        <placeName ref="pl2003">South Brittain</placeName>, who or some other
                    Warlike tribe of Gauls might have furnished them with the Bag-pipe. Be that how
                    it will, MacLeod, for time Immemorial kept a College of pipers Upon his Estate
                    by the Mackrūmens who Enjoyed an Appointment in Lands And were resorted to by
                    apprentices from the Neighbourhing Chieftans. Macdonald had also his Mackarters
                    and Irish tribe in the Same Employment, one whom, it is said, played a Lively
                    tempestuous tūne, still on the finger-Ends of the pipers, at the batle of
                        <placeName ref="pl2486">Harlaw</placeName> fought by <persName ref="pe1962">Donald Lord of the Isles</persName> against <persName ref="pe1963">Robert
                        Duke of Albany</persName> in the year <sic>14ii</sic>.</p>
                <p>The Danish forts Are called Dūns in Erse, but originally they were called by the
                    builders Būrrows, which word is still preserved in the names of the places where
                    they stand. Dun answers to the Latin word arx and means a fort or a high round
                    hill Such as <placeName ref="pl2710">Dun-canna</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl0952">Rasay</placeName>. I am not surprised tho there may be few
                    traces of these Duns in <placeName ref="pl0835">Norway</placeName> or <placeName ref="pl2709">Denmark</placeName>, for people who put Up in a conquered
                    coūntrey among their Enemies will stand more in need of a Fortification than
                    Where they Are at home among their friends. At the Same time our Norvegian Duns
                    are so regularly built; that I am sure they were not novices in Masonry who put
                    them up And <add place="above">if</add> building in Stone was introduced to
                        <placeName ref="pl0777">Brittain</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl0889">Irland</placeName> by these Northern Adventurers, I am apt to believe that
                    some even of these old forts woud be found particularly in <placeName ref="pl0835">Norway</placeName>. Nature woud soon point out the Art of
                    Fortification, for Security <pb/><fw>5<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></fw> In
                    time of fewer Numbers or of a defeat, Sometimes by opening up <add place="above">a</add> deep broad ditch And throwing the Earth to the Inside, Sometimes,
                    by felling trees in the heart of a thick wood And Piling them over One Another
                    &amp; at Other times by raising a stout Stone Wall round the Town As they called
                    it. We have a few traces of the Ditch-fortification and Several of the Duns
                    which are Surely Norvegian.</p>
                <p>The Urns Are found in Large cairns within a stone chest composed of four stone
                        <add place="above">standing on Edge &amp; one below another Above</add>
                    standing on the Lowest Stone covered with a thin flat stone of small weight.
                    This Chest And Sometimes more than One are found in the Same Cairn under a
                    prodigious heap of Stones.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <opener><salute>Dr Sir</salute></opener>
                <p>I received Yours Last week only for it came by <placeName ref="pl0665">Dunvegan</placeName>. <placeName ref="pl0660">Sconser</placeName> is the
                    Next Office to me And when you are pleased to write me Again pray address it by
                        <placeName ref="pl0660">Sonser</placeName>. I return you thanks for the <rs ref="ar0358">view</rs> of <placeName ref="pl0715">Inveraray house</placeName>
                    which is prettily executed. I shall be glad to receive the views in <placeName ref="pl0715">Sky</placeName> of which I am a better Judge.<note type="editorial">Pennant's <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0008">A tour in Scotland and
                                Voyage to the Hebrides</title></bibl> (1774) would contain a number
                        of Moses Griffith's views of Skye: <rs ref="ar0359">'Women at the <hi rend="italic">Quern</hi>, and at the <hi rend="italic">Luagh</hi>,
                            with a view of TALYSKIR'</rs>, plate XXXIV, p.328; <rs ref="ar0040">'View from <hi rend="italic">Beinn-na-caillich</hi>, in Skie'</rs>,
                        plate XXXV, p.329; <rs ref="ar0360">'View of DUNVEGAN castle, and the loch
                            beyond'</rs>, plate XXXVII, p.338, and <rs ref="ar0362">'DUN-TUILM
                            castle'</rs>, plate XXXVIII, p.350.</note> It is right you mention
                        <persName ref="pe0446">MacLeod</persName> for his own Sake and for that Sake
                    of Others but your are not to Mention Me on that Occassion. The remains of
                    Chieftancy Might be turned to good Account on Every Estate where the Spirit of
                    it, is so faint that by Any Management it cannot be applyed to bad purposes.</p>
                <closer><salute>I shall be glad to hear from you when you Are at Leasure for I am
                        with Much Esteem, Dr Sir, <lb/>Your Most Obedient <lb/>&amp; <lb/>Most
                        humble Servt</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0069">Don: Macqueen</persName></signed>
                <dateline><placeName ref="pl0742">Kilmuir</placeName> Nov. 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                    <lb/><hi rend="underline">1773</hi></dateline></closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>I coud Only mean by the poor's multure that the Millars generally Grind their
                        gleanings on the field And their Contributions from Among the Tennants
                        without paying multure.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><handShift/>answered Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 1773.</p>
                <p>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Macqueen <lb/>on the clans of Skie</p>
                <p><handShift/><address>
                        <addrLine>To</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Thomas Pennant Esqr,</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>of Downing in Flintshire</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>South Brittain.</addrLine>
                    </address></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>