<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0412">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Donald MacQueen to Thomas Pennant</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP297</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>7</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0069">Donald MacQueen</persName>
                    <date when="1774-01-19"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0742">Kilmuir</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct0413"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct0412"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gd">Gaelic</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
                <p>I had your kind favour Yesterday, And now sit down to make an answer to it. We
                    have Baron Baileys amongst Us, Who decide the maters of Property which do not
                    Exceed 40 Shillings Sterling, — the Jurisdiction Act hath thus restricted them,
                    And the bulk of our Processes Among the Smaller people Seldom come Up to that
                    Sum. We have also a Sherriff Substitute, Who hath his commission from the
                    Sheriff-depúte of <placeName ref="pl2230">Inverness-shire</placeName>, some of
                    our Processes, however, are brought to <placeName ref="pl0156">Inverness</placeName> And others to the Court of Session, where the
                    Subjects of importance or the Passions of Parties are wrought Up too high to
                    attend to the calm Reflections of Reason or to the Less compulsive decrees of a
                    Small Judge.</p>
                <p>Tiern is the Laird and Armen is properly a Military Leader, arm-man, that is, the
                    man of Arms. The Proprietor of Lands was Always the Armen of his own Men, but
                    when Several of these Independant Chieftans Joined together the Principal was by
                    way of Eminence called the Armen. I have been always of Opinion, that the
                    Destroyer of <persName ref="pe1965">Quintilius Varus</persName> and the Legions
                    Under him in <placeName ref="pl1472">Germany</placeName> the celebrated
                        <persName ref="pe1966">Arminius</persName>, had this name bestowed Upon him
                    from his Office, As being the Leader of the German Tribes And the brave
                    undaunted Asserter of the Liberties of his Countrey, whom neither bribes threats
                    or Losses could Unhinge, tho he was Engaged with the Power of <placeName ref="pl1623">Rome</placeName> in it's most flourishing state, supported by
                    his brother, his Father in Law &amp; Other deserters from the common Cause.
                    Therefore, to inflame the courage of Other Chiefs, the Bards Employed their
                    Talents Upon him And he became the war-Song of the barbarous Nations down to the
                    days of <persName ref="pe1967">Tacitŭs</persName>, As our Armens Also continued
                    to be Long after they were Laid Low.</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe1961">Nero's</persName> Insatiable Passion for fame &amp;
                    Popularity, to which Natural Talents seem to have Entitled him, if they were not
                    to Inconsiderably quieted, Led him among other Tryals of Skill, to pass a bow,
                    that he woud Enter the Lists as a bagpiper, Utricularis, which he never woud
                    have done, if he had not already Learned the Trade And if it was not much in the
                    hands of Others. See <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0675">Sueton.'s
                            Nero</title>
                        <biblScope unit="chapter">Chap. 54.</biblScope></bibl>
                    <pb/><persName ref="pe1968">Canus</persName> also an Eminent Piper of the Court
                    of <persName ref="pe1969">Galba</persName>, (chorautus) who from the Merite of
                    his musical Instrument seems, to <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0676">Martial</title></bibl>, capable of Patronizing the Suitors for
                    preferment at <placeName ref="pl1623">Rome</placeName>, if they should beat
                    applause to his Singing, woud in the Same Poet's opinion Scorn to be a Bagpiper,
                    when he puts it as an Unseemly question to Priscus Et concupiscat esse Canus
                    Ascaulis.' This is Enough to prove that the Bagpipe was in Use down from the
                    days of <persName ref="pe1969">Galba</persName> And As the Romans &amp; Greeks
                    had already reed-pipes on their Theatres, at their feasts &amp; Religious
                    processions for Many preceeding Ages, the Addition of the Bag must naturally be
                    Supposed An Improvement of theirs, which was introduced by them among the
                    barbarous Tribes, more probably among the Gauls who before this period had pipes
                    of no kind that we can See. An old Greek poet says that the Pipers blew out a
                    part of their Souls at the first blast into the Instrument And to this day they
                    continue As Litle remarkeable for the mental faculties As the Other Eminent
                    professors of Music, Whose Whole study, attention &amp; happyness dwells on
                    &amp; consists in diversifying And adjusting Small holes And Crotchets to <add place="above">one</add> Another.</p>
                <p>I think I writ you something about Charms. I wished I had put you in mind that
                    the Grave old <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0663">Cato</title></bibl> had
                    dealt in that Sort of Stuff. Chaps 160 de re rustica p.89 Ed, plantin, 159 &amp;
                    S.F. (Sumtas fracto) Motas danaries clarico dardu<del rend="overstrike">nd</del>ries Astataries. This is the Charm he prescribes for a Strain. None of
                    our old wives need be Ashamed of this folly when the Venerable Sage recommends
                    Such unmeaning Jargon for the Relief of the distressed. I am sure he knew he
                    coud produce no Effects but divert the Mind a Litle &amp; inspire it with the
                    hopes of recovery. I coud repeat Several of this complexion Which were once
                    highly valued tho our common people have now got so much Phylosophy into their
                    heads As to despise Every Species of Superstition.</p>
                <p>I do not remember whether I mentioned an Observation to you I long since made
                    "That among an Unmixed people the different Tribes have their different
                    Characteristics — this is no where So <pb/>Visible as among the Highland Clans —
                    the founder of Each family hath Struck his Leading colors into All his race —
                    Education continues from one Generation to Another what neither Commerce, a
                    mixture with strangers or a change of Government among them hath hitherto
                    defaced. I would point out these distinguishing qualities of Several of them but
                    I will rather Say that the Julian, Manlian, the Cato families &amp;c were from
                    first to Last distinguished by their different Characters.</p>
                <p>When you are pleased to Send me the book you will <sic>ordered</sic> it to be
                    delivered to <persName ref="pe0446">Mr Norman MacLeod</persName> Preacher of the
                    Gospel, to be found at <persName ref="pe1964">Mr Duncan Macdonald's</persName>
                    writer at <placeName ref="pl0076">Edin<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></placeName>
                    And he will immediately fall Upon a way of conveying it.</p>
                <closer><salute>I am, Dr Sir, with much Esteem <lb/>Your very Obedient humble
                        Servt</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0069">Don: Macqueen</persName></signed></closer>
                <dateline><placeName ref="pl0742">Kilmuir</placeName> Janry the 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                    <lb/>1774</dateline>
                <postscript>
                    <p>The <placeName ref="pl0715">Sky</placeName> Emigration <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell><list>
                                        <item>From <placeName ref="pl0956">portrie</placeName> &amp;
                                                <placeName ref="pl0655">Sleat</placeName> in the
                                            year 1771.</item>
                                        <item><placeName ref="pl2711">Bracadle</placeName> in the
                                            year — 1772 ..</item>
                                        <item><placeName ref="pl0956">Portrie</placeName> &amp;
                                                <placeName ref="pl0955">Uist</placeName> in the — ..
                                            1773 ...</item>
                                        <item><placeName ref="pl2711">Bracadle</placeName> in the .
                                            ... 1773.</item>
                                    </list></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><list>
                                        <item>400</item>
                                        <item>240</item>
                                        <item>230</item>
                                        <item>150</item>
                                        <item>1020</item>
                                    </list></cell>
                            </row>
                        </table></p>
                    <p>Some of these Numbers came from the Main Land</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><handShift/>armin &amp; Tiern.</p>

                <p><handShift/><address>
                        <addrLine>To</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Thomas Pennant Esqr,</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>of Downing </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>in Flintshire</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>South Brittain.</addrLine>
                    </address></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>