<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0414">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Donald MacQueen to Thomas Pennant</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP297</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>9</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <additional>
                        <p>The enclosed corrections and letter are written continuously on the same
                            sheet.</p>
                    </additional>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0069">Donald MacQueen</persName>
                    <date when="1774-04-11"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0742">Kilmuir</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct0415"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct0413"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gd">Gaelic</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="grc">Ancient Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="enclosed">
                <p>Corrigenda<note type="editorial">The following are apparently corrections for
                        draft sheets of Pennant's <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0008">A tour
                                in Scotland and Voyage to the Hebrides 1772</title></bibl> (1774).
                        The page references given by MacQueen do not correspond to those of the
                        published text.</note></p>
                <p>For <placeName ref="pl2476">Ormadale</placeName> page 283. Line 2<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> read <placeName ref="pl2476">Armadale</placeName>. In stead of tyed with Ropes, fastened from the horn p.284
                    line 17<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> read tyed with twisted woodies, fastened
                    from the Under-chain of the one to the tail of the preceeding. In stead of
                    Luaghadh p.285 Line 27<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> read Luagh. In stead of
                    Bein-na-grian p.287 read Bein-an-ghrianan.<note type="editorial">An adjoining
                        peak of <placeName ref="pl0837">Beinn na Caillich on Skye</placeName>,
                        possibly <placeName ref="pl2715">Beinn Dearg Mhòr</placeName>. See Pennant,
                            <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0008">A tour in Scotland and Voyage
                                to the Hebrides 1772</title></bibl> (1774), p.329.</note> Grianan or
                    Grianhan, the house of the Sun, is the name of Various places amongst Us, where
                    there is Generally a Litle Inclosure, in which on the Return of that Salutary
                    Planet, they burnt large fires and very probabley offered Sacrifices in honour
                    of the Intelligence which they supposed had Animated it. Hence the <persName ref="pe1981">Grinneus Appollo</persName> of the Greeks and the <persName ref="pe1981">Appollo Grannus</persName> of the Scots which is the word
                        Gria<unclear reason="illegible">n</unclear>ich <add place="above">Sunny</add> Latinized, from the root Grian the Sun. The Spirit of the Sun
                    is in our Language called <persName ref="pe1981">Grūagich</persName>, the One
                    with the fair tresses, answering Literally to the Epithet ακερσε-κομος given by
                        <persName ref="pe1107">Homer</persName> to <persName ref="pe1981v">Appollo</persName>.<note type="editorial">This account of the origins of
                        the Gruagach appears in <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0008">A tour in
                                Scotland and Voyage to the Hebrides 1772</title></bibl> (1774),
                        p.359. See also the description based on MacQueen's letter of <ref target="0416.xml">August 18 1774</ref> in Pennant, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0010">A Tour in Scotland 1772, part
                                II</title></bibl> (1776), pp.434-38.</note> A Stone or Altar for
                        <persName ref="pe1981">Gruagich</persName> lies almost in Every district for
                    he seems to have drawn more of the attention of the people than the Other
                    Subaltern Divinities As guideing the Source of Light And Fertility around the
                    world. He contented himself with Small Libations of Milk on Every Saturday in
                    the Last <add place="margin">generation</add> And some of the Preceeding
                    generations, tho I know they Offered him more costly Sacrifices before the
                    Introduction of Christianity. This is a Digression.</p>
                <p>If it were not to spoil the very pretty Elegant description you have given of
                        <placeName ref="pl0841">Quillin</placeName> on this page, I woud say that
                    the Cluster of Hills which go Under that name, have no connection with our
                    Countrey man <persName ref="pe1640">Cuchullin</persName>, for <placeName ref="pl0841">Quillin</placeName> or <placeName ref="pl0841">Cuilin</placeName> plainly Signifies narrow dark hollows, which are
                    numerous Among these Lofty Excrescences And Imports the same meaning with the
                        <placeName ref="pl2716">furcæ Caudinæ</placeName> of <placeName ref="pl1164">Italy</placeName>, the Forks of <placeName ref="pl0697">North
                        America</placeName> And Seems not much different from the <placeName ref="pl1166">Mons Grampiūs</placeName> of <placeName ref="pl0705">Caledonia</placeName>, for Gramp is the common Erse word for a fork. The
                    Highest hill in old <placeName ref="pl2719">Arcadia</placeName> was Also
                        <placeName ref="pl2717">Cyllene</placeName> which when the C is pronounced
                    like the greek καππα is the very Name of our Hill. yet I woud be Loath to
                    Sacrifice your Poetical beauties to so dull And but to a few so very
                    Uninteresting Observation Unless it were Enlivened Under Your hand.</p>
                <p>For <placeName ref="pl2718">Camisketel</placeName> 287 Line 16<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> read <placeName ref="pl2718">Camiseketel</placeName>. The paragraph preceeding the words "to the recent
                    Victory of <placeName ref="pl0155">Culloden</placeName> woud infer that the
                    two-handed Swords Were Used in the year 1745, whereas it is Universally known,
                    that upwards of a Century Preceeding that Period, they were altogether Laid
                        Aside.<note type="editorial">See Pennant's description of Highland weaponry,
                            <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0008">A tour in Scotland and Voyage
                                to the Hebrides 1772</title></bibl> (1774), pp.332-33.</note> In
                    stead of Braolauch Page 295. read Braloch.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
                <p>I met with your acceptable favour Last week in my way to <placeName ref="pl0660">Sconser</placeName> and must Acknowledge you have prettily dressed up Small
                    matters, So as to render them Entertaining &amp; agreeable, for tho I am
                    Acquainted with all your Observations, I am much pleased when I read them in
                    your descriptive Stile. The Corrections on the Other Page, are of Litle
                    consequence — if they Overtake You in my time, they may be attended to, if not,
                    One in five thousand of Your Readers will not advert to them, tho, Indeed, a
                    work of Yours Which hath a Chance to be read <del rend="overstrike">for
                        read</del> for Generations to come, shoud not be neglected in the Smallest
                    Particle.</p>
                <p>Your Character of <persName ref="pe0446">Mr MacLeod</persName>,<note type="editorial">A reference to Pennant's guarded approval of Norman
                        Macleod's paternalistic conduct as a Highland chief in <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0008">A tour in Scotland and Voyage to
                                the Hebrides 1772 (1774)</title></bibl> p.338.</note> seems to me
                    Just Enough, which you have properly qualyfyed with the words "actions if
                    persisted in, for it is said of <persName ref="pe1982">Brittanicus</persName>
                    <hi rend="underline">retinuit famam Sine Experimento</hi> and the Same might be
                    said of your <persName ref="pe0829">Edward the 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></persName> And there were several who had their Golden days and the
                        reverse.<note type="editorial">MacQueen is comparing Macleod, then around
                        the age of twenty, to promising rulers from history whose lives were cut
                        short by early death.</note></p>
                <p>I shoud be Sorry that you gave Yourself Unnecessary trouble in the Affair of
                        <persName ref="pe0155">Lord Seaforth</persName>, for I hear his Factor hath
                    recommended a Tennant's Son of his own.<note>In his <ref target="0413.xml">previous letter</ref>, MacQueen had asked for Pennant's assistance in
                        securing his son John's preferment as minister to a parish on Seaforth's
                        estate.</note></p>
                <p>I shall be glad to hear from you when you Are at Leisure,</p>
                <closer><salute>for I am with true <lb/>Esteem Dr Sir, <lb/>Your very Obedient &amp;
                        very humble Servt</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0069">Don: Macqueen</persName></signed>
                <dateline><placeName ref="pl2719">Kilmuir</placeName> April the 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                    <lb/>1774.</dateline></closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>I told you some where that it woud Seem to me that our Celtic Ancestors Sung
                        And danced to the Creation of the world for thus they Expressed all their
                        Religious Doctrines. I have taken Up an opinion that they Also danced to A
                        Song called the Conflagration of the world <unclear reason="illegible">ορχησίς τισ κοσμου εκπυρωσίς</unclear>
                        <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0678">Athen. dipnosoph Lib.
                            14.</title></bibl> Analogous in Some degree to the Spirit of this dance
                        was the conduct of <persName ref="pe1961">Nero</persName>, when he Entered into
                        his Domestic Theatre And sung or acted the destruction of <placeName ref="pl2116">Troy</placeName> while <placeName ref="pl1623">Rome</placeName> was in Flames
                        about his Ears, a part which few ill be disposed to Act in time of the
                        General ruin, prefigured in the above dance. This however is out of your
                        road &amp; I shall trouble you no More about it.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><address>
                        <addrLine>To</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Thomas Pennant Esqre</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>of Downing in Flintshire.</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>South Brittain</addrLine>
                    </address></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>