<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1042">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Thomas Pennant to Richard Bull</title>
            <respStmt>                     <name>Transcribed by Ffion Mair Jones; edited by Ffion Mair Jones; encoded by Vivien Williams. (2019)</name>                 </respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                        <idno>5500C</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>no. 44</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <date when="1784-12-21"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage> <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
                <p>It is with no small chagrin that I find you persevere in your silence: the only consolation I had was a letter some time ago from 
                    <persName ref="pe0293">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Burel</persName> which informed me of y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 
                    welfare &amp; that the <persName ref="pe0336">invalid of y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> family</persName>
                    was on the recovery: but let me have the satisfaction of having it confirmed from yourself.</p>
                <p>At length <persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName> has begun on the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0032">journey to London</title></bibl>:
                    He works for you &amp; me alternately: nor shall he labor for any one else till it is completed. for a fortnight past we have been clad in snow attended with severe frost. the snow began singularly: it fell without a breath of wind, 
                    &amp; by its weighty abundance has done infinite damage to our woods. My pleasure grounds have suffered greatly for the evergreens unable to bear the burden, are dreadfully shattered. 
                    <sic>Polilitics</sic> warm us with a vengeance: &amp; we are all by the ears about a man who a very short time ago was the detestation of the country &amp;
                    with good cause: but old <placeName ref="pl1094">Cambria</placeName> is grown frantic, &amp; plays all the pranks of the wildest times, burns her sons in Effigy 
                    &amp;c &amp;c. There is more at the bottom of this than is thought, &amp; depend on it the <persName ref="pe0426">Dean</persName>
                    is but an Instrument as many more have been.<note type="editorial">For Pennant's visual expression of his response to the acquittal of William Davies Shipley for seditious libel, see Peter Lord, <hi rend="italic">Words with Pictures: Welsh images and images of Wales in the popular press, 1640–1860</hi> (Aberystwyth: Planet, 1995), pp. 75–80.</note> as to myself; I find myself in the minority at home: but as before, in the majority above. Pray write soon
                    &amp; treat us with the news of <placeName ref="pl0699">the town</placeName>. I hear that the amorous begin to pair as if it was the warm month of may:
                    &amp; married men quit their nuptial bed to run away with smock faced boys. I hope things will mend before march, or I had best keep in my bottle.</p>
                <p>When you see <persName ref="pe0293">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Burel</persName> &amp; 
                    <persName ref="pe0332">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Storer</persName> I request my best compli<hi rend="superscript">mts</hi>.
                    I had a dismal political Letter from the last: but as I had no comfort to give him, have been rude enough not to answer.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I am
                    <lb/>Dear Sir
                    <lb/>most faithfully y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi></salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0232">T Pennant</persName></signed>
                    <dateline><placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName> Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 21. 1784.</dateline>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>every good wish of the season attend you &amp; y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>.</p>
                    <p>I shall be very glad to be favored with the receipt for the making paste, having lost it</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><address>
                        <addrLine/>
                        <addrLine/>
                    </address></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>