<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1097">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Richard Bull to Thomas Pennant</title>
            <respStmt>                     <name>Transcribed by Ffion Mair Jones; edited by Ffion Mair Jones; encoded by Vivien Williams. (2019)</name>                 </respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/ TP 189</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>19</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                    <date when="1790-02-17"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0759">Stratton Street</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage> <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="fr">French</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir.</salute> <dateline><placeName ref="pl0759">Stratton Street</placeName>. 17 Feb<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>. 1790</dateline></opener>
                <p><persName ref="pe0105">Captain Grose</persName> told me yesterday, you was wondering at my not answering your last letter, 
                    and I should have reason to wonder as much at myself, if I had not done it. the date of yours was January 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.<note type="editorial">See <ref target="1096.xml">1096</ref>.</note>- 
                    on January 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, I replied, and been ever since expecting a rejoinder, but as you could not have
                    receiv’d my letter, neither could You answer it. the reason is not worth troubling you with, at this distance at large, but
                    it was owing to <add place="above">a</add> servant, who has condescended to rob me even of the penny’s <del>with</del>
                    which attended my letters to the post-office. I told you in that, or in a former letter, that <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0062"><persName ref="pe0846">Yeakell</persName>, and <persName ref="pe0847">Gardiners</persName> map of <placeName ref="pl0922">Sussex</placeName></title></bibl>,
                    were sold at <persName ref="pe0389">Fadens</persName>, but upon so large a scale, and at so high a price, that I should not 
                    buy them without a fresh order. I remember also to have told you, that no impressions of <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0290"><persName ref="pe0436">Worsley</persName>'s <placeName ref="pl1020">Isle of Wight</placeName></title></bibl>
                    were printed upon large paper, all the copies being of the same size, and in order to dissuade you from buying one at the present advanc’d price, I offer’d to send 
                    <del>you</del> down to your house my copy, for present use, and to keep as long as you wanted it, and I suggested the probability that 
                    <persName ref="pe0436">Sir Richard</persName> might publish a second Edition e’er long,<note type="editorial">There is no evidence that a second edition of Worsley, <hi rend="italic">A History of the Isle of Wight </hi>was ever published.</note> including the plates of the Statues, 
                    &amp; Jewels he lately imported, some of which are already engrav’d &amp; in a stile of great expence. The quantity of things he has now added to 
                    <rs type="art" ref="ar0043"><placeName ref="pl1392">Appuldurcombe</placeName></rs> is prodigious, the Drawings of places very fine indeed, among the 
                    rest of his marbles, Jewels, and paintings, sunt bona – sunt mediocra – sunt mala. –<note type="editorial">'some are good – some are mediocre – some are bad'. Bull quotes an epigram by Martial: 'Sunt bona, sunt quædam mediocria, sunt mala plura'.</note>
                    There <add place="above">are</add> various sets of the <rs type="art" ref="ar0159">Kings of <placeName ref="pl0925">France</placeName></rs>,
                    from Quarto size to duodecimo. – of some of their kings there are prints from original Portraits, of which I recollect 
                    <rs type="art" ref="ar0159">Francis I<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. Charles VII. Louis XI. XII. &amp; XIII, and of Course all the subsequent kings</rs>.
                    I have a print with the Plan and elevation of the Music room, said (<hi rend="underline">in M.S.</hi>) to have been erected at 
                    <placeName ref="pl1251">Holywell</placeName> 1743. – pray inform me whether such a building does, or did exist there.<note type="editorial">See <ref target="1094.xml">1094</ref>.</note></p>
                <p><rs type="art" ref="ar0041">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Pitts Portrait</rs> is engraving, the same size, as the Drawing you sent me from 
                    <persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName>, which you say he had so bad an opinion of, that it was <add place="above">not</add>
                    charg’d in my account, but both him, and <rs type="art" ref="ar0160">his father</rs> are charg’d, and <hi rend="underline">so I would have them to</hi>
                    be, – for time is the estate of <persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName>.</p>
                <p>I have nothing new to tell you. opposition play their game wretchedly, and are breaking their own faggot into splinters. I receiv’d last night a letter from a relation at
                    <placeName ref="pl1023">Paris</placeName>, who says every thing there is just now, in the most perfect tranquility, owing to the 
                    <persName ref="pe0824">Kings</persName> popular step, in going to the assemblée nationale.<note type="editorial">Louis XVI attended the National Assembly on 4 February 1790. Jones, <hi rend="italic">Longman Companion to the French Revolution</hi>, p. 13.</note>
                    my friend<note type="editorial">It is unclear whether this 'friend' is the same as the 'relation' mentioned earlier in this paragraph. Perhaps the change in terms suggests that the 'relation' was a brother-in-law, husband of the sister mentioned in <ref target="1089.xml">1089</ref>.</note>
                    saw the serment civique<note type="editorial">'civic oath'.</note> administer’d <add place="above">to the several members</add> <del>there</del> on the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.
                    past, in consequence of the <persName ref="pe0824">Kings</persName> appearance there. <persName ref="pe0987">Mirabeau</persName>
                    was very refractory, and absolutely refused to take the oath, till he <add place="above">had</add> given the <persName ref="pe0988">president</persName>
                    the trouble of explaining it at large, and then with apparent disgust, roar’d out “Je le Jure donc.<note type="editorial">'I swear it, then'.</note></p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I am Dear Sir, yours always.</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0313">Rich<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>: Bull</persName></signed>
                    <dateline><placeName ref=""/></dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>