<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1130">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Richard Bull to Thomas Pennant</title>
            <respStmt>                     <name>Transcribed by Ffion Mair Jones; edited by Ffion Mair Jones; encoded by Vivien Williams. (2019)</name>                 </respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/ TP 189</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>31</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <additions><p><hi rend="italic">Endorsement in Thomas Pennant's hand at the top of the first page</hi>: <hi rend="underline">Answ<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></hi></p></additions>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                    <date when="1791-04-08"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0759">Stratton Street</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage> <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="it">Italian</language>
                <language ident="fr">French</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir.</salute> <dateline><placeName ref="pl0759">Stratton Street</placeName>. April 8. 1791.</dateline></opener>
                <p>I desire to thank you again, and again, for the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0271">new Edition of your London</title></bibl>
                    upon large paper, which I have got from <persName ref="pe0328">Faulder</persName>, to whom I have sent my Copy of the 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0039">first Edition</title></bibl> <add place="above">&amp; <hi rend="underline"><bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0040">appendix</title></bibl></hi></add>
                    neat and clean, &amp; hot press’d, with which he seems pleased. I directed him to sell it, and place it to your account, which I will beg you to 
                    <hi rend="underline">keep in your remembrance</hi>, for I would by no means, in no manner, trespass upon generosity, where I have such an obvious way of avoiding it. The 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0039">first Edition</title></bibl>, <hi rend="underline">with <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0040">the Appendix</title></bibl></hi>, 
                    may be as saleable to a common reader, as the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0271">second</title></bibl>, but not so to me, for reasons I have already told You.</p>
                <p>You have furnish’d me so plentifully with the works of the <persName ref="pe0009">Edinburgh barber</persName>, 
                    that I have no occasion for more, unless he has done any, never intended to be sold.</p>
                <p>The <persName ref="pe0378">Good B<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>p of Mar:<hi rend="superscript">lles</hi></persName> was certainly buried, but is it as certain 
                    that he had an Epitaph to his memory? in addition to what you know of that place, you will find in the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0434">Burghley state papers</title></bibl>;
                    that “at <placeName ref="pl1705">Southwick</placeName> was a house of Augustine Canons, founded by <persName ref="pe1282">Henry 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>.</persName>
                    and granted at the dissolution to <persName ref="pe1283">John White</persName>.<note type="editorial">This quotation from 'Burghley Papers, II, 797', appears in John Nichols, <hi rend="italic">The progresses, and public processions, of Queen Elizabeth</hi> (London: printed by and for the editor, 1788), II, p. 3.</note>
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0358">Magna Britannia</title></bibl> says "<persName ref="pe0629">Henry 8</persName>
                    exchang’d it, with the <persName ref="pe1284">Lord Chamberlain Sir Thomas Wrotheslay</persName>. utrum horum mavis, accipe;<note type="editorial">'take whichever you prefer'.</note>
                    I should suppose the former to be most accurate. It was never a Royal house, but was hired for the King, <del>when</del>
                    (of the Norton Family,) when <persName ref="pe0600">Charles 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>.</persName> had a temporary residence there.<note type="editorial">Charles I stayed with Sir Daniel Norton at his home, Southwick Priory, Hampshire, in June 1627, awaiting the embarkation of a fleet for France from Portsmouth. <hi rend="italic">Hist P</hi> s.n. Sir Daniel Norton.</note></p>
                <p>I have got most of <persName ref="pe0402">Hollars</persName> <rs type="art" ref="ar0242">sea fights</rs>, but being without dates or inscriptions, am at loss to know the battle of 
                    1636.<note type="editorial">For Hollar's depiction of the Battle of the Downs, 1639 (wrongly dated both here and there to 1636), see <ref target="1128.xml">1128</ref> and the artwork <rs type="art" ref="ar0237">'De Spaanse, Engelse en Hollandse vloten voor Deal, 1639'</rs>.</note>
                    Where the terrible <rs type="art" ref="ar0238">Negro prints</rs> came from, I cannot tell, nor have I ever seen any others of that kind. – I don’t recollect I am in immediate want of any of 
                    <persName ref="pe0416">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Nash</persName>'s prints. ––– Where can people get mony to answer all their purposes, for every body purchases what they wish for, and at any expense? A Sale of Books brought from 
                    <placeName ref="pl1023">Paris</placeName> by <persName ref="pe0387">Edwards</persName>, 
                    produced at auction, last week, very near £7000, and the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0431">Catalogue</title></bibl>, a very small one, only 636 articles. – A couple of 8<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>.
                    M.S.S sold for more than 200 £
                    – then – how <hi rend="underline">are</hi> we ruind?</p>
                <p>You think more about me, and my little pursuits, than I have any right to expect, and I ought not to omit thanking you, for what you flatter me with the hopes of receiving, when your
                    <persName ref="pe0234">young Lady</persName> comes to <placeName ref="pl0699">town</placeName>. and here let me note my own, and 
                    my daughters<note xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
                        <xi:include parse="text" href="Bulls.xml"/>
                    </note> best acknowledgements, <del>for wishing to</del> to you, and your <persName ref="pe0238">Sposa</persName>,
                    for wishing to see us in <placeName ref="pl0731">wales</placeName>, where we have long wish’d to see ourselves, and what you have said is an additional inducement to us all. The 
                    dies volvenda<note type="editorial">'passage of time'.</note> may bring it about, but not this year; tho’ 
                <hi rend="underline">you</hi> have a <hi rend="underline">devoir</hi>, to visit the 
                    <placeName ref="pl1020">Isle of Wight</placeName>, if you mean to say anything particular about it; believe me, 
                    <persName ref="pe0436">Sir Rich<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. Worsley</persName>'s Collection<note type="editorial">Worsley's collection is described in some detail in Bull's list <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0065">'A selection from the principal paintings, cultures, and drawings in the house at Appuldurcombe'</title></bibl>.</note> 
                    would well pay you for the trouble, and ’tis very seldom that all my beds are engag’d at the same time.– we go the 
                    <del><gap unit="letters" quantity="1" reason="illegible"/></del>middle of June. - <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>
                    is so full at present, that it takes me up sometimes half an hour, before I can cross <placeName ref="pl2035">piccadilly</placeName>, for a walk in the 
                    <placeName ref="pl2036">Green Park</placeName>, and I for one am pleasur’d  to death. my head is turn’d but I hope not my heart. The 
                    <persName ref="pe0393">prince <add place="above">of</add> Wales</persName> has made it up with the <persName ref="pe0465">King</persName>
                    for the present. – When he has not a guinea left, He arises, and goes to his father, like a true prodigal Son – the 
                    Dutch loan<note type="editorial">The <hi rend="italic">Kentish Gazette</hi>, 4 March 1791, reported on 'A loan for three hundred thousand pounds now said to be negotiating at Antwerp' whereby the revenues of a certain Dutch duchy and bishoprick were to be assigned in trust to six British noblemen.</note>
                    to him cannot be negotiated, nobody will lend him half a crown, upon the Security he has offerd, and he has none other to give. – not long since there was an Execution in his 
                    <placeName ref="pl2037">Palace in Pall: Mall</placeName>, but it seems, he is so little <persName ref="pe1286">Harry V.</persName>, that all
                    his faults are lost in the Expectation of <add place="above">the</add> future greatness of his character. – I have just heard that 
                    <persName ref="pe0380">Lord Cholmondeley</persName> has declar’d himself to <persName ref="pe0370">Lady Charlotte Bertie</persName>,
                    I think he is the first Man in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>, for sweetness of disposition, and elegance of manners, and She is most perfectly good humour’d, and, par bricole at least, 
                    will find the comforts of the beggars blessing, which the World gives him the credit for being so fully possess’d of.
                    <persName ref="pe0372">Lord Cardigan</persName> Æta: 65, has offerd to <persName ref="pe1287">Lady Eliz: waldegrave</persName>
                    æta: 25, and is accepted. this is all the news I know of, except that <del><gap unit="letters" quantity="6" reason="illegible"/></del>
                    the idea of a <sic>warr</sic> grows less and less every day. – This frank is large, and so I have enclos’d some trumpery prints, 
                    &amp; if one of the whole, is of any use to You, my purpose will be Answer’d. </p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I am Dear Sir, 
                        <lb/>Always yours.</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0313">Rich<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>: Bull</persName></signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>P.S. I hear the <persName ref="pe0949">Duke of York</persName> is going Volunteer, to join the Prussian Army.<note type="editorial">Frederick, duke of York and Albany (1763–1827), spent time on the continent during 1791 serving as a volunteer with the Prussian army in case of an outbreak of war against Russia, which in the event did not take place. John Philippart, <hi rend="italic">The royal military calendar: containing the services of every general officer in the British army, from the date of their first commision</hi> (2 vols., London: printed by A. J. Valpy, Tooke's Court, Chancery Lane, 1815), I, p. 2. A contemporary newspaper reported in mid-April 1791 that 'The Duke of York will depart in about a fortnight for Prussia'. <hi rend="italic">Northampton Mercury</hi>, 16 April 1791.</note></p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>