<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1185">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Richard Bull to Thomas Pennant</title>
            <respStmt>                     <name>Transcribed by Ffion Mair Jones; edited by Ffion Mair Jones; encoded by Vivien Williams. (2019)</name>                 </respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/ TP 189</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>23/1</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <additions>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Endorsement in Thomas Pennant's hand</hi>:</p>
                            <p>answ<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></p>
                            
                        </additions>
                    </physDesc>
                    <additional><p><hi rend="italic">Condition</hi>: slight damage to paper near end of letter</p></additional>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                    <date when="1795-08-30"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl1013">North Court</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage> <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="fr">French</language>
                <language ident="it">Italian</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute> <dateline><placeName ref="pl1013">NorthCourt</placeName>. <placeName ref="pl1020">Isle of Wight</placeName>. August 30. 1795</dateline></opener>
                <p>I know not how it happens, but you always find somebody to frank your letters to me, but a black Swan or a White Lion, is not a greater rarity, than a member of Parliament on our side the water, and upon that account, I have been unwilling to trouble you with a letter merely to say how d'ye do, tho I should be sorry indeed to lose such a pleasant correspondent as you are, from a motive perhaps, of false delicacy. I hope, and my 
                    daughter's<note xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" type="editorial"><xi:include href="Bulls.xml"/></note> hope, that you have perfectly recover'd from every bad effect of that unfortunate slip you made in the Spring, and that your knee has regain'd its lost Strength.<note>For Pennant's reference to this accident, see <ref target="1184.xml">1184</ref>.</note> I left 
                    <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> towards the end of May, very lame with a broken shin, occasion'd by an awkward fall over a packing box, and after a confinement of more than six weeks, it became only a secondary complaint, for a violent humor spread it self all over the lower part of my face and made me unfit to associate even with my own family; It was perhaps an effort of nature, to prevent some thing worse, for I was quite otherwise than well, when it came upon me.</p>
                <p>
                    It gave me pleasure to hear that your usual Ardor for literary Amusements still continues, and I hope you will <add place="above">give</add> it proper encouragement, for your own happiness, and for the pleasure, and the instruction of mankind. I have begun to buy prints again, and am making up more Books, not quite in my dotage I trust, tho' in the 74<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                    year of my Reign; And if your Enfant gaté<note type="editorial">'spoilt child'. Bull presumably refers to Moses Griffith.</note>
                    would furnish me with a few more drawings I would finish the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0023">Arctic Zoology</title></bibl> as it should be; but <persName ref="pe0014">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Griffyth</persName>
                    (no longer <persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName>) has married a <persName ref="pe0344">wife</persName> and I understand has not always leisure <del>even</del> to do business even for his great benefactor, much less for your friends. perhaps his 
                    <persName ref="pe0344">Cara Sposa</persName><note type="editorial">'beloved wife'.</note> thinks <hi rend="underline">her</hi> <hi rend="underline">business</hi> is sufficient for all his leisure, but that is 
                    kicking against the Pricks and He should admonish her of it. You had once the goodness to say you would procure somebody to make me a copy of your <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0475">outline of the World</title></bibl>,
                    as far as it respected the little <placeName ref="pl1020">Isle of wight</placeName>,<note type="editorial">See 'Outlines of the Globe', <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0657">vol. XXI</title></bibl>.</note> about which I take much Interest, and <gap unit="letters" quantity="several" reason="illegible"/> in common with all others,
                    <gap unit="letters" quantity="several" reason="illegible"/>fied with the catch penny accounts which have appear'd this year and the last, upon our <placeName ref="pl1020">Island</placeName> subject.</p>
                <p>
                    We have found full employment here, for a score of workmen for near three years, and, like all other Simpletons, have expended three times the sum we proposed to have laid out, but the place is a new Creation, both within and without, and if it is not become too large for such a <sic>mènage</sic> as mine, the poor laborers in my Vinyard are heartily welcome to the Wages they have earned. Having seen what it was, I wish for an opportunity of shewing you what <hi rend="underline">it i</hi>s.</p>
                <p>
                    What a disastrous Crusade the poor Emigrants made upon the Coasts of <placeName ref="pl0925">France</placeName>! And I fear it will not be long, before we shall have a second Edition of the same tragedy with English notes, as A fleet of three, three deckers, two seventy fours, and four frigates, with above an hundred transports full of English and french troops, are 
                    <hi rend="underline">said</hi> to have sail'd upon a secret Expedition against some part of <placeName ref="pl2544">Britany</placeName>.<note type="editorial">The expedition to the island of Yeu (l'île d'Yeu), 26 August – 21 November 1795.</note>
                    <persName ref="pe0974">Compte D'Artois</persName> went in the Queen Charlotte, and 'tis supposed, they have receivd some important informations, from the Royalists, since the death of the <persName ref="pe1769">Boy king</persName>.</p>
                <p>
                    My daughters<note xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" type="editorial"><xi:include href="Bulls.xml"/></note> desire their best good wishes to all of the 
                    house of Pennant, 
                    and if you have thought my silence has arisen from indolence, or from want of attention, unthink it again <supplied>as</supplied> fast as you can, I beseech you,</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>and believe me, as ever, sincerely yours.</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0313">Rich<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>: Bull</persName></signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>
                    <stamp type="postmark">C AU 31 95</stamp>
                    <stamp type="handstamp"><gap unit="letters" quantity="1" reason="illegible"/> <placeName ref="pl1020">ISL<supplied>E</supplied> OF W<supplied>IGH</supplied>T</placeName></stamp></p>
                <p><address>
                    <addrLine><persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName> Esq<hi rend="superscript">re</hi>: / <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName> / <hi rend="underline"><placeName ref="pl0702">Flintshire</placeName></hi></addrLine>
                    </address></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>