<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1301">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Daniel Lysons to Thomas Pennant, 19 September 1767</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>Warwickshire County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>CR 2017/TP294/2</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <additional>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Condition</hi>: two small tears at seal</p>
                    </additional>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0408">Daniel Lysons</persName>
                    <date when="1767-09-19"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl1276">Gloucester</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct1302"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct1300"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><dateline><placeName ref="pl1276">Glocester</placeName> Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 19.1767
                </dateline><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
                
                <p>The Salmon particularly frequents the <placeName ref="pl1226">Severn</placeName> &amp; in such quantities that a single
                    Draught or Pool in the <placeName ref="pl1226">severn</placeName> is frequently let for 30 or 40 £ per Ann without 
                    any land belonging to it. This Pool is a part of the river perhaps about a quarter of a mile in length, where the bottom
                    of the River being cleard from any inequalities as <add place="above">heaps</add> mud <add place="above">or</add> sand banks,
                    [<del>...</del>]logs of wood, or stones [<del>...</del>]the nets may be then drawn smoothly down the Stream. The pool being
                    thus made (which is commonly at a considerable expence) four men go with a boat to the top of the pool one of which holds a 
                    line in his hand to which the net is fastened. By this line he holds the net close to the shore whilst 
                    <add place="above">two of</add> the others row the boat over the river with a pair of oars to the opposite <sic>shoar</sic>. 
                    In the mean time the fourth man throws out the net <add place="above">gradually</add> from the stern of the boat in order 
                    that it may not be entangled. The net being thus let down the men in the boat keep the net as near as they can to the opposite
                    <sic>shoar</sic> whilst the other continues on that side where the net was first cast out. The net is carried down by the 
                    Stream with <add place="above">such</add> great force that the man who holds the line has hard work to keep it close to the 
                    <sic>shoar</sic>. As soon as the net has taken its proper sweep the boat is rowed over to the landing place, &amp; the two men
                    who rowed taking a line which was fixed to the end of the net next the boat draw that <add place="above">end of the</add>
                    net over as fast as possible. The length of the net &amp; the violence of the stream makes this also very hard work. The 
                    business of the fourth man is to row the boat out of the net after having staid at the landing place 
                    <add place="above"><sic>padling</sic> &amp; disturbing the water</add> untill the net is drawn close to land, &amp;
                    encloses the boat. Both ends of the net being brought to <sic>shoar</sic> they draw out the net and land the fish in the 
                    same manner as with any other common <del>Draught</del> net. You see that the man who throws out the net at the Stern of the boat, 
                    &amp; who takes care of it whilst the net is landing, has very easy work whilst the other three work hard; but they all three 
                    take their turns at his post, &amp; he also at theirs, so that upon the whole no one is favoured. In large fisheries there are
                    commonly two boats, the 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. shooting out their net at the time the first lands, &amp;
                    so they follow one another alternately. When the water is clear they fish chiefly by night, when muddy by Day, &amp;
                    when the fish are plenty in the River they often continue working night &amp; day, with as little intermission as possible.
                </p>
                <p>The Master has half the profits of the fish, the 8 men the other. The master pays the rent &amp; finds nets the men mend them,
                    &amp; perhaps assist in making. You see <del>what</del><add place="above">how considerable</add> the whole profits must be 
                    when the
                    Master pays his rent of 30 or 40 £ per Ann, is maintaind &amp; his family supported from half the profits of a single fishery.
                    Besides Salmon they also take Lampreys &amp; Shad with these long nets, but the principal <sic>dependance</sic> of the great
                    fisheries is upon Salmon. They begin fishing for Salmon in the beginning of November, &amp; cease the 
                    1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. of august the other three being by act of parliament fence months that the Salmon may go up to
                    spawn. And there is an act that no Salmon big with spawn or that has spawned &amp; not return’d to the Sea shall be taken under
                    a great penalty. These fish are well known to the fishermen, &amp; calld old fish, but they never let them go whenever they can
                    get possession of them. These fish are of a brown colour, &amp; have the under chap much more prominent than the upper, or at
                    least much more so than when it is in its healthy state. Its body is emaciated, &amp; its flesh white &amp; insipid. With these
                    unseasonable fish the <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> markets are often supply’d to the great discredit of 
                    <placeName ref="pl1226">Severn</placeName> Salmon.</p>
                <p>The young Salmon return from the head of the <placeName ref="pl1226">Severn</placeName> <add place="above">to the Sea</add>
                    in the months of <add place="above">February &amp;</add> March, &amp; at that time weigh between one &amp; two ounces. These 
                    fish return to the <placeName ref="pl1226">Severn</placeName> again in the months of June &amp; July &amp; then weigh a pound 
                    or two, &amp; some larger. The largest sort weighing 3 or 4 pound come up the river as far as 
                    <placeName ref="pl1276">Glocester</placeName> or higher, but the smaller go up the welch Rivers &amp; are taken in great 
                    numbers under the name of Sewin.<note type="editorial">The sewin is a fish of the Salmon tribe 
                        (<hi rend="italic">Salmo cambricus</hi> or <hi rend="italic">eriox</hi>), the bull-trout, found in Welsh rivers. 
                        <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>. An example from  <hi rend="italic">British zoology</hi> (2nd edn., 1768–70), III, iv, 248, is quoted: 'Taken in the river 
                        Wye, where it is known by the name of Sewin, or Shewin'. See also <hi rend="italic">GPC</hi> s.v. sewin, sewyn, 
                        siwin<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>, siwyn<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> for Cornish and Breton forms of the word and for 
                        examples of usage in Welsh.</note> </p>
                <p>The above method of taking Salmon with the long net as above, is practiced chiefly in deep water, &amp; where the River is not
                    more than an hundred yards over. The same method is used in shallow water where the water is broader; but there they have also
                    another me<unclear>thod</unclear>  of taking them with nets besides the <unclear>co</unclear>mmon one of waves. A single man 
                    armd with boots which come up to his [<del>...</del>]hips walks into the water when the sands are overflowd <del>with water</del> &amp;
                    the water being shallow he can see where the fish is by the waves it makes in swimming, &amp; as they always swim against the
                    Stream he claps his net in before the fish, &amp; so takes it. The net is in form of a S<hi rend="italic">t</hi>. Andrews cross,
                    exactly corresponding with our heave nets  at <placeName ref="pl1347">oxford</placeName>.<note type="editorial"><hi rend="italic">OED</hi> 
                        doesn't include 'heave net' as a compound, but refers to the use of the noun 'haaf' in Shetland and Orkney, defining it as 
                        related to deep-sea fishing and giving examples of various compounds, including haaf-fishing and haaf-boat. For 
                        'Haaf, or heave, netting' as a traditional way of fishing for salmon and sea trout in the rivers of the North West, especially
                        the Lune and Ribble, and on the Solway estuary, 
                        see <ref type="http" target="https://www.visitcumbria.com/haaf-netting-in-cumbria">here</ref> [accessed 20 February 2018].</note> In 
                    one of these nets a sturgeon 
                    was lately taken weighing above 150 lb. this I assure you is true however impossible it may appear. It will now be too late to add any 
                    farther list of the finny inhabitants of the <placeName ref="pl1226">Severn</placeName> which shall be the subject of my next, which will 
                    probably be <add place="above">dated</add> from <placeName ref="pl0796">Bath</placeName>, to which place I shall go in a few days for a 
                    slight complaint in my stomach &amp; bowels. It has been on me almost a year, but as I am as certain as can be that 
                    <placeName ref="pl0796">Bath</placeName> is my cure. I can add <sic>nomore</sic> at present but that I am </p>
                
                <closer><salute>Yours sincerely</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0408">D. Lysons.</persName></signed>
                    <dateline/></closer>
                <postscript><p>P.S. you shall hear from me again soon</p></postscript>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>
                    <stamp type="handstamp"><placeName ref="pl1276">GLOUCESTER</placeName></stamp>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <address><addrLine>To <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant Esq<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName> at 
                        <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName> near <placeName ref="pl1251">Holywell</placeName> 
                        <placeName ref="pl0702">Flintshire</placeName> Single sheet</addrLine></address>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>