<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1387">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Thomas Pennant to John Lloyd, Caerwys, 17 April 1783</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                        <idno>4857D</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <date when="1783-04-17">17 April 1783</date>
                    <placeName ref="pl1201">Upper Brook Street</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0333">John Lloyd</persName>
                    <placeName ref="">Caerwys</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct1388"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct1386"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><dateline><placeName ref="pl0753">Upper Brook street</placeName><lb/>
                    April 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1783
                </dateline><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
                
                <p>There has been for a long time such a variation in politics that I might as safely as given you the state of the wind 
                    as those of the hour.<note type="editorial">Pennant refers to the resignation of William Fitzmaurice, Earl of Shelburne, 
                        on 24 February 1783, the failure of George III to persuade William Pitt, the younger, to form the next administration 
                        on 27 February, and the establishment of a coalition between Fox and North on 1 April, with William Henry Cavendish Bentinck, 
                        third duke of Portland, as first lord of the Treasury. By 19 December Pitt had assumed power. 
                        <hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi> s.n. William Pitt [known as Pitt the younger].</note>  at present there is a little permanency; but I believe I may safely say that you cannot pick out 
                    three members of administration who does not fear a jail or an execution: so you may judge of the prospect poor Britain
                    has before her.
                </p> 
                <p>I have felt much for the particular distresses of our county, &amp; lament the riotous disposition shewen by my neighbors. 
                    I am not a <persName ref="pe0769">crœsus</persName> in anything but my thoughts. Yet as far as I can go I will. I hope that 
                    this week a vessel freighted at my expence with barley will sail for <placeName ref="pl0695">Mostyn</placeName> mark; the Cargo 
                    of which shall be sold at prime cost first to the poor of <placeName ref="pl1332">Whiteford</placeName> then of 
                    <placeName ref="pl1251">Holywell</placeName> &amp; if any can be spared to the poor of any other parishes who may be properly 
                    recommended. Corn from the english counties has been so poured into this great mart as to make it comparatively to what it is 
                    with us most amazingly cheap.</p>
                <p>Be pleased to consult with <persName ref="pe0770">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Foulks</persName> &amp; your Brother 
                    <persName ref="pe0253">Parry</persName> about the quantity our parish will want till the middle of September, that I may not be 
                    obliged to buy a second time. for I shall never be able to see our Country in misery without exerting my abilities. we set out for
                    home on the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. I have set out with a more chearful heart. my little ones now are the forcible 
                    attractors<note type="editorial">Pennant refers to the two children from his second marriage, <persName ref="pe0235">Sarah</persName>
                        and <persName ref="pe0421">Thomas</persName>.</note></p>
                <closer><salute>I am Dear Sir<lb/>sincerely y<unclear>ours</unclear></salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0232">Tho. Pennant</persName></signed>
                    <dateline/></closer>
                <postscript><p>I hope <persName ref="pe0741">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Lloyd</persName> &amp; all your family are well.</p></postscript>
            </div>
            <div><p><address><addrLine>To | The <persName ref="pe0333">Reverend M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lloyd</persName></addrLine>
                <addrLine><placeName ref="pl1201">Caerwis</placeName>.</addrLine></address></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>