<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0008">
    <teiHeader type="w">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Katherine Plymley, ‘Journey to Anglesey’
                    <date>1792</date></title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Edited with an introduction by Elizabeth Edwards</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Shrewsbury</settlement>
                        <repository>Shropshire Records and Archive Centre</repository>
                        <idno>567/5/5/1</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>1</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <pb n="1v"/>
                <fw>f. 1v</fw>
                <p><date>August 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1792</date>
                    <lb/><persName ref="pe0923">My Brother</persName>, <persName ref="pe1217">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Plymley</persName>, <persName ref="pe1218">Panton</persName>, <persName ref="pe1219">Josepha</persName>, &amp;
                        <persName ref="pe1220">Jane</persName> set out on a visit to <persName ref="pe0323">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Panton</persName>'s in
                        <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName> &amp; through the kindness of
                        <persName ref="pe0923">my Brother</persName>
                    <persName ref="pe1061">my Sister</persName> &amp; I accompanied them. We were a
                    large party, <persName ref="pe0923">my Brother</persName>, <persName ref="pe1217">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Plymley</persName>, &amp; two
                    of the young folks in their own chaise, <persName ref="pe1061">my
                        Sister</persName>, myself, the other little girl &amp; a <persName ref="pe1581">a maid servant (Nancy Hotchkiss)</persName> in another – two
                    men Servants &amp; two led Horses, on which some- <pb n="2r"/>
                    <fw>f. 2r</fw> times <persName ref="pe0923">my Brother</persName>, &amp; often
                    my Nephew rode – <lb/>It was a fine morning, we passed an hour or two in
                        <placeName ref="pl0740">Shrewsbury</placeName> &amp; about 12 o’ clock set
                    out from thence – <lb/>Pretty woody scenery coming down to <placeName ref="pl1944">Montford bridge</placeName>. considerable plantations belonging
                    to <persName ref="pe1221">Lord Clive</persName> - the church at a small distance
                    on the left, white &amp; back'd finely by the hills – a new bridge nearly
                    finished of three arches – A little further, on <add place="above">the
                        right</add>
                    <placeName ref="pl1945">Hensdon house</placeName> built by <persName ref="pe1221">Lord Clive</persName> - <pb n="2v"/>
                    <fw>f. 2v</fw> now inhabited by farmers – <placeName ref="pl1946">Ness</placeName> on the right, at a little distance from the road, 2 or 3
                    good houses – <lb/>a little farther, are fine rocks rising among trees, on the
                    right, some small plantations of Firs on their tops, in these rocks is a cave,
                    known by the name of <placeName ref="pl1947">Kynaston’s cave</placeName>, at
                    present inhabited by a poor family – <lb/>As we proceed we pass <placeName ref="pl1948">Aston</placeName> on the left, the seat of <persName ref="pe1582">Mr. Lloyd</persName>, pretty planta- <pb n="3r"/>
                    <fw>f. 3r</fw> tions about it. the church is very near the house. here is a fine
                    view of the hills, indeed the whole way from <placeName ref="pl0740">Shrewsbury</placeName> to this place the <placeName ref="pl2393">Breyddin</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1950">Moel y Gollfa</placeName>,
                    &amp; <placeName ref="pl1951">Cevn y Castell</placeName>, (<placeName ref="pl1242">Montgomeryshire</placeName> hills) present a fine prospect to
                    the left – from hence <placeName ref="pl1952">Oswestry church</placeName> &amp;
                    many of the houses appear among trees, well back’d by hills – the whole country
                    finely wooded – <lb/>Dined at <placeName ref="pl1260">Oswestry</placeName> (18
                    mile from <placeName ref="pl0740">Shrewsbury</placeName>) the church yard <pb n="3v"/>
                    <fw>f. 3v</fw> is pleasant, &amp; there are some very good houses about it –
                    <lb/>The road was excellent the whole way from <placeName ref="pl0740">Shrewsbury</placeName> &amp; beyond <placeName ref="pl1260">Oswestry</placeName> continues equally good – to the left is a fine view of
                    the woods about <placeName ref="pl1256">Chirk Castle</placeName> - on the right
                    is <add place="above">seen</add> the tower of a church called <placeName ref="pl2394">S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Martins</placeName> &amp; the
                    tower of <placeName ref="pl1953">Chirk church</placeName> before us – the road
                    very steep down to the bridge, as we approached <placeName ref="pl3069">Chirk</placeName>, &amp; when pass’d the bridge the ascent is equally steep
                        <pb n="4r"/>
                    <fw>f. 4r</fw> to the town. The view very fine; beautiful woods on each side the
                    road – &amp; the brook over which is the bridge at the bottom – <lb/>Just beyond
                        <placeName ref="pl3069">Chirk</placeName> pass the kitchen garden belonging
                    to the castle on the right – a great distance from the house – fine view of
                        <placeName ref="pl0761">Wynnstay</placeName> at some distance on the right
                    &amp; <placeName ref="pl1256">Chirk castle</placeName> on the left &amp; of the
                    woods belonging to each – Turning into a road <pb n="4v"/>
                    <fw>f. 4v</fw> on the left we enter the <placeName ref="pl0793">vale of
                        Llangollen</placeName>, rather a narrow, but a beautiful &amp; sublime
                    valley. Thro the greatest part the road is formed on the side of a hill or
                    hills, rising directly on the left hand &amp; a precipice on the right, to the
                    bottom – the road uncommonly excellent. <add place="above">at</add> the bottom
                    of the precipice the <placeName ref="pl1138">river Dee</placeName> winds in a
                    most beautiful manner, beyond it rise hills, suddenly <pb n="5r"/>
                    <fw>f. 5r</fw> in picturesque shapes, with marked summits, one in particular on
                    the top of which is <placeName ref="pl0794">Castle Dinas Brân (or Crow
                        castle)</placeName> is uncommonly fine. the whole is finely wooded – It was
                    one of those serene &amp; cheerful evenings when every thing appears so calm
                    &amp; peaceful, smoaks ascended in many places among the trees, beautiful light
                    streaked the western sky &amp; was reflected with great lustre <pb n="5v"/>
                    <fw>f. 5v</fw> in the river, as we caught it in its different turns among the
                    trees – night came on just before we entered <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> &amp; every thing suited the solemnity of the scene
                    – <lb/><date>14<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></date>
                    <lb/>Walk’d this morn<hi rend="superscript">g.</hi> to <placeName ref="pl1614">Plas Newydd</placeName> the beautiful cottage belonging to <persName ref="pe0954">Lady Elinor Butler</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe0957">Miss
                        Ponsonby</persName> it is almost contiguous to <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName>. being not fully <pb n="6r"/>
                    <fw>f. 6r</fw> apprised that it was a necessary ceremony to send a written
                    message we sent a verbal one, a very civil answer was returned informing us we
                    should be very welcome to see it if we would send a written message, which being
                    done a note was returned written in a very fine hand – It is small but very neat
                    &amp; elegant. <pb n="6v"/>
                    <fw>f. 6v</fw> Only two rooms are shewn, a small dining Parlour, ornamented with
                    drawings, some by artists &amp; some by friends – One demands particular
                    attention, it is hung over the chimney piece &amp; represents an inside view of
                        <placeName ref="pl1782">Tintern Abbey</placeName>, drawn in crayons,
                    beautifully tinted, by Miss <persName ref="pe1222">Harriet Bowdler</persName>.
                    Thro’ this parlour is the Study, a beautiful small <pb n="7r"/>
                    <fw>f. 7r</fw> gothic room, a study table in the middle, a compass window with a
                    great deal of painted glass: three gothic bookcases let into the wall, brass
                    wire doors, a gothic chimney piece over which are several pleasing miniature
                    portraits of some of their friends – several good prints framed &amp; glazed –
                    view from the window a small lawn surrounded by <pb n="7v"/>
                    <fw>f. 7v</fw> trees &amp; shrubs, a view of hills above them among which
                        <placeName ref="pl0794">Castell Dinas Bran</placeName> is conspicuous &amp;
                    forms a fine feature. The pleasure ground is entered thro’ a prettily contrived
                    gothic door with a bell hung in the ornamented top – it consists of little more
                    than a gravel walk, kept in nice order, being swept with a hair broom, through
                        <pb n="8r"/>
                    <fw>f. 8r</fw> shrubs surrounding the lawn. There are some seals with
                    inscriptions, chiefly in French – I suppose there are few places that travellers
                    make a point of seeing, so small, &amp; it perhaps owes much of its celebrity to
                    the romantic history of its inhabitants. Two young ladies leaving all their
                    friends in <placeName ref="pl0889">Ireland</placeName>, landing <del>in</del>, I
                    think <add place="above">in</add>
                    <placeName ref="pl1245">south <pb n="8v"/>
                        <fw>f. 8v</fw> Wales</placeName>, &amp; wandering till they fixed on this
                    spot, making a vow never to sleep out of it, which was for many years kept, it
                    has, I am told, lately been dispensed with – It is said they had very unpleasant
                    homes, but as their Fathers were living their income, having left them
                    privately, was very confined. they are now reconciled to their friends <pb n="9r"/>
                    <fw>f. 9r</fw>
                    <persName ref="pe1583">Lady Elinor’s father</persName> is dead, &amp; she is, I
                    understand, in very good circumstances. <lb/>The view from <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> churchyard is very good, it stands high
                    above the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName> - but is terribly crowded with
                    beggars, most of them young children, many however old enough to procure their
                    own living, at least to do much towards it; it is melancholy to see <pb n="9v"/>
                    <fw>f. 9v</fw> the rising generation brought up in such total idleness.
                        <placeName ref="pl1714">Llandysilio</placeName> being only two miles
                    distant, <persName ref="pe0923">my B<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi></persName>
                    Called upon <persName ref="pe1223">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                        Jones</persName> who pressed him much to bring all his party to dine with
                    him, &amp; promised to meet us at <placeName ref="pl0785">Valle Crucis
                        Abbey</placeName> which lies a very short way from the road. <persName ref="pe1223">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Jones</persName> was punctual,
                    &amp; we saw the beautiful remains of this <pb n="10r"/>
                    <fw>f. 10r</fw>
                    <placeName ref="pl0785">Abbey</placeName> which quite answered my expectation,
                    the west end is uncommonly fine, the best representation of it I ever saw is <rs type="art" ref="ar0329">a drawing</rs> of <persName ref="pe1223">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Jones</persName> which he had the goodness to
                    give me, &amp; which I esteem much – one part of the ruin is much disfigured by
                    a smart modern <placeName ref="pl2395">summer house</placeName> with a straight
                    canal by the side of it, built by the owner to make <pb n="10v"/>
                    <fw>f. 10v</fw> dining parties in – The road from hence to <placeName ref="pl1714">Llandysilio</placeName> is very beautiful thro’ a birch wood,
                    among them many of the hanging birch finer than any I had before seen, the
                        <placeName ref="pl1138">river Dee</placeName> runs among the trees at the
                    bottom over a very rocky bed &amp; has a fine effect. Coming out of the Wood,
                        <add place="above">the view of</add>
                    <placeName ref="pl1714">Llandysilio</placeName> is very striking, the house
                    appears embosomed <pb n="11r"/>
                    <fw>f. 11r</fw> in woods which conceals the walled garden in from &amp; the cut
                    yews which on a nearer approach disfigure a place that nature has been profusely
                    kind to, its possessor too has very good taste but too indolent to exert it, his
                    intimate friends have remonstrated in vain, he admits the justice of their
                    remarks but the yew trees still <pb n="11v"/>
                    <fw>f. 11v</fw> stand &amp; walls still surround the house – he &amp; his sister
                    received us most hospitably, we dined &amp; drank tea with them &amp; then
                    proceeded to <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName>; the <placeName ref="pl1138">River</placeName> running between <placeName ref="pl1714">Llandysilio</placeName> &amp; the road to that place obliged us to return
                    to <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName>. The <placeName ref="pl1954">bridge</placeName> has five arches &amp; is over a part of the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName> where the bed is more than commonly <pb n="12r"/>
                    <fw>f. 12r</fw> rocky, it is, as it were, quite sheets of rock – In the road to
                        <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName> when opposite to <placeName ref="pl1714">Llandysilio</placeName> the view is remarkably beautiful. The
                    road is cut out of a rocky hill, about midway up it, a precipice down to the
                    river, which winds with uncommon beauty over a rocky bed, the sides wooded to
                    the edge of the water, the trees in some <pb n="12v"/>
                    <fw>f. 12v</fw> of the turns concealing it – <placeName ref="pl0794">Dinas
                        Bran</placeName> appears very fine – the birch wood we passed through to
                        <placeName ref="pl1714">Llandysilio</placeName> here appears in grand beauty
                    from the opposite side – <placeName ref="pl1714">Llandysilio</placeName> again
                    shews all its beauties &amp; conceals its defects, wooded in front, wooded
                    fields appearing like fine lawns rising behind it – A singularly rocky hill
                    called the <placeName ref="pl1955">Glisseg rocks</placeName>
                    <pb n="13r"/>
                    <fw>f. 13r</fw> forms a striking feature great part of the road – after having
                    travelled along this precipice which in general having no fence, may create some
                    alarm notwithstanding the road is wide &amp; uncommonly good if the beautiful
                    scenery did not almost exclude other ideas, we come into a low &amp; rather
                    dreary road, though I think it is only <pb n="13v"/>
                    <fw>f. 13v</fw> for a very short way that it is allowable to term it dreary – we
                    reach <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName> in the dusk of a fine evening.
                        <lb/>15<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> Delightful morning – look at the
                        <placeName ref="pl1665">church</placeName>, in form of a Cathedral. one part
                    appropriated for a school, the boys were just assembling, most of them without
                    shoes or stockings which to those not much <pb n="14r"/>
                    <fw>f. 14r</fw> accustomed to see it appeared very comfortless, I <add place="above">hope</add> habit makes it no great inconvenience to the boys,
                    for they were otherwise full as well dressed as those of the same rank in
                        <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> - Fine views from the church
                    yard which is situated under a vast rocky hill – In the church yard is a
                    building consisting of six small houses, for the widows of clergy <pb n="14v"/>
                    <fw>f. 14v</fw> in <placeName ref="pl1235">Merionethshire</placeName> only, it
                    is of stone, as the houses in general in this part of the country are – Set out
                    – pass a <placeName ref="pl1956">bridge</placeName> of 5 arches over the
                        <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName>, fine views down the river, but more
                    like <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> than what I have lately seen –
                    pass <placeName ref="pl2396">Rûg</placeName> on the right – an old house, pretty
                    little brook, wood behind &amp; small chapel not far distant, <pb n="15r"/>
                    <fw>f. 15r</fw> pass another bridge of 2 wide arches over the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName> - the river winds on the left side of the road
                    over a very gravelly &amp; in some parts very rocky bed – See <placeName ref="pl2397">Maes Mawr</placeName> on the right – The road assumes a more
                    romantic appearance – pass a bridge of 1 arch over the Tower – Go up rather a
                    steep ascent with fine rocks rising directly on <pb n="15v"/>
                    <fw>f. 15v</fw> the right on the left a stone wall – we alight – Look over the
                    wall on <add place="above">the <placeName ref="pl2398">Glyn</placeName></add> a
                    most beautiful wooded glen through which a brook dashes over a rocky bed. the
                    ground rises suddenly on the other side, Fine rocks bursting through the trees –
                    As we walk the beauty of this noble scenery increases. A cascade falls <pb n="16r"/>
                    <fw>f. 16r</fw> down the rocks between the trees, at one place resting, as it
                    were, in a basin &amp; then dashing with impetuosity over the rocks – The Sun
                    shone bright upon the water &amp; added to the lustre of the scene – after this
                    delightful glen, the road becomes rather barren &amp; dreary – hills with
                    scarcely a tree, &amp; very few inclosures, a bridge of <pb n="16v"/>
                    <fw>f. 16v</fw> one arch appears in the midst of the scene. Pass <persName ref="pe2163">Mr. Wynne</persName>'s <add place="above"><placeName ref="pl1957">Veolas</placeName></add> on the right, a white house with
                    trees about it, a bridge near it – one wide arch – On all sides extensive heaths
                    – stone wall enclosures &amp; here &amp; there a tree &amp; hedge – Pass through
                    the first village I’ve seen with the church bells placed in open arches. See the
                    road a long way <pb n="17r"/>
                    <fw>f. 17r</fw> before us in rather a barren country, but the view rendered very
                    striking by a noble sight of the <placeName ref="pl1234">Caernarvonshire</placeName> mountains at a great distance whose noble &amp;
                    grotesque summits rising one above another seem at last to hid themselves in the
                    clouds; the day was very clear &amp; the blue colour of them beau- <pb n="17v"/>
                    <fw>f. 17v</fw> tiful – here I caught the first sight of <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>, farther distant than any of the rest of this grand
                    chain. our <placeName ref="pl1021">Shropshire</placeName> hills shrank into
                    banks in my imagination whilst I contemplated this grand scenery. Change horses
                    at <placeName ref="pl1576">Shernioge</placeName>, a single house with some trees
                    about it. – Pass through the village of <placeName ref="pl3070">Voylass</placeName>, the church on the right &amp; the <pb n="18r"/>
                    <fw>f. 18r</fw> hall house – some woods about it – The road becomes dreary –
                    Lose sight of the mountains – An uncommon rocky brook – Nothing but heaths –
                    Again see the <placeName ref="pl1234">Caernarvonshire</placeName> mountains
                    appear rocky, without verdure – the view bold &amp; romantic – Ascend rather a
                    steep, a precipice to the left, reach the top. the beautiful vale of <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>
                    <pb n="18v"/>
                    <fw>f. 18v</fw> opens upon us, a steep down to it – fine view of the <placeName ref="pl1533">Town</placeName> with the beautiful <placeName ref="pl1531">bridge</placeName> of <persName ref="pe1159">Inigo Jones</persName>, the
                    situation very charming in a rich valley surrounded with hills. The <placeName ref="pl2384">Conway</placeName>, here a very small river, runs on our left
                    in its course to <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName> - Dine at
                        <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName> – <placeName ref="pl1879">Church</placeName> in the form of a Cathedral, one chapel entirely belongs
                    to <pb n="19r"/>
                    <fw>f. 19r</fw> the <placeName ref="pe1586">Gwydir family</placeName>. it is
                    their burial place – Pass <placeName ref="pl1532">Gwydir</placeName> on the
                    left, very near <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>. back’d by a fine
                    wood, very old house, the ancient seat of the <persName ref="pe1587">Wynnes</persName>. now possessed by a branch of the <persName ref="pe2164">Duke of Ancaster’s</persName> family <note type="editorial">Gwydir Castle
                        passed from the Wynn family to the Duke of Ancaster by marriage in the late
                        seventeenth century.</note> - The road from hence to <placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName> is through a fine valley surrounded by hills, consisting
                    of fine meadow, <pb n="19v"/>
                    <fw>f. 19v</fw> pasture &amp; arable land, several houses interspersed, here was
                    hedges &amp; trees – the <placeName ref="pl2384">river Conway</placeName> on the
                    right gradually encre<add place="above">a</add>sing in width. In approaching
                        <placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName> I was quite struck with the
                    magnificence of the <placeName ref="pl1530">Castle</placeName>. I have seen many
                    views of it which had given me some idea of its form, but I never saw the place
                    that a drawing is so inadequate to represent, never <pb n="20r"/>
                    <fw>f. 20r</fw> were my expectations so far surpassed, its awful vastness &amp;
                    magnificence to be conceived must be seen. <persName ref="pe1061">My
                        sister</persName> very well said, as we approach’d the gate-way leading to
                    the Tower (the noble walls of the castle surround the town) “Walk about Sion,
                    &amp; go round about her: &amp; tell the towers thereof. Mark well her
                    bulwarks.” (Psalm <pb n="20v"/>
                    <fw>f. 20v</fw> 48).<note type="editorial">Psalm 48:12-13 (KJV).</note> After
                    alighting at the Inn walk to the <placeName ref="pl1530">Castle</placeName>, the
                    situation on a rock above the <placeName ref="pl2384">Conway</placeName>, which
                    though I had seen it little more than a brook this morn<hi rend="superscript">g.</hi> was here especially at high tide almost a sea, is very striking
                    &amp; adds greatly to its magnificence, the hills on the opposite shore are
                    finely wooded. as we looked over the walls of the <placeName ref="pl1530">castle</placeName> we <pb n="21r"/>
                    <fw>f. 21r</fw> saw the ferry boat passengers land beneath us. the time of the
                    evening before we could persuade ourselves to leave it was late, it was dusk.
                    The scene was uncommonly grand. On viewing this astonishing edifice, my mind
                    dwelt with pleasure for a moment on the times in which it was erected, feeling
                    the pleasure these noble ruins gave <pb n="21v"/>
                    <fw>f. 21v</fw> me, I was ready to exclaim how pleasant must those times have
                    been which saw it in its perfection, these ideas were soon checked by the
                    reflection that the very grandeur I admired was a proof of feudal times when the
                    many were slaves to <del>the</del>
                    <add place="above">a</add> few powerful lords. Nothing but extensive power could
                    have enabled anyone to construct such a building <pb n="22r"/>
                    <fw>f. 22r</fw> &amp; the nature &amp; thought of it evince the hostilities in
                    which these lords lived. So those who lived in those times could not raise the
                    ideas it does in us, for antiquity adds greatly to its charms. Time has made it
                    venerable, I am thankful to live in a time in which such buildings are useless;
                    but it is so very fine that I hope it will always remain a monument of feu- <pb n="22v"/>
                    <fw>f. 22v</fw> dal grandeur – <lb/>16<hi rend="superscript">th:</hi> The
                    morning rainy, but rather cleared as we set out. The clouds resting midway on
                    the mountains leaving the summits free, brought strongly to our recollection the
                    lines of <persName ref="pe1224">Goldsmith</persName> rendered doubly striking by
                    having been quoted by <persName ref="pe1590">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Wilberforce</persName> when he moved the Abolition last April - <note type="editorial">A reference to a parliamentary debate on the abolition of
                        the slave trade (2 April 1792). See <ref target="http://historyofparliamentonline.org/volume/1790-1820/member/wilberforce-william-1759-1833">here</ref> Plymley and her brother were longstanding abolitionists. As
                        Harriet Guest explains, in her early 1790s diaries ‘Plymley allied herself
                        with those who saw the campaign for the abolition of the slave trade as part
                        of more all-embracing “cause of liberty” which focused on the need “to
                        reform real defects” in the political organization of the country’. See
                        <hi rend="italic">Unbounded Attachment: Sentiment and Politics in the Age of the French
                        Revolution</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2013), p. 118.</note>
                    <lb/>As some tall cliff that lifts its <hi rend="superscript">awful form</hi>
                    <lb/>Swells from the vale, &amp; midway leaves the storm <pb n="23r"/>
                    <fw>f. 23r</fw> Tho’ round its breast the rolling <hi rend="superscript">clouds
                        are spread,</hi>
                    <lb/>Eternal sunshine settles on its head.<note type="editorial">Oliver
                        Goldsmith, ‘The Deserted Village’ (1770), ll. 189-92, in Roger Lonsdale
                        (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The New Oxford Book of Eighteenth Century Verse</hi> (Oxford: Oxford
                        University Press, 1987), p. 527.</note></p>
                <p>The road hilly – over <placeName ref="pl2400">Sychnant</placeName> it is
                    strikingly romantic, it is an excellent road made over the hill, at the bottom
                    lies the old narrow road, which was in some places almost impassable. we are
                    surrounded on all sides by rocky hills, with furze &amp; a remarkably fine
                    purple heath intermixed.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <pb n="1v"/>
                <fw>f. 1v</fw>
                <p>this we had observed on many hills on our road; the day was misty with some
                    drizzling rain, the clouds rolled over the hills which rose above us. As we
                    advance the view opens in a point between hills to the open sea. a little
                    farther &amp; we see the island of <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName>
                    running out in a point, the <placeName ref="pl1959">Puffin Island</placeName>,
                    &amp; <pb n="2r"/>
                    <fw>f. 2r</fw> the promontory of <placeName ref="pl1958">Orms Head</placeName>.
                    as we descend <placeName ref="pl2400">Sychnant</placeName>, we see before us the
                    road over <placeName ref="pl1338">Penmaen Mawr</placeName>, perpendicular over
                    the sea – reach <placeName ref="pl1338">Penmaen Mawr</placeName>, an excellent
                    road cut in the rocks &amp; secured by a wall at the edge of the precipice to
                    the sea. we alighted &amp; walk’d over this wonderful road – looking over the
                    wall we saw the waves <pb n="2v"/>
                    <fw>f. 2v</fw> of the sea break against the rocks beneath us. The view a fine
                    open sea. <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1959">Puffin Island</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl1958">Orms
                        Head</placeName>, a noble cape rising high out of the waves – on the other
                    hand the side of this great rock rises perpendicular above our heads with crags
                    standing out in a stupendous manner; such is now this road, formerly almost
                    impassable &amp; no wall <pb n="3r"/>
                    <fw>f. 3r</fw> to secure the travellers from being through a false step thrown
                    into the sea – <del>Pass</del> The day continued misty, pass <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName>, some good houses &amp; the <placeName ref="pl2025">Cathedral</placeName> looks very picturesque among trees –
                    Reach <placeName ref="pl1563">Bangor Ferry</placeName> about a mile &amp; half
                    beyond the town. Send the horses in one boat, cross ourselves in another. the
                        <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai</placeName>, this arm of the sea appears a <pb n="3v"/>
                    <fw>f. 3v</fw> most noble &amp; beautifully winding river, it is so surrounded
                    with hills, that few winds affect it. it was today quite still. the low rocky
                    shore of <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName> at the place of crossing
                    was a fine contrast to the highly cultivated part of the shore we had seen from
                    other parts of the road – land in <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName>
                    &amp; reach <placeName ref="pl1960">Plasgwyn</placeName>
                    <pb n="4r"/>
                    <fw>f. 4r</fw> to dinner 6 miles from the ferry – A very handsome house, in a
                    low situation built part on a rock &amp; part on a bog, it has many trees about
                    it, principally ash – there are many young plantations, the only view from the
                    house is trees except from some of the windows the hill of <placeName ref="pl1961">Llwydiert</placeName> - here we met a family, that I believe
                        <pb n="4v"/>
                    <fw>f. 4v</fw> were truly glad to see us, our mutual attachment to <persName ref="pe1225">my Brothers first wife</persName>, an attachment founded on her
                    sweetness, prudence, &amp; piety, formed a strong connexion between us, &amp;
                    the sight of her children, whom we have hitherto had the happiness to educate,
                    was what they had long wished for, but <persName ref="pe0923">my B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName>: had not been able to persuade
                    himself to re- <pb n="5r"/>
                    <fw>f. 5r</fw> trace the scenes he had first known her in whilst he was a
                    widower – Our dear <persName ref="pe1219">Josepha</persName> who had not been
                    well for some time previous to her journey was much better for travelling – When
                    we arrived the family consisted of <persName ref="pe0226">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName>: &amp; <persName ref="pe1226">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>: Panton</persName>, <persName ref="pe1227">Miss Panton</persName>, <persName ref="pe1228">Miss Elizabeth</persName>
                    &amp; <persName ref="pe1229">W. Bulkeley Panton</persName>, &amp; <persName ref="pe1591">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>: Perry</persName>, a witty
                    woman who knew &amp; loved the <persName ref="pe1225">first M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>: Plymley</persName> &amp; <pb n="5v"/>
                    <fw>f. 5v</fw> longed to see her children. In the evening we walked to
                        <placeName ref="pl1962">Red wharf bay</placeName>, &amp; had a fine view of
                    open sea – In the walk see many rocks – <persName ref="pe0226">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: Panton</persName> has a large shrubbery,
                    planted on very uneven ground in some parts quite steep &amp; several fine peeps
                    at the Sea – <lb/>18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>: <persName ref="pe0323">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: P. Panton</persName> arrived he was on the
                        circuit<note type="editorial">i.e. the legal circuit</note> &amp; came here
                    before he went <pb n="6r"/>
                    <fw>f. 6r</fw> to <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName> &amp; brought
                        <persName ref="pe1592">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>:
                            <unclear>Mander</unclear></persName> one of the council with him, when
                    he arrived we happened to be putting the little people to bed he ran up to our
                    rooms &amp; welcomed us to <placeName ref="pl1960">Plasgwyn</placeName> with
                    much kindness. <lb/>19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>: <lb/>Went to <placeName ref="pl1963">Pentrath church</placeName> a low situation, on the road to it
                    is a fine view to open sea, some trees about it – heard the service read in <pb n="6v"/>
                    <fw>f. 6v</fw> Welsh for the first time today – In the evening walk upon the
                    road to <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName>, from whence is a fine
                    view of the <placeName ref="pl1672">Carnarvonshire</placeName> mountains.
                        <lb/>21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>: the little girls bathed, went in the
                    carriage &amp; it was their dressing room – <lb/>22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>: Went with the younger part of the family to a ball at <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName> given by <persName ref="pe1230">Lord
                        Uxbridge</persName>. A very <pb n="7r"/>
                    <fw>f. 7r</fw> smart one &amp; a great deal of dancing. there was a supper &amp;
                    it was very late before we returned; before the ball we drank tea at <persName ref="pe1594">Mr. <unclear>J</unclear> Pantons</persName> who is married
                    &amp; has a small house at <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName>. The
                    road from <placeName ref="pl1960">Plasgwyn</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName> has very fine views of the sea &amp; of
                    the <placeName ref="pl1672">Carnarvonshire</placeName> mountains, we drove
                    through <persName ref="pe1232">Lord Bulkeley</persName>'s <pb n="7v"/>
                    <fw>f. 7v</fw> grounds which gave us a sight of many additional beauties –
                        <lb/>23<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>: <persName ref="pe0323">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Panton</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe1592">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: <unclear>Mander</unclear></persName>
                    returned from <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName>. <lb/>24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>: the little girls bathed - <lb/>25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>: We dined at <persName ref="pe1232">Lord
                        Bulkeley</persName>'s publick day, he has one every week - this was a visit
                    perfectly novel to me, there were at least fifty people about an equal <pb n="8r"/>
                    <fw>f. 8r</fw> number of gentlemen &amp; ladies, <del>all</del><add place="above">most of</add> the ladies remarkably well dressed – The view
                    from <placeName ref="pl1964">Baron hill</placeName> is the most striking I ever
                    saw, the house, which is an excellent one, as far as I saw, &amp; has many noble
                    rooms, stands upon an eminence above the sea. <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName> is situated at the bottom of an extensive lawn close
                    to the shore &amp; its <placeName ref="pl1968">old castle</placeName>
                    <pb n="8v"/>
                    <fw>f. 8v</fw> is a noble object, the sea stretches out on one hand as far as
                    the eye extends, opposite, &amp; on the other side, the lofty <placeName ref="pl1672">Carnarvonshire</placeName> mountains bound the prospect, the
                    bases of them are finely cultivated, the promontory of <placeName ref="pl1958">Orms head</placeName> wherever it is seen is a noble sight, it here appears
                    an island. <persName ref="pe1231">Lady Bulkley</persName> has the pret- <pb n="9r"/>
                    <fw>f. 9r</fw> tiest green house I ever saw where she often sits &amp; works.
                    the walls of it are cover’d with Geraniums, trailled to them like fruit trees,
                    they are now in full blossom – <lb/>27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>: We dined
                    at <persName ref="pe1230">Lord Uxbridge</persName>'s publick day, who likewise
                    gives one every week. Here were about 30 people dined – these visits look
                    something like <pb n="9v"/>
                    <fw>f. 9v</fw> what I should conceive of the court of some petty Prince. we were
                    shewn into the drawing room, presented to the <persName ref="pe1230">Lord</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe1595">Lady</persName> of the house
                    &amp; then seated in a circle, after dinner (which was here an excellent one,
                    much otherwise at <persName ref="pe1232">Lord Bulkley</persName>'s), we broke
                    into parties, all form ceased, we walk’d about &amp; enjoyed the delightful
                    scenery <pb n="10r"/>
                    <fw>f. 10r</fw> with which these places abound – we met with extraordinary
                    civility in both places – <placeName ref="pl1965">Plas Newydd</placeName> is an
                    admirable house, the rooms very noble – the view from it is not so grand as from
                        <persName ref="pe1232">Lord Bulkleys</persName>. Had I not, however, seen
                        <placeName ref="pl1964">Baron Hill</placeName> first I should have called
                        <add place="above">it</add> very grand, it is situated on the banks of the
                        <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai</placeName>, this beautiful arm of the <pb n="10v"/>
                    <fw>f. 10v</fw> sea is seen for a great length of way from the house &amp; is at
                    last lost among the mountains, <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName> is
                    here a very fine object; the woods are very fine &amp; feather down to the
                    water; among the woods are two fine Cromlechs<note type="editorial">Neolithic
                        burial chambers in the grounds of Plas Newydd; see <ref target="http://www.coflein.gov.uk/en/site/93829/details/plas-newydd-burial-chamber.">here</ref></note> - In the woods here &amp; at <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName> are numbers of fine old oaks. I do not recollect
                    seeing many oaks in any <pb n="11r"/>
                    <fw>f. 11r</fw> other parts of the island I have seen – <lb/>28<hi rend="superscript">th:</hi> We rode to <placeName ref="pl1966">Llandyfnan</placeName>, <persName ref="pe1596">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: Lewis</persName>'s, nothing remarkable – In all our rides &amp;
                    walks fine views of the <placeName ref="pl1672">Carnarvonshire</placeName>
                    mountains, the top of <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName> seldom clear –
                    The little girls continue bathing which they like much – <persName ref="pe1219">Josepha</persName> quite recovered – which makes us very thankful – <pb n="11v"/>
                    <fw>f. 11v</fw> 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>: took a walk up <placeName ref="pl1961">Llwydiart</placeName> - an extensive view from it – see the
                        <add place="above">sea</add> about three parts round us – see <placeName ref="pl1018">Holyhead mountain</placeName> from it &amp; indeed from many
                    other places, for there are few hills in <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName> &amp; none very high - We are most conveniently &amp;
                    comfortably lodged here &amp; our entertainment is in all respects very good.
                        <persName ref="pe0226">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Panton</persName> has
                    the kindness <pb n="12r"/>
                    <fw>f. 12r</fw> to let the young folks breakfast dine &amp; sup in his study
                    except <persName ref="pe1218">Panton</persName>, who dines with us, they have
                    the free range of three large Parlours the Study &amp; the Hall &amp; enjoy
                    themselves very much – <lb/>30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>: We took a ride
                    upon the sands at <placeName ref="pl1962">Redwharf</placeName> which are
                    remarkably safe. It blew as hurricane last night – I never heard such wind. the
                    family said it <pb n="12v"/>
                    <fw>f. 12v</fw> is not once in half a year that there is such a storm – it
                    subsided this morning &amp; it being low water we rode very far on the sands,
                    the waves continued in great agitation, I never was more delighted. we rode till
                    we almost touched the waves, they appeared like green mountains with the white
                    foam dancing on their summits – <pb n="13r"/>
                    <fw>f. 13r</fw> my little horse (for <persName ref="pe0923">my B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>:</persName> had the goodness to bring him for
                    me) canter’d most pleasantly, &amp; was not at all startled – The seagulls &amp;
                    cormorants were walking about quite tame – <lb/>31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>: We made a most pleasant excursion to the <placeName ref="pl1719">Parys
                            <add place="above">copper</add> mine</placeName> &amp; the port of
                        <placeName ref="pl1967">Amlwch</placeName>, which is very near the mine – As
                    I am not used to see mines, I cannot <pb n="13v"/>
                    <fw>f. 13v</fw> be so sensible of the wonders of this as I otherwise should be,
                    but from all I hear, it is the most wonderful in the world. there is no
                    underground work which, I believe is one of its extraordinary properties. not so
                    much as a blade of grass is to be seen near it – The Port of <placeName ref="pl1967">Amlwch</placeName> I was quite charmed with &amp; quite
                    unwilling to <pb n="14r"/>
                    <fw>f. 14r</fw> leave. It was well I saw the mine first or I should scarcely
                    have quitted it in time to see anything else – we went on board a sloop &amp;
                    had a very hearty reception from the captain, who knew <persName ref="pe1232 pe1226">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: Bulkley
                        Panton</persName> very well – whilst we were there three ships passed very
                    near in full sail, which is a sight that pleases me much – <pb n="14v"/>
                    <fw>f. 14v</fw> Sep<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>: rode towards <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName>-
                        <lb/>5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>: rode to <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName> through the grounds at <placeName ref="pl1964">Baron
                        hill</placeName> &amp; by <placeName ref="pl1968">Beaumaris
                        castle</placeName> - the sea comes close up to the town, which is like all
                    the Welch towns I have seen, a very poor one, at the custom house are many small
                    vessels – <lb/>6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>: Went to a ball at <placeName ref="pl1965">Plas Newydd</placeName>. it was con- <pb n="15r"/>
                    <fw>f. 15r</fw> ducted most capitally, there was a magnificent supper – about
                    thirty couples danced – a pleasant circumstance attends welch balls, the
                    gentlemen are so fond of dancing that I believe no lady sits still but from
                    their own choice – after supper, before the gentlemen joined us, six ladies
                    danced Scotch reels in two sets, very prettily – We <pb n="15v"/>
                    <fw>f. 15v</fw> were very late before we returned – <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName> affords very little fruit, at <persName ref="pe1230">Lord Uxbridge</persName>'s was great plenty brought from <placeName ref="pl1367">Staffordshire</placeName> - <persName ref="pe0226">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: Panton</persName> has five wall’d gardens
                    &amp; no fruit – <lb/>8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>: rode to <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName> through the grounds at <placeName ref="pl1964">Baron hill</placeName>, saw <persName ref="pe1232">Lord
                        Bulkleys</persName> Hawks sent off. He is training them <pb n="16r"/>
                    <fw>f. 16r</fw> to revive the diversion of Hawking – as we were riding through
                    the grounds <persName ref="pe1230">Lord Uxbridge</persName> passed in his
                        cutter.<note type="editorial">Small to medium-sized sailing boat built for
                        speed.</note>
                    <persName ref="pe1232">Lord Bulkley</persName> makes a point of saluting him on
                    these occasions from a small fort that he has in his grounds, we happened to be
                    near, but our horses stood better than I expected – these two lords are here
                    little <pb n="16v"/>
                    <fw>f. 16v</fw> monarchs. I think <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName>
                    is the most dependent place I ever saw – <persName ref="pe1230">Lord
                        Uxbridge</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe1232">Lord Bulkley</persName>
                    have now agreed to divide the county between them – they use their interest to
                    confer obligations upon every family of any consequence in the island, it is
                    wonderful by acting together, how many appointments they have procured <pb n="17r"/>
                    <fw>f. 17r</fw> for the gentlemen’s sons. I lament when I see gentlemen of
                    independent fortune (which is often the case) accept of these things, but so it
                    is here, almost all are under obligations to them, &amp; do them homage on their
                    court days, as I think their publick dinners may be called – <lb/>9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>: Left <placeName ref="pl1960">Plasgwyn</placeName>, it being Sunday we went first <pb n="17v"/>
                    <fw>f. 17v</fw> to church – the latter part of the time we spent there <persName ref="pe1605">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>: Parry</persName> had left it
                    &amp; <persName ref="pe0226">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName>: &amp;
                        <persName ref="pe1226">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>: Panton</persName>
                    arrived, we left them there. The face of the county is very unlike what I had
                    been used to, the enclosures are mostly mounds of earth, but so much overgrown
                    with grass, fern, brambles &amp;c that it has the effect of hedges <pb n="18r"/>
                    <fw>f. 18r</fw> at a distance – some enclosures are made with stone. there is
                    scarcely a tree to be seen except about the gentlemens houses, which have all
                    some wood about them – the general view is, these enclosures with spots of trees
                    which mark the gentlemens houses – the ground is fruitful yet very near the
                    rock, which starts out in some part <pb n="18v"/>
                    <fw>f. 18v</fw> of most of the fields – the sea views are very fine, &amp; the
                        <placeName ref="pl1672">Carnarvonshire</placeName> mountains are fine
                    features in their prospect – there is not a gentlemans house on the island more
                    than four mile from the sea, &amp; most are much nearer – the county is popular,
                    &amp; there are a great many gentlemans families who visit much together. I
                    never <pb n="19r"/>
                    <fw>f. 19r</fw> was anywhere where domestic news travelled so quick it reminded
                    me of the voyages to the south seas,<note type="editorial">Voyages to the South
                        Seas – Captain James Cook led three expeditions to the South Pacific between
                        1768 and 1779, in search of new geographical and scientific knowledge. For
                        an account of Cook’s voyages, and examples of the illustrations made by some
                        of the naturalists and artists who took part in them, see <ref type="http" target="http://www.artstor.org/collection/cooks-voyages-south-seas">here</ref>.</note> where one finds, in the society &amp; friendly
                    islands in particular, what was done in one place was soon known all over the
                    island – <persName ref="pe1227">Miss Panton</persName> crossed the ferry with us
                    dined with us at <placeName ref="pl1969">Jackson’s (the Inn)</placeName> &amp;
                    parted with us <pb n="19v"/>
                    <fw>f. 19v</fw> after dinner – beautiful view down the river from hence – called
                    upon <persName ref="pe1605">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>:
                            <unclear>P.</unclear> Parry</persName> of <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName> - her house very near the sea – noble view on the road
                    from the ferry – mountains in front – <placeName ref="pl1958">Orms
                        head</placeName> to the left appearing insulated, <placeName ref="pl1959">Puffin island</placeName> - from <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName>
                    - Sea with <placeName ref="pl1959">Puffin island</placeName> point of <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName> - <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName> fair <pb n="20r"/>
                    <fw>f. 20r</fw> today, the street quite crowded the dress of the woman almost
                    universally, long blue cloth cloaks &amp; beaver hats - as soon as we pass the
                    Town see the vessels at anchor, <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName>,
                        <placeName ref="pl1959">Puffin island</placeName>
                    <placeName ref="pl1958">Orms head</placeName>, mountains - Pass <add place="above">on the left</add>
                    <placeName ref="pl1970">Lime grove</placeName> a beautiful small villa of
                        <persName ref="pe1234">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: Wyatt</persName>
                    (brother to <persName ref="pe1236">the architect</persName>) steward to
                        <persName ref="pe0420">Lord Penrhyn</persName> - Grand view of <pb n="20v"/>
                    <fw>f. 20v</fw> mountains finely cultivated at bottom – <placeName ref="pl1183">Snowdon</placeName> just opposite, cloud capt – country finely cultivated –
                    to the left <placeName ref="pl1650">Lord Penrhyn’s</placeName> at some distance
                    from the road it appears very handsome – Pass close to the road <add place="above">on the left</add> the <placeName ref="pl1971">church of
                        Llandegai</placeName>, it is new &amp; very neat in form of a cross – just
                    beginning to build a new bridge over <pb n="21r"/>
                    <fw>f. 21r</fw> the <placeName ref="pl2415">Ogwen</placeName> - Fine sea view to
                    the left. long shore of <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1959">Puffin
                        island</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1958">Orms head</placeName>,
                        <placeName ref="pl1338">Penmaen mawr</placeName> - Noble terrace to
                        <placeName ref="pl1595">Aber</placeName>, the same fine view continues to
                    the left, fine mountains in front &amp; to the right – evening rains –
                        <placeName ref="pl1595">Aber</placeName> - the houses white - it is a very
                    pretty object from <pb n="21v"/>
                    <fw>f. 21v</fw>
                    <placeName ref="pl1964">Baron hill</placeName>, drink tea at the Inn - The
                    evening clears – noble terrace continues &amp; the same delightful views
                    continue towards <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName> &amp; in only
                    varying as we turn, a beautiful purple tinge upon the prospect – Open Sea, of a
                    beautiful green – the white waves dancing – Pass <placeName ref="pl1972">Bryn y
                        Neuadd</placeName> - Reach <placeName ref="pl1338">Penmaen mawr</placeName>,
                    the world <pb n="22r"/>
                    <fw>f. 22r</fw> of waters beautiful, the sea very green – the waves gently
                    dashing against the shore beneath the lofty promontory we are going over – the
                    view takes in <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1959">Puffin island</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1958">Orms
                        head</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl2400">Sychnant</placeName> - the waves
                    roll finely &amp; break against the shore – Leave the sea more to the left &amp;
                    begin to ascent <placeName ref="pl2400">Sych- <pb n="22v"/>
                        <fw>f. 22v</fw> nant</placeName>, we are surrounded by rocky mountains with
                    a small fertile valley between – Over <placeName ref="pl2400">Sychnant</placeName> lofty barren rocky mountains surround us – The sky was
                    stormy, it seemed to promise much worse weather than we now experienced, for the
                    evening was solemnly fine – when over <placeName ref="pl2400">Sychnant</placeName> there is a fine <pb n="23r"/>
                    <fw>f. 23r</fw> open towards <placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName> - See
                    the noble <placeName ref="pl1530">castle</placeName>, the <placeName ref="pl2384">river</placeName> &amp; a beautiful wooded eminence – Reach
                        <placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName> - <lb/>10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>: Morning very stormy, the sea very rough, we were to cross the
                    Ferry having promised <persName ref="pe0232">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>:
                        Pennant</persName> to make <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName> in
                    our way home. The chaise &amp; horses went over first, they had been</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>
                    <pb n="1v"/>
                    <fw>f. 1v</fw> gone an hour when we set out, yet they had not reach’d the
                    opposite shore, the waves beat violently against the chaise – As none of <add place="above">us</add> except <persName ref="pe0923">my Brother</persName>
                    had been at all used to the water we had no apprehension of danger &amp; I was
                    eager to go, as I wish’d to know what a rough sea was, <persName ref="pe0923">my
                            B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.</persName> proposed waiting till the
                    next <pb n="2r"/>
                    <fw>f. 2r</fw> day but we were told that there was no chance of its being any
                    better for many days as an equinoxial (their phrase) had come down the night
                    before &amp; wou’d continue to blow some days – he then wish’d to avoid the
                    ferry by going round over the hills, but was informed the roads were impractical
                    even with four horses – at <pb n="2v"/>
                    <fw>f. 2v</fw> length we got into the boat – the master of the Inn came with us
                    to direct the boatmen to keep the boat right to the waves, for we afterwards
                    learnt had the waves broke against the side of the boat they probably would have
                    come in, &amp; had we shipped two or three of these waves they wou’d have sunk
                    us – the wind was violent <pb n="3r"/>
                    <fw>f. 3r</fw> men &amp; women tied their hats on – the view was fine – from
                        <placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName> side <placeName ref="pl1973">Marle</placeName>, &amp; <placeName ref="pl1974">Bodscallen</placeName> the
                    latter on an eminence above <placeName ref="pl1973">Marle</placeName>, rises
                    among woods – as we row from <placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName>, its
                    noble <placeName ref="pl1530">Castle</placeName> rising at the water’s edge, the
                    walls &amp; round towers running along the shore, the roughness of the sea – all
                    was striking. When the boat came to <pb n="3v"/>
                    <fw>f. 3v</fw> the waves broke over us – it was high tide &amp; about a mile
                    over – as we rise on the opposite shore the view of <placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName> back’d by wood &amp; mountains is inexpressively grand.
                    In a short time we turn to the left, leave these fine views, go through a pretty
                    valley between hills – on the left rocky &amp; prettily wooded – <pb n="4r"/>
                    <fw>f. 4r</fw> Pass a pretty brick house to the right, fine open sea to the left
                    – Pass a small house on the shore with fir plantations – Go along a noble
                    terrace – fine open sea – walk up a steep, look back, the hills above <placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName> appearing beyond <placeName ref="pl1958">Orms head</placeName> - pass through a small village – pass at some little
                        <pb n="4r"/>
                    <fw>f. 4r</fw> distance a gentlemans seat close to the shore, <placeName ref="pl1975">Gwrych</placeName>, formerly belonging to a friend &amp; school
                    fellow of <persName ref="pe0923">my B<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi></persName>:
                        <persName ref="pe1235">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: Lloyd</persName> - by
                    his death it pass’d to <persName ref="pe1041">his sister</persName> married to
                        <persName ref="pe1040">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: Hesketh</persName> -
                    Sea view but less grand that what we have seen from the want of the fine lofty
                    mountains – See <placeName ref="pl1203">Abergelly</placeName> before us – Wind
                    continues <pb n="5r"/>
                    <fw>f. 5r</fw> very high, the waves break nobly – See only one vessel, a brig –
                    tost about &amp; seems to remain almost in the same place – Sun breaks out &amp;
                    throws a fine radiance over the waves. Pass through <placeName ref="pl1203">Abergelly</placeName> - look at the <placeName ref="pl2019">church</placeName>, it is large, from the church yard a fine view of open
                    sea &amp; <placeName ref="pl1958">Orms Head</placeName> - The <pb n="5v"/>
                    <fw>f. 5v</fw> road farther distant from the sea, but still fine views of it,
                    pleasing shore – A cultivated county opens before us – fine view of <placeName ref="pl1978">Rhuddlan</placeName> - Pass through a village –Fine view of
                        <placeName ref="pl1371">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>: Asaph</placeName> -
                    were we going the other way the sea wou’d be finer – Pass <placeName ref="pl1976">Kimmel</placeName> a fine park &amp; magnificent house, which
                        <pb n="6r"/>
                    <fw>f. 6r</fw> must enjoy a charming land &amp; sea prospect – See a good house
                    near the sea – <placeName ref="pl1371">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>:
                        Asaph</placeName>, situated in a delightful cultivated country, on an
                    eminence, appears very fine before us, the contrast is so great to the views we
                    have lately seen, that I am ready to think I never saw so cultivated <pb n="6v"/>
                    <fw>f. 6v</fw> a scene. Approach <placeName ref="pl1371">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>: Asaph</placeName> go over rather a pretty <placeName ref="pl1977">bridge</placeName> of five low wide arches – reach the
                        <placeName ref="pl2416">Inn</placeName> which is exactly opposite the
                        <placeName ref="pl1561">cathedral</placeName> - fine trees <add place="above">in</add> its yard – the <placeName ref="pl1561">Cathedral</placeName> small, but the choir has lately been fitted up in a
                    very good stile by <persName ref="pe1236">Wyatt</persName> - the cieling very
                    neat. the tabernacle work good <pb n="7r"/>
                    <fw>f. 7r</fw> painted with oker - a small Organ – As we came out a <persName ref="pe1237">Lady</persName> hasten’d to meet us &amp; said, as we appeared
                    to be looking about us, she would, if we pleased, shew us the Palace – She
                    proved to be <persName ref="pe1237">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>:
                        Bagott</persName>, the <persName ref="pe0365">bishop</persName>'s lady. The
                        <persName ref="pe0365">bishop</persName> is building part of the palace
                    quite new &amp; altering &amp; fitting up the old <pb n="7v"/>
                    <fw>f. 7v</fw> part – the front is entirely new &amp; of a beautiful stone, it
                    will be an excellent house – her civility was beyond anything I ever experienced
                    from a stranger – I had some years before seen her at <unclear>Acton
                        Barnet</unclear>, &amp; <persName ref="pe0923">my Brother</persName> had
                    formerly known her at <placeName ref="pl1347">Oxford</placeName>, when we had
                        <unclear>walked</unclear> about. She enquired the names <pb n="8r"/>
                    <fw>f. 8r</fw> of the party she was with. when she heard it, she mentioned to
                    have known a young man of that name formerly at <placeName ref="pl1347">Oxford</placeName> - <persName ref="pe0923">my B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName>: &amp; she recognised each other – she pressed us to
                    dine with her &amp; take their commons, for she said whilst the palace was
                    building they had their dinner from an Inn - We <pb n="8v"/>
                    <fw>f. 8v</fw> had however bespoken our dinner &amp; with many thanks took our
                    leave – she sent us a basket of fine fruit – The situation of the palace is snug
                    &amp; pretty – We are now in the <placeName ref="pl1443">Vale of
                        Clwyd</placeName>, a fine cultivated country – get out to walk, look back
                    over the vale, the view fine, Ruddlan marsh - <placeName ref="pl1978">Ruddlan
                        castle</placeName>, <pb n="9r"/>
                    <fw>f. 9r</fw> the open sea beyond it, <placeName ref="pl1958">Orms
                        head</placeName>, distant view of the <placeName ref="pl1672">Carnarvonshire</placeName> mountains - Wide common rather dreary – Evening
                    very rainy, attemp to go a nearer road – find it only fit for a horse, after
                    some difficulty reach <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName> - Only
                        <persName ref="pe0232">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName>: &amp;
                        <persName ref="pe0238">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>Pennant</persName>:
                    &amp; <persName ref="pe0235">Miss Sarah</persName> at home - <pb n="9v"/>
                    <fw>f. 9v</fw> 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>: Leave <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>, a most charming spot, where we spent some very
                    pleasant days – our time did not permit us to see nearly all the numberless
                    drawings, &amp; curiosities that <persName ref="pe0232">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: Pennant</persName> has collected, yet we were never idle, &amp;
                    were highly entertained – the house is of stone, &amp; a very good &amp;
                    comfortable <pb n="10r"/>
                    <fw>f. 10r</fw> family residence. The grounds are very fine about it, a
                    beautiful lawn like valley with fine woods on each hand – In <del>whom</del><add place="above">one</add> a romantic dell, with a brook, at one time quite
                    obscured by trees, at another breaking through them, runs at the bottom, the
                    other rises in an eminence in which there are many <pb n="10v"/>
                    <fw>f. 10v</fw> seats which command fine views, see the sea from all of them,
                    but, except at high tide, it is a great part sand – <persName ref="pe0232">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: Pennant</persName> has a person of the name
                    of <persName ref="pe1607">Williams</persName> to dine at his house every day, he
                    has continued it for 30 years – he is a very inoffensive character, rather weak
                    &amp; odd. <persName ref="pe0232">Mr Pennant</persName> seems <pb n="11r"/>
                    <fw>f. 11r</fw> much diverted with him – In <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> the custom of giving toasts whilst the Ladies stay
                    continues, <persName ref="pe0232">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>:
                        Pennant</persName>, whilst we were there, omitted it, <persName ref="pe1607">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: Williams</persName> did not seem to
                    like it, "<persName ref="pe0232">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>:
                        Pennant</persName>, said he, You forget all your friends” – It struck <add place="above">me</add> as the best reason I ever heard for giving daily
                    toasts, there is something rather pretty <pb n="11v"/>
                    <fw>f. 11v</fw> in the idea of remembering our friends at meals – Here our three
                    little people sat for their pictures to <persName ref="pe0014">Moses
                        Griffith</persName> a very ingenious &amp; truly modest man, <persName ref="pe0232">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: Pennants</persName> Artist - In
                    the road from <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1251">Holywell</placeName> we see the sea almost the whole way, the
                    estuary of the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName>, &amp; the opposite
                        <placeName ref="pl1362">Cheshire</placeName> shore, as we approach
                        <placeName ref="pl1251">Holywell</placeName>
                    <pb n="12r"/>
                    <fw>f. 12r</fw> to the left are fine dells &amp; woods with the large buildings
                    for the cotton works among them – <placeName ref="pl1251">Holywell</placeName>
                    is a wide street but not long. we called upon <persName ref="pe0226">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: Panton</persName> who has a good house here,
                    where he resides two or three months in the spring, he left <placeName ref="pl1960">Plasgwyn</placeName> a few days before us, his mining business
                    call’d him into <placeName ref="pl0702">Flintshire</placeName>
                    <pb n="12v"/>
                    <fw>f. 12v</fw> we walked to see the <placeName ref="pl1979">celebrated
                        well</placeName>, one of the finest springs in the kingdom &amp; to which
                        <placeName ref="pl1251">Holywell</placeName> owes its increasing trade as
                    numerous cotton manufactories are erected upon it, as well as many mills for
                    various purposes<note type="editorial">For an overview of industrial
                        developments in Wales in this period, particularly as recorded in
                        topographical art, see Mary-Ann Constantine, ‘John Hassell, Wales and the
                        “industrial picturesque”' <ref type="http" target="https://www.bl.uk/picturing-places/articles/john-hassell-wales-and-the-industrial-picturesque">here</ref></note> - Set out again – view, the estuary of the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1391">Parkgate</placeName>
                    on the opposite shore, pass a pretty white house <pb n="13r"/>
                    <fw>f. 13r</fw> to the right – soon after another – See Flint <placeName ref="pl1289">Town</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl2418">Castle</placeName> on the sands, look over a flat but well cultivated
                    country – See <placeName ref="pl0002">Chester</placeName> situated on the
                        <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1391">Parkgate</placeName> - the whole bounded by the distant <placeName ref="pl1362">Cheshire</placeName> hills - magnificent
                        <unclear>Stables</unclear> to the right – Pass through a village – pretty
                    church – See vessels at anchor at <placeName ref="pl1289">Flint</placeName> -
                    Pass some fine <pb n="13v"/>
                    <fw>f. 13v</fw> woods – Go through <placeName ref="pl0703">Northop</placeName>,
                    good tower to the <placeName ref="pl1980">church</placeName> - from hence lose
                    sight of the sea – The first view of <placeName ref="pl1857">Mold</placeName>
                    striking – handsome tower to the <placeName ref="pl2419">church</placeName>,
                    situated in a fine country, see many gentlemens houses about it – A large
                    building erecting for a cotton manufactory<note type="editorial">Edward Pugh
                        describes this five-storey building as a ‘handsome and stupendous cotton
                        factory, close to the town … lighted by 220 windows; and is a useful
                        neighbour to Mold as it employs a great number of the poor.’ <hi rend="italic">See Cambria
                        Depicta: A Tour Through North Wales</hi> (London: E. Williams, 1816), pp.
                        345-6.</note> - Set out again from <placeName ref="pl1857">Mold</placeName>,
                    fine wooded <pb n="14r"/>
                    <fw>f. 14r</fw> country to the right, see three gentlemens seats at one view,
                    Tower &amp; the two <placeName ref="pl1981">Leeswoods</placeName>, <note type="editorial">For an overview of the complex history of the Leeswood
                        estate, see <ref type="http" target="https://archiveshub.jisc.ac.uk/search/archives/9b70ab84-4f70-3ce1-b114-c92b61fa51af">here</ref></note> one belonging to <persName ref="pe1608">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: <unclear>Waining</unclear></persName>, the
                    other <persName ref="pe0496">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: Eyton</persName> -
                    Pass another gentlemans seat to the right – catch a peep at <add place="above">the ruin of</add>
                    <placeName ref="pl1982">Caergwrle castle</placeName>, pass a church to the right
                    – view of <placeName ref="pl1982">Caergwrle castle</placeName> - pass a village,
                    a bridge <pb n="14v"/>
                    <fw>f. 14v</fw> &amp; a mill – <placeName ref="pl1265">Hope</placeName> to the
                    left – come to a part of the road shaded by a row of trees on each side – Pass
                    the fine woods &amp; house of <persName ref="pe1238">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: Humberston</persName> - The approach to <placeName ref="pl0792">Wrexham</placeName> flat – the road from <placeName ref="pl1857">Mold</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0792">Wrexham</placeName> in general
                    flat, except about <placeName ref="pl1982">Caergwrle</placeName> - appeared very
                    tame – The tower of <pb n="15r"/>
                    <fw>f. 15r</fw>
                    <placeName ref="pl1983">Wrexham Church</placeName> wonderfully rich &amp;
                    beautiful gothic work – The town the best I’ve seen in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> many good houses in &amp; near it – a very gay &amp;
                    hospitable neighbourhood – the diversion of Archery much the fashion. Slept at
                    the Inn <add place="above">14th</add> breakfast at <persName ref="pe0496">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: Eyton</persName>'s who at present, till he
                    has finished his alteration at <placeName ref="pl1981">Leeswood</placeName>
                    <pb n="15v"/>
                    <fw>f. 15v</fw> resides at his house called <placeName ref="pl2421">the
                        mount</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl0792">Wrexham</placeName>, ascend a
                    number of steps to it – view from the drawing room quite
                        <unclear>country</unclear> - <persName ref="pe0496">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName>: &amp; <persName ref="pe0497">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>: Eyton</persName> were going today to a Bow meeting,<note type="editorial">For contemporary illustrations of bow meetings at Erddig
                        Hall and Gwersyllt Park, see <ref type="http" target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:The_meeting_of_the_Royal_British_Bowmen_in_the_grounds_of_Erthig,_Denbighshire.jpeg">here</ref> and <ref type="http" target="http://www.bsat.co.uk/image_collections/photo_more?id=181">here</ref></note> she was in her uniform, green jacket <add place="above">&amp; pettegoat</add> trimmed in Vandyck points with buff,
                    beaver hat &amp; feather with a device in Silver placed in front emblema- <pb n="16r"/>
                    <fw>f. 16r</fw> tical of the diversion, <persName ref="pe0496">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: Eyton</persName> wore a black ribbon under
                    his coat, with the same device, but being a Clergyman, he decently buttoned it
                    up – Pass <placeName ref="pl1244">Erthig</placeName> to the left fine stone
                    house with woods – Pass a pretty looking irregular house on the right – Go
                    through <placeName ref="pl1199">Rhiwabon</placeName>, alighted &amp; were <pb n="16v"/>
                    <fw>f. 16v</fw> shewn the church by our old acquaintance <persName ref="pe1609">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: Denman</persName>, it is very handsome,
                    a beautiful monument in it to the memory of the last <persName ref="pe1239">S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: Watkin William’s first Lady</persName>,<note type="editorial">For an image of this monument, to Lady Henrietta Williams
                        Wynn, see <ref type="http" target="http://www.artandarchitecture.org.uk/images/conway/06a5177a.html">here</ref></note> it is a statue of her, here is an Organ, &amp; a
                    beautiful font, presented by the old <persName ref="pe0326">S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: W. W.</persName> on the christening of his
                        <persName ref="pe0941">son</persName> - Proceed, handsome stone gateway to
                    the <pb n="17r"/>
                    <fw>f. 17r</fw> left leading to <placeName ref="pl0761">Wynnstay</placeName> -
                    see <placeName ref="pl0761">Wynnstay</placeName>, fine woods - see <placeName ref="pl1984">Plas Maddock</placeName> to the right – fine distant view of
                        <placeName ref="pl1256">Chirk Castle</placeName>, go over the new <placeName ref="pl2422">bridge</placeName> on the Dee - steep down to it &amp; up again
                    fine wooded banks – fine view to the right into the <placeName ref="pl0793">Vale
                        of Llangollen</placeName> - <placeName ref="pl0794">Castle Dinas
                        Bran</placeName> - <placeName ref="pl2018">Trevor</placeName> to the right –
                    fine view of <placeName ref="pl1256">Chirk Castle</placeName> &amp; woods <pb n="17v"/>
                    <fw>f. 17v</fw> to the right – <placeName ref="pl2423">Chirk bridge</placeName>
                    pretty rocky river, trees feather to the water – pretty little valley – pass a
                    brick house to the right fine woods – dine at <placeName ref="pl1260">Oswestry</placeName> - very rainy evening – drink tea at <placeName ref="pl0740">Shrewsbury</placeName>, reach <placeName ref="pl1695">Longnor</placeName> - After a most agreeable &amp; prosperous excursion,
                    &amp; have the happiness of returning <pb n="18r"/>
                    <fw>f. 18r</fw> all well – We have reason to be very thankful – Just before we
                    left <placeName ref="pl1960">Plasgwyn</placeName> we heard of the death of
                        <persName ref="pe1119">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: Falconer</persName> -
                    he died on the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>: And on coming home <persName ref="pe0923">my B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>:</persName> rec<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> a letter from <persName ref="pe1530">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>: Falconer</persName> the D<hi rend="superscript">r's</hi>: wife, informing him of it – He was a man of
                    great learning, very various &amp; extensive <pb n="18v"/>
                    <fw>f. 18v</fw> reading &amp; possessed a most retentive memory – He was every
                    ready to communicate his knowledge to those who were desirous of it – To the
                    young he was a most instructive companion, he loved their company &amp; if they
                    were teacable, he was ready to improve them – His life had been much clouded by
                    a dreadful nervous dis- <pb n="19r"/>
                    <fw>f. 19r</fw> order that seized him the day before he was to have been called
                    to the bar – for two years he thought his life in danger. In some degree he
                    recovered but was constantly afflicted with nervous complaints. The spasms in
                    his stomach were daily so violent as to oblige him to have recourse to Brandy
                    &amp; Ginger in large quantities; his <pb n="19v"/>
                    <fw>f. 19v</fw> constitution must have been originally very strong, for through
                    all these complaints &amp; the remedy pain obliged him to fly to, he lived to
                    the age of fifty nine. He was quite worn out, his memory lately failed him, his
                    head was confused, he was <unclear>comotous</unclear>, &amp; in the state he had
                    for some time been in, death was a happy release – He had studied the Scriptures
                        <pb n="20r"/>
                    <fw>f. 20r</fw> much, was very pious, &amp; firmly attached to the church of
                    England; he composed some Sacramental mediations which he printed to give to his
                    friends but did not publish. For many years past he had been engaged in a new
                    edition of <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0252">Strabo</title></bibl>,
                    which is to be printed at the Clarendon press,<note type="editorial">The edition
                        of Strabo mentioned by Plymley was completed by Falconer’s nephew, Rev.
                        Thomas Falconer (1772-1839); the final volume of this work was published in
                        Oxford in 1807.</note> he did not live to see it come <pb n="20v"/>
                    <fw>f. 20v</fw> out – His friends were very numerous, &amp; he was attached to
                    them with great tenderness, he never loved to take leave of them &amp; always
                    avoided that ceremony – When <persName ref="pe0923">my Brother</persName> was at
                        <placeName ref="pl2424">Chester School</placeName>, <persName ref="pe1119">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: Falconer</persName> first saw &amp; was
                    pleased with him, he had him much with him, Sundays &amp; Holydays, he seldom
                    missed, &amp; he <unclear>confined</unclear> his attachment invariably – <pb n="21r"/>
                    <fw>f. 21r</fw> He generally passed some time every year at <placeName ref="pl1696">my Fathers</placeName>, &amp; when <persName ref="pe1070">my
                        Father</persName> left <placeName ref="pl1696">Longnor</placeName> at
                        <placeName ref="pl2425">my Brothers</placeName>; he had, I believe, a
                    sincere regard for all our family – He was always ready to converse &amp; told a
                    story admirably – Some thought him too fond of talking, I loved to hear him; but
                    latterly, I will confess, he degenerated sometimes so <pb n="21v"/>
                    <fw>f. 21v</fw> much into prattle that, if I could have chosen, none should have
                    heard him but those who knew how to respect his many estimable qualities, &amp;
                    do pity those disorders that had so much hurt him, unfortunately he was not
                    select in his acquaintance – In politicks he was of violent high church
                    principles &amp; was much bigoted <pb n="22r"/>
                    <fw>f. 22r</fw> to them, it was, therefore, to us often unpleasant to hear him
                    on this subject – In reading poetry he had a solemn peculiar cadence, that when
                    I was a little accustomed to I thought agreeable – he read Scripture admirably,
                    I never was more struck then with his reading the 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>: chapter of Job – a favourite chapter with him – He was very
                    excellent in reading plays, <pb n="22v"/>
                    <fw>f. 22v</fw> both in the solemn scenes of Tragedy &amp; in the humourous ones
                    of Comedy, in the last he was truly laugable – He had a good taste in paintings
                    &amp; drawings &amp; had a large collection of prints; music he did not love,
                    yet could talk of it very well – His features were strong &amp; plain, he had
                    the look of a foreigner &amp; a gentleman – He left his fortune, which was such
                    as enabled him to live in elegance &amp; hospi- <pb n="23r"/>
                    <fw>f. 23r</fw> tality, to <persName ref="pe0876">his<add place="above">X</add><note type="authorial">I believe I was misinformed, it was to
                            his Brother in the first instance –</note> nephew, his Brothers
                        son</persName>, now at <placeName ref="pl1347">Oxford</placeName>,
                        <del>&amp; of</del> whose education he had always been at the expence of –
                    He left many small legacies – 20£ was the highest except to <persName ref="pe0923">my Brother</persName> who is distinguished by 50£–</p>
                <p>I was willing to say this much of a man whom I highly respected, &amp; to whose
                    various communications I am much obliged – <pb n="23v"/>
                    <fw>f. 23v</fw> He once, singularly enough, advised me never to speak of
                    religion to a clergyman, he pressed it much, make it a rule, said he – I suppose
                    this much be understood with some limitations, &amp; perhaps principally meant
                    never to begin the subject with them – So far I think is perfectly right – </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>