<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0011">
    <teiHeader type="w">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Catherine Hutton’s Tour of Wales: 1796
                    <date>1796</date>
                </title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Edited with an introduction by Mary-Ann Constantine</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                        <idno>MS 19079C</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <pb n="1"/>
                <p>Letter 1 <note type="editorial">Published in the Monthly Magazine (June, 1815),
                        410-11.</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p style="right"><placeName ref="pl1515">Mallwyd</placeName>, July 26 1796.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>My Dear Brother<note type="editorial">Written on a pasted-in strip of paper. This
                        first page has been considerably edited by pasting in order to rewrite or
                        remove phrases. It is not now possible to recover the earlier phrasing. The
                        transcription indicates these erased sections thus: [------], and words
                        crossed out on the page thus: [<del>xxxx</del>]</note></p>
                <p>[------------]</p>
                <p>I mounted my pillion, behind the servant, and set out on the romantic expedition
                    of riding into <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>, you said nothing; but
                    your looks threatened me with all sorts of misfortunes. May heaven avert your
                    prophecies! May it keep our horses from starting and stumbling! [----] Fatigue I
                    dread not, and bad weather I can bear. Before roads were made for wheels, a lady
                    commonly travelled on a pillion; and can it be less safe, now roads are better?
                    You are only unaccustomed to it. My noble and spirited animal, though not
                    intended by nature for such double drudgery, has proved that your fears were
                    groundless and has carried his burden with great propriety.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>[Four lines of text erased
                    ----------------------------------------------------]</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At <placeName ref="pl0740">Shrewsbury</placeName> it was the Assizes, and a
                        <persName ref="pe2180">Bishop</persName> was to be tried for a riot [---].
                    The novelty of the case had filled every house. At the <placeName ref="pl1610">Lion</placeName> we could not get beds; and met with the same fate,
                    successively, at the <placeName ref="pl3091">Talbot</placeName>, the <placeName ref="pl3090">Bell &amp; Raven</placeName>, and the <placeName ref="pl3092">Fox</placeName>. At last we were fortunate enough to procure admittance
                    into an Alehouse; or, more correctly speaking, a farmer’s inn. Fatigued with
                    having ridden twenty-six miles, I [was]<hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">desired to be</hi> shewn into a [---] bedchamber. It
                    contained two beds, and I supposed <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">it</hi> was the dormitory of the maids of the house, but
                    our landlady assured me it was </p>
                <pb n="2"/>
                <p>[p.2] </p>
                <p>her own room, that she was clean and wholesome, her parents just and true and
                    upright; and I might with safety lie down on her bed. She added that her temper
                    was such that she could not bear to see people in distress; that she had taken
                    me in out of compassion; would give us a broiled fowl and mushroom sauce for our
                    supper, and procure me a bed in a private house. Further, she advised me to be
                    patient, and submit to what I did not like, for she knew we could not do better.
                    Her last argument we could not doubt, for we had tried [<del>in vain</del>] <hi rend="subscript">^</hi><hi rend="superscript">our utmost</hi> to do better. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I took the counsel of my landlady; a morsel of her bread and butter, and a glass
                    of wine; and lay down on her own bed. The decorations of the room amused me. I
                    could not number the different articles, without removing what I had no mind to
                    touch. It is sufficient to say that every <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">imaginable</hi> piece of female apparel was scattered on
                    the floor, strewed on the chairs and chests, hung against the walls, and pinned
                    to the curtains. My landlady frequently bustled in and out of the chamber, to
                    fetch something she wanted, or deposit something she did not; and, as I shut my
                    eyes, to avoid further conversation, I heard her say to one of the assistants,
                    "the poor <hi rend="underline">cratur's</hi> tired to <hi rend="underline">death</hi>, and fast asleep."</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At nine o’clock the provident care of M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Notable had
                    got a vacant parlour, and I was summoned down to our broiled fowl. This parlour,
                    about eight feet square, smelled so strong of tobacco that I feared it would
                    overcome my inclination for my supper. But I opened the window; the air of the
                    stables, which </p>
                <p>[p.3] </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>rushed in, made it tolerable; and, with a dirty tablecloth, and knives that
                    deserved to be chained, we made a hearty meal; to which laughter was a better
                    sauce than even mushrooms. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The next morning, having declined a glass of brandy, courteously offered me by
                    mine hostess, we rode about twelve or thirteen miles, and crossed <placeName ref="pl1207">Offa’s Dyke</placeName>.<note type="editorial">In their earlier
                        crossing of the Dyke near Bishop’s Castle in 1787, Catherine’s father
                        William Hutton ‘leaped out of the chaise’ to examine it, expressing ‘a wish
                        which will never be gratified, to travel from end to the other’. Later he
                        would consider it a ‘monument of iniquity’, promoting ‘blood instead of
                        peace’. William Hutton, <hi rend="italic">Remarks on North Wales</hi>
                        (Birmingham: Knott and Lloyd, 1803), 2 and 222-23. For other travellers’
                        responses to Offa’s Dyke see Constantine, <hi rend="italic">Curious
                            Travellers</hi> (forthcoming).</note> It is <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> immediately: the country hilly, the views enchanting; the
                        <placeName ref="pl2393">Breiddin Hills</placeName>, mountains to </p>
                <p>me, rising on the right. We passed the <placeName ref="pl1226">Severn</placeName>
                    on a wooden bridge, dined at <placeName ref="pl0741">Pool</placeName>, and saw
                        <placeName ref="pl1509">Powis Castle</placeName>, with its terraces,
                    overlooking the beautiful Vale of Montgomery.</p>
                <p>The road to <placeName ref="pl1514">Llanfair</placeName> is over barren hills.
                    The town is surrounded by such; but is built on a smaller one, with a steep
                    descent of rock and wood to the river <placeName ref="pl1863"><sic>Vŷrnyw</sic></placeName>. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>To soften the ill impression of the uncouth assemblage of consonants in the Welsh
                    names of places, I will give you a few rules for their pronunciation. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>W is always oo </p>
                <p>Dd is the same as th in that;</p>
                <p>Ll is different from any English sound. It is formed by putting the tip of the
                    tongue against the back part of the roof of the mouth, and forcing the breath
                    outwards. </p>
                <p>Ch has the same gutteral sound as in the Scottish dialect. It is very difficult
                    to the English organs of speech. </p>
                <p>The Welsh have, strictly speaking, neither V nor K; though <persName ref="pe0232">Pennant</persName> frequently gives us both; but he is very slovenly in the
                    orthography of his native tongue. <note type="editorial">Hutton was a great
                        admirer of Pennant but could also be a sharp critic; in fact both ‘v’ and
                        ‘k’ were sometimes used in the period, especially following the
                        lexicographer William Owen Pughe’s attempts at orthographical reform.</note>
                    C is always sounded like K. </p>
                <p>[p.4]</p>

                <p>F is always sounded like V, and whenever our V is to be expressed, it is written
                    Ff, as in <placeName ref="pl1529">Nant Ffrancon</placeName>; ŷ, thus marked, is
                    sounded like u; thus fŷnnon is pronounced funnon; y alone, as in <placeName ref="pl3093">Drws y Coed</placeName>, is sounded as in French;<note type="editorial">That Hutton chooses these two striking Snowdonia locations
                        to illustrate her point about orthography may indicate that this section was
                        added after the 1796 tour, with a view to publication; she visited these
                        places in 1797.</note>
                </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At <placeName ref="pl1514">Llanfair</placeName>, we saw a funeral. The coffin was
                    laid on a bier, and covered with an awning like a tilted wagon, over which was
                    thrown a white sheet. It was borne on the shoulders or four men, and attended by
                    twenty or thirty persons, of both sexes, singing psalms. The singing, as well as
                    the service, was Welsh. There were no signs of mourning in the apparel of any;
                    but the behaviour of all was serious and devout. Those whom I imagined to be the
                    relations of the deceased, <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">together with</hi> the bearers, knelt down in the aisle,
                    around the corps. Instead of sculpture and flattering epitaphs, the walls of
                    this church, the simple receptacle of <hi rend="underline">The</hi> not <hi rend="underline">unhonour’d dead</hi>
                    <note type="editorial">Thomas Gray’s poem, <hi rend="italic">Elegy in a Country
                            Churchyard</hi> (1751) evokes the ‘th’unhonour’d dead’.</note>were stuck
                    with lacquered plates, such as are placed on coffins, containing the name of
                    each departed parishioner, and when he lived and died. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At <placeName ref="pl3089">Llanerfyl</placeName> we crossed the <placeName ref="pl1863">Vŷrnyw</placeName> on a wooden bridge, which I did not choose
                    should carry me and my horse at the same time. We breakfasted at <placeName ref="pl1511">Cann Office</placeName>, remarkable only for a tumulus, of
                    which </p>
                <p>[p.5] </p>
                <p>nobody there can give any account, and the remains of a camp.<note type="editorial">The Cann Office earthwork is thought now to be medieval,
                        possibly associated with a motte. See <ref type="http" target="https://coflein.gov.uk/en/site/306527/details/cann-office-hotel-earthwork#site-details">here.</ref>
                    </note> We had been apprehensive of rain at setting out, and had taken the
                    opinion of every Welshman we met on the subject. Their predictions accorded with
                    our fears, and the event verified both, for at this place I was obliged to dry
                    all my <sic>cloaths</sic>. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>From <placeName ref="pl1511">Cann Office</placeName> we travelled by the side of
                    the <placeName ref="pl1863">Vŷrnyw</placeName>, till it dwindled to a gutter,
                    and then disappeared. A moment after, we found, in its stead, a stream taking a
                    contrary course. We had met the other all the way up from the <placeName ref="pl1226">Severn</placeName>, and we accompanied this down to the
                        <placeName ref="pl3268">Dŷfi</placeName>. The place where both spring up is
                    rugged, wild, and barren. It is called the Dolmaen, or the Stoney Field.<note type="editorial">The source of the Vyrnwy is now a large lake of that name
                        created by damming in the 1880s.</note>
                </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The <placeName ref="pl3269">Cleifion</placeName>, our new found river, ran in a
                    deep bottom, between two ranges of stupendous hills, to <placeName ref="pl1515">Mallwyd</placeName>, originally Maenllwyd, Greystone, where we now
                        are.<note type="editorial">There is no evidence for ‘maen’ in earlier forms
                        of this name; ‘ma’ is more likely to mean simply ‘place’.</note> Our road
                    was a terrace cut on the side of the northern range; generally fenced with a
                    hedge, now and then without a fence; sometimes on bridges thrown over streams,
                    which poured down from the mountains, across our road; and sometimes through
                    them: while, swelled by the rains into little torrents, they tumbled into
                    cascades into the river below. The sublimity of these scenes shook my nerves.
                    The only way in which I could contemplate these towering hills, woody glens, and
                    rushing waters, was on my feet. We sent the servant on with the horses, and
                    walked nearly four miles before we reached <placeName ref="pl1515">Mallwyd</placeName>; chiefly in the rain; always in the mire; but
                    enraptured at every step we took.<note type="editorial">Hutton’s general fear of
                        heights is often expressed as a particular anxiety about roads which drop
                        away on one side. This appears as a striking leitmotif throughout her tours
                        (see, e.g., her comments on ‘new’ and ‘old’ roads between Dolgellau and
                        Barmouth below).</note>
                </p>
                <p/>
                <p>Letter 2<note type="editorial">Published in the <hi rend="italic">Monthly
                            Magazine</hi> (June, 1815), 411-13.</note></p>
                <p/>
                <p><del>My Dear Brother</del>, </p>
                <p>
                    <placeName ref="pl1515">Mallwyd</placeName> July 27, 1796</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1515">Mallwyd</placeName> is a village on the confines of the
                    counties of <placeName ref="pl2917">Montgomery</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1235">Merioneth</placeName>, which consists of a few houses and
                    church; </p>
                <p>[p.6]</p>
                <p>but it is situated at the conflux of the <placeName ref="pl3268">Dŷfi</placeName>, the <placeName ref="pl3269">Clifion</placeName>, and the
                        Mowddû;<note type="editorial">Mallwyd sits at the confluence of the Dyfi,
                        the Cleifion and the Cerist; Hutton’s ‘Mowddû’ seems to be a projection of
                        the name of the commote of Dinas Mawddwy onto the Cerist or another river.
                        There is no historical evidence for this usage, but it not uncommon as a
                        phenomenon and may reflect local practice; see Hutton’s general remarks on
                        river-names below.</note> at the junction of four vales, and consequently
                    the meeting of four roads; for here roads cannot get over the hills. The eastern
                    road we had travelled. The western leads up the Mawddû to <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelly</placeName>, and thence to <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName>, where we are going; the northern up the <placeName ref="pl3268">Dŷfi</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName>;
                    and the southern vale has two roads, one on each side of the river. That on the
                    left leads to <placeName ref="pl2029">Machynlleth</placeName>, and thence to
                        <placeName ref="pl1240">Aberystwith</placeName>; that on the right to
                        <placeName ref="pl3270">Towyn</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl3271">Aberdŷfi</placeName>, where the vale and river end in sea. </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1515">Mallwyd</placeName> is the interior of <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>. Here the common people speak no English. </p>
                <p>The dress of both sexes is entirely supplied by the sheep of the country, except
                    the shirt and neck-handkerchief of the men, and two printed handkerchiefs for
                    the women; one worn round the neck, the other on the head, crossed under the
                    chin, and tied behind. Over this bulky head-dress, summer and winter, in doors
                    and out, they wear a black hat, only distinguishable from the man's by a ribband
                    tied round the crown. With garments of flannel and woolen, and this load on the
                    head, shoes and stockings are a superfluity. They trudge along, bare-footed, and
                    bare-legged, with as little inconvenience as the sheep that formerly carried the
                    burthen. <hi rend="superscript">The female who fills the several offices of
                        waiter and chamber-maid at the <hi rend="subscript">^</hi> inn, is
                        distinguished by shoes and stockings, and a mob cap.</hi></p>
                <p>The diet of the common people, and even of the farmer's servants, is oat cake, or
                    sour bread made of a mixture of rye and barley; butter and cheese without
                    limitation; whey curds; stir-up, made of boiled whey, thickened with oatmeal;
                    and the servants are allowed a small portion of salted meat or bacon on a
                    Sunday. Their universal beverage is buttermilk. </p>
                <p>[p.7] </p>
                <p>The men are thin; but tall and athletic; the women healthy; ruddy, stout, and
                    handsome; and the children, if possible yet more so. But I think an old woman
                    looks older than in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>. Perhaps the air
                    of the mountains <hi rend="subscript">^</hi><hi rend="superscript">may</hi> give
                    health and strength while youth and activity enable them to breathe it
                    uncorrupted; and the closeness of their huts may plant wrinkles in the place of
                    roses, when age confines them more within doors. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The best farms in this country let at from ten to fifteen shillings an acre; and
                    sell at about twenty <hi rend="subscript">^</hi><hi rend="superscript">eight</hi> years purchase. There is a certain portion of mountain allotted
                    to each, which never varies from generation to generation; and it is an
                    established rule that no man shall send a greater number of sheep to the
                    mountain in summer, than his farm will maintain in winter. The proportion of
                    mountain belonging to the Hafod farms, in the adjoining <placeName ref="pl1233">county of Cardigan</placeName>, is as follows:-<note type="editorial">Despite slightly idiosyncratic spelling (which may reflect local
                        pronunciation) all of the farm names can be plausibly identified with places
                        mentioned in the Hafod Collection (Accession 1301, Ceredigion Archives), a
                        corpus of documents relating to the land-holdings of the Hafod estate, which
                        in the late 1790s was being famously ‘picturesqued’ by Thomas Johnes, who
                        also acquired and developed farmlands and sheepwalks. Dolgwyn may be Dolwen
                        (often coupled with Tŷ Gwyn); Bwlchwater is Bwlch Gwalter (Bwlchgwallter);
                        Dolgorse is Dol-y-Gors and the curious Bolecott seems likely to be
                        Botcol.</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Hafod farm 250 acres enclosed--- 600 acres of Mountain</p>
                <p>Dolgwyn Farm 100 1200 </p>
                <p>Bwlchwater Farm 130 800 </p>
                <p>Dolgorse Farm 160 700 </p>
                <p>Bolecott Farm 60 600 </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The mountain part of one farm near <placeName ref="pl1513">Dinas
                        Mowddû</placeName> keeps 3000 sheep. It is divided into three distinct sheep
                    walks. The commanding officer of a whole is a man; the acting officers are dogs,
                    of which are kept from fifteen to twenty. The <hi rend="superscript">sheep</hi>
                    walks are divided, not by hedges, ditches or stone walls; but by boundaries
                    drawn by the eye. Such bounds as these the sheep might easily overleap, and not
                    only</p>
                <p>[p.8]</p>
                <p>trespass upon each other, but upon their neighbours. It is the business of the
                    dogs to take care they do not. Early in the morning the shepherd climbs the
                    mountain, taking with him three dogs. He points out to each his walk, and they
                    immediately go upon duty. They know exactly the confines; and, by always taking
                    that side on which the sheep show an inclination to stray, they oblige them to
                    remain in their proper pasture. But this post is so fatiguing to the dogs that
                    two or three hours is as long as they can bear it. The shepherd then appears on
                    his stand with three other dogs, one for each sheep-walk, to relieve guard. He
                    calls, and waves his hand; they joyfully obey the summons; and each takes his
                    turn till night sends the flocks to rest. [<del>xxx</del>] Invaluable would be a
                    breed of dogs that could <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">thus</hi> restrain headstrong man within his proper
                    limits! That would bite the heels of every sovereign that invades his neighbour,
                    or instigated other sovereigns to do so!<note type="editorial">Napoleon’s
                        campaign in Italy had begun in April 1796.</note></p>
                <p>This situation of <placeName ref="pl1515">Mallwyd</placeName> is charming. The
                    mountains which encompass it are so high that it is difficult to determine
                    whether the white specks we see near their tops are stones or sheep, till we
                    observe them change their place. On the sides are small patches of wood, or
                    inclosed lands, with here and there are cottage. So remote are these dwellings
                    from the haunts of men, that, on the approach of our servant,<note type="editorial">A servant named ‘John’ appears in William Hutton’s comic
                        verse account of their journey from Birmingham to Caernarfon in 1799. <hi rend="italic">Remarks on North Wales</hi> (1803), 107.</note>
                    <del>all</del> the women and children ran away in terror; nor could all his
                    gestures prevail on them to return, when they found the man in the pied coat did
                    no mischief. I entered one of their huts, which was miserably dark, with a small
                    piece of turf mouldering to ashes on the hearth. The floor was in no danger; for
                    nothing but an earthquake could destroy it.<note type="editorial">See William
                        Hutton’s description of entering a cottage near Mallwyd. <hi rend="italic">Remarks</hi>, 22-24.</note>
                </p>

                <p>The range of hills on the <placeName ref="pl1515">Mallwyd</placeName> side of the
                    river look as if they </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>[p.9]</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>had been ploughed by the hand of Brobdingnagians,<note type="editorial">The
                        Brobdingnagians are the giants in Jonathan Swift’s <hi rend="italic">Gulliver’s Travels</hi> (1726).</note> and the turf afterwards suffered
                    to grow. The waters have worn gullies, at almost regular distances, like the
                    furrows of a plough, while the lands between resemble immense ridges. I
                        <del>once</del>
                    <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">formerly</hi> travelled by the side of the <placeName ref="pl1227">Wye</placeName>, on a terrace road, cut near the base of such a
                    range of hills, for some miles. Every gutter, at a distance, was a shining white
                    ribbon; at hand, it was a small cataract. I was in a close carriage, with four
                    horses; and our road so narrow that not a horse, scarcely a cat, could have
                    passed us. We were obliged to follow every prominence and recess in the surface
                    of the mountains, and our carriage and horses were continually describing the
                    figure of a bow.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Above <placeName ref="pl1515">Mallwyd</placeName>, while there is yet a meadow
                    between the <placeName ref="pl3268">Dŷfi</placeName> and the <placeName ref="pl3269">Clifion</placeName>, there is a bridge over each. The former
                    river rushes over huge stones; while the latter, a deep and silent stream, moves
                    slowly between two walls of perpendicular rock. Below <placeName ref="pl1515">Mallwyd</placeName> is a bridge over the united rivers, which is generally
                    visited by strangers, on account of the romantic situation. The water dashes
                    over broken rocks, which, in one place, form a salmon leap.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>In the churchyard of <placeName ref="pl1515">Mallwyd</placeName> is a yew-tree,
                    that, tradition says, is 700 years old; and it is not easy to imagine a spot
                    where a yew-tree could <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">have</hi> witnessed fewer vicissitudes in the objects
                    around, during that length of time.<note type="editorial">A selection of tourist
                        descriptions of this yew group, which still stands in the graveyard of St
                        Tydecho’s church, can be found <ref type="http" target=": https://www.ancient-yew.org/userfiles/file/Mallwyd%202019.pdf">here.</ref></note> The rivers, the rocks, and the mountains, are
                    immutable. The woods are the lineal descendants of those that flourished when
                    the yew was planted. The houses, probably differ little in number, and <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">but</hi> few of them in convenience. The roads are
                    undoubtedly the same; for nowhere else could they be made to </p>
                <p>[p. 10] </p>
                <p>pass: they are only widened to admit a carriage. The yew-tree has nine distinct
                    trunks, one in the centre, and eight that surround it; and the circumference of
                    their united branches is computed at upwards of two hundred feet.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>That you may not stand astonished at my prodigious knowledge of this
                    principality, considering the short time I have been in it I will let you into
                    the secret. The wind whistled all night among the mountains, by which <placeName ref="pl1515">Mallwyd</placeName> is environed; the rain beat against my
                    casement; and I requested my father to pass the day here. I have spent the rainy
                    part of it in studying the inhabitants; and the fair, in acquiring some idea of
                    their country.</p>
                <p/>
                <p>Letter 3<note type="editorial">Published in the <hi rend="italic">Monthly
                            Magazine</hi> (July, 1815), 489-90.</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>
                    <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName> Aug 4 1796</p>
                <p/>
                <p> My Dear Friend,</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Having crossed the two rivers <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">of <placeName ref="pl1515">Mallwyd</placeName></hi>, we
                    turned the angle of a mountain, and went through <placeName ref="pl1513">Dinas
                        Mowddû</placeName> one of the poorest of British towns; though Dinas
                    signifies city.<note type="editorial">This is a trope in various descriptions of
                        the village of Dinas Mawddwy; Joseph Cradock makes great play of its ‘civic’
                        institutions and attractions in <hi rend="italic">An account of some of the
                            most Romantic parts of North Wales</hi> (London, 1777) 9-14; as does
                        William Hutton, <hi rend="italic">Remarks</hi>, 16-17; Pennant explains that
                        it was an administrative hub for a wide area, <hi rend="italic">Tours in
                            Wales</hi> (1784) II, 91-92.</note> It speaks louder in favour of these
                    Cambrians' <del>love of</del><hi rend="superscript">propensity to</hi> liquor
                    than religion; for they have two public houses of their own, but are content to
                    go to <placeName ref="pl1515">Mallwyd</placeName> to church. Our road, for four
                    or five miles, was by the side of the Mowddû, and near the bottom of the
                    mountains, till the one could no longer be discovered, and the others met at
                    their base. Nothing shewed the hand of man, or the least token of his existence,
                    but the road. We had here to climb what the Welsh call a Bwlch, which literally
                    means a notch; but is used to denote a gap between two summits. Our road
                    [------] was cut on the side </p>
                <p>[p.11] </p>
                <p>of one of the mountains, and ascended till it reached the pass; by which time it
                    looked down a frightful precipice. The ascent was a mile, and without a fence.
                    It is called <placeName ref="pl1597">Bwlch Oerddrws</placeName>. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>As we walked slowly up the mountain we were overtaken by a Welshman, on his
                    poney, and a woman on foot, who was fully a match for him and his
                        <del>keffil</del>
                    <hi rend="superscript">horse</hi>.<note type="editorial">‘Ceffyl’ is Welsh for
                        horse; Hutton often uses the term to denote a Welsh pony.</note> It was a
                    comfort to meet with our fellow creatures in so desolate the region, though we
                    could not communicate our ideas to each other. The ideas of the woman, if we
                    might judge by her words, were very copious, for her tongue was never at rest.
                    [-----------] They accompanied us to <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelly</placeName>, nearly six miles, keeping close to our horses heels;
                    walking when we walked, and trotting when we trotted; the woman trudging
                    barefooted; always talking, never out of breath or discovering the smallest
                    symptom of fatigue. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The top of <placeName ref="pl1597">Bwlch Oeddrws</placeName> is so tremendous on
                    a stormy day, that horses have been frequently known to turn back, and could
                    scarcely be made to pass it. On the other side the descent was not steep; but
                    the face of the country was changed, and the sheep were become real stones,
                    sprouting out of the scanty herbage. I saw a rill spring up under my feet; at
                        <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelly</placeName> it was navigable, and at
                        <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName> a sea. This was very fine,
                    [---------] but not strictly true, for I have since found that it is joined by
                        <hi rend="superscript">an</hi>other river, both at and after <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelly</placeName>. </p>
                <p>Rivers are so numerous in this country that it is not easy to find out their
                    names, or even to be certain whether the bridge one is now passing be over the
                    same stream one crossed ten minutes ago. </p>
                <p>[p.12] </p>
                <p>If you apply to the common people for information they do not understand you; and
                    if you meet with a man that can speak English, it is a thousand to one he does
                    not know. Even at <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName> they are ignorant
                    of <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">the name of</hi> their river. Ask a sailor, and he will
                    tell you it is the <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelleu</placeName> river, because
                    it comes to him from <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelleu</placeName>. Ask a man
                    more enlightened, and he will say it is the Avon,<note type="editorial">I.e. the
                        Welsh word 'afon'.</note> because it is the general Welsh name for all
                    rivers. You are very fortunate if you find a person who can tell you it is the
                        <placeName ref="pl3097">Maw</placeName>. </p>
                <p>After travelling along barren and rocky moors, we found ourselves at the top of a
                    steep and lofty hill, which overlooked the town of <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelleu</placeName>, seated among rich meadows. A town, a fertile plain,
                    a winding river, a handsome bridge, and neat white houses, it gave us the idea
                    of a different world; while the mountains that hedged them in, among which was
                    the mighty <placeName ref="pl1866">Cader Ydris</placeName>, convinced us we were
                    yet in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>. From this bird's eye view we
                    had a long descent to <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelleu</placeName>. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgellau</placeName> we again overtook the Assizes,
                    and a clergyman was to be tried for murder; but, as our business was only to
                    breakfast, it was of little consequence, and we were content with a window to
                    ourselves in a public room, where the gentlemen of the county were conversing
                    and promenading in different parties, as they had done the night before, when it
                    was enlivened by fiddles, Welsh harps, and Welsh Ladies, at the Assize Ball. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>From <placeName ref="pl2029">Machynlleth</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelleu</placeName>, and from <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelleu</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName>, are
                    reckoned two of the finest rides in <placeName ref="pl1221">North
                        Wales</placeName>. The latter was our road. I had heard much at <placeName ref="pl1515">Mallwyd</placeName> of billows foaming </p>
                <p>[p.13] </p>
                <p>at our feet, and impending rocks, threatening immediate destruction, over head;
                    and I had conceived such a terror of these dangers that I actually formed the
                    wise and prudent project of walking the whole way. But, as I could not walk ten
                    miles at one time, I purposed to divide it into two stages, and, having
                    atchieved one of them, to sleep in my cloaths at some cottage, and accomplished
                    the other the next day. On further reflection, however, I thought I might as
                    well not walk till I did not dare to ride, and we set out on horseback along a
                    noble road, guarded by two stone walls.</p>
                <p>Having reached the river <placeName ref="pl3097">Maw</placeName>, a little below
                        <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelleu</placeName>, the road accompanies it to
                    its mouth, and is certainly more charming than imagination can picture. It
                    passes by farms, over bridges, and by one beautiful cascade. It deviates from
                    the river, and goes behind the rocks and woody hills. It returns to it again,
                    and affords a prospect of the opening sea. The last mile and a half before it
                    reaches <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName>, the mountain slopes to the
                    water's edge; and the rock was blown up with gunpowder, before the road could be
                    made. Expense was two guineas and a half a rood, and the Gentlemen of <placeName ref="pl1235">Merionethshire</placeName> are justly proud of having completed
                    such an undertaking. The road is <hi rend="subscript">^</hi><hi rend="superscript">cut</hi> at different <sic>heighths</sic> above the
                    water, with a precipice on the left, and masses and perpendicular walls of rock
                    rising on the right. True it is [-----] that there is frequently no fence on the
                    falling side. At such places I always walked; but, as for foaming billows, and </p>
                <p>[p.14] </p>
                <p>impending rocks, they did not <hi rend="superscript">happen</hi> to trouble me. </p>
                <p>A gentleman who is at this place<note type="editorial">The Huttons were staying
                        at the Cors-y-Gedol Inn at Barmouth, described further below. </note> is so
                    delighted with the scenery of <placeName ref="pl3087">Pont-ddû</placeName>, the
                    waterfall I mentioned, that he has offered forty years purchase for the
                    adjoining farm, besides paying for the wood. The rent is thirty one pounds a
                    year; but the number of acres is neither know nor guessed at, for here they have
                    no notion of measuring land. It is much covered with small oaks, the natural
                    production of the soil, and has, here and there, a patch of grass or grain, but
                    not one foot of ground where a house could be placed, without a very steep
                    ascent to it. The owner has rejected the offer. The song does well to celebrate
                        <hi rend="underline">Our native oak</hi>, for in this country, where much is
                    in a state of nature, every glen it is wooded, and almost all wood is oak.<note type="editorial">This may be the song ‘Ye Mariners of England’, which has
                        the line ‘With thunders from her native oak/She quells the floods below’. Or
                        it may more simply refer to the better known ‘Hearts of Oak’.</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Till the road at I have described was formed, which is not twelve years ago, the
                    way from <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelleu</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName> was over the mountains, and the descent to
                    the town a steep zig-zag above the tops of the houses. It may be imagined that
                    no stranger travelled it but from necessity. If by chance the carriage had
                    occasion to approach the place, it was taken to pieces at <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelleu</placeName> and sent down by a boat.
                    [------------------]</p>
                <p>The old Welsh roads kept their undeviating line through vales, or over passable
                    hills, as </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>[p.15] </p>
                <p>they lay before them. They are sometimes stony, and sometimes present us with a
                    piece of uncovered native rock, but they are more commonly fine hard gravel, and
                    are excellent roads for a horse. The modern roads follow the course of the
                    rivers, to avoid the hills; and are cut on their sides to avoid the floods. They
                    are consequently terraces, and, as they are often unfenced, are more dangerous,
                    notwithstanding their breadth than the ancient ones, that run over the
                    hills.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Letter 4<note type="editorial">Published in the <hi rend="italic">Monthly
                            Magazine</hi> (July, 1815) 490-91.</note></p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName> Aug 7 1796</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>My Dear Brother</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The shore of <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName> is a fine sand, from
                    which the sea retires about two hundred yards at low water. A mountain
                    completely fills the angle between the river and the sea, which, as I mentioned
                    before, has been cut to make a passage to the town. Having turned this angle, a
                    slip of land, along the shore, affords room for a street. This is the grand
                    thoroughfare of <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName>. Here are the inns,
                    the <placeName ref="pl1887">Cors y gedol Arms</placeName> and the Red Lion, both
                    in the hands of one person; and the latter occupied as a lodging house, by such
                    as chuse to be quiet, that is, to hear the noise of each other, rather than that
                    of tourists, who are here today and gone tomorrow. The remainder of <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName> consists of eight rows of houses, one over
                    the other, on the site of the mountain, which are inhabited by the Aborigines of
                    the country. In general, one man's chimney is on a level with his neighbour's
                    floor, so all have an opportunity of inhaling the smoak for nothing. When a
                    visitor arrived at <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName> by the old road,
                    he might call in upon his friends, from one a perch to another, till he dropped
                    down on those upon the shore. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Above all the houses of <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName> a fine
                    spring [----] issues from </p>
                <p>[p.16] </p>
                <p>the rock, which supplies this curious city with water, and where the bare-legged
                    ladies wash their woolens and potatoes. To carry their cloaths to the water,
                    rather than the water to their cloaths, seems the common practise of the place,
                    for I have seen a spot on the shore, near a rivulet, [------] frequently
                    occupied by these cleansers of woolen, with their beating logs, while their caps
                    are stewing in a porridge pot over a fire of sticks. I believe it was so in the
                    days of Homer.<note type="editorial">For images of Welsh women washing clothes,
                        see <ref type="http" target="https://sublimewales.wordpress.com/material-culture/washing/">here.</ref></note>
                </p>
                <p>The <placeName ref="pl1866">Cader</placeName>, or Chair, of Ydris is a noble
                    mountain, and, like Saddle Back, in Cumberland, receives its name from its
                    shape. I have been puzzled to find out who this <del>Ydris</del><hi rend="superscript">gentleman</hi> was, who fixed upon the highest seat in
                    the country, though felt assured his head must have been stronger than mine or
                    he would have been content with a lower station. My wonder at this choice has
                    ceased, now I have discovered that he was a giant, which the following well
                    known legend puts beyond a doubt. He was walking by the Pool of three grains, at
                    the foot of his chair, when he found himself incommoded by some stones that had
                    crept into his shoe, he took off the shoe and shook them out, and there they
                    remain to this day, three enormous rocks, which have given name to the
                        pool.<note type="editorial">Henry Penruddocke Wyndham mentions ‘this
                        ridiculous story’ in <hi rend="italic">A gentleman's tour through
                            Monmouthshire and Wales, in the months of June and July, 1774</hi>
                        (London 1781), 114-15. For a contemporary image of the 'Pool of the Three
                        Grains' by S. H Grimm see <ref type="http" target="https://www.peoplescollection.wales/items/20298">here.</ref>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The <placeName ref="pl1887">Cors y gedol Arms</placeName> is a good inn. The
                    company dine at a public table, and are generally numerous enough to form an
                    agreeable society.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>[The most remarkable of my female associates, though I do not rank her amongst
                    the most agreeable, is a lady from the remote part of <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>. I should despair of doing justice to her character, if
                    I were to attempt it. I will only say that I am in a miserable situation with
                    regard to her. She must talk, and talk incessantly; a young lady of eighteen,
                    giddy, gawkey, and uncultivated </p>
                <p>[p.17] </p>
                <p>as the <placeName ref="pl1235">Merionethshire</placeName> mountains, though
                    sometimes stumbling on shrewd remarks, she considers as a child, beneath her
                    notice: her own daughter, a pleasing young women, having heard her stories at
                    least five hundred times, affords the mother little satisfaction as an auditor:
                    a Welsh lady of high descent keeps her at a distance: I, poor I, am the
                    unfortunate victim of her unceasing eloquence. I know all the relations, all the
                    acquaintances, all the servants, all the disorders, and all the physicians she
                    ever had in her life. She possesses the most perfect politeness; for while she
                    is attentive to all forms, she makes herself the only object of attention. She
                    insists upon the pleasure of breakfasting with me, and shows me how to make the
                    coffee. She places me at the head of the table, and corrects my carving. All
                    this I could forgive; but she talks to me while my horse is waiting at the door;
                    talks to me till I have not time to dress; and never lets me escape from her
                    without violence.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Among the male part of our company, we have a very great man; for he weighs
                    twenty six stone. Last night he actually broke down his bed-stead. Another
                    gentleman of our party had the reputation of being still greater; for the honest
                    townsmen of <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName> believed him to be the
                    Prince of Orange, and would have set their bells a ringing, if they had any.
                    What could be the reason? His servants wore liveries faced with orange
                        colour.]<note type="editorial">This revealing section, a snapshot of the
                        complexities of seaside sociability, is lightly scored through in the
                        manuscript, and omitted from the published version of this tour in the <hi rend="italic">Monthly Magazine</hi>.</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At all funerals in <placeName ref="pl1221">North Wales</placeName> a wooden bowl
                    is placed on a communion table; and, after the service in the church is ended,
                    every person present drops money in it; the poorer sort, copper; the richer,
                    shillings, half crowns, even guineas, and sometimes to the number of five. This
                    offering is made from respect to the memory of the deceased, and the greater the </p>
                <p>[p.18] </p>
                <p>sum the greater the respect shown. But the poor clergyman reaps the benefit; it
                    is his perquisite, and frequently exceeds the rest of his revenue. </p>
                <p>After the service at the grave is ended, there is a smaller contribution for the
                    clerk. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>[Section pasted over and insert indicated to take its place [-------]. 2 </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> 2[In <placeName ref="pl1245">South Wales</placeName>, when a poor person dies,
                    the neighbours and acquaintance take each a large fluted mould candle, made on
                    purpose for such occasions, called a burying candle, and, having deposited it in
                    the house, they sit all night by the dead body, and join in singing psalms. This
                    they call <hi rend="underline">Waking the corpse</hi>, and they continue the
                    practice every night till it is buried. Where the neighbourhood is populous,
                    these midnight wakers fill the house, which indeed seldom consists of more than
                    two rooms. Tea is made for their refreshment.]</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Throughout the principality the common people constantly see <hi rend="underline">corpse candles</hi> which are the forerunners of death. These are large
                    walking candles, that pass by in the night, and these <hi rend="subscript">^</hi><hi rend="superscript">see-ers</hi> can tell, by the colour of the
                    flame, and the kind of noise it makes in walking, whether it be man, woman, or
                        child.<note type="editorial">It is not clear what has prompted this
                        reflection on funeral customs (although it is a common trope in tourist
                        writing); nor why the customs and superstitions of ‘South Wales’ should be
                        invoked here in an insert. It may indicate a later revision for the
                        published version (see discussion in Introduction). Henry Penruddocke
                        Wyndham, A Gentleman’s Tour (1781 ed.) 177-79, has a similar, if less
                        sympathetic account of the payment to the clergyman (he also mentions five
                        guineas).</note> [-----]</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The courtships of the Welsh, in bed, with no other fence for the virtue of the
                    woman than a flannel petticoat, are well known, and have scandalized them in the
                    eyes of many of their English fellow subjects. But it is certain that proofs of
                    incontinence are not more frequent among them than among the farmer's servants
                    in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>, who sit up all night by the
                    kitchen fire; and for the same reason, that their courtship may not interfere
                    with the labours of the day.<note type="editorial">If this was written in 1796,
                        it is, as Michael Freeman notes, very early to be referring to the custom of
                        ‘bundling’ or ‘caru ar y gwely’ as something well-known to English readers
                        (see <ref type="http" target="https://sublimewales.wordpress.com/material-culture/customs/bundling/">here</ref>). The anonymous author of <hi rend="italic">Letters for
                            Snowdon</hi> (1770) rather coyly refers to pre-marital sex as a way of
                        testing fertility, but does not describe the practice of lying clothed on
                        the bed. Hutton’s refusal to see this as scandalous is typical,
                        acknowledging as it does that the labouring classes have little private
                        space for courtship.</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Letter 5<note type="editorial">Published in the <hi rend="italic">Monthly
                            Magazine</hi> (October, 1815) 226-28.</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>
                    <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName> Aug 12 1796</p>
                <p>My Dear Friend,</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>To the great relief of my spirits, my loquacious companion is gone; [though the
                    burden has been lighter, as</p>
                <p>[p.19]</p>
                <p>it has been was divided -------] </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>[This morning, after she had privately found fault with every item in the bill,
                    and publicly disputed some of them, I saw her leave sixpence for the harper who
                    plays to us at all our meals, and stepped into her carriage. The favour I stood
                    in with this lady has made me rather shy to the rest. I find myself so very
                    amiable, in other words, our party is so small, that it requires my utmost
                    caution not to become an appendage to somebody. Though I wish for the good
                    opinion of every living soul, I think my time too great a sacrifice to obtain
                        it].<note type="editorial">Section lightly scored through, as above, but
                        (perhaps erroneously?) included in the <hi rend="italic">Monthly
                            Magazine</hi>.</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Three days ago I desired our man to put a sandwich and a cruet full of wine in
                    his pocket, and I set out to take a peep at <placeName ref="pl1521">Harlech
                        castle</placeName>, ten miles from hence. The road is all the way near the
                    shore, and the country sufficiently populous, for I passed five villages with
                    parish churches, a number of scattered cottages, and a Methodist meeting house,
                    with green shutters. The first church, at two miles distance from <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName>, is that of Llanaber, to which <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName> belongs for it has no church of his own.
                    At four miles, on the hill on the right, is the house of <placeName ref="pl1239">Cors y gedol</placeName>, with its woods shaven to a straight line by the
                    sea breezes. It formerly belonged to the Vaughans, but is now, by marriage, the
                    property of the Mostyns, who have left it to servants; I dare say wisely, for
                    they must be very unfortunate if they have not a pleasanter place
                        elsewhere.<note type="editorial">The last male representative of the
                        Cors-y-Gedol Vaughans was Evan Lloyd Vaughan; when he died in 1791, the
                        estates passed to his niece Margaret, wife of Sir Roger Mostyn.</note>
                </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I passed, in my road, two large upright stones, called Druid stones. I am told
                    they are scattered all over the country. I also passed the entrance into
                        <placeName ref="pl3101">Glyn Artro</placeName>, the opening to the
                        <placeName ref="pl1200">Cwm Bychan</placeName> (small hollow), where is
                    situated the secluded domain of Pennant's Mr <persName ref="pe2188">Evan
                        Lloyd</persName>, whose family has resided on the spot seven hundred </p>
                <p>[p.20] </p>
                <p>years. I longed to visit his romantic territory, and his hereditary oatmeal
                    chests; but the road was unknown to me, and I feared it might not be safe
                    footing for my English horse. I do not mention my being a stranger as an
                    objection, for such is my opinion of Welsh hospitality, but I have no doubt that
                    circumstance alone would have procured me a welcome, especially in a place so
                    unperverted by intercourse with the world.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The view from the hill above <placeName ref="pl1520">Harlech</placeName> is so
                    stupendous it shook my whole frame. On the right, wild mountains, heaped one
                    upon the other; on the left, far below me, the sea. Before me, the yet loftier
                    mountains of Caernarvonshire, with <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>
                    at their head, inclosing a vast bay, &amp; the estuaries of two rivers, Traeth
                    mawr and Traeth bychan, and under my feet the town of <placeName ref="pl1520">Harlech</placeName>, and its noble <placeName ref="pl1521">castle</placeName>. As I descended the hill on foot, an old man came out of
                    his cottage, uttered the word <hi rend="underline">castle</hi>, and shewed a
                    key; I answered Yes, and followed him. </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1521">Harlech castle</placeName> is a strong square building,
                    with a round tower at each angle, and one on each side the entrance. Besides
                    these are four turrets, smaller and higher, which rise above the towers at the
                    angles, and are in a more ruinous state. The entrance is a pointed arch, which
                    formerly contained six gates, one behind the other. Though the castle is every
                    where unroofed, undoored and unwindowed, it has not a dilapidated appearance.
                    There are broken stone staircases in every tower, which led to the top of each;
                    and there is one <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">still</hi> entire, in the area which now leads only to
                    the top of the walls. Pointed, arched fire places are visible in all rooms,
                    though the rooms are no longer divided from each other. Window </p>
                <p>[p.21] </p>
                <p>places also remain; and those in the state apartment three on a row, and
                    spacious; the others a tolerable size within, but narrowing to a chink
                        without.<note type="editorial">Hutton’s responses to Harlech castle are
                        further discussed in Constantine, <hi rend="italic">Curious Travellers</hi>
                        (forthcoming). </note>
                </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1520">Harlech castle</placeName> stands on a rock, which rises
                    abruptly, not from the sea, but from a marsh called the <placeName ref="pl3103">Gamlas</placeName>, nearly a mile in breadth, which lies between it and the
                    sea, and is so level that it probably was once covered with the water. On this
                    side the rock is almost perpendicular; at either end it is extremely steep; in
                    front it is on an equal <sic>heighth</sic> with the town, from which it is
                    separated by a deep ditch, and the mountains within land of soar high above it.
                    The castle occupies the whole platform of the rock, except a space of about four
                    or five feet in breadth, which forms a beautiful, verdant path around it, on the
                    brink of an abyss. </p>
                <p>Having rewarded my guide for his “Three shemney”, “Room”, “Strong wall” and
                    “Centry box”, which was all the information he could give, and all the English
                    he could utter, I sat down on a rock and ate my sandwich, regretting nothing in
                    this world but that I could not see <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>,
                    here called Y Widdfa, or, the Conspicuous, whose head was hid in the clouds. I
                    then walked back through the town of <placeName ref="pl1520">Harlech</placeName>, the county town of <placeName ref="pl1235">Merionethshire</placeName>, where the Member of Parliament is chosen,
                    though the Assizes are held alternately at <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelleu</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName>. </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1520">Harlech</placeName> consists of one small street of poor
                    houses, and might pass for a pretty village in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>. There are two inns, without provisions or
                    accommodations; and a Dealer in Tea, without a shop. The only person I met with
                    in the place who could speak English was the guide that conducts travellers
                    across the Traeths;<note type="editorial">Traeth Mawr and Traeth Bychan – sands
                        needing guides. Paul Sandby.</note> and it is certain that there was </p>
                <p>[p.22] </p>
                <p>no stable door high enough to admit my horse; though the owner of one insisted,
                    by signs, upon his shoulder being measured (a pig having previously been turned
                    out), to prove it. [--------]<note type="editorial">Section pasted over and
                        replaced with paragraph marked ‘3x.’</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>[3x. <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelleu</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName>, and <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan-y-Bwlch</placeName>,
                    form a triangle. From a bridge over the Maw, where the roads to <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan-y-Bwlch</placeName> divide, which is a mile on this side of <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelleu</placeName>, it is about nine miles to the former of
                    those towns, and seventeen to the latter. From <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan-y-Bwlch</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName> is
                    about eighteen. The space which these roads enclose is wholly filled up with
                    mountains untrodden, and undescribed by any English tourist. The only place
                    where they can be crossed is <placeName ref="pl3105">Bwlch Drws
                        Ardudwy</placeName> (the gap of the door of the district of Ardudwy), the
                    natural pass in the mountains; and Pennant is the only traveler I know who has
                    seen it.] His description of it is so remarkable that I transcribe it. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>'' I was tempted,'' says he, '' to visit this noted pass, and found the horror of
                    it far exceeding the most gloomy idea that could be conceived of it. The sides
                    seemed to have been rent by some mighty convulsion into a thousand precipices,
                    forming at their tops rows of shelves, which the peasants, comparing to the
                    ranges in a dove-cote, style <sic>Carreg-y-Clommenog</sic>, or the rock of the
                    Pigeons. The bottom of this passage is covered with a deluge of stones, which
                    have streamed from the sides; and along it is a narrow horse path, on the
                    slippery rock, formed by the removal of a few of the fragments which in other
                    places disposed into form of most steep and hazardous flights of steps."<note type="editorial"><hi rend="italic">Tours in Wales</hi>, II (1784) 122.
                        Pennant in fact has <hi rend="italic">Carreg y Klommenod</hi>. (Modern
                        spelling: <hi rend="italic">colommenod</hi>, doves or pigeons).</note>
                </p>
                <p>Between this mountainous tract and the sea, in the way from <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName>, to <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan-y-Bwlch</placeName>, is a slip of land which I believe, is never a mile
                    in <unclear>breadth</unclear><note type="editorial">Word cut off at
                    edge.</note></p>
                <p>This I rode along in my way to <placeName ref="pl1520">Harlech</placeName>; and
                    this must necessarily be well inhabited, if men existed at all in the country,
                    for beyond it nothing could live but a grouse.</p>

                <p> </p>
                <p>Letter 6<note type="editorial">Published in the <hi rend="italic">Monthly
                            Magazine</hi>, January 1816, 503-05.</note>
                </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>My Dear Brother <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName> Aug 18 1796</p>
                <p> </p>

                <p>When I had finished my last letter, not feeling disposed to join the company at
                    supper, I strolled down to the sea-side alone. A piece of Quixotism I should not
                    have ventured upon in my native part of the island of Great Britain; but I
                    believe the Welsh too honest to either attack my purse or my person. It was
                    between eight and nine o'clock. </p>
                <p>When I reached the sands I heard a loud hallowing and laughing, and seven young
                    girls, about fifteen or sixteen years of age, made their appearance. They
                    undressed to the last petticoat, amidst the highest mirth and gaiety, when one
                    of them stopped suddenly, fancying she heard a noise. While we were all
                    listening, three sailors ran towards us, and three of the girls dressed, and
                    declared they would not bathe, as the sailors would steal their cloaths. The
                    other four, still undressed, were hesitating to struggle with their disturbers,
                    when I offered to be the guardian of their apparel. They made up each her
                    bundle, while my presence scarcely kept the lads from interrupting them. I sat
                    down on one, and laid my arms over the other three, and the damsels ran into the
                    sea, whither their pursuers did not choose to follow them, at the expense of
                    wetting their shoes and trowsers. They were however, so daring that I had need
                    of all my vigilance to prevent their snatching away some of the cloaths.
                    [p.24]</p>
                <p>When the lasses had played and jumped some time in the sea, they ran out and,
                    squatting round me, each put on her flannel <hi rend="underline">chemise</hi>,
                    and dropped her wet petticoat. All care about their appearance was now at an
                    end; a scene of romps ensued between young men, who plundered, and girls, who
                    recovered, their different pieces of apparel; till, their toilette finished,
                    they formed into five couples, and began an English country dance. One of the
                    lasses supplied the music, though it was beyond my English ear to distinguish
                    any tune. The dancing was tolerable, and the dancers as <del>pleased and
                        happy</del>
                    <hi rend="subscript">^</hi><hi rend="superscript">delighted</hi> as ever was
                    lady at a ball. After two dances they gave over. Two of them came to me with
                    offered arms, and the spokeswoman told me that they were the daughters of poor
                    people in <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName>; that they worked and
                    spun all day, and at night they bathed and danced, that they were happy and
                    merry; and that it was a long established joke of the young men of their
                    acquaintance to follow them when they bathed, and to hide their cloaths. Though
                    tired with the labours and amusements of the day, they had the good nature to
                    offer to walk with me as far as I pleased, and one of them actually carried <hi rend="subscript">^</hi><hi rend="superscript">me</hi> through the splashes I
                    could not cross. </p>
                <p>The sight was new to me, and altogether, one of the most striking I had ever
                    seen. It something resembled a pantomimic dance at <persName ref="pe2189">Astley</persName>'s.<note type="editorial">In an early visit to London in
                        1780 Hutton wrote, ‘On Tuesday evening we were at Astley’s, where we saw
                        such tumbling as would have astonished you. You could not suppose the human
                        frame capable of such agility’. <hi rend="italic">Reminiscences of a
                            Gentlewoman</hi>, 24.</note> The scene was the black outline of the
                    mountain, the inequalities of its side not being discernable, and under it the
                    lodging houses of <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName>, illuminated at
                    almost every window. The stage, a fine even sand, with the moonlight playing on
                    a calm sea. The performers handsome ruddy young girls, who, with streaming hair
                    and half a covering, might well be taken for sea nymphs; and sturdy lads, whose
                    clumsy dark </p>
                <p>[p.25] </p>
                <p>blue jackets and trowsers, uncouth noises, and rude assaults, qualified them to
                    represent monsters. The piece concluded with a dance by the characters; but the
                    whole was as much superior to pantomime as nature is to art, or reality to
                    imitation. </p>
                <p>I have already said that the Welsh women are stout,[<del>xxx</del>] healthy, and
                    handsome; besides this they are honest, open, and friendly, and will render one
                    every assistance in their power. The better sort, I believe, are proud, heedless
                    of shewing their dislike, where they take any, and kind to those they fancy.
                    They are partial to their country, and resent any reflections upon it with a
                    warmth that one of them ingenuously called,<hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">when speaking of it</hi> to me, the <hi rend="underline">Welsh fever</hi>.<note type="editorial">Cf William Hutton, ‘To a Welchman,
                        every thing belonging to Wales carries in it the first excellence, and a
                        little contradiction will give, what they call the Welch fever.’ <hi rend="italic">Remarks upon North Wales</hi> (1803), 29.</note> But who,
                    that did not deserve reproof, would disparage the country to its natives; or
                    who, that had eyes to see, and a heart to feel, would speak contemptuously of
                        <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> at all. </p>
                <p>Of the Welsh men, I can say but little. They are not, in general, so handsome as
                    the women; and those of the common sort, I believe, to be lazy; while the women
                    are drudges. </p>
                <p>The distance between the gentry and the peasants is great in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>. It may be compared to our hills and
                    valleys. In <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>, it is still greater.
                    Perhaps I should not err if I said, as great as between their [<del>xxx</del>]
                    mountains and [<del>xxx</del>] glens. In <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>, as in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>, there
                    is a middle class, inhabiting the towns; but these approach much nearer the
                    lower than in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>, where commerce has
                    raised numbers, and enabled some to put themselves on a footing with their
                    neighbours, who have inherited large estates from their ancestors. </p>
                <p>The Welsh gentry all learn the language of the country from their nurses, before
                    they learn English; but they seldom speak it after they grow up, except to their
                    servants, and the peasants, who understand nothing else. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>[p.26] </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>In the last generation, a gentleman of <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>
                    kept open house at Christmas for a month. All his friends were welcome, and all
                    the friends they chose to bring. A gentleman, in the neighbourhood of <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName>, has entertained a hundred persons for a
                    week together, at that season, besides servants.<note type="editorial">The
                        Vaughans of Cors-y-Gedol Hall were until 1791 noted patrons of Welsh poets
                        and musicians. William Vaughan (1707-75), M.P. for Meirionydd was a friend
                        of the Morris brothers and the first President of the Honourable Society of
                        Cymmrodorion See <ref type="http" target="https://biography.wales/article/s-VAUG-COR-1250">here</ref>
                        However the direct line ceased in 1791, so they are unlikely to be the
                        gentry family described here, whose son organizes the convivial dinner at
                        the summer-house.</note> It is not to be imagined that he could lodge them
                    all at one time; but some slept, while others drank or danced, and each took his
                    turn to rest. One of the domestics was a harper, who wore the family livery, and
                    had fifteen guineas a year wages, when no other servant had more than five. [He
                    played in the hall constantly during the times of breakfast, dinner, and supper,
                    even when the family was alone].<note type="editorial">Inserted on strip of
                        paper.</note> The cost of stringing a harp is twenty three shillings; and
                    the annual expense to supply those <hi rend="subscript">^</hi><hi rend="superscript">strings</hi> that break is about five guineas. The
                    Christmas hospitality is no longer to be found in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>; but the harper is still retained in the great families,
                    and is introduced in the great inns. At <placeName ref="pl1240">Aberystwith</placeName>, and at <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName>, the company eat to the sound of the violin, as well
                    as the harp.<note type="editorial">For accounts of the harp playing which became
                        standard fare at many tourist inns during the period see Michael Freeman's
                        account <ref type="http" target="https://sublimewales.wordpress.com/material-culture/harpers/">here.</ref></note> It is the only time I do not like music; I cannot
                    attend to it, [<del>xxx</del>] amidst the clatter of knives and forks, and the
                    bustle of servants, and it only adds to the confusion.</p>
                <p>That the spirit of hospitality is not extinct in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>, I am a witness. The son of the gentleman above-mentioned
                    invited the whole company at the <placeName ref="pl1887">Cors y gedol
                        Arms</placeName>, to dinner, at a summer-house [---] bordering upon the sea.
                    His own grounds supplied mutton, [---] his farmyard poultry [---] in abundance,
                    and grouse the adjoining mountains. Beef is a luxury not always to be met with
                    in this country. It happened <hi rend="subscript">^</hi><hi rend="superscript">that</hi> an ox was killed in the neighbourhood; the gentlemen mounted his
                    horse, and rode after it, and was fortunate enough to secure a sirloin. The cook
                    sat up all night, <hi rend="subscript">^</hi><hi rend="superscript">with proper
                        assistants</hi>, roasting, boiling, baking, potting; and a cart was loaded
                    next day with baskets of provisions, hampers of wine and beer, and every
                    requisite for setting out a table; for the table </p>
                <p>[p. 27] </p>
                <p>only, and a set of chairs, was all the building afforded towards the repast.
                    Escorted by two maids, and two men, the cart marched to the summer house, which
                    was three miles distant from the mansion. We sat down, fourteen to dinner, and
                    eleven servants afterwards dined upon the grass.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>
                    <unclear>Dec<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> 26 1815</unclear></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><unclear>See p 23 for ????</unclear></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Letter 7<note type="editorial">Published in the <hi rend="italic">Monthly
                            Magazine</hi> (March, 1816), 109-1.</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>My Dear Brother <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName> Sept 2 1796</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>You will see by the date of this that I have left <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName>; but I shall not allow you to leave it till you are
                    acquainted with another excursion I made from thence. </p>
                <p>A Welsh lady,<note type="editorial">At present unidentified.</note> an open,
                    frank, kind hearted woman, with who<hi rend="subscript">^</hi><hi rend="superscript">m</hi> I had been on intimate terms at the <placeName ref="pl1887">Cors y gedol Arms</placeName>, pressed me much to accompany
                    her, when she returned home; and esteem for the lady, curiosity to
                        <del>see</del>
                    <hi rend="subscript">^</hi><hi rend="superscript">observe</hi> the domestic
                    economy of a Welsh mansion, and an opportunity it would give <hi rend="subscript">^</hi><hi rend="superscript">me</hi> to see <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y Bwlch</placeName> [-------], determined me to go. </p>
                <p>In my opinion of <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">the lady</hi> I could not be mistaken. I received all
                    that kindness and hospitality could bestow, during four days. With regard to the
                    style of <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">living</hi> I found little originality. The better sort
                    among the Welsh procure all their furniture and all their cloaths from
                        <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>, or <placeName ref="pl0002">Chester</placeName>. The only difference I saw between this family and one
                    of the same rank in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> was, that the
                    art are spinning their own beautiful chamber and bed linen was still practiced
                    here, and that the inferior servants spoke nothing but Welsh. I will now give
                    you an account of my ride to <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y Bwlch</placeName> in
                    which I was accompanied by a Welsh clergyman, carrying his wife behind him, his
                    sister riding single, and a young lady behind a servant. I assure you my </p>
                <p>[p.28]</p>
                <p> style of travelling is that of people of very great fashion in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>.</p>
                <p>At a short distance before we should have reached <placeName ref="pl1520">Harlech</placeName> we turned to the right, and after passing over high,
                    uncultivated, uninhabited moors, we descended the side of the mountain, and
                    entered a charming Woody glen. About three miles from the place where we quitted
                    the <placeName ref="pl1520">Harlech</placeName> road, we passed by <placeName ref="pl3100">Maesyneuadd</placeName>, the house of Mr Nanny,<note type="editorial">Either a reference to the recently-deceased William Wynn
                        (d.1795), who changed his name to Nanney for the purposes of inheritance; or
                        his son the Reverend John Nanney (d.1838). See <ref type="http" target="https://biography.wales/article/s-WYNN-NAN-1275.">here.</ref></note> built on the steep side of a mountain, but near its
                    base. Behind it rise woods, above these, cornfields; and, still higher, the
                    sterile summit, incapable of culture. Before it, are lawns, which the steep
                    descent of the ground has obliged to be cut into terraces; then the road; then a
                    mixture of wood and pasture, hill and glen. From a lake at top of the mountain
                    issues a small river, which, passing near the end of the house, forms a dozen
                    cascades in its way to the sea, rushing down a dell of rock and wood, and making
                    an opening, through which the sea is seen. </p>
                <p>The road beyond <placeName ref="pl3100">Maesyneuadd</placeName> and the grounds
                    about it, make me fancy I was in a gentleman's park, though it is the public
                    road from <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan-y-Bwlch</placeName>, [---] <placeName ref="pl1523">Ffestiniog</placeName>, and <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>,
                    for those who do not choose to ford the Traeths. Having passed the small lake,
                        <sic>Lllyn</sic>Tegwyn issa, and admired the village of <placeName ref="pl3099">Llantegwyn</placeName>, scattered on the side of a verdant hill
                    before us, and in the hollows or cwms about the bottom, we came to a horseblock,
                    an infallible sign on an old Welsh road, like the <hi rend="underline">Put-on</hi> or <hi rend="underline">Put-off</hi> on ours, that a steep hill
                    is at hand. It is not in going up the hills that the Welsh make use of the
                    horseblock; we therefore passed it, though I pitied my horse for carrying me up;
                    but in returning we found the advantage of it, for few choose to ride down their
                    hills, especially </p>
                <p>[29] </p>
                <p>if the horse carry two<hi rend="italic">.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Near the top of the hill is the <placeName ref="pl3197">church</placeName> of
                    Llantegwyn, with a Methodist meeting house for its neighbor.<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note> Perhaps its envied neighbour, for the
                    Methodists in this country are very numerous, and have pervaded every nook and
                    corner. I passed it on a Sunday; and, though no Methodist myself, was affected,
                    to hear their voices raised, in sweet and solemn concert, to sing their Maker's
                    praise; and, as I returned, in the interval between morning and evening service,
                    to see a crowd of decent rustics, too far from home to go and return again
                    making a frugal meal on the grass; or, having made it, soberly conversing with
                    each other. </p>
                <p>After a descent, we came to Llyn Tegwyn ucha, or the upper lake of Tegwyn, the
                    Fair and Lovely of Pennant.<note type="editorial">Pennant, <hi rend="italic">Tours in Wales</hi> (1784) II, 136.</note> It is larger than the lower,
                    being more than a mile in circumference; but it is, otherwise, neither <hi rend="underline">so</hi> fair or <hi rend="underline">so</hi> lovely, having
                    neither woods, fields or habitations, in view. It is very deep, embosomed in
                    lofty naked mountains, and, except by a road, just wide enough for a carriage,
                    and without a fence, cut along one side, and from five to fifteen yards above
                    the water, is inaccessible to man - unless, indeed, he be a Welsh man. </p>
                <p>I walked along this road under as hot a sun as ever shone in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>; and, fainting with thirst, I caught the
                    water that distilled from the rocks in the hollow of my hand, and warmed the
                    delicious beverage in my mouth before I durst swallow it. A little further ride
                    brought us to summit of a steep hill that overlooked the vale of <placeName ref="pl1523">Ffestiniog</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan-y-Bwlch</placeName>. </p>
                <p>Fertile meadows; a winding stream; a bridge; an inn, encircled by rocks and
                    woods, out of one of which rises a noble mansion; and these again encircled by
                    stupendous mountains, <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName> among the
                    number – such </p>
                <p>[30] </p>
                <p>is the celebrated vale of <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan-y-Bwlch</placeName>; and
                    such were the beauties I came to see. As I stood contemplating the vale, I
                    considered that I had a better view of it than if I were there. I might, indeed,
                    have seen a waterfall about half a mile from the foot of the hill; but
                    waterfalls had lost much of their consequence, owing to the dry weather; the
                    hill was nearly a mile to the bottom; to ride down it was impossible; and to add
                    it to my walks, in such intense heat, was risking my life. So I bade farewell to
                    the vale of <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan-y-Bwlch</placeName>, and returned the
                    way I came; for nothing but the birds of the air could have found another.</p>
                <p>This morning, early, we quitted <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName>, and
                    breakfasted at <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelleu</placeName>. [----------] I was
                    told at <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName>, that I had entered
                        <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> by a back way. Desirous to see the
                    highway, which my informer said was through <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName>, and
                        <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName>, we turned to the left at
                        <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelleu</placeName>, and are come eighteen miles
                    to this place. </p>
                <p>We followed the course of a river about nine miles: I believe the <placeName ref="pl3108">Onion</placeName>; but, in a matter of such uncertainty, I will
                    not positively affirm it. Many of these miles the road ran on the sides of steep
                    hills; wooded high above us, and down to the water's edge. At first the vale was
                    wide enough to admit of fertile pastures, on the other side of the river, before
                    the opposite barrier of mountains rose. These vanished by degrees. At five miles
                    we walked down to a crazy wooden bridge, above which the river forms a beautiful
                    cascade. At eight miles we come to <placeName ref="pl3109">Drws-y-Nant</placeName>, the Door of the Valley, where Howel Dha an old
                    Welsh legislator, is hung out to inform travellers that they are at liberty to
                    enter a decent <placeName ref="pl3111">house</placeName>. If they do, they may
                    find eggs</p>
                <p> [31]</p>
                <p> and bacon for themselves, and corn and hay for their horses. We declined the
                    invitation, but we had done wiser to have accepted the corn and hay part of it,
                    for 18 miles was an unmerciful stage for our horses. </p>
                <p>From <placeName ref="pl3109">Drws-y-Nant</placeName> the country assumes a ruder
                    form, the river vanishes, and the road is cut on the sides of lofty barren
                    mountains. It then goes over a long, though not a steep, hill, and reaches the
                    upper end of the <placeName ref="pl2101">pool of Bala</placeName>, the largest
                    lake in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>, being three miles and a half
                    in length, and from half to three-quarters of a mile in breadth.[----] We
                    travelled by its side; and at about half a mile before we arrived at the lower
                    end, we passed the <placeName ref="pl3198">church</placeName> of <placeName ref="pl3110">Llanycil</placeName>, to which the town of <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName> belongs, having, according to the custom of
                    the country, no church of its own. </p>
                <p>Standing at the lower end of the lake, and looking up this noble sheet of water,
                    the view is singular and romantic. The Pool is enclosed on three sides (the only
                    open one being that where we stand) by a range of hills, shooting down to the
                    very brink of the water, and either cultivated or covered with a wood. Behind
                    these rise rude and lofty mountains; and, at the upper end, the fence is triple,
                    for above, and beyond the rest, at the distance of twenty three miles, towers
                    the <placeName ref="pl1866">Cader Idris</placeName>, in all its majesty. </p>
                <p>The town of <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName> is about quarter of a mile
                    from the foot of the lake. It is a flourishing place, the prettiest I have seen
                    in the country, with one broad straight street, and two good inns. <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName> is the centre of <placeName ref="pl1221">North
                        Wales</placeName>, and roads lead from it to <placeName ref="pl1513">Dinasmowddû</placeName>, to <placeName ref="pl0741">Pool</placeName>,
                        <placeName ref="pl3196">Llanfyllin</placeName>, to <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName>, to <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>, to
                        <placeName ref="pl1523">Ffestiniog</placeName>, and to <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelleu</placeName>. <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName>
                    is the staple for knit woolen stockings, of which every woman in the country,
                    whether sitting, standing, or walking, is a manufacturer. In this </p>
                <p>[32] </p>
                <p>land of knitting, the women knit mechanically, without trouble or attention, and
                    so quick that one of them will make a stocking in a day worth half-a-crown.
                    This, after deducting a shilling, the value of the yarn, would make her daily
                    earnings eighteen pence, if it were not for the profit of the Bala merchant. I
                        saw,<hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">however</hi>, good coarse knit stockings, in a shop at
                        <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName>, at fifteen pence a pair; and was
                    told they <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">were to be</hi> had [---] as low as nine pence.</p>
                <p>I have frequently seen the women at <placeName ref="pl1240">Aberystwith</placeName> carrying a large pitcher of water on their heads,
                    and a child in a piece of woolen wrapped round their waists, and knitting at the
                    same time as they walked along the streets.<note type="editorial">Hutton was in
                        Aberystwyth with her invalid mother in 1787, and uses almost the same phrase
                        in a letter written then (<hi rend="italic">Reminiscences of a
                            Gentlewoman</hi>, 52). Many tourists comment on the industrious knitting
                        of Welsh women, most especially in the Bala area.</note>
                </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Letter 8<note type="editorial">Published in the <hi rend="italic">Monthly
                            Magazine</hi> (April, 1816) 205-07.</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> Sept.3.1796</p>
                <p>My Dear Brother</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>From <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName>, a distance of eleven miles, we found hills in the place
                    of mountains. The country is no longer romantic, and the road is rugged. Though
                    we follow the course of the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName> the whole
                    way, it is never visible (except at its coming out of <placeName ref="pl2101">Bala pool</placeName>) till we cross it, a mile before we reach <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName>. Spiteful hills intercept from our view the
                    delicious <placeName ref="pl3098">vale of Eidernion</placeName>, through which
                    it runs. We saw the entrance and the exit of a road that would have led us
                    through the vale, but, strangers as we were, we durst not attempt it. </p>
                <p>At a modest little <placeName ref="pl2463">inn</placeName>, with the interesting
                    sign of the Druid, we entered the great road of <placeName ref="pl1221">North
                        Wales</placeName>, leading from <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>
                    to <placeName ref="pl1018">Holyhead</placeName>, which will carry us to
                        <placeName ref="pl0740">Shrewsbury</placeName>. </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName> is a poor village between the
                        <placeName ref="pl1667">Berwyn</placeName> mountains on one hand, and the
                    mountains of Yale on the other; the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName>
                    running in the vale. Its situation on the high road maintains a tolerable inn,
                    the sign </p>
                <p>[33] </p>
                <p>of <persName ref="pe0495">Owen Glyndwr</persName>, the <placeName ref="pl3115"><sic>scite</sic> of whose habitation</placeName> is still pointed out,
                    on the banks of the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName> about three miles
                    below. </p>
                <p>At <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName> my eyes were gratified with the
                    sight of a steeple, a low square tower. All I had seen in the interior of
                        <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> resembled a chimney; and the
                    principal mark of distinction between a house and a church was, that the chimney
                    of the one was open at top to emit smoke, while that of the other was open on
                    the sides to shew a bell. </p>
                <p>From <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName>, we followed the windings of the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName>, between two ranges of mountains;<hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">frequently</hi> on [----] a high terrace, cut on their
                    side. The scenery was noble, and perpetually varying; but there are not words to
                    vary it on paper. I could tell you of approaching mountains, wooded hills [---],
                    verdant pastures, and a winding river; and of each of these you could form an
                    idea. Of their combination you could not. A very fine point of view is where a
                    tall, insulated, naked rock, with the ruins of <placeName ref="pl0794">Castle
                        Dinas Bran</placeName> on its top, seems to stop up the end of the vale. The
                    bed of the river is altogether the most rocky I ever saw, and nowhere more so
                    than at <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName>, where it is paved by
                    nature with huge flat stones. </p>
                <p>After a long descent, we reached <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName>,
                    where is a <placeName ref="pl1954">bridge</placeName> over the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName>, that must be crossed by those going to
                        <placeName ref="pl1246">Ruthin</placeName>. <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> is a low disagreeable town, in this scene of
                    enchantment. Its only inn displays the bloody hand of Sir Watkin.<note type="editorial">This is presumably now the Hand Hotel. In 1796 ‘Sir Watkin’
                        was the 5th Baronet of that title (1772-1840), and had sat as Tory M.P. in
                        the House of Commons for 2 years.</note> In <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>
                    <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">this gentleman</hi> has no other name. The master of the
                    house - I was going say - but I will rather call him the <hi rend="underline">man</hi> of the house - is a melancholy warning to<hi rend="underline">him
                        who standeth</hi>, to<hi rend="underline"> take heed lest he fall</hi><note type="editorial">A quotation from I Corinthians, 10:12: 'Wherefore let him
                        that thinketh he standeth take heed lest he fall' (KJV).</note>. For the
                    first six-and-thirty years of his life he drank nothing but water, and, though
                    never industrious, was decent in his manners. I should now depreciate a
                    respectable name of <hi rend="underline">Beast</hi>, if I were to call him</p>
                <p> [p.34] </p>
                <p>by it. Drunk as often as he can get liquor; mad when he is drunk, and abusive
                    when sober; his wife commands him, the waiter treats him with contempt, and the
                    maids return openly the curses he mutters between his teeth. </p>
                <p>It is impossible to be at <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> without
                    saying something of the ladies of Llangollen Vale; though, if you have seen an
                    account of them published in a news-paper I never saw, or read a poem of
                        <persName ref="pe1033">Miss Seward</persName>’s on this same subject, I
                    never read, you probably are better acquainted with them than myself.<note type="editorial">A newspaper report about the Ladies entitled ‘Extraordinary
                        Female affection’ appeared in the <hi rend="italic">St James Chronicle</hi>,
                        17-20 July 1790, with a shortened version in the <hi rend="italic">London
                            Chronicle</hi>, 20-22 July 1790, and an article entitled ‘Extraordinary
                        Affection’ in the <hi rend="italic">General Evening Post</hi> 24 July 1790.
                        (Information courtesy of Michael Freeman; see <ref type="http" target="https://sublimewales.wordpress.com/?s=Ladies+of+Llangollen">here.</ref>) See also Elizabeth Edwards (ed), E<hi rend="italic">leanor
                            Butler and Sarah Ponsonby, Account of a Journey in Wales; Perform’d in
                            May 1778 By Two Fugitive Ladies</hi> ( <ref type="http" target="https://editions.curioustravellers.ac.uk/pages/show.html?document=0004.xml">here</ref> ). For Anna Seward’s poem ‘Llangollen Vale’ (1796) see
                        Elizabeth Edwards, <hi rend="italic">English-Language Poetry from Wales
                            1789-1806</hi> (Cardiff: University of Wales Press, 2013).</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>All I have heard of the ladies of Llangollen Vale is, that they were too young
                    Irish women of noble families, who entered into a solemn renunciation of the
                    male part of the species; vowed an eternal friendship for each other; eloped
                    from their friends; and, after roving about some time in search of a situation
                    to their mind, settled in the vicinity of <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName>. The cottage they found built to their hands, and
                    they rent it at £20 the year; but they have expended a great deal of money in
                    improvements. The neatness of the inside is such as exceeds belief, and every
                    part of it is ornamented in a manner that could only be contrived and executed
                    by an women of the most elegant taste, who had no other employment. </p>
                <p>No man is ever admitted to speak to the ladies, but their relations, and their
                    gardener, who is a married man, and does not live in the house.<note type="editorial">This is overstating the case; the Duke of Wellington was
                        among several male visitors to Plas Newydd. See <ref type="http" target="https://sublimewales.wordpress.com/attractions/mansions-and-grounds/ladies-of-llangollen/descriptions-of-plas-newydd-and-the-ladies-of-llangollen/">here.</ref></note> They frequently receive visits from female friends,
                    and <persName ref="pe1033">Miss Seward</persName> has been of the number; but
                    they never lodge anybody. Their domestics are two women servants, besides one
                    they brought over with them, who is their <persName ref="pe2184">housekeeper</persName>, and on whom the ladies bestow such portion of their
                    esteem, that to affront her is to offend them. They are fond of their garden;
                    and an idea of their neatness maybe formed from its being confidently asserted,
                    though it is not true, that their walks</p>
                <p> [35] </p>
                <p>are swept with a hair broom. </p>
                <p>I was told by a gentleman who went over the house, some years ago, that a curious
                    box, covered with white sattin and embroidery, was seen in the dining room; and
                    on undrawing a curtain, an old fat lame lap-dog appeared, as the inhabitant: and
                    I am now informed, that Fidel has paid the debt of nature, and his tomb is shewn
                    to strangers, in the garden. Persons who have families, and live in the world,
                    laugh at this: to me it is very natural. Women must do something with their
                    affections; and what the ladies had to spare from each other, and their maid,
                    could not, in their situation, be better bestowed, than on an animal that was
                    sensible of their caresses, and returned their attachment. </p>
                <p>Here the ladies have lived fifteen years, and scandal has not dared to say, that
                    they have ever repented their vow. </p>
                <p>The outside of the cottage I saw; it is exquisitely neat and elegant, and
                    beautifully situated on an eminence, rising out of the vale and sheltered by the
                    mountains. The inside I might have seen; but I was told, that the frequent
                    exhibition of their house to strangers, had become troublesome to the ladies;
                    and I did not think it right to intrude upon them for my own gratification. </p>
                <p>My next walk was to the ruins of the Abbey of Llan Egwest, perhaps better known
                    to you, if you know it at all, by its Latin name <placeName ref="pl0785">Valle
                        Crucis</placeName>. It is a mile and a half from this place. I was very
                    minute in my enquiries concerning the road; as my father chose to visit the
                    castle of <placeName ref="pl0794">Dinas Bran</placeName> instead of the
                        <placeName ref="pl0785">Abbey</placeName>. My instructions were, to go along
                    the Ruthin road, till I came to a barley field, opposite a cottage, when I must
                    turn to the right, and was assured I could not miss my way. [---] I found the
                    cottage, saw the barley field, </p>
                <p>[p.36]</p>
                <p> turned to the right, and began to mount a steep hill. I was <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">certain</hi> I should have to go down again, as I never
                    knew a set of monks in my life that did not settle in a valley; and, after
                    toiling up more than half a mile, and seeing mountains still before me, I began
                    to doubt whether I was right. Fortunately there was a farm house near; I sent
                    the servant to inquire the way, and found I had to descend to the Ruthin road
                    again, and search for another cottage and another barley field further on. I
                    went back faster than I came, vexed at having spent my strength for nought, and
                    soon found the right barley field, which led me to a wood, and a steep winding
                    path <hi rend="subscript">^</hi><hi rend="superscript">down its side</hi> led me
                    to the <placeName ref="pl0785">Abbey</placeName>. </p>
                <p>It was not without reason that I judged well of the taste of monks. Of all the
                    situations I ever saw of the kind none has equalled this. A large level meadow,
                    as luxuriant as nature could form, or art improve it, intersected by a running
                    stream, skirted by rising woods, and surrounded by lofty mountains. There <hi rend="underline">may</hi> be, and, as part of the <placeName ref="pl0785">Abbey</placeName> is converted into a farm house, I suppose there <hi rend="underline">is</hi>, a road into it for a cart, but no such thing
                    appears. The very path by which I entered is not visible, and there seems no
                    transition from it but to the heavens.<note type="editorial">J.M.W. Turner’s
                        picture of the ruins in 1794/5 nicely captures this ethereal quality and the
                        farmyard (complete with pigs): see <ref type="http" target="https://www.tate.org.uk/art/artworks/turner-valle-crucis-abbey-with-dinas-bran-d00703">here.</ref></note> I never saw so delightful a retreat for religion,
                    love, or friendship, or any kind of enthusiasm or romance; and during the time
                    that the good fathers must necessarily wait before they could reach those
                    heavens, the auxiliary aid of the fertile soil was not a contemptible object. </p>
                <p>I could scarcely admire, as they deserved, the ruins of the <placeName ref="pl0785">Abbey</placeName>, for contemplating the beauties of its
                    situation; though the ruins are considerable, and the broken arches and Gothic
                    windows, <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">half hidden by trees, are</hi> very picturesque. The only
                    building in this sequestered Vale, besides the farmhouse above mentioned,
                    consists of two rooms in a barbarous taste, erected by the proprietor; </p>
                <p>[p.37]</p>
                <p> who occasionally retires to them to smoak his pipe. He should have made them a
                    grey [----] cottage, covered with ivy.<note type="editorial">Note in a later
                        hand – ‘Inserted in April Mag.<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>
                    1816’.</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> Letter 9<note type="editorial">Published in the <hi rend="italic">Monthly
                            Magazine</hi> (May, 1816) 304-306.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <placeName ref="pl0740">Shrewsbury</placeName> Sept 5th 1796</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>My Dear Brother,</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>From <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> the road still follows the
                    course of the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName>, and still runs along the
                    sides of the mountains. The vale is narrow, sometimes little more than the
                    breadth of the river; beautiful and fertile, though not quite so romantic as
                    above <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName>. Having travelled through
                    it about four miles, the hills enclosed it at the bottom, the river wound
                    between them, and the mountains on the left took a northerly course towards
                        <placeName ref="pl0002">Chester</placeName>. Our road turned suddenly to the
                    right, became an ordinary highway, and I lost, in a moment, the magnificent
                    scenery of <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>. How striking it must be to
                    enter the country on this road, and burst upon its beauties at once. </p>
                <p>Before we turned, we had a view of the house and woods of <placeName ref="pl0761">Winstay</placeName>, the seat of <persName ref="pe0941">Sir Watkin Williams
                        Wynne</persName>; and, when we had turned, of <placeName ref="pl1256">Chirk
                        Castle</placeName>, the seat of the Middletons. But, after rivers, rocks,
                    and mountains, stone and mortar interested me little, and even a park had lost
                    much of its effect; I looked at it now and then, as its beauties were pointed
                    out to me, but my mind rested on what I had left behind. About six miles from
                        <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> we passed through <placeName ref="pl3069">Chirk</placeName>, a large handsome village; but an assemblage
                    of red houses disgusted me. From thence we walked down a steep hill, crossed the
                    river Ceriog, on an elegant stone bridge, and set our feet in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>. </p>
                <p>You know me too well to suspect me of affectation. My disgust at brick buildings,
                    and my indifference for stone, were real; but I will own to you </p>
                <p>[p.38] </p>
                <p>that my feelings might have been influenced by circumstances. Place me, in a dark
                    night, in one of the terraces of the Vale of Llangollen, or, in a thunderstorm,
                    on the top of <placeName ref="pl1597">Bwlch oer Ddrws</placeName>, and I should
                    undoubtedly prefer the meanest brick house in <placeName ref="pl3069">Chirk</placeName>. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>[When our intended expedition was first mentioned to you, alarmed for the safety
                    of our father, who had not, of late, been accustomed to ride on horseback, and
                    whose horse had been more accustomed to harness than the saddle, you said, <hi rend="underline">we should curse <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName></hi>: Though I have little faith in modern prophets, the
                    expression sunk deep into my mind, already weakened by the recent loss of my
                    other parent. If I saw a stone in a road at which a horse might stumble, or an
                    object at which he might start, I thanked God that my father had passed it,
                    regardless that I had yet to pass it myself. [<del>xxxxx</del>] Having had this
                    dreadful load upon my mind during the whole journey, I was ready to go down upon
                    my knees, as I saw his horse take his last foot from the bridge, to thank God
                    that I should not curse <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>.
                </p>
                <p>The prediction having thus, happily, passed over our heads]<note type="editorial">Section pasted in on separate sheet.</note>, we now trotted on to
                        <placeName ref="pl1260">Oswestry</placeName>, where we dined; and, after
                    riding 10 miles further, through a pleasant country, we stopped at the
                        <placeName ref="pl3118">Old Pigeons</placeName>, at <placeName ref="">Nescliff</placeName>, which, but for the Pigeons, could not have been
                    distinguished from a farm house.<note type="editorial">‘At Ness-cliff, a cottage
                        stands under the hill / Where you with good chear, and good nature may fill,
                        / The landlady treats with the best in her power, / You think it abundant –
                        she wishes ‘twas more.’ Hutton, <hi rend="italic">Remarks on North
                            Wales</hi> (1803) 105. </note> Here the grand difficulty was to procure
                    beds; but, by the ingenious arrangements of the mistress of the house, and our
                    consenting to share one of the apartments with the malt and cheese already in
                    possession of it, it was at last got over. It was pleasant now to see the good
                    woman looking out at her best tablecloth, airing her best sheets, and taking
                    down, from her corner cupboard, odd china plates and figured jugs, whose general
                    business in the house was only to be looked at. </p>
                <p>While our supper was preparing, we walked up a steep, red, sandy rock, the cliff
                    from which the place takes its name. It rises alone out there plain, and seems
                    as if Nature, when she had been sowing rocks and mountains in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>, having an odd one left, dropped it here. It
                    commands a noble prospect into <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> and
                        <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>. We mounted to <placeName ref="pl1947">Kynaston's Cave</placeName>, which is twenty-five steps,
                    besides the ascent before we reach them.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1947">Kynaston's Cave</placeName> is cut in the rock; a hole in
                    the roof is all the chimney, and the door admits all the light; it is now the
                    comfortless dwelling of a labourer and his family, but it is said formally to
                    have been the retreat of <persName ref="pe2191">Henry Kynaston</persName>, a
                    noted robber, whose name it bears, and whose cipher, H. K. with the date, 1594,
                    cut into the rock, are still shown, in evidence of the tradition. From his
                    elevated nest, <persName ref="pe2191">Kynaston</persName> watched the plain
                    below, and when any traveller appeared, he pounced upon them, and subsisted on
                    their spoils. An inner apartment, which just holds the bed of the present
                    inhabitants, is said to have been <persName ref="pe2191">Kynaston</persName>'s
                    stable. I will not presume to dispute the fact, but his horse must have been
                    very docile, as well as very sure-footed, to have walked in safety up and down
                    the twenty-five steps. The rock rises considerably above the cave, and on summit
                    is <persName ref="pe2191">Kynaston</persName>'s garden, but night coming on, we
                    did not climb so high. </p>
                <p>On our return, the mistress of the Pigeons sent us in an excellent dish of peas
                    and bacon, a pot of hoarded sweetmeats, and a bason of cream. Here I saw the
                    first scarlet cloak since I left <placeName ref="pl1514">Llanfair</placeName>;
                    Blue is the colour of <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>. </p>
                <p>How little avail our resolutions! Whom should <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">I have</hi> believed that had told me six weeks back I
                    should go again to our inn at <placeName ref="pl0740">Shrewsbury</placeName>?
                    Impelled by gratitude to the woman who took us in, when all else denied us
                    admittance, to stop <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">there</hi> now was my own proposal; but the motive for
                    going was as fallacious as the resolve to go no more; for we have only
                    breakfasted, and we have eaten so heartily, and been charged so moderately, that
                    I verily believe she has lost by our bread and butter. </p>
                <p>You will now set me down where you took me up. The rest of the way you will know
                    too well to need any description of it from me. Whether the account of my
                    journey may have amused or interested you, I know not; at any rate, I will not
                    allow you to call me an idle traveller, for I have omitted nothing in my power
                    to accomplish.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>