<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0024">
   <teiHeader type="w">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Diary of the Welch Tour begun from Erthig
               <date>1766</date></title>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Edited with an introduction by Elizabeth Edwards</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>Hawarden</settlement>
                  <repository>Flintshire Record Office</repository>
                  <idno>D/E/1209</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <ab><locus/></ab>
               </msContents>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <!-- delete as appropriate -->
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <pb/>

            <p style="center">Diary of the Welch Tour begun from <placeName ref="pl1244">Erthig</placeName>, August the 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1766 – ended at
                  <placeName ref="pl1244">Erthig</placeName> Sep:<hi rend="superscript">tr</hi> the
                  5:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1766 –</p>

            <p>August 13 </p>
            <p>A <sic>Desert</sic> Ride from <placeName ref="pl1244">Erthig</placeName> to
                  <placeName ref="pl1246">Ruthin</placeName> – <placeName ref="pl1246">Ruthin</placeName> situated in the <placeName ref="pl1443">Vale of
                     <sic>Cluid</sic></placeName>; a most fertile Vale, twenty miles in length,
               three in breadth, fortified on three sides by Mountains, on the North side it sinks
               into a large plain bounded by the Irish Sea – on one of the Hills near <placeName ref="pl1246">Ruthin</placeName>, plain vestiges of a British Camp.<note type="editorial">The Clwydian Range near Ruthin is notable for a string of Iron
                  Age hillforts. Yorke may be referring particularly to Moel Arthur, one of the best
                  preserved examples; see <ref type="http" target="http://coflein.gov.uk/en/site/306899/details/moel-arthur-hillfort">here</ref></note>NB: Danced at the Assize Ball,<note type="editorial">Ball
                  timed to coincide with the assize court (regional court held
               periodically).</note></p>
            <p>14:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></p>
            <p>Remained at <placeName ref="pl1246">Ruthin</placeName>, and took a second Hop with
               Miss N: W:<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note></p>
            <p>Friday 15:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></p>
            <p>Went in the afternoon by <placeName ref="pl2080">Buchumbedd</placeName> (S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
               <persName ref="pe1339">Walter Bagot</persName>’s) to <placeName ref="pl1477">Denbigh</placeName> – The <placeName ref="pl1880">Castle</placeName> was built on
               a very strong, and extensive plan by <persName ref="pe1340">Lacy Earl of
                  Lincoln</persName> in <persName ref="pe1341">Edward the first</persName>’s time,
               by whom the Lordship of <placeName ref="pl1477">Denbigh</placeName>, and other large
               possessions in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> was granted to the Lacies –
               It devolved again to the Crown, and was given with the tithe of <placeName ref="pl1477">Denbigh</placeName> to <persName ref="0477">Dudley</persName>
               afterwards Earl of <sic>Liecester</sic>, prime Favourite to <persName ref="pe0357">Queen Elizabeth</persName> his Benefactress –<pb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Handsome Cathedral was begun to be erected by <add place="above">this</add>
               <persName ref="0477">Robert Earl of <sic>Liecester</sic></persName> within the Castle
               walls; His death interrupted the Completion of the plan<note type="editorial">A
                  reference to St David’s or Leicester’s Church, a ruined sixteenth-century church
                  in Denbigh that was never completed; see <ref type="http" target="http://coflein.gov.uk/en/site/93307/details/st-davids-or-leicesters-church-denbigh">here</ref></note> – He had finished the side Walls only and the great East
               Window, which still remain pretty entire – By the power of this Minister the See of
                  <placeName ref="pl1371">St Asaph</placeName> was to have been removed to
                  <placeName ref="pl1477">Denbigh</placeName> – Some letters still remain written by
                  <persName ref="pe1342">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Price</persName> a strong
               Partizan of <persName ref="pe0477">Dudley</persName>’s and one of his chief Agents in
               <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> – <persName ref="1342">Price</persName> having been guilty of many exactions
               &amp; numberless Oppressions, and fearing a just Retaliation in one <add place="above">of his</add> letters thus addresses <persName ref="0477">Dudley</persName> – In thee O Lord have I put my trust, let me never be
               confounded – <persName ref="pe1344">William the third</persName> granted the Lordship
               of <placeName ref="pl1477">Denbigh</placeName> together with other considerable
               powers to <persName ref="pe1345">W: Earl of Portland</persName> – this exorbitant
               Grant on a petition of the House of Commons he revoked, and otherwise rewarded his
               Favourite – The Chief Opposition<note type="authorial">Vide Life of Baron
                  Price.</note><note type="editorial">In 1695-6, the Denbighshire-born MP and lawyer
                  Robert Price (1655-1733) successfully opposed the king’s award of the lordships of
                  Denbigh, Bromfield and Yale to the Earl of Portland. Price’s speeches during the
                  affair were published in 1702 as <hi rend="italic">Gloria Cambriae; or the Speech
                     of a Bold Briton in Parliament against a Dutch Prince of Wales</hi>. The text
                  Yorke refers to here was published as <hi rend="italic">The Life of the Late
                     Honourable Robert Price, Esq</hi> in 1734.</note> and most spirited was given
               to this Grant by <persName ref="pe1350">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                  Price</persName> a Denbighshire Gentleman, afterwards one of the Barons of the
               Exchequer – </p>
            <pb/>
            <p>The <placeName ref="pl2082">Town Hall</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl1477">Denbigh</placeName> is well worthy looking in.</p>
            <p>From <placeName ref="pl1477">Denbigh</placeName> we proceeded in the evening by
                     <sic><placeName ref="pl1560">Bucheigrigg</placeName></sic>
               <persName ref="pe1378">S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thomas Salusbury</persName>’s
               (leaving <placeName ref="pl1262">Llanerch</placeName>
               <persName ref="pe1403">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Davies</persName>’s on the
               left) to Mr Williams of <sic><placeName ref="pl1268">Boddlewiddan</placeName></sic>,
               as one of the most Hospitable Stations for a wearied Traveller to rest at in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>; I
               shall never fail to recommend any of my friends to so comfortable a place – </p>
            <p>Saturday 16:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></p>
            <p>Surveyed the Ruins of <placeName ref="pl1978">Rhuddlan Castle</placeName> (within two
               miles of <placeName ref="pl1268">Boddlewiddan</placeName>) originally built by
                  <persName ref="pe1365">Henry the 2:<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi></persName> but
               improved by <persName ref="pe1341">Edward the 1:<hi rend="superscript">st</hi></persName> who held here a Parliament to settle the Government of the
               subdued Country of <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName><note type="editorial">A reference to the Statute of
                  Rhuddlan, issued by Edward I in 1284, which was intended to settle the government
                  of Wales after the deaths of the Welsh princes Llywelyn and Dafydd ap Gruffydd in
                  1282-3. The Statute, which declared that Wales had been annexed to England,
                  introduced English law to native Welsh law.</note> – the Name signifies, the Red
               Place, pointing to the Situation of <placeName ref="pl1305">Rhuddlan</placeName>,
               which stands on a red Bank above the River Cluid, here navigable for
                  <sic>vessells</sic> of large Burden – One of the most pleasing of our Old Welch
               Tunes is called Morva Rhuddlan<note type="editorial">The tune ‘Morfa Rhuddlan’ has
                  been used in harp music, as a dance, and set to words on numerous occasions. See
                  Phyllis Kinney, <hi rend="italic">Traditional Welsh Music</hi> (Cardiff:
                  University of Wales Press, 2011), p. 48. For a representation of the tune, see
                     <ref type="http" target="http://www.folktunefinder.com/tunes/176827">here</ref></note> (id est) Rhuddlan Marsh; alluding to a very memorable
                  <sic>battel</sic> fought here in early Times; it is said to have been composed as
               an Elegy and lamentation over the Slain; indeed the Musick very much echoes this
               sense-------</p>
            <pb/>
            <p>Went to <placeName ref="pl1561">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Asaph
                  Cathedral</placeName>, small but kept in neat repair, and originally well built –
               The <persName ref="pe2038">Bishop</persName> hath the most numerous Patronage of any
               of his Brethren – After dinner at <placeName ref="pl1268">Bottlewiddan</placeName>
               proceeded by [three words illegible] Ferry to <placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName> where we lay this night.</p>
            <p>Monday 18:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></p>
            <p>Viewed with pleasure and amazement the noble ruins of <placeName ref="pl1530">Conway
                  castle</placeName>, built (with many other strong Fortresses) by <persName ref="pe1341">Edward the first</persName>, to awe his new conquered Subjects – The
               Town of <placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName> [illegible – cancelled word] hath
               sprung up within the outward walls of the <placeName ref="pl1530">Castle</placeName>,
               originally those that inclosed the Castle Yard, tho ignorantly supposed to have been
               built as a security to the Town; some Seats immediately on the opposite shore of the
               River – <placeName ref="pl1973">Marl</placeName>
               <persName ref="pe1366">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Prendergast</persName>’s,
                     <sic><placeName ref="pl1974">Bodsgallan</placeName></sic>
               <persName ref="pe1698">Miss Wynne</persName>’s, now <persName ref="pe1698">Lady
                  Mostyn</persName>, and <sic><placeName ref="pl2089">Gloddath</placeName></sic>,
                  <persName ref="pe0015">S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Roger Mostyn</persName>’s –
               Dined this day at the <placeName ref="pl2090">Eagles</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>, a House of a mean Appearance, but of very good
               Accomodations [sic] – <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName> is remarkable for
               a <placeName ref="pl1531">bridge</placeName> the Work of <persName ref="pe1159">Inigo
                  Jones</persName>, the center Arch remaining in the </p>
            <pb/>
            <p><sic>in the</sic> State he left it, is worthy of his extensive Genius; the two
               smaller Arches having been in the eye of the Country since repaired, their original
               Beauty is much impaired – The Original name of this very extraordinary Genius was
               Unner ap Jones; he was born near <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>, and
               was early encouraged in the study of Architecture by <persName ref="pe1369">S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Richard Wynne</persName> of <sic><placeName ref="pl1532">Gwider</placeName></sic> near <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName> Bart, Treasurer to Henrietta Maria Queen of Charles the
               first – By the munificence of this Gentleman, Jones was supported in his travels, and
               afterwards recommended to the notice of Charles the 1:<hi rend="subscript">st</hi>.
               In Italy he drop’d his British appellation of Unner ap Jones, and received the name
               of Inigo – Two small Chapels were built by him for <persName ref="pe1369">S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Richard Wynne</persName>, one at Gwider,<note type="editorial">Possibly a reference to the private chapel at Gwydir Uchaf,
                  though this was not built until later in the seventeenth century; see <ref type="http" target="http://coflein.gov.uk/en/site/43667/details/chapel-of-holy-trinitygwydir-chapelcapel-gwydir-uchaf-llanrychwyn-llanrwst">here</ref></note> the other at <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>
               before he left <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> – you would distinguish neither as the Work of <persName ref="pe1159">Inigo Jones</persName>; In the Chapel at <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>, <persName ref="pe1369">S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                  Richard Wynne</persName> put up a Marble with the </p>
            <pb/>
            <p>following Inscription:<note type="editorial">For a photograph of this monument,
                     see<ref type="http" target="http://www.oldukphotos.com/churchphotos/images/Wales/Caernarfonshire,%20Llanrwst,%20Gwydir%20Chapel%20-%20the%20royal%20lineage%20of%20the%20Wynn%20Family.jpg">here</ref></note> I could easily anticipate the Comment every Englishman (I
               should have said Saxon) will make thereon – Take the following however as a true and
               authentick Copy – </p>
            <p>This Chapel was erected Anno Domini 1633 By <persName ref="pe1369">S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Richard Wynne</persName> Bart: of <placeName ref="pl1532">Gwidr</placeName> in the County of <placeName ref="pl1565">Carnarvon</placeName>, Treasurer to the High and Mighty Princess <persName ref="pe0601">Henrietta Maria</persName> Queen of England, daughter to <persName ref="pe2039">Henry the 4:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></persName> King of France
               and wife to our Sovereign <persName ref="pe2040">King Charles</persName> – Where
               lieth his Father Sir <persName ref="pe0321">John Wynne</persName> of <placeName ref="pl1532">Gwidr</placeName> in the County of <placeName ref="pl1565">Carnarvon</placeName> Knight and Baronet, Son and Heir to <persName ref="pe2041">Maurice Wynne</persName>, Son and Heir to <persName ref="pe2042">John
                  Wynne</persName>, Son and Heir to <persName ref="pe2043">Meredith</persName>,
               which three lieth buried in the <placeName ref="pl2859">Church of
                  Dolwyddelan</placeName>, with Tombs over them. This <persName ref="pe2043">Meredith</persName> was Son and Heir to Evan,<note type="editorial">For an
                  overview of the Wynn family, including some of the members of the family listed in
                  the following section of this tour, see <ref type="http" target="https://biography.wales/article/s-WYNN-GWY-1300">here</ref></note> son
               and Heir to Robert, son and Heir to Meredith, son and Heir to Howell, son and Heir to
               David, son and Heir to Griffith, son and Heir to Caradock, son and Heir to Thomas,
               son and Heir to <persName ref="pe2045">Roderick Lord of Anglesey</persName>, son to
                  <persName ref="pe0641"><sic>Owen Gwinedd</sic></persName> [sic] Prince of Wales,
                  <add place="above">(David)</add> who married <persName ref="pe2046"><hi rend="underline">Emma</hi> Plantagenet</persName> Sister to <persName ref="pe1365">King Henry</persName> the second – There succeeded this <hi rend="underline"><persName ref="pe2044">David</persName></hi> three Princes; His
               nephew</p>
            <pb/>
            <p>NB: The Inheritance of <placeName ref="pl1532">Gwidr</placeName>, now valued at 5000L
               per Annum or more, passed by a Daughter to the Marquis of Lindsey, and is now held by
               their immediate Descendant – the present <persName ref="pe2050">Duke of
                  Ancaster</persName></p>
            <note type="editorial">This authorial note in the manuscript will be found on the facing
               page to the following text.</note>
            <pb/>
            <p><persName ref="pe2047">Leolinus Magnus</persName>, who married <persName ref="pe2048">Jane</persName> Daughter to <persName ref="pe2049">King John</persName>; David
               his Son, Nephew to <persName ref="pe2051">King Henry</persName> the third; and
               <persName ref="pe2022">Leoline</persName> the last Prince of <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> of that House
               and Line, who lived in <persName ref="pe1341">King Edward</persName> the first’s
               time. S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
               <persName ref="pe0321">John Wynne</persName> married <persName ref="pe2053">Sydney</persName> (who lieth buried here, the daughter of S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
               <persName ref="pe2052">William Gerard</persName> Knight Lord Chancellor of Ireland)
               by whom he had Issue S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
               <persName ref="pe2054">John Wynne</persName>, who died at <placeName ref="pl2860">Lucca</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl1164">Italy</placeName>, Sir <persName ref="pe1369">Richard Wynne</persName> now living, Thomas Wynne who lieth here,
               Owen Wynne<note> For further members of the Wynn family, mentioned in this passage,
                  see <ref type="http" target="https://biography.wales/article/s-WYNN-GWY-1300">here</ref></note> now living, Robert Wynne who lieth here, Roger Wynne who
               lieth here, William Wynne now living, Maurice Wynne who lieth here, Ellis Wynne who
               lieth buried at <placeName ref="pl2861">Whitford</placeName> in the County of Flint,
               Henry Wynne now living, Roger Wynne who lieth here, and two Daughters – <persName ref="pe3056">Mary</persName> now living married to S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
               <persName ref="pe2055">Roger Mostyn</persName> in the County of Flint Knight, and
                  <persName ref="pe2058">Elizabeth</persName> now living, married to S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
               <persName ref="pe2057">John Bodvil</persName> in the County of <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> Knight.</p>
            <pb/>
            <p>Tuesday 19:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></p>
            <p>Sailed down the <placeName ref="pl2384">River Conway</placeName> from Trevern (within
               a mile of <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>) and made it twelve miles to
                  <placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName> – This <placeName ref="pl2384">River</placeName> flows through a deep and narrow Vale, shut in on each side by
               very high and craggy Rocks, in some few places however softening into Wildness, with
               Birch and other Shrubs crawling up their sides – When I looked up to these Rocks from
               the <placeName ref="pl2384">River</placeName> (which washes their Base) <persName ref="pe0494">Shakespeare</persName>’s description of Dover Cliff immediately
               occurred – </p>
            <p>There is a Cliff whose high and bending Head</p>
            <p>Looks fearfully on the confined deep.<note type="editorial">A reference to
                  Shakespeare’s King Lear, Act 4, Scene 1, where Gloucester contemplates committing
                  suicide at Dover (‘There is a cliff, whose high and bending head looks fearfully
                  in the confined deep: Bring me to the very brim of it, and I’ll repair the misery
                  thou dost bear’).</note></p>
            <p>Returned at night to our good Host Mr Ellis<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note> of <sic><placeName ref="pl2096">Keffdu</placeName></sic> – I
               should have remarked that the <placeName ref="pl2384">River Conway</placeName>
               becomes navigable within 14 miles of its rise; it is <del>indeed</del> a tide River,
               of considerable width and depth.</p>
            <p>Wednesday 20:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></p>
            <p>Visited the Cataracts <sic><placeName ref="pl2851">Rhaidr y Wanol</placeName></sic>,
               and <placeName ref="pl2852">Rhaidr yr Pandy</placeName> Penmachno, both within six
               miles of <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName> – They are both so very
               extraordinary, that I fear</p>
            <pb/>
            <p><del>as</del>
               <add rend="above">lest</add> my Description, the nearer it approaches the Truth may
               be thought the further to wander from it – <placeName ref="pl2851">Rhaidr yr
                  Wanol</placeName> is a long continued <add rend="above">River and</add> Cataract,
               tearing through an excavated Rock, formed into its Channel; in many places the
               Channel breaks very abruptly, and creates numerous and delightful Falls; – On all
               sides, this River is enclosed by high Rocks covered with low Shrubs that make a
               beautiful <sic>accompanyment</sic> of Wood to the several Cascades – </p>
            <p><placeName ref="pl2852">Rhaidr yr Pendy</placeName> Penmachno is a Curiosity no less
               extraordinary, tho much differing from the other – Here amidst an Amphitheatre of
               stupendous Rocks, the Rivers Machno and <placeName ref="pl2384">Conway</placeName>
               join their Streams: The Course of the Machno, I followed up for some way, climbing
               and scrambling from one vast stone to another, that obstruct the very narrow</p>
            <pb/>
            <p>Channel of the River, which from the vicinity of the Impending Rocks on each side can
               never be widened – The Stones I am speaking of, are hollowed and worn into a vast
               variety of whimsical Cavities, others again diminish’d to Porridge pots, some by the
               continual eating of the Water formed into a sort of Arches, and supported by Rude
               Pillars; under these the clearest, and most living Water I e’er beheld trickles – To
               compleat this most Romantick Scene (upon the summits and brows of the Rocks that I
               have observed rise perpendicularly from the River) grow some large Trees; these take
               up and arch the space from Rock to Rock, and with a considerable shade overhang and
               darken the Channel below – </p>
            <p>Returned this night and lay at <placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName>
               --------</p>
            <pb/>
            <p>Thursday 21:<hi rend="superscript">st</hi></p>
            <p>Travelled on over the sands to <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName>, made there
               an inconsiderable stay – The <placeName ref="pl2025">Cathedral</placeName>
               indifferent, but the See valuable. Reached <placeName ref="pl1565">Carnarvon</placeName> by dinner and danced that night at the Assembly.</p>
            <p>Friday 22:<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi></p>
            <p>Remained at <placeName ref="pl1565">Carnarvon</placeName>, dined with Counsellor
                  Williams<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note> (a Hospitable Soul) and
                  repe<add place="above">ate</add>d a second dose at the Ball, the first I had been
               at within ten days, having <add place="above">besides</add> thro’ necessity escaped
               one at <placeName ref="pl1246">Ruthin</placeName> – </p>
            <p>23:</p>
            <p>Walked over the striking Ruins of <placeName ref="pl1565">Carnarvon</placeName>, the
                  <placeName ref="pl1566">Castle</placeName>, and Walls, originally those as at
                  <placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName> inclosing the Castle Yard – the
               distinction between the Castles of <placeName ref="pl1530">Conway</placeName> and
                  <placeName ref="pl1566">Carnarvon</placeName> seems to be – that the latter being
               intended as the immediate residence of the Prince of <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> (where were fixed his
               different Courts of Judicature and Revenue, as also his Mint) was built more <add place="above">for</add> habitation and bears more the Air of a Palace – <placeName ref="pl1530">Conway</placeName> on the </p>
            <pb/>
            <p>contrary is more of a Fortress and in that respect exceeds <placeName ref="pl1566">Carnarvon</placeName> in natural and artificial strength</p>
            <p>Sunday 24:<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></p>
            <p>Sailed down the <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName>; about 14 miles – dined at <sic><placeName ref="pl1965">Plasnewidd</placeName></sic>
               <persName ref="pe1371">S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> R: Bayley</persName>’s (a fine
               situation on the rising Banks of the <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai</placeName>
               fringed with Wood) passed <placeName ref="pl2853">Baldon Ferry</placeName> in most
               wretched Weather, and reached <placeName ref="pl1565">Carnarvon</placeName>
               benighted, and dreadfully soaked</p>
            <p>Monday 25:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></p>
            <p>Passed <placeName ref="pl2097">Tan yr Voila Ferry</placeName> and took a delicious
               Ride (the <placeName ref="pl1093">Angelsea</placeName> side of the River) to
                  <placeName ref="pl1965">Plasnewidd</placeName>, along a beautiful
                  <sic>Terras</sic>, commanding a noble view of the Mouth of the <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai</placeName>, the Walls, and Castles of <placeName ref="pl1565">Carnarvon</placeName> (the Town happily appearing to be lost, and <add place="above">the</add> outward Walls appearing as in their original state and
               [?meaning]) the dead Flat of <placeName ref="pl1093">Angelsea</placeName> on one side
               contrasted by the View of the Carnarvonshire Hills (particularly <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>) on the other ------</p>
            <pb/>
            <p>Tuesday 26:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of August – </p>
            <p>Passed <sic><placeName ref="pl2098"><sic>Porthithway</sic></placeName></sic> Ferry,
               and ride through Welch Roads, and a bad Country to <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName> – <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName> situated on
               a Flat very near the Sea, is flanked with double Walls battlemented, and with Towers.
               The Town is small but well built: Within the <placeName ref="pl1968">Castle</placeName> is a Chapel with vau˄lted Arches, which remains very entire;
               there are several small recesses with windows towards the Chapel which we concluded
               were private Confessional Closets – There appears to have been a noble Room of State
               up one Story – the whole is a fine Ruin – <placeName ref="pl1964">Baron
                  Hill</placeName> (<persName ref="pe1232">Lord Bulkeley</persName>’s Seat) lies a
               mile from hence – the House is a vast pile, without Convenience, without beauty of
               uniformity; the Situation is noble, commanding the mouth of the <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai</placeName>, and a fine Back Ground of the Carnarvonshire
               Mountains and Rocks – the view is said to be very similar to that of <placeName ref="pl2854">my Lord Edgcumbe</placeName>’s in <placeName ref="pl0766">Cornwall</placeName>.</p>
            <pb/>
            <p>Tuesday 26:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> In the morning</p>
            <p>Remained at <placeName ref="pl1565">Carnarvon</placeName>, walked to view the old
               Walls, which are said to be the Ruins of <placeName ref="pl2023">Segontium</placeName> a Roman Station – the River still retains the name of
               Seiont, and about a quarter of a mile from hence near its mouth washes the sides of
                  <placeName ref="pl1565">Carnarvon</placeName>; to build which Edward the 1:<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> is said to have employed the then considerable Ruins
               and Materials of the Old Town of <placeName ref="pl2023">Segontium</placeName>.</p>
            <p>Wednesday 27:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></p>
            <p>Took a Guide from <placeName ref="pl1565">Carnarvon</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName> in our way thither passed by <sic><placeName ref="2855">Bettus Garmon</placeName></sic>, no ways remarkable, then by
                  <placeName ref="pl2856">Pont-Cerrig yr Rud</placeName> (a beautiful Cascade) to
                     <sic><placeName ref="pl1526">Lynn Quellin</placeName></sic>, an extensive and
               transparent Lake. The Banks of this Lake slope gently off, not unlike the Flintshire
               downs; this softness soon vanishes; in the back Ground close upon them press some
               high Hills, and craggy Rocks, down whose rugged sides roared innumerable Cataracts,
               supplying the Lake below – These Falls are indeed temporary; the Weather being very
               rainy (which we did not regret) the falls were in high perfection.</p>
            <pb/>
            <p>[facing page – ie facing page beginning ‘Near one of the Rocks’]</p>
            <pb/>
            <p>NB – </p>
            <p>Our design was to have ascended <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>, but the
               Weather would not permit – the Easiest ascent (and best Road from <placeName ref="pl1565">Carnarvon</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>)
               is by the Lakes of <sic><placeName ref="pl1527">Llanberris</placeName></sic> [sic] – </p>
            <pb/><note type="editorial">This authorial note in the manuscript will be found on the facing
               page to the following text.</note>
            <p>Near one of the Rocks (I before mentioned) called <sic><placeName ref="pl2857">Castel
                     Cidum</placeName></sic> is a very extraordinary Echo – To paint truly the ride
               between <placeName ref="pl1526">Lynn Quellin</placeName> and <sic><placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelart</placeName></sic>, you may well use two lines of
                  <persName ref="pe2059">Churchill</persName> –</p>
            <p>Far as the Eye could stretch no tree was seen</p>
            <p>Earth clad in russet scorn’d the lively Green<note type="editorial">A quotation from
                  Charles Churchill, <hi rend="italic">The Prophecy of Famine. A Scots Pastoral</hi>
                  (London: G. Kearsley,1763), p. 15.</note></p>
            <p><placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgellart</placeName> we were told was formerly the site of
               a Monastery tho no traces are now to be seen; the <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgellart</placeName> Monks (contrary to the general use of their Fraternity)
               were very abstemious in the choice of this their Situation; it hath neither richness
               of Soil, nor indeed any one of the comforts of Life to recommend it: We roosted this
               night at <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgellart</placeName> –</p>
            <p>Thursday 28:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></p>
            <p>Rose very early having indeed little temptation to lye in bed, and set out with a
               Guide for <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y Bwlch</placeName> – a mile and half from
                  <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgellart</placeName> we passed <placeName ref="pl1525">Pont Aber Glaslin</placeName> – This is a Curiosity by no means to be omitted in
               the tour of <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> – It is a natural rocky semicircular Dam making a very full and
               noble Fall;</p>
            <pb/>
            <p>Just below the Cascade stands a <placeName ref="pl1525">bridge</placeName> of one
               handsome Arch – The Spring Tides of the Sea terminate at this place, and bring up
               Salmon which leap up the Dam, and go up the River to spawn. During our short stay on
               the <placeName ref="pl1525">Bridge</placeName> we saw two or three Salmon leap – the
               River is called Nanwynan; Its Channel by <placeName ref="pl1525">Pont Aber
                  Glaslin</placeName> is filled with immense stones, which seem to be fragments of,
               and to be broken off the perpendicular rocks which rise from the River on either
               side. We proceeded on through a most wild and desolate Country, totally uncovered
               with soil or Herbage in many parts, but absolutely paved with Rocks – I cannot omit
               an observation made by one of the Servants (a Country Lout) on the inhospitable
               Prospect before us. Sure Sir, quoth the Bumpkin, this Country must be very old. Why
               so Jack. I think Sir, tis quite worn to the Bones – After having pursued thus our
               Journey for ten miles, we suddenly broke on <persName ref="pe1374">Mr
                  Griffith</persName>’s of <placeName ref="pl1570">Tan yr Bwlch</placeName> – The
               Strong Contrast this Spot bears to the Country we had been before too long accustomed
               to, surprized us most</p>
            <pb/>
            <p>agreeably; It is a mountain (rising in the form of a Pyramid) to a very considerable
               Height, and is covered with good Timber; Craggy Rocks, bosomed high in tufted Trees
               overtop these Woods – the House which stands in the Centre of these Woods, commands a
               view of the Vale of Dyffryn Bwlch Coed, through which the River Rhydd Agored winds
               itself most beautifully, till it is at last lost between two Rocks under a Wood, and
               the Arch of a Bridge:<note type="editorial">For a series of images illustrating Plas
                  Tan y Bwlch in its surroundings, see <ref type="http" target="https://coflein.gov.uk/en/site/28687/details/plas-tan-y-bwlch-bwlch-coed-dyffryn-snowdonia-national-park-study-centre">here</ref></note> It is much to be lamented that Nature hath been so blindly
               bountiful to a set of Animals equally void of Gratitude and understanding to assist
               her, or take any advantage of her Favours – A Moderate degree of Taste and very
               little labour render <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan yr Bwlch</placeName> one of the most
               delicious spots my Eyes ever behold, or my Imagination can paint; But Alas! the Woods
               are impervious, and all those beautiful Points, from whence you might reasonably
               expect the most charming Views are shut up in utter darkness and Oblivion
               -----------</p>
            <pb/>
            <p>Friday 29:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></p>
            <p>We designed going to <placeName ref="pl1520">Harlech</placeName> and <sic><placeName ref="pl1594">Crickaith</placeName></sic> to see the Castles at those places,
               but were deterred by the Weather; We made a short excursion to Lynn yr Rhaiddy,<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note> a Cataract well worth seeing; it empties
               itself into a Pool of a very considerable depth; the Country people assert that it
               hath no bottom – This Day turned out very rainy, and we were driven back to our
                  bed<note type="authorial">A very comfortable one – – </note> Station (<placeName ref="pl1571">Tan yr Bwlch</placeName>) <sic>were</sic> we were locked up the
               remainder of this day.</p>
            <pb/>
            <p>Saturday 30:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></p>
            <p>The Weather at length permitting us to creep our of our Holes, we proceeded to
                  <placeName ref="pl1523">Festiniog</placeName>, a mean Village, with one very
               tolerable publick House – Near this place are three Cataracts – viz: <sic>Kynant
                  Velin</sic>, <sic>Kynant Cwm</sic>, and <sic>Pistil Du</sic><note type="editorial">Probably a reference to Rhaeadr Du, falls on the Afon Gamlan in Snowdonia.</note>
               – The first within half a mile of <placeName ref="pl1523">Festiniog</placeName> we
               saw, more the Cascade than the Cataract; Kynant Cwm was represented to us as one of
               the finest in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>, and the last was said to be worth seeing – Our Ride from
                  <placeName ref="pl1523">Festiniog</placeName> was desert like till we came within
               four </p>
            <pb/>
            <p>Miles of <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelly</placeName>, the Country altering very
               agreeably, being composed of Deep dark Dells, Rushing Rivers, and cultivated Brows –
               Under this description the beautiful part of <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> (as I think) falls – <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelly</placeName> is situated in a pleasant narrow Vale, by the
               side of a good River with a handsome bridge over it; it is closely encompassed on all
               sides by gently rising Hills covered with Wood – In the back Ground to the South
               rises the second Mountain of <placeName ref="pl1221">North Wales</placeName> called <placeName ref="pl1866">Cader-Idris</placeName> viz. Arthur’s Chair.</p>
            <p>Sunday 31:<hi rend="superscript">st</hi></p>
            <p>Rose at four in the morning and mounted to the very Pinnacle of <placeName ref="pl1866">Cader Idris</placeName> which sharp point is called the Cader or
               Chair – It is a mighty Hill, and commands in fine Weather (which may only be expected
               in the Months of May and June) a most extensive View; we could see little in
               perfection, thick Clouds encompassing us on all sides – It employed us six hours in
               going and returning from this Hill. From <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelly</placeName>
               continued our Journey by Pont Newidd<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note></p>
            <pb/>
            <p>a Bridge of one Arch (very well worthy Observation) to Pont Drws Nant (a comfortable
               [?Cottage]) from thence taking the Right Hand side of Lake <sic><placeName ref="pl2101">Lyntegid</placeName></sic> [sic], proceeded on to <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName> – This lake is a most noble <sic>peice</sic> of
               Water, three miles in length, and in some parts one in breadth, remarkable clear as
               signified (Wallice) by its name – The Rivers Avon yr Pandy and <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName> besides many inconsiderable Springs and Rivulets from
               the neighbouring Hills, supply this charming Lake – Where the Lake ends, is the first
               bridge on the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName>, which River becomes early
               considerable from the Assistance of so noble a Reservoir. I must somewhere observe
               and I may as well do it here that the Bridges in <placeName ref="pl1221">North
                  Wales</placeName> are universally well if not finely built – The Piers and
               Buttresses of every Arch are often fixed on the Rock which in many places very
               [?apropos] rises above the bed of the River – I could mention several immediately
               under this description -----------</p>
            <p><placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName> famous for Woollen Stockings – </p>
            <pb/>
            <p>Monday Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 1:<hi rend="superscript">st</hi></p>
            <p>Proceeded on by <placeName ref="pl2858">Llandrillo</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName>, one of the sweetest Rides in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>; It would be
               supererogation in me to enter into a minute detail of the Charms of this Ride; The
               following Letter (written as I have very good Reason to believe by one of our Party)
               under the description of the View from <sic>Keven Ucha</sic>, particularly points out
               the similar Beauties of the Country between <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName> by <placeName ref="pl2858">Llandrillo</placeName>. <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName> Romantickly situated under a Rock which almost
               overhangs and threatens a part of the Town: In our Road from <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> along the
               steep Banks of the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName> passed <sic><placeName ref="pl1258">Glendowrdy</placeName></sic>, the Estate and Seat of that Old
               Conjurer and Arch Rebel <persName ref="pe0495">Owen Glendower</persName> (as
                  <persName ref="pe0494">Shakespeare</persName> calls him) properly Owen of
                  <placeName ref="pl1258">Glendowrdy</placeName> -----</p>
            <p>Reached <placeName ref="pl1244">Erthig</placeName> this night having spent on the
               tour of <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> four Weeks within two days
               ------</p>
            <pb/>
            <p>S.<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></p>
            <p><sic><placeName ref="pl0793">Langollen</placeName></sic> is a small Town, about four
               miles from <sic><placeName ref="pl1256">Chirck Castle</placeName></sic> in <placeName ref="pl1216">Denbighshire</placeName> (the noble and delightful Seat of <persName ref="pe0704">Richard Myddelton</persName> Esq<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.) and
               about twelve miles from <placeName ref="pl1260">Oswestry</placeName>; it is situated
               in a little Vale, upon the River <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName>, over which
               there is a very elegant strong stone <placeName ref="pl1954">Bridge</placeName> of
               four or five large Arches, whose foundation is not to be shaken, each buttress and
               Pier being built upon the same Rock, which extends itself from one side of the River
               to the others. The Rapidity and great winding Progress of the Water occasions a foam
               and noise extremely <sic>awfull</sic> and pleasing; almost every ten yards exhibits
               the finest Cascade in nature the whole River being composed of them. Many Hills in
               various directions, of most amazing and different Heights almost encompass the Town –
               There is to be had plenty of good provision, particularly Mutton, for which
               <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> is ever in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> famous – I
               mentioned this that if any </p>
            <pb/>
            <p>person has an Inclination to visit this Paradisical Spot, I can promise him most
               pleasing entertainment, and good Food. But Sir! I have not yet done with the beauties
               of this Place; I treat you in the order in which I was treated myself; for I was an
               Itinerant and the Visitor of a day only. About a mile off are the ruins of a Castle,
               called by the Inhabitants of the Country <placeName ref="pl0794">Castel Dinas
                  Bran</placeName>, which some tell us signified in English the Castle of Crow City;
               Bran being Welch for a Crow, and therefore it is often called Crow Castle; but I have
               reason to believe from some accounts which I have received that it was built by one
               Prince Brennus<note type="editorial">Yorke is following the claim made in the twelfth
                  century by Geoffrey of Monmouth in <hi rend="italic">Historia Regum
                     Britanniae</hi> (‘The History of the Kings of Britain’) that the conqueror of
                  Rome was a Briton named Brennius (or Brennus). See John T. Koch (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Celtic Culture: A Historical Encyclopedia</hi>, Volume 1 (Santa
                  Barbara and Oxford: ABC Clio, 2006), p. 246. The association of Dinas Bran with
                  the figure of Brennus is made repeatedly in Welsh travelogues in this period,
                  though Thomas Pennant explicitly rejected it (see <hi rend="italic">A Tour in
                     Wales</hi>, vol. 1, p. 280).</note> who lived here many Years, and then
               withdrew and died at Rome. The Castle is situated upon the top of a most singularly
               strange and amazing Hill, of a Conical Figure, whose Base cannot be above one hundred
               Yards in diameter, and yet I </p>
            <pb/>
            <p>think its perpendicular <add place="above">Height</add> from the plain is not less
               than three hundred Yards; on the top of this romantick place, are the ruins of the
                  <placeName ref="pl0794">Castle</placeName>; it is extremely difficult to ascend
               the Hill; particular care must be taken in fixing your feet, otherwise you slip many
               yards down without before you stop. The Tradition of the Country is that there are
               great treasures within the <placeName ref="pl0794">Castle</placeName>, concealed in
               an Iron Cradle, a considerable depth in the ruins, but that it is most dangerous to
               attempt to get at them, as the Devil resides there and has the care of the Cradle.
               This is most seriously believed by the Country People, and till this last summer no
               person has had the boldness to search for those riches, nor would any one have
               ventured then without the Assistance of a noted Conjurer in that neighbourhood, whose
               skill in raising the Wind, finding lost goods, and other tricks and fears in
               necromancy, are firmly credited by the Weak illiterate people for many miles round;
               this conjurer undertook to keep the old Guardian of the Iron Cradle in</p>
            <pb/>
            <p>subjection, and then he, and some Welch Miners came to an agreement with M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
               <persName ref="pe0704">Myddelton</persName>, the proprietor of the <placeName ref="pl0794">Castle</placeName>, for leave to search there for treasure, and a
               formal lease was eventually drawn up and engrossed. The Men had been at Work for some
               time this summer, and had discovered an entrance into a Vault; but as the agreement
               was not executed by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
               <persName ref="pe0704">Myddelton</persName> the miners were persuaded not to proceed.
               The Conjurer is an honest Carpenter with whom I have had a few days ago some
               Conversation upon this subject; it seems that he, and his Companions, have no kind of
               doubt but that there is money concealed in this Iron Cradle: but they are sometimes
               fearful lest it should prove of an inferior quality to Gold or silver; and that if
               the Cradle should contain wooden or leathern Money only, the Guardian would serve
               them a devilish trick. I have been at the top of this very amazing Place, which is
               most wonderful and astonishing, and saw where the poor Fellows had been at labour,
               [?brutales]!</p>
            <pb/>
            <p>I could not see the Iron Cradle or terrifick protector of it. It is said, that Prince
               Brennus left papers behind him in Italy, which are now in some Repository at Rome,
               and were a few years ago discovered by some Gentlemen there, which gave an account of
               this <placeName ref="pl0794">Castle</placeName>, and the treasure which is concealed
               within it. Certain it is, that two Italian Gentlemen<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note> came over to England, and applied to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
               <persName ref="pe0704">Myddelton</persName>’s father for permission to search the
               Ruins; and it is said, they could not agree about it. By the appearance of the ruins,
               the <placeName ref="pl0794">Castle</placeName> was a large building and covered the
               whole top of the Hill, and seems to have been built with the Stones dug from the Rock
               there. About a mile from this <placeName ref="pl0794">Castle</placeName>, and the
               same distance from <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName>, are very curious
               and pleasing Ruins of the <sic><placeName ref="pl0785">Abbey of
                  Crusis</placeName></sic>; several Arches and Towers are yet standing, and a Farm
               House and Barn are formed out of some of the Apartments. The Situation of this
                  <placeName ref="pl0785">Abbey</placeName> is perhaps the finest in the World for </p>
            <pb/>
            <p>a melancholy and monkishly religious Retirement; hills, hanging Woods, a winding
               rushing <placeName ref="pl1138">River</placeName>, and a few fine Meadows surround
               it. In my ride from <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> towards <placeName ref="pl1256">Chirk Castle</placeName>, on the top of a large Hill, called
               Keven-Ucha, I saw one of the finest ravishing prospects possible to be conceived by
               man; I think no poetic description can exceed it; I really cannot describe it with
               any justness; on one hand are the fine high pointed Hills around <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> with <placeName ref="pl0794">Crow
                  Castle</placeName> on the top of one of them; on the other hand, you have a most
               extensive View for above fifty miles, of a great part of <placeName ref="pl1216">Denbighshire</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl0702">Flintshire</placeName>,
                  <placeName ref="pl1362">Cheshire</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1021">Shropshire</placeName>, and <placeName ref="pl1367">Staffordshire</placeName>. At
               the foot of the Hill on which I stood, is an amazing and most enchanting sight of the
               rolling meandering <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName>; above which, on the
               opposite side, are fine hanging Woods, interspersed with rich pastures and corn
                  <sic>Feilds</sic>; at the bottom, upon the margin of the River, are beautiful
               Meadows with neat Cottages, and behind the Hill</p>
            <pb/>
            <p>is a continual Range of Mountains, some of which are heathy, while others have a fine
               Verdure. It is really worth any person’s while to travel two hundred miles for the
               sake of this prospect only. This with the other Views and appearances about
                  <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> have given me greater pleasure than
               ever I received from the finest Garden, parks, or buildings in England. <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> and the circumjacent places only two miles
               round, are I think the greatest Curiosities, the most romantick, the most pleasing,
               the most astonishing and delightful upon the face of the Earth. I never read of any
               Views so luxuriant and Ravishing.</p>
            <p> I am, Sir!</p>
            <p> Yours etc:</p>
            <p> Dico tibi – </p>
            <pb/>
            <p>From a green</p>
            <p>turf <sic><placeName ref="pl1207">Offa’s dike</placeName></sic>
            </p>
            <p>Sept:<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 5:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1766 </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>