<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0029">
   <teiHeader type="w">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Journal of a Tour in Wales by The Rev. George Capper
               <date>1802</date></title>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Edited with an introduction by Elizabeth Edwards</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                  <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                  <idno>NLW 21235B</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <ab><locus/></ab>
               </msContents>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <!-- delete as appropriate -->
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <fw>f. 1r</fw>
            <p>On Wednesday May 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1802 I left <placeName ref="pl2988">Clifton</placeName> &amp; reach’d my <persName ref="pe2096">Uncles</persName> at
                  <placeName ref="pl2808">Cathays</placeName> the same Evening. On the 14th we dined
               with <persName ref="pe2097">Mr Rous</persName> at <sic><placeName ref="pl2987">Courticoura</placeName></sic>. A spot where Nature has done much &amp; which
               he had had taste enough to improve by a neat appropriate house a small pleasure
               ground well-planted with ornamental shrubs, &amp; walks judiciously cut along a lofty
               &amp; steep bank well wooded to its bottom. On the opposite side a little stream,
               which in passing thro’ his Grounds has four falls of six or seven feet each, rises a
               rock still more abrupt <add place="above">than the other</add> &amp; equally well
               clothed with wood. The view from the drawing room Window extends towards the East
               along a Valley adorn’d by a few neat Cottages, a farm House &amp; a Parish Church,
               &amp; looks on the S.E. beyond the stream over a considerable lawn of rising Ground
               which is bounded by a crescent of Wood. The Possessor of this palace is a Single Man
               between 50 &amp; 60 years old of pleasing manner &amp; good general information. He
               was formerly the Captain </p>
            <fw>f. 1v</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p><placeName ref="pl1840">Cardiff</placeName> – </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 2r</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>of an East Indiaman but has resign’d for some years the tumult &amp; bustle of a
               Sailors life for the more peaceful occupations of a Farmer – Upon my return in the
               Evening I found Hammond at [?Cardiff?] whom I had left at <placeName ref="pl2988">Clifton</placeName> under a promise of joining me at <placeName ref="pl1840">Cardiff</placeName>. The <placeName ref="pl1841">Castle</placeName> at this place
               is well worthy of Notice &amp; has fortunately fallen into the hands of a person who
               will attend to its preservation. It was formerly made use of as a place of
               confinement to <persName ref="pe1138">Robert Carthouse</persName> Son of William the
               Conquerer. The Tower call’d from him “<placeName ref="pl2809">Roberts
                  Tower</placeName>” still remains. But the strictness of his confinement to that
               Tower may be doubted; as, ’till within these few years, there were evident marks of
               communication betwixt that place &amp; the Keep of the Castle. Some few years back
                  <persName ref="pe0278">Lord Bute</persName> intended making it a place of
               occasional residence &amp; <persName ref="pe2098">Holland</persName> was employ’d to
               build, or rather to alter &amp; add to, a house within the walls. But after 2 or 3000
               £ were expended upon it the design was laid aside, &amp; what was completed of it
               remains as a gross memorial of <persName ref="pe2098">Mr Hollands</persName>
               utter</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 2v</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>[blank]</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 3r</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>want of Taste &amp; of his total ignorance of Gothic Architecture – Not far from the
               Castle are remains of a <placeName ref="pl2989">Convent of Grey Friars</placeName> –
               but it is falling so quickly into decay that probably in a few years there will be
               little more than the foundations to be seen. The <placeName ref="pl2990">Church</placeName> is a fine building &amp; its Tower beautiful – The latter
               seems to be finish’d in the fine florid style of Henry 6 or 7th time. The Windows of
               the Church seem to be of the architecture of an earlier time I should suppose of
               Henry 3d or Edward 1st. But I speak with hesitation as I am by no means properly
               qualified to decide upon the matter. About a Mile from the Town to the South is a
               fine Sea Lock which terminates the Canal from <placeName ref="pl2993">Merthyr</placeName>. Brigs<note type="editorial">Two-masted merchant
                  vessel.</note> of large burthen enter by this Lock &amp; have Water sufficient in
               the Canal to float at all times. To the North of the Town about a Mile is situated
                  <placeName ref="pl2991">Cathays</placeName>, a small, comfortable house belonging
               to <persName ref="pe0278">Lord Bute</persName> which he has given up to my <persName ref="pe2096">Uncle</persName> rent-free for life. It commands a fine view of the
               Castle Church &amp; Town of <placeName ref="pl1840">Cardiff</placeName></p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 3v</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>[blank]</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 4r</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>is kept in perfect order &amp; is as pretty as the flatness of the Country about
                  <placeName ref="pl1840">Cardiff</placeName> will admit. He has improved it greatly
               by a walk upon the Bank of the Canal to the Castle walks which he has planted towards
               the West. He has made the inside of his House the seat of Temperance &amp;
               Philosophy. His hours are early Breakfast at eight dinner at three &amp; goes to bed
               at ten – He drinks but little or no wine &amp; employs his time in reading writing
               &amp; attending to the concerns of a little farm. His mind is cheerful &amp; his
               conversation entertain<add place="above">in</add>g &amp; informative. He has seen
               &amp; studied Man in most Countries &amp; in all ranks. His second daughter &amp; a
               Son of the late Sir John [?Dallings] a youth of about twelve years constitute his
               family.</p>
            <p> On Saturday the 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> I quitted my Uncle’s with regret
               &amp; proceeded with Hammond to Newbridge. We left the high road about three Miles
               from <placeName ref="pl1840">Cardiff</placeName> &amp; bent our course for <placeName ref="pl1843">Caerphilly castle</placeName>. At the summit of the [2 words
               illegible – faint] after leaving the flat in which <placeName ref="pl1840">Cardiff</placeName> is</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 4v</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p><placeName ref="pl2810">Caerphilly</placeName> – 7 Miles </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 5r</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>situated the view is striking, extensive &amp; grand. To the West is a Valley in high
               cultivation, richly wooded &amp; well-water’d by little tributary streams supplying
               the canal &amp; falling into the <placeName ref="pl2810">Taaf</placeName> the whole
               bounded by the <placeName ref="pl2992">Garth</placeName> – one of the highest
               mountains in South Wales – To the South your Eye is carried over a rich plain with
               the Towns of <placeName ref="pl1840">Cardiff</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl1690">Llandaff</placeName> at the extremity of it, to the coasts &amp;
                  <placeName ref="pl1300">Glostershire</placeName> [sic] &amp; <placeName ref="pl1387">Somerset</placeName>, beyond the <placeName ref="pl1226">Severn</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl2974">Bristol Channel</placeName>. And
               to the East are the hills of <placeName ref="pl1229">Monmouthshire</placeName>. About
               two miles North of this point over Mountains which contain coal to within a few yards
               &amp; in some places within a few feet of the surface, lies <placeName ref="pl2810">Caerphilly</placeName>. There are still very considerable remains of the Castle;
               sufficient to impress the mind with ideas of its former strength &amp; magnificence.
               There is a Tower, by some convulsion probably that of Gunpowder thrown eleven feet
               from its perpendicular </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 5v</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>Newbridge – 7 Miles</p>
            <p><placeName ref="pl2994">Bridgewater Arms</placeName> – the people civil &amp; clean
               &amp; charges moderate. –</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 6r</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>&amp; yet by the adhesiveness of its mortar continuing in that impending state. [3?
               words illegible] of excellent [2 words illegible] &amp; charming ??? we stretched on
               to Newbridge. This place is remarkable for a most beautiful <placeName ref="pl1776">arch</placeName> thrown over the <placeName ref="pl2810">Taaf</placeName> its
               span is 144 feet &amp; its heighth [sic] is 38. The weight upon the buttresses is
               ingeniously reliev’d by three cylindrical excavations at each end. From Newbridge to
                  <placeName ref="pl2993">Merthyr</placeName> we walk’d along the banks of the
                  <placeName ref="pl2995">Canal</placeName>. The scenery the whole way is
               delightful. The path lies thro’ a valley of about a mile or somewhat less in width,
               cultivated &amp; abounding in water. About ten miles short of <placeName ref="pl2993">Merthyr</placeName> the canal bears a singular appearance, it is carried on
               Arches over that river &amp; is seen descending by a succession of locks some hundred
               feet down the sides of a Mountain. Art has been but little employed in beautifying
               this tract &amp; yet the lands are as [2 words illegible] as if she had been most
               advantageously consulted. In many parts they</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 6v</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p><placeName ref="pl2993">Merthyr Tydvil</placeName> – 13 </p>
            <p> </p>
            <p>* say 50,000£</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 7r</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>bear the appearance of Gentlemans [illegible] &amp; are on each side flank’d by lofty
               Mountains. The situation of <placeName ref="pl2993">Merthyr</placeName> is
               picturesque – at the end of <hi rend="superscript">a</hi> Valley surrounded by
               Mountains except on the side by which you approach it. There are several Iron works
               establish’d here of considerable magnitude but <placeName ref="pl2996">those</placeName> of <persName ref="pe2099">Mr Crawshay</persName> are of the
               greatest extent. The expenses for labour only in his works are 3000£ a Month. The
               average earnings of Men Women &amp; Children are 3£ a Month. The wages of some amount
               to as much as a Guinea <hi rend="superscript">per Month</hi>. <persName ref="pe2099">Mr C</persName> is supposed to be [illegible] to the amount of *36,000£ p<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> annum. Indeed this Sum large as it is does not seem at
               all improbable when you see the immensity of his works &amp; consider at how slight
               an expense all the material required for the formation of Iron are procured. Close to
               the spot, in the Mountains above, are inexhaustible sources of Iron ore, Coal, Lime
               Stone, [?Tin] Stone &amp; [?Fire] clay, which are brought from </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 7v</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>[blank]</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 8r</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>thence in small four-wheel’d carriages called [illegible] running upon plates of Iron
               with so little friction that one horse will easily convey a ton Weight. Nothing can
               exceed the ingenious facility with which every part of the work is carried on. There
               is one stupendous wheel of 52 feet in Diameter which works the blasts of four
               furnaces &amp; turns several sets of rolling Machines, and yet its [?formation] at a
               little distance has the neat appearance of Clock-Work. – </p>
            <p>On Monday the 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> we quitted this abode of the Cyclops
               &amp; stretched over a wearisome tract of barren Mountain for ten Miles. In this
               whole space there is nothing for the Eye to rest upon but here &amp; there an Iron
                  <sic>foundery</sic> in a distant valley. The scene was not improved by occasional
               storms of Hail &amp; Snow driving from the North – I felt disposed to execrate such
               inhospitable country ’till I consider’d that Nature was not so churlish as she at
               first appear’d to be &amp; that under</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 8v</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>At <placeName ref="pl2997">Llanelly</placeName> – pronounc’d Llanethly</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 9r</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>that barren unsightly surface lay [illegible] invaluable depths of Mine &amp; Coal.
               This reflexion disposed my mind to <hi rend="superscript">the</hi> enjoyment of
               Country singularly beautiful in itself but perhaps <add place="above">still</add>
               more so for its contrast with that I had left. After traversing a region of black
               Mountains you are at first gratified by the sight of so few trees, &amp; the mind is
               relieved from an expanse of [illegible] desolation by the nearer prospect of a
               defined habitable tract. The road for at least seven Miles is formed for local
               carriages only of nearly the same form but of a larger size than those used at
                  <placeName ref="pl2993">Merthyr</placeName> &amp; employ’d for the conveyance of
               Coal &amp; Mine. About four Miles below the spot where the country becomes enclosed
               are large Iron-Works.* &amp; the whole of that way is a varied path of the richest
               &amp; boldest scenery. High abrupt rocks clothed at intervals: &amp; <hi rend="superscript">in places</hi>
               <del>others</del>
               <hi rend="superscript">rocks</hi> less <add place="above">steep</add> but well
               cultivated form the</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 9v</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>Hammond thought this scenery like the neighbourhood of <placeName ref="pl1884">Matlock</placeName>. – </p>
            <p> </p>
            <p> </p>
            <p><placeName ref="pl1787">Abergavenny</placeName> – 32. Miles</p>
            <p><placeName ref="pl2811">The Angel</placeName>.</p>
            <p> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Saunders<note type="editorial">In the eighteenth
                  century, The Angel at Abergavenny was run first by Samuel Saunders (dates unknown)
                  and then by his son, Charles Hanbury Saunders (dates unknown).</note> is very
               improving &amp; the attendance excessively bad.</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 10r</fw>
            <p>scenery on the left – On the right a small stream, at a vast depth <del>beyond</del>
               <hi rend="superscript">beneath</hi> the level of the road; descending in a bed work’d
               by time thro’ the rocks &amp; at slight distances falling in natural cascades many
               feet, with each side of its course beautifully ornamented with Oak Ash Thorn &amp;
               Fir conducts you to the Iron Works. About a Mile beyond this the <placeName ref="pl2999">Usk</placeName> &amp; a rich Valley on each side opens to view. Three
               miles to the right you see <placeName ref="pl1787">Abergavenny</placeName>, which
               place we reach’d at eight O Clock. – </p>
            <p> There is little to be said of <placeName ref="pl1787">Abergavenny</placeName>. The
               whole Vale thro’ which the <placeName ref="pl2999">Usk</placeName> runs is beautiful
               &amp; this small Town is one of the situations upon its banks. There is tho’, I
               think, an appearance of more comfort &amp; better condition amongst the lower classes
               of people in this place than [illegible] at <placeName ref="pl1791">Brecon</placeName>. There is an old Gate Way in good preservation &amp; some
               remains of the Keep of a <placeName ref="pl2998">Castle</placeName>.</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 10v</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>[blank]</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 11r</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>At our departure for <placeName ref="pl3000">Crickhowell</placeName> on the 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> a watch of mine was missing from a <sic>draw</sic> in
               Hammonds room &amp; strong suspicions falling upon an Irish Servant belonging to a
               Gentleman who had slept in the Inn the night before a Messenger was dispatch’d to
               accuse him of the theft. From the proceedings on this occasion one would suspect the
               Master had a little plundering blood in his veins for by way of coming at the truth
               he taxes the Servant with the fact &amp; is satisfied with the Mans making an
               affidavit, before a Magistrate that he had never been in the room. I understand that
               at his return from this solemn farce the Rascal was search’d &amp; the Watch not
               being found upon him, was pronounc’d clear of the foul aspersion. but as the fellow
               was absolutely detected in attempting to steal a [illegible] from the stable I must
               withhold my belief of his innocence. </p>
            <p> The road to <placeName ref="pl3000">Crickhowell</placeName> lies along the
                  <placeName ref="pl2999">Usk</placeName> &amp; I reach’d the place big</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 11v</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p><placeName ref="pl3000">Crickhowell</placeName>. 6. – </p>
            <p><placeName ref="pl2812">The Bear</placeName>.</p>
            <p> A civil good Woman keeps the house who is very attentive to her business &amp;
               moderate in her charges.</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 12r</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>with hopes of the rarest fishing – but alas the season was past. and the wind was
               blowing hard at East. However a knowledge of then plenty of good fish in the river
               &amp; hopes of a change of wind &amp; weather induced me to stay four days &amp; in
               that time I caught but a brace of Fowl. This part of the stream is likely to become
               soon as famous as it was a few years back for the finest fishing. A want of proper
               attention to the river &amp; the leniency of <persName ref="pe1124">Admiral
                  Gell</persName> towards Poachers has brought it to so low an ebb that for three or
               four years there were no fish to be caught. But of late an Angling Society has been
               establish’d &amp; the stream been properly protected – the consequence is a plenty of
               Fish &amp; many of good size. March &amp; April are the proper Months for sport. When
               besides the greatest quantity of Trout you may catch abundance of Salmon.</p>
            <p> At this place I had the misfortune to lose my travelling companion who was obligd
               [sic] to go to <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>. He gave me</p>
            <p/>
            <fw>f. 12v</fw>
            <p/>
            <p><placeName ref="pl1791">Brecon</placeName>. 14:</p>
            <p><placeName ref="pl3001">The Lion</placeName></p>
            <p> Dinners bad, Wine better than usual. Charges moderate. The house dismally dark.
               Mournfully quiet all day &amp; troublesomely noisy all Night I believe owing to their
               not having a frequency of company &amp; the [illegible] arriving at two in the
               Morning..</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 13r</fw>
            <p/>
            <p>hopes of seeing him again on my [illegible – page blotted]. On Sunday the 23. I
               proceeded by the Canal side to <placeName ref="pl1791">Brecon</placeName> &amp;
               reach’d it <add place="above">at</add> six O Clock after suffering excessively from
               an oppressive heat. This Town covers a great deal of ground but does not seem very
               thickly inhabited. Its site is somewhat triangular &amp; chiefly upon rising ground.
               It has three Churches of which one, the <placeName ref="pl1793">Priors
                  Church</placeName>, bears marks of great antiquity. It is placed upon the top of a
               small hill &amp; has very pretty walks thro’ a bank of Oaks at the back of it.
               Adjoining the Church is the Priory, the stables [?the] [?barns] of which are of the
               same age with the Church but the house is converted into a modern building. At a few
               yards distance to the South are the remains of a large <placeName ref="pl1794">Castle</placeName> standing in a most commanding spot upon the <placeName ref="pl2999">Usk</placeName>. It must have been a place of great strength, &amp;
               there are still extensive remains of it but when any stones are wanted for the repair
               of the Town, the walls are most</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 13v</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p><placeName ref="pl1796">Llandovery</placeName>. 20. – </p>
            <p><placeName ref="pl1797">Castle</placeName></p>
            <p> Clean – comfortable – reasonable</p>
            <p><placeName ref="pl1799">Llandilo</placeName> – 12 Miles by the [?Ford] &amp; 14 by
               the Turnpike</p>
            <p>
               <placeName ref="pl2813">The Bear</placeName>.</p>
            <p> A dull, dirty house. indifferent wine &amp; worse cooking.</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 14r</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>sacrilegiously pull’d down &amp; applied to that purpose. The property of the Castle
               is vested in <persName ref="pe1125">S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> C.
                  Morgan</persName> &amp; if his Agent has so little taste &amp; respect for
               Antiquity as to demolish some of its finest remains He himself should step in &amp;
               forbid the violation. I intended on the 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> to have
               ascended to the top of a neighbouring Mountain called the [?“Beygons”] &amp; set off
               for that purpose but unfortunately the wind was so high &amp; the path up the
               Mountains so steep that it was impossible for me to advance above a few hundred
               yards. Early in the morning on Tuesday 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> I march’d
               from <placeName ref="pl1791">Brecon</placeName> &amp; breakfasted at a small Village
               – Trecastle. – I arriv’d at <placeName ref="pl1796">Llandovery</placeName> about 4 O
               Clock.</p>
            <p>On 26 I reach’d <placeName ref="pl1799">Llandilo Vawr</placeName>.</p>
            <p>A letter from Miss Head to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> [?Beynon] was of the utmost
               advantage to me in this place. It introduced me to a Man of strong understanding
               improved by intensive reading. Fortunately he had as much pleasure in pointing</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 14v</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>The little Town of <placeName ref="pl1799">Llandilo</placeName> stands upon the side
               of Hill &amp; is a sweet object to all the Country around, but is in itself a pretty
               wretched place.</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 15r</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>out every thing worthy of Notice as I had in attending him – The following are the
               most prominent. Immediately joining the Town is <placeName ref="pl2012">Newton
                  Park</placeName> the seat of <persName ref="pe1126">Lord Dinevor</persName>. The
                  <placeName ref="pl1801">castle</placeName>, the remains of which are still large
               enough to make most picturesque object, was formerly the seat of the Princes of South
               Wales &amp; the situation is in every way deserving a royal residence. Nothing can be
               more happy than the natural formation of the Grounds. nothing seems to have been left
               for Art to improve upon. In the only point where modern Taste has presumed to make
               additions, the scenery is the worse for Scotch Fir but will accord with the sublime
               grandeur of venerable Oaks &amp; Ivy-mantled Towers [four words illegible –
               cancelled]. – </p>
            <p> We proceeded from this delightful place to <placeName ref="pl2815">Grongar
                  hill</placeName>. On this eminence was formerly a British encampment. The view
               from it is beautiful. the rich bold bank of Wood in <placeName ref="pl2012">Newton
                  Park</placeName> with the <placeName ref="pl1801">Castle</placeName> &amp; the
                     <sic><placeName ref="pl2697">Towey</placeName></sic> flowing at its foot</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 15v</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p><placeName ref="pl2814">Druslon Castle</placeName>.</p>
            <p> </p>
            <p>Gwlwg y Byd<note type="editorial">Welsh translation (properly ‘golwg y byd’) of
                  ‘Prospect of the World’ in the text on the facing page (f. 16r).</note></p>
            <p> </p>
            <p>The Vale of Towey. – </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 16r</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>have the finest effect imaginable. The beauty of this scenery first inspired
                  <persName ref="pe0511">Dyers</persName> Muse<note type="editorial">For the text of
                  John Dyer’s loco-descriptive poem ‘Grongar Hill’ (1726), see <ref type="http" target="http://spenserians.cath.vt.edu/TextRecord.php?textsid=33959">here</ref></note>. The <placeName ref="pl2816">house</placeName> where he lived
               is just under “<placeName ref="pl2815">Grongar Hill</placeName>” &amp; some part of
               family are still in possession of the estate. Our road from hence carried us across
               the Vale of Towey &amp; the river. In our way we pass’d a singular natural curiosity
               – it is a rock rising abruptly in the middle of the Valley &amp; of sufficient size
               to have had a Castle built upon it in former days. – After crossing the river we
               ascended Mountains for some extent &amp; at length arrived at a point called the
               “Prospect of the World.” The command of Country from this spot it, as the appellation
               imports, grandly extensive. The Eye is carried uninterruptedly along a rich
               cultivated Valley of at least 27 Miles in length, closed to the West by the Town of
                  <placeName ref="pl1802">Carmarthen</placeName> embosom’d in lofty Mountains. –
                  <placeName ref="pl2012">Newton</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl2815">Grongar
                  Hill</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl2814">Druslon Castle</placeName> &amp; the
               little Town of <placeName ref="pl1799">Llandilo</placeName> are features in the
               scenery. </p>
            <p> We return’d to <placeName ref="pl1799">Llandilo</placeName> by <placeName ref="pl2013">Golden Grove</placeName></p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 16v</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>[blank]</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 17r</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>– <persName ref="pe1267">Mr Vaughns</persName> – This Gentleman has one of the best
               landed estates in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> &amp; derives a
               consequence from it in the County which an Englishman can form no idea of. Besides
               that respect which is every where paid to large property, a Welshman has a sort of
               reverence for the domain &amp; person of one of their antient families. If he talks
               of him, it is as if of a superior Being – If he meets him, it is with the protraction
               of the whole frame. – That equalizing spirit tho’ that has gone forth in the world
               has reach’d this corner of the Island &amp; I understand that the minds of <add place="above">the</add> Welsh are visibly affected by it. If this be the case a
               very few years will suffice to rid them of all superfluous respect for their
               superiors. But I think great doubt may be entertain’d whether they will be either the
               better or the happier for their change of manners. At present they are civil,
               obliging, hospitable. Willing to give you any information in their power &amp; ready
               at all times to set before you the best fare their houses will </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 17v</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>[blank]</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 18r</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>afford. Except in the immediate neighbourhood of Towns the farms are small – many of
               them of not more than [?10th rent] – This small tract enables a Man to support his
               family with decency. What little wheat he grows, is generally sent to Market, whilst
               his own family live upon Oat Cakes. I suppose it is in consequence of these small
               occupations that in the Markets you see people retailing Wheat to so low a measure as
               a Peek. – In general corn is not sold from sample but in bulk. The attendance at
               Fairs &amp; Markets in these parts is astonishing. You would suppose, the times these
               are held, that the whole Country had risen en masse &amp; were come for mutual
               barter. They depend entirely upon these times for the vent of their goods &amp; the
               supply of their wants. And as a Welshman is naturally a light-hearted social Being he
               generally adjourns from the Market-Cross to the Ale House &amp; stays till he is more
               indebted to his Horses head</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 18v</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>[blank]</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 19r</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>than his own for his safety home. This accounts for the number of Ale Houses in every
               petty Town. In <placeName ref="pl1796">Llandovery</placeName>, which consists of
               little more than two small streets, I reckon’d 23 of these houses. </p>
            <p> There are houses of a still more ruinous resort &amp; equally abundant in this
               Country – the Offices of Attorneys. No Monkey is so litigious as a Welshman. He is at
               good will with all the world except his next neighbour – but there his love of a
               law-suit gets the better of him: &amp; he will absolutely <add place="above">in the
                  night</add> make a Gap in his own fence for his neighbours cattle to come, that he
               have the pleasure of suing for a trespass the next morning. In the small Town of
                  <placeName ref="pl1802">Carmarthen</placeName> are one or two &amp; thirty
               Attorneys. – To return to <placeName ref="pl2013">Golden Grove</placeName>.</p>
            <p> It is to be regretted that the present possessor of this estate does not pay the
               slightest attention to the improvement of the place. &amp; the Park which was once
               finely wooded is now little more </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 19v</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p><placeName ref="pl1800">Craig Kennen</placeName></p>
            <p> </p>
            <p> </p>
            <p><placeName ref="pl3002">Llwchwr</placeName>. – </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 20r</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>than a wet bleak hill with a few Thorns &amp; two or three small, bad clumps of
               Scotch Fir. The Park is separated from the house by a Turnpike Road &amp; some
               plantations – </p>
            <p> The 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> was spent in seeing the other Lions of the
               place. About seven Miles from <placeName ref="pl1799">Llandilo</placeName> across the
               mountains is <placeName ref="pl1800">Craig Kennen</placeName> or the Castle on the
               river Kennen. It takes its appellation from a small river which runs at its foot
               &amp; was in days of old a Post of impregnable strength. It is built upon the extreme
               edge of a lofty perpendicular rock &amp; seems to have been rais’d to command a pass
               from the Coast of <placeName ref="pl1231">Carmarthenshire</placeName> towards
                  <placeName ref="pl1791">Brecon</placeName>. Almost facing it &amp; within a Mile
               distance is the source of the <placeName ref="pl3002">Llwchwr</placeName> or
                  <placeName ref="pl3002">Loughor</placeName>. At its head is it seen running in a
               stream of at least five yards wide &amp; comes pouring from a cleft in a rock on one
               side of the black Mountain. The spot is highly</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 20v</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>I think I understood as far as 200 yards. </p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 21r</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>romantic. The whole rock is cover’d with wood &amp; just about the stream is a
               natural Cavern extending into the Mountain. People have gone * some hundred yards in
               without coming to an end of it &amp; in that space they cross the river twice. I
               can’t say that my curiosity is strong enough to lead me into such dismal abodes! –
               But if I was unwilling to try further for its source I had great pleasure in
               following its course for about three miles where it enters the grounds of Mr [?D.]
               [?Brigson/Brisson]. Its rapidity encreases with its way &amp; in this place it is
               precipitated in one body down a height of about four &amp; thirty feet. I can’t give
               a description of the sport at all adequate to its merits, nor is it possible to
               express the feelings with which the grandeur of the scenery impresses you. For some
               way the river is lost between two steep banks thick set with wood. You come upon it
               again just below the falls</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 21v</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>[blank]</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 22r</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>where the deep shade of over-spreading Oaks, a bed excavated in the rock by the force
               of the current, &amp; the furious dashing of the water in their fall, all together
               strike the imagination with awe &amp; dispose the mind to sublimest contemplation. I
               would pass days in such a spot!</p>
            <p> The other objects we saw were of a very different nature. The first was an old
               British encampment capable of holding many thousand Men.<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note> It is upon the summit of a Mountain &amp; surrounded by a
               bank – a [?vellum] of loose stones to a considerable height &amp; of a great
               thickness. It must have been impregnable in those days when there were no shot to
               scatter them about the ears of the besieg’d. I believe it was in this part of Wales
               that <persName ref="pe1341">Edward</persName> gain’d his decisive battle over the
               Welsh &amp; if so it is more than probably that it was an encampment of <persName ref="pe2022">Llewellyn</persName>’s</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 22v</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>[blank]</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 23r</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>his other sight was a Cromlech or Druids altar.<note type="editorial">Unidentified.</note> It consists of a stone of about eleven feet in length, four
               in thickness &amp; eight in width, supported by one stone at its larger end &amp; by
               two at its smaller – the large end somewhat the higher. It was impossible to see this
               stone upon which perhaps hundreds of our fellow-creatures have been offer’d up in
               sacrifice, without comparing our blessed religion with the impious [illegible]
               idolatory of some of the heathens, &amp; feeling grateful for the merciful
               dispensation vouchsafed to us. It was late in the Evening when we return’d from our
               ride &amp; I am afraid my compassion was a little tired with his expedition. We
               afterwards dined together &amp; I felt the value of his society too much not to feel
               excessively sorry at parting with him.</p>
            <p> On the 29th I was up with the Lark</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 23v</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>[blank]</p>
            <p> </p>
            <fw>f. 24r</fw>
            <p> </p>
            <p>&amp; reach’d <placeName ref="pl1802">Carmarthen</placeName> to breakfast. There had
               been some rain in the Night &amp; the break of the Morning was most lovely. Soon
               after Sun-Rise the valleys were clear but the Mountains were long cover’d with fogs –
               the clouds seem’d unwilling to quite their resting place. – The whole of the road is
               beautiful &amp; commands the Vale of Towy. [3 words illegible – cancelled] upon the
               left.</p>
            <p> It was Market day at <placeName ref="pl1802">Carmarthen</placeName>.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>