<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0030">
    <teiHeader type="w">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Catherine Hutton’s Tour of Wales: 1797
                    <date>1797</date></title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Edited with an introduction by Mary-Ann Constantine</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                        <idno>MS 19079C</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
           <p> </p>
                <p>Letter 10<note type="editorial">From this point onwards, the published ‘Letters’
                        labelled 10-18 which appeared intermittently in the <hi rend="italic">Monthly Magazine</hi> from July 1816 to August 1819, offer a condensed,
                        amalgamated and frequently depersonalized version of Hutton’s travels in
                        1797, 1799 and 1800 as she described them in Letters 10-29, given in full
                        here. While I have occasionally drawn attention to one or two significant
                        alterations in the footnotes, I have not pursued a detailed comparison of
                        the two texts; more information about the differences between the 29 letters
                        in NLW MS 1907C and the 18 letters published in the <hi rend="italic">Monthly Magazine</hi> can be found in the Introduction above.</note>
                </p>
                <p style="right"><placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName> Aug 24 1797</p>
                <p>My Dear Brother</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>You will see me thus on my way to <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>.
                    We have pursued the track of our return last year; <placeName ref="pl1260">Oswestry</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName>, and
                        <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName>, and from thence have kept the
                    great road, instead of quitting at the <placeName ref="pl2463">Druid</placeName>, where we first entered it from <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Our road from the <placeName ref="pl2463">Druid</placeName> was good; up and down
                    hills; but not great </p>
                <pb n="p.40"/>
                <fw>p.40</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>hills, the country diversified with fields and woods; a river running on our
                    left. At two miles we ascended a longer hill than the others and found ourselves
                    high above the bed of the river, on a terrace road, cut out of solid rock. The
                    river, whose name I would give you if I could, after running peace<hi rend="subscript">^</hi><hi rend="superscript">a</hi>bly along the upper
                    lands, approaches this defile between the mountains, and forces its way to the
                    bottom, dashing over rocks and huge stones. A bridge, called <placeName ref="pl2829">Pont-y-Glyn</placeName>, the Bridge of the Glen, is thrown from
                    rock to rock over the highest and principal fall, I was told at seventy or
                    eighty feet above the water. [------]</p>
                <p>The road is cut at a <sic>heighth</sic> which made me tremble to look down;
                    though it is fenced by a high strong wall. The rocks rise perpendicularly above
                    it, on the right. From a point near the farther end is <del>xxx</del>
                    <hi rend="superscript">discovered</hi> the pont, of one noble lofty arch, and
                    the torrent pouring down below it, between the woody mountains. This is the
                    grandest sight I have seen in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>; and I
                    should <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">think</hi> rocks, and woods, and water, can scarcely
                    combine to form anything more beautiful.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>From <placeName ref="pl2829">Pont-y-Glyn</placeName> the country was no longer
                    romantic, but hilly and wild. The road, which was excellent, lay along a valley
                    though upon high ground, and wound round the bottoms of the hills, till it
                    reached <placeName ref="pl3129">Cerrig-y-Druidion</placeName>, the Rock of the
                    Druids, ten miles beyond <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName>. In this
                    bleak and elevated region, the small driving rain struck upon my face like
                    needle points, and the wind was so high, that I frequently held fast, by both
                    hands, to keep my-self upon my horse.</p>
                <pb n="p.41"/>
                <fw> p.41</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl3129">Cerrig y Druidion</placeName> is a considerable Welsh
                    village, with a church, an inn, and a shop; but there is no rock to be seen, or
                    Druid to be heard of. It was now the fair; and about two hundred home-spun coats
                    and blue coats were assembled, in the midst of three or four stalls of cloth,
                    two of earthen ware, and half a dozen of gingerbread and cakes, intermingled
                    with a small number of cattle. About three or four men appeared in broadcloth
                    coats; but not a silk hat or bonnet was to be seen among the women; or a cotton
                    gown, except one upon a dirty trollop,<note type="editorial">This appears
                        (perhaps unsurprisingly) in the published version as: ‘except for one dirty
                        creature, who seemed to be the refuse of another country.’</note> who seemed
                    the refuse of another country. Here, an old woman had a piece of striped woolen
                    under her arm, for sale; there, another had a remnant of linen, or a pair of
                    stockings, the produce of her own industry, and the overplus of the family
                    apparel: but I saw very little buying and selling. Both men and women were
                    chattering in small parties; and the women universally, were knitting. Two
                    harpers and a fidler arrived; and I was <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">informed</hi>, that many of the people would dance all
                    night, and some all the next day.</p>
                <p>The public house was so crowded we could not enter it; and as for a stable for
                    our horses, we should have been laughed at if we had asked it, for the keffils
                    stood by fifties in little inclosures. Indeed this is a regular piece of Welsh
                    economy; and each person pays a halfpenny for the standing of his horse, except
                    on Sundays, when the churchyard commonly serves for that purpose. We remained
                    therefore out of doors; the servant and horses drawn up at the horse-block,
                    ourselves walking the fair of <placeName ref="pl3129">Cerrig-y-Druidion</placeName>, and making a part of the shew.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>[From <placeName ref="pl3129">Cerrig y Druidion</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1576">Cernioge</placeName> is three miles; two and a half of which
                    appear, at once, in a straight line, over dreary uninhabitable bogs. <placeName ref="pl1576">Cernioge</placeName>, though the epithet of Mawr, Great, is
                    added </p>
                <pb n="p.42"/>
                <fw>p.42</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>to it, consists of nothing that I recollect, but the inn, which keeps one or more
                    post-chaises. Its mistress, having attained some degree of refinement by living
                    on the great road, had grafted a bedgown of beautiful printed cotton on the
                    native woolen petticoat of the country, and crowned the whole with a costly,
                    heavy cap of fine muslin and fine lace. The parlour, I believe the only parlour,
                    was occupied, and we fancied the master did not make us very welcome to our post
                    near the kitchen fire, where we took a sandwich and a pint of wine; so I armed
                    myself with a resolution to proceed to <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>, eleven miles farther, and that resolution remained
                    unshaken, though it rained when we set out, and unrepented of, though it
                    continued every step of the way.<note type="editorial">For the Inn at Cernioge
                        see <ref type="http" target="https://curioustravellers.ac.uk/en/the-cernioge-inn-a-forgotten-spot-on-the-welsh-tour/">Kirsty McHugh</ref> and <ref type="http" target="https://curioustravellers.ac.uk/en/further-notes-on-the-inn-at-cernioge/">Michael Freeman</ref>. </note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The first eight miles of the road was over wild moors; up and down hill but all
                    high ground. At two miles we passed through the village of <placeName ref="pl3119">Capel Voelas</placeName>, having a church, as its appellation,
                    Capel, denotes. From these high moors I sometimes caught a glimpse of a
                    mountain, as the clouds broke for a moment. Had the weather been clear, the
                        <placeName ref="pl1183">Alps of Caernarvonshire</placeName> would have stood
                    before me. At the end of the moors, we found ourselves hanging, at an immense
                        h<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>ight over the Vale of Llanrwst]. </p>
                <p>[-------]</p>
                <p>The Vale of Llanrwst is composed of grass of the finest verdure, and corn of the
                    richest yellow, divided by green hedges. The river <placeName ref="pl2384">Conwy</placeName>, not, like the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName>,
                    foaming over its rocky bed, but a placid, though a noble stream, moves
                    majestically along it. White houses, of every description, from the cottage to
                    the palace enliven it, and the town of <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>, with its elegant <placeName ref="pl1531">bridge</placeName>, appears towards the further end. The whole is encircled
                    by hills, rocks, and woods. Magnificent mountains, with <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName> at their head, should have risen above these, on the
                    left, if the atmosphere had so pleased. [The approach, over barren hills, and
                    the </p>
                <pb n="p.43"/>
                <fw>p.43</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>sudden appearance of these beauties under our feet, add to the impression <hi rend="superscript">they make</hi>. Wonder-struck and frightened to see
                    myself so high, I durst not sit upon my horse. It rained terribly! Wet I must
                    be, and wet I chose be, on foot. Father shared my fate, fearing only for me,
                    whilst I felt only for him; we passed three mile stones on the mountain, and a
                    fourth before we reached <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>. An
                    excellent greatcoat, with capes <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">to the elbows</hi>, kept the upper part of my person dry;
                    but sure such petticoats were never seen. The water ran in rivulets over the
                    road, and streamed from our cloaths, and by the time we arrived at <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName> my greatcoat had imbibed so much I could
                    scarcely carry it. I might have spared myself this heroic atchievement, if my
                    nerves had not been overpowered at the top of the mountain, for the descent was
                    both safe and easy. At <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName> I [----] got
                    between two good blankets, till a total change of habits could be provided].
                        <note type="editorial">This description of the effects of the weather and
                        the soaking petticoats – valuable information for the historian and full of
                        touches of Hutton’s self-deprecating humour - is typical of the material
                        omitted from the printed version.</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The inn at <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName> is the best I have seen
                    in the country. A Welsh harp welcomed our arrival [---], though we entered on
                    foot, and dropping like the water-works at <placeName ref="pl1542">Chatsworth</placeName>.<note type="editorial">An extensive series of
                        cascades, pools and fountains were developed in Chatsworth gardens from the
                        seventeenth century. </note> The town is ill-looking, and ill-paved. The
                        <placeName ref="pl1531">bridge</placeName>, of one large centre arch, and a
                    smaller on each side, is the work of <persName ref="pe1159">Inigo
                        Jones</persName>, and deservedly admired for its elegance and lightness. The
                    workmanship is said to be so true, that if you lean against a large stone, in
                    the centre of one of the parapet walls [---], while a person strikes a large
                    stone in the centre of the other [---], you feel the shock. This I experienced.
                    But the truth of the work will probably accelerate its destruction, for the
                    stone has been so often struck that it has given way. The date of the bridge is
                    1636.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The largest of the white houses that spot the Vale of Llanrwst is <placeName ref="pl1532">Gwidir</placeName>, a fine old mansion, near the <placeName ref="pl1234">Caernarvonshire</placeName> foot of the bridge </p>
                <pb n="p.44"/>
                <fw>p.44</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>which gives the title of Baron to the former Sir <persName ref="pe0177">Peter
                        Burrell</persName>. A lofty perpendicular rock, sprinkled with wood, river
                    behind it.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Letter 11</p>
                <p style="right"><placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> Aug 27 1797</p>
                <p style="center">
                    <note type="authorial">[see page 45]</note>
                    <note type="editorial">Note written in Catherine Hutton's hand.</note>
                </p>
                <p>My Dear Brother,</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Having crossed the <placeName ref="pl2384">Conwy</placeName>, at leaving
                        <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>, we travelled four or five mile
                    along the vale, by its side, under stupendous mountains which rose abruptly on
                    our left. Three torrents, made magnificent by the late rains, poured down from
                    different lakes at top, and, crossing our road, under bridges, rushed into the
                    river. Afterwards, we quitted the Vale of the Conwy and rode over high hills,
                    the mountains <sic>receeding</sic> to the left, till the top of our last hill
                    presented us with a sight wholly new to me: a town, surrounded by a wall, with
                    battlements and towers, seemingly perfect; and, situated on the side of a
                    sloping hill before us, we saw the whole at once. The beautiful <placeName ref="pl1530">castle of Conwy</placeName> rose upon a rock at one end. I
                    viewed the scene with admiration, and could almost have imagined myself
                    transported back to the days of <persName ref="pe0650">Edward the
                        First</persName>.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>[<placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName> is only two miles from the sea, to
                    which the river makes an opening; but its winding course, and the elevation of
                    its banks, do not permit the sea to be seen.]<note type="editorial">Inserted on
                        a separate slip of paper.</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>There are only two entrances into the town of <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName>, one from the land, and one from the water, both arched
                    gateways in the wall. We had no sooner passed through the former of these than
                    we were attacked by a sort of hostler who offered to conduct us to the inn; and,
                    without further ceremony, laid hold of the bridle of one of the horses. I
                    desired him to let go his hold, and supposing, from eagerness, that there were
                    two inns, and remembering the old adage <hi rend="underline">Good wine needs no
                        bush</hi> I determined not to be directed by him. As both were unknown to
                    me, we enquired of a man we met in the street which was the best. Whether he had
                    been bribed I know not, but he named the <placeName ref="pl1893">Bull</placeName>, the house the scout was sent from, and thither we went.
                    We found a large </p>
                <pb n="p.45"/>
                <fw>p.45</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>house and a good dinner. With our lodging we had less reason to be satisfied, and
                    if I go to <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName> again, I shall try the
                        <placeName ref="pl3124">Harp</placeName>.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I am told that the <placeName ref="pl3124">Harp</placeName> is the old house, and
                    the <placeName ref="pl1893">Bull</placeName>, the new; and that the <placeName ref="pl1893">Bull</placeName> has taken this extraordinary method of sending
                    out its emissaries to forestall travellers, in order to supplant its rival. The
                        <placeName ref="pl3124">Harp</placeName>, in its own defence, had adopted
                    the same plan; and it has happened more than once, when the contending parties
                    have met, that they have come to an engagement, and the vanquished obliged to
                    retreat, with a black eye or bloody nose. It is even said, that the mistress of
                    the <placeName ref="pl1893">Bull</placeName><note type="editorial">Possibly a
                        Mrs Read, widow of the previous landlord, who had married Samuel Read in
                        1778.</note> has defeated the chambermaid of the <placeName ref="pl3124">Harp</placeName> in single combat.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName> was the first Welsh town in which I
                    observed an air of industry, and a greater number of people appeared in its
                    streets than any I had seen before; yet their staple article is the
                    entertainment of travellers and its principal trade is to convey them across the
                    river: I need not tell you that over that river lies the high road from
                        <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1018">Holyhead</placeName>. At high water, it is nearly a mile in breadth.<note type="editorial">The <hi rend="italic">Monthly Magazine</hi> (Letter X,
                        Volume 41, p. 504) relocates the section on mail-coaches from MS Letter 15
                        (below), and inserts it here.</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The beauty of <placeName ref="pl1530">Conwy Castle</placeName>; the strength of
                    its towers; the elegance of its turrets; the magnificence of its great hall; the
                    wonder of the tower still standing, though its base, a mighty ruin, is long
                    since prostrate on the shore; and its charming situation, viewed from either
                    land or water, - have been often described. It is well they have, for I do not
                    at present think of any words to do them justice.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>From <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName> is twelve miles. Our course had been due north. Our road
                    from thence to <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>, was at first west, and then inclining
                    to the south; but insuperable mountains forbade our taking a nearer way. Two
                    miles and a half of steep, hilly</p>
                <pb n="p.46"/>
                <fw>p.46</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>road, brought us from <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl2400">Sŷchnant</placeName>, the top of a pass over the mountains down
                    to the <placeName ref="pl1564">straights of Menai</placeName>. From whence the
                    sea, <placeName ref="pl1959">Puffin</placeName> or <placeName ref="pl1959">Priestholm Island</placeName>, and the Isle of <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName> opened upon us at once. The descent is steep, on the
                    brink of a precipice, but secured by a wall. The smacking of a whip,
                    reverberated by the opposite mountain, sounded like a shower of stones. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>From the bottom of this pass to <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarfon</placeName>,
                    the road lies on the shore of the <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai</placeName>, and
                    is constantly up and down hill, though neither long together, except at
                        <placeName ref="pl1338">Penmaen Mawr</placeName>. There is every where
                    cultivated lands between the mountains and the straits, except, as before
                    excepted, at <placeName ref="pl1338">Penmaen Mawr</placeName>, <del>which
                        is</del> a huge promontory jutting into the sea, and the road climbs up its
                    side. Much has been said of this tremendous road, and frightful, as well as
                    dangerous, it must have been; as it runs very high above the sea, with a steep
                    precipice on one hand, and an impenetrable rock on the other; but it is now
                    fixed with a stone wall, which has the peculiar advantage of being cemented with
                    mortar. In one place, however, it has given way, though arches are turned under
                    the road to afford a passage for the water that comes down from the mountain.
                    Pains are taken to remove the rocks that from time to time fall down upon the
                    road, but I saw enough remaining, propped, or hanging by a thread, to make me
                    wish to avoid travelling that way when they had been loosened by rain or
                    frost.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The sixth mile stone from <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName> is above
                        <placeName ref="pl1338">Penmaen Mawr</placeName>, and the whole of the road
                    over it may be about a mile and a half. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At nine miles from <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName> we rode through
                        <placeName ref="pl1595">Aber</placeName>, where is a Welsh inn,<note type="editorial">This is another Bull’s Head.</note> under the mountains. At
                    thirteen miles we crossed the <placeName ref="pl2415">Ogwen</placeName>, and saw
                    an opening on our left, through which that river comes down through the
                    mountains. Before us, on a hill, was the <placeName ref="pl1971">church of
                        Llandegai</placeName>, handsome </p>
                <pb n="p.47"/>
                <fw>p.47</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>for a village church, any where, but in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>
                    a prodigy. On the right was the mansion of <persName ref="pe1198">Lord
                        Penrhyn</persName>; all about it proclaiming the riches and taste of its
                    noble owner. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName>, six miles beyond <placeName ref="pl1595">Aber</placeName> and nine short of <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>, would only be noticed as a neat little Welsh town,
                    if it were not an episcopal see, which, I suppose, confers upon it the rank of
                    city. It is environed by hills that shut it out from the <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai</placeName>. The cathedral is respectable, though its tower steeple
                    is low. A steeple of any kind, however, is a mark of dignity in this country.
                    The <placeName ref="pl2026">Bishop’s palace</placeName> and the <placeName ref="pl3130">Deanery</placeName> are its accompaniments, and are a couple of
                    snug, warm situations. The tombs are black stone of a remarkably fine texture,
                    resembling Wedgwood’s tea-pots.<note type="editorial">Josiah Wedgwood had
                        perfected a type of ‘black basalt ware’ by the late 1760s; in 1790 he
                        produced a copy of the (Roman) Portland Vase in black jasperware. See <ref type="http" target="http://www.wedgwoodmuseum.org.uk/learning/discovery-packs/pack/classical/chapter/black-basalt">here.</ref></note> As the sculptor might have gone in vain to the
                    Herald’s office, for the titles of the dead, he has gone to their occupations,
                    and is content with informing the world, that one was a mercer, another a
                    grocer, and another a taylor <del>of this parish</del>.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> the first thing one meets with
                    is the <placeName ref="pl3112">Hotel</placeName>, a house built by <persName ref="pe1230">Lord Uxbridge</persName>, and such as his lordships self might
                    live in. It is kept by an Englishman, and is frequented by all English
                    travellers. The Welsh stick to a good old <placeName ref="pl1890">King’s
                        Head</placeName> of their own, farther in the town.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1566">Caernarvon Castle</placeName> is the finest I have seen.
                    The guide who shewed it assured us it was the finest in <placeName ref="pl0777">Great Britain</placeName>. Whether he was qualified to make the assertion,
                    I doubt, but xx I am not qualified to disprove it, <hi rend="subscript">^</hi><hi rend="superscript">and</hi> I see no reason why I may not
                    implicitly believe it. The principal entrance is in the side next the town, and
                    has the statue of <persName ref="pe0650">Edward the First</persName>, its
                    founder, high above it.<note type="editorial">An additional line from the <hi rend="italic">Monthly Magazine</hi> has no equivalent anywhere in the
                        manuscript, and is uncharacteristic of Hutton, who goes out of her way to
                        paint the Welsh in a positive light. ‘It is said, that the features were
                        perfect till very lately; when on the circumstance being noticed by an
                        Englishman, one of the Welsh, in hatred to the memory of their conqueror,
                        took the pains to climb up and deface them’. (July, 1816) 504-05.</note> The
                    gate by which <persName ref="pe0136">Eleanor</persName> entered to give the
                    Welsh a Welshman for their prince is at the end next to what is called the
                    Castle Green, and the <placeName ref="pl2387">Eagle Tower</placeName>, where
                    that prince was born, is at the opposite end. The walls of that tower are nine
                    feet and a half in thickness; the whole must have been a place of prodigious
                    strength. All the windows </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.48"/>
                <fw>p.48</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>that look towards the country or the sea, are slips through which the soldiers
                    could point their arrows, without fear of annoyance in return: those within the
                    castle walls are beautiful gothic windows, with frames of stone. One only
                    remains intire. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The town of <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarfon</placeName>, like that of
                        <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName>, is surrounded by a wall. <del>The
                        side of the <placeName ref="pl1566">castle</placeName> forms one end of the
                        inclosure.</del> The inclosed space was not originally intended for its
                    present purpose, but was an area belonging to the <placeName ref="pl1566">castle</placeName>; and the town was half-a-mile further up the country.
                    When the <placeName ref="pl1566">castle</placeName> was no longer necessary to
                    keep the Welsh in awe, <del>the walls that proceeded from it were thought by the
                        inhabitants to be some security for</del> the town. <del>It
                        accordingly</del> moved its station, and pitched in the castle yard, where
                    it consists of one straight and tolerably wide street, with an arched gateway at
                    each end [-----], and three or four smaller ones which cross it at right angles.
                    A long irregular street, without the walls, is the high road, and a few mean
                    ones proceed from it, towards the country. On the outside the wall, towards the
                        <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai</placeName>, and close to it, is a beautiful
                    gravel walk.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The church disdained to follow the town in its peregrination. It remains near the
                        <sic>scite</sic> of Old Caernarvon, which is plainly discernible, though
                    there is not one stone left upon another. The church is called the <placeName ref="pl2020">church of Llanbeblic</placeName>. It is built in the form of a
                    cross, and has a tower steeple, but the regularity of the edifice is destroyed
                    by a chapel that runs out from the north side of the chancel which was erected
                    to cover the remains of Griffith, lord of Vaenol. He and his lady, in white
                    marble, lie on a tomb within, he in armour and trunk hose, she in the dress she
                        wore.<note type="editorial">For the Vaynol monument, see <ref type="http" target="https://coflein.gov.uk/en/archive/6387978/details/504">here.</ref></note> The figures are well executed and I could not help
                    admiring the neatness of the white marble mat on which they lay. The date, 1543,
                    is still legible on the tomb, but the inscriptions, arms, and even </p>
                <pb n="p.49"/>
                <fw>p.49</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p> the features are defaced, not only by the rude hand of time, but hands still
                    more mischievous. Vaenol is on the shore of the <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai</placeName>, about four miles from <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>. The present lord is <persName ref="pe0944">Ashton
                        Smith</persName> Esqr .</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Were I a great Welsh heiress, descended from the Madogs and Molwynogs of the
                    country, I would not change my name for that of Oakley or Smith. If I could not,
                    like <persName ref="pe2195">Lady Penrhyn</persName>, marry into my own family, I
                    would, at least, give myself and my possessions to one of my countrymen. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> Letter 12 </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p style="right"><placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>, Sept 13 1797</p>
                <p>My Dear Brother,</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I am sorry <hi rend="subscript">^</hi><hi rend="superscript">that</hi> I must
                    confine my good opinion of the people of <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> to those who have had little intercourse with the
                    English. Some years ago a few persons of taste and curiosity visited the noble
                    scenery of <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>. They found the inhabitants
                    simple and honest; the accommodations very indifferent; and the roads almost
                    impracticable. From the report of these, other tourists have followed; till they
                    have come in swarms; and these chiefly the rich and the great. The consequence
                    has been that the roads are improved; the farms are raised; money is introduced;
                    and the people are rapacious. An honest Welsh clergyman lamented <hi rend="superscript">to me</hi> that the English Mountain-hunters ha<hi rend="superscript">ve</hi>d his country so dear that he <del>cannot</del>
                    <hi rend="subscript">^</hi><hi rend="superscript">could</hi> not afford to live
                    in it. Four or five of the principal inns on this road are kept by Englishmen,
                    who set an example to the natives. They are only inferior to the English inns in
                    convenience, accommodations, and attendance: not at all in expence. I am sorry
                    for it; the English will improve the country and spoil the inhabitants.</p>
                <p>One instance of that English magnificence which teaches the Welsh</p>
                <pb n="p.50"/>
                <fw>p.50</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>not to under rate their services, we heard from the poor old Barber who shews the
                    castle. He had just gone over it with <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">a party of</hi> three gentlemen, who had given him three
                    half crowns for his trouble. He would gladly have mowed the beards of ninety of
                    his countrymen for the same sum! And an instance of their profiting by the
                    lesson I had from a young man, who hired a sorry keffil at <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> for a day to visit <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName>, twelve miles distant, and, on his
                    return, in the evening, the owner charged him ten shillings. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>, though it seems to a stranger
                    half Welsh and half English, is not so; there are few Englishmen reside in it,
                    and still fewer women. All the trades-people, all the poor people, all the
                    sailors, are Welsh. Many of the gentry are Irish. It was a matter of surprize to
                    me, when I first came, to find so large a number of lodgings, and so <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">small a number</hi> of sea-bathers. But I understand that
                    it is common for the Irish to live too fast in their own country, and to come
                    here to live back again. They are, however, of such a social and convivial turn,
                    that when a number of them meet, they dine drink, and play, and are obliged to
                    quit <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>, for the same reason.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The introduction of travellers and riches has made an odd jumble in the dress of
                    the middling class of women here. They mingle the cotton manufacturers of
                        <placeName ref="pl0489">Manchester</placeName> with their own wool, and
                    often hold up a gown with all the colours of the rainbow to display a petticoat
                    of the original striped woolen of the country. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The poor people live in wretched huts, in the suburbs, though they join each
                    other, and form a street. They have often but one room, which holds the family
                    day and night. The floor is unpaved, or rudely laid with large stones, and the
                    light is admitted by one shabby window, but the door is always open; and one
                    sees the mother and frequently the grand</p>
                <pb n="p.51"/>
                <fw>p.51</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>mother spinning or knitting, and the finest rosy children that imagination can
                    conceive playing around them. To say nothing of the pigs, for they are joint
                    tenants, as well as free of the city. They are invariably clad (that is, not the
                    pigs but the women) in a woolen bedgown and petticoat. Some have coarse shoes
                    and no stockings; many have stockings that reach to the foot, and fasten by a
                    loop round the second toe, and no shoes. Patched garments are often seen, ragged
                    ones scarcely ever.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I have already said that the Methodists of <placeName ref="pl1221">North
                        Wales</placeName> are very numerous. They have a general meeting once a
                    year, alternately at <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> and
                        <placeName ref="pl3213">Pwllheli</placeName>; when they assemble out of
                    doors; for no building could contain them. On these occasions their ministers
                    preach to them successively, till they are wrought up to such a pitch of
                    enthusiasm, that they first groan and distort their features; then throw their
                    heads about; then their arms; and then they begin to jump; which they continue
                    to do so long, and with such violence, that the women have been known to jump
                    out of their hats, caps, and handkerchiefs, and, almost, out of their
                    petticoats. [------------]</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The market at <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> is much crowded, but
                    many of the articles of sale are not regularly supplied. They are brought by the
                    country people round and are, as at the fair of <placeName ref="pl3129">Cerig y
                        Druidion</placeName>, the overflowing of the family. One brings to market
                    bread, another cheese, another oat cakes, <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">poultry</hi>, shoes, with wooden soles, a pair of woolen
                    stockings, a remnant of linsey, a roll of flannel, vegetables, gooseberries,
                    apples, or mats, halters or horse furniture, made of fine rushes. Buttermilk </p>
                <pb n="p.52"/>
                <fw>p.52</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>and potatoes never fail. Money will not purchase the whole of what you see. I
                    once inquired the price of a basket of eggs. The woman wanted to barter them for
                    yeast. Another basket was only to be exchanged for old linen to wrap a little
                    stranger in, whom its owner expected soon to bring into the world.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>On market day the country people pour into <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> on horseback, six women at least, to one man.
                    Sometimes the keffil carries wooden boxes, with covers, on each side; sometimes
                    coarse wicker panniers, sometimes the woman <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">has</hi> only a basket on her arm; but I have a notion it
                    often happens that the whole lading is not worth half-a-crown. If she be a poor
                    woman, she turns her horse loose into a wide part of the street, from whence he
                    is never known to stray; if one of the better sort, she pays a penny for his
                    standing in a small paddock. In either case he waits for her ready bridled and
                    saddled, till the afternoon if not the evening. Oats are a luxury the poor
                    beasts never know, they are meat for their masters; and, I daresay, they are
                    never indulged with a morsel of hay while it is possible for skin and bone to
                    pick a scanty subsistence off the ground. The country people carry back
                        <del>hats</del> the small part of their apparel <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">made of cotton</hi>, the few luxuries they can afford to
                    purchase, and any of their neighbours who may chance to be on foot, for sparing
                    the poor horse is an idea that never enters their heads.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>There is a printing press at <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>; I
                    believe the only one in <placeName ref="pl1221">North Wales</placeName>,<note type="editorial">Written above this phrase in a later hand ‘See p.98’. The
                        printing press in Caernarfon was very recent – set up in a room off the High
                        Street in 1796 by Thomas Roberts, who had learned his craft in the religious
                        community at Trefecca, near Talgarth in Breconshire. Hutton is right to
                        suggest that the bulk of printing presses were based in south and mid-Wales,
                        although Holywell and Mold had also seen new arrivals in 1796. See Ifano
                        Jones, <hi rend="italic">Printing and Printers in Wales and
                            Monmouthshire</hi> (William Lewis: Cardiff, 1925) 146-48.</note> except
                    one at <placeName ref="pl0792">Wrexham</placeName>; and there are all sorts of
                    shop-keepers, in a creditable style. But the grand article of commerce at
                        <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> is the slates, which are
                    brought down from the mountains and piled up by millions on the quay, waiting
                    their turn to be shipped off. <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> is
                    an encreasing town, and land for building upon, difficult to be got.</p>
                <pb n="p.53"/>
                <fw>p.53</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The weather, since I have been here, has been one continued storm. You know I do
                    not hope to climb mountains; for high places are as much forbidden to me now, as
                    they were to the children of Israel of old. I look at those which form a chain
                    near this place with awe, almost with reverence. I long to see the beautiful
                    scenes they inclose, and have made two attempts to reach them; but have been
                    glad to escape from approaching rain. There is a fatality attends my designs on
                    the mountains, and such is the impression they have made on my mind, that I
                    sometimes think I should not dare to look on them, if I were there. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>, though only nine miles distant,
                    cannot be seen from <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>, or any place
                    in its immediate vicinity, being intercepted by a large round smooth mountain,
                    called <placeName ref="pl3126">Moel Elian</placeName>. I pay my daily devotion
                    to one of his sons from the top of a rocky hill, that rises at the back of the
                    Hotel, and think myself very fortunate if I can see a small part of the object
                    of my adoration, which emerges from behind that mountain; but in general, like
                    other idolators, I worship in the dark.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> Letter 13 </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p style="right"><placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>, Sept 22, 1797</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>My Dear Brother,</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At last I have got among these mountains, so long the objects of my ardent
                    curiosity. I have seen the Lakes of <sic>Llanberris</sic>, which fill the space
                    between two of the most magnificent ranges of them, and I have been to
                        <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1525">Pont Aber Glaslyn</placeName>. In the first of these vales the foot of
                        <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName> is close on the right hand; in
                    the second, on the left. In my way to the Lakes of Llanberris, and about two
                    miles from this place, I crossed the river which issues out of them, and into
                    the sea here. By dint of inquiries I have found out that its true name is the St
                        Helen’s<note type="editorial">A chapel to St Helen (Capel Elen) was situated
                        on the banks of the Seiont; the saint/princess is associated in medieval
                        Welsh texts with the building of a Roman road (Sarn Elen).</note></p>
                <pb n="p.54"/>
                <fw>p.54</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>and that it is vulgarly called the <placeName ref="pl3128">Seont</placeName>. In
                    its short course it is crossed by three bridges. This is <placeName ref="pl3138">Pont Rûg</placeName>; the next, on the road to <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName>, is <placeName ref="pl3139">Pont
                        <sic>Newyd</sic></placeName>; and the third, on the road to <placeName ref="pl3213">Pwllheli</placeName>, is <placeName ref="pl3140">Pont
                        Saint</placeName>. In the centre of Pont Rûg is an iron plate, with this
                    inscription, <hi rend="underline">Harry Parry, the modern Inigo, erected this
                        bridge 1770</hi><note type="editorial">Cf Peter Bayley Williams, ‘After
                        travelling about a mile and a half from Carnarvon, we obtain a view of the
                        River Seiont, and having proceeded along its banks a short way, we cross it,
                        over a handsome Arch, built in 1769, by one Henry Parry, as appears by a
                        stone in the Battlement, and where he is undeservedly denominated the modern
                        Inigo’, <hi rend="italic">The Tourist’s Guide</hi> (1821) p. 107. </note>.
                    The bridge has one noble arch, and for aught I know, the work of the modern
                    Inigo may be worthy of the first.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Between one and two miles farther, a gate opens into a large tract of rocky land,
                    that has no barrier to divide it from the mountains, and the road across it is
                    like a rugged, ill-paved street. You will here observe that, in this country,
                    nature lets herself down softly. After producing tremendous mountains, she forms
                    rocky hills, and then, rugged, broken ground, until she reaches the sea. A
                    hollow in this range of hills, I now got over, and on the other side had a view
                    of the Lakes of Llanberis. They were closely hemmed in by the mountains;
                        <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName> distinguished from the rest by
                    its summit being covered by a cloud. The place is called <placeName ref="pl3141">Cwm y Glo</placeName>: I believe, the Hollow of the Glowing Coal. For what
                    reason I know not. It contains a few poor houses. </p>
                <p>After another week of storms, I found a fine morning, and set out for <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName> with Pennant’s description of the road,
                    as far as <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>, in my pocket, as well as
                    my head; for, fearful of missing the grand object of my research, I transcribed
                    it before I left home. I passed the <placeName ref="pl2020">church of
                        Llanbeblic</placeName>, and after crossing the <placeName ref="pl3128">Seont</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl3139">Pont Newyd</placeName>, I
                    passed <placeName ref="pl3142">Glandwna</placeName>, a house and estate lately
                    purchased by an English gentleman, who is shewing the Welsh what English money
                    and English skill can perform in agriculture.<note type="editorial">Thomas Lloyd
                        of Shrewsbury; his daughter, Frances Williams (b. 1798) was an Anglesey
                        artist, a co-founder of the Anglesey Lifeboat Association and the
                        grandmother of the C20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Welsh artist Kyffin
                        Williams.</note></p>
                <p>The road keeps still ascending. At about three miles on the right is a large old
                    uninhabited house so completely covered in ivy that <hi rend="italic">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">it</hi> seems built of green leaves. Still ascending, I
                    came to a continuation of the </p>
                <pb n="p.55"/>
                <fw>p.55</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>rocky open ground I had crossed on my way to the Lakes of Llanberis, and then
                    went down into a valley where I found an excellent road between two green
                    hedges, a river and a bridge. I now began to con my lesson. <hi rend="underline">Crossed the Fai or <placeName ref="pl3163">Gwyrfai</placeName> at
                            <placeName ref="pl3165">Pont y Bettws</placeName></hi> (the Bridge of
                    the Bead-house, or religious house). <hi rend="underline">Went through the
                        village of Bettws. Under <placeName ref="pl3126">Moel Elian</placeName>, a
                        round, smooth, stupendous mountain covered with smooth green turf. By the
                            <placeName ref="pl1526">Lake Cwellyn</placeName>, which here almost
                        fills the valley. Above, on the right, soars the magnificent
                            <sic>Mynnydd</sic> Vawr, but the sides receeding inwards, exhibiting a
                        tremendous precipice. Soon after the vale expands, and <placeName ref="pl2862">y Wyddfa</placeName> appears in full view.</hi> Nothing
                    could be more correct than this description. I had passed the <placeName ref="pl3163">Gwyrfai</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl3165">Pont y
                        Bettws</placeName>; I had passed through the village of <placeName ref="pl2855">Bettws</placeName>, which is situated directly under <placeName ref="pl3126">Moel Elian</placeName>, and consists of about half a dozen
                    houses and a church. The road still proceeded along the bottom, and crossed
                    innumerable little torrents, which, in this rainy season, rush down the
                    mountains. On the right was a few starved meadows, now half under water, and
                    beyond these, Mynnedd Vawr, well deserving the epithet Magnificent. In front, at
                    the end of the vale, was <placeName ref="pl3166">Nant mill</placeName>, and a
                    beautiful cascade, not high, but broad and rapid. At the mill the road wound
                    suddenly to the left, and I entered the margin of <placeName ref="pl1526">Cwellyn Pool</placeName>. I rode more than a mile by its side. Having
                    passed the lake I rode on; the vale instead of expanding became narrower. Where
                    was <placeName ref="pl2862">y Wyddfa</placeName>? Mountains upon mountains could
                    I see, but no <placeName ref="pl2862">Wyddfa</placeName>, though there was not a
                    cloud in the atmosphere! [---] I had passed that too! I, who knew <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName> so well, who had seen it on two sides, and
                    had contemplated it four days together on one of them when I was in
                    Merionethshire, had ridden over its base, not without seeing it, but without
                    knowing it was <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>. To this error two or
                    three circumstances might contribute. I now saw <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName> on a third side, where its appearance was</p>
                <pb n="p.56"/>
                <fw>p.56</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>different. It is a mighty mountain among others, which, from the bottom, appear
                    almost as great. Had I been on the summit, it would have had no competitor. And,
                    with due submission to Pennant, whom nobody admires more than myself, I think he
                    helped to mislead me; for the Vale expands, and <placeName ref="pl2862">y
                        Wyddfa</placeName> appears, not <hi rend="underline">after</hi> the
                        <placeName ref="pl1526">Lake Cwellyn</placeName> but before it. The foot of
                    the mountain <hi rend="underline">is</hi> the side of the lake, and the guide’s
                    house is at the head of it; from whence the most common and most easy ascent
                    begins. <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">It is three miles and three quarters to the summit</hi>.
                    The lake was now a beautiful, still water, and the mountains reflected on it
                    made almost its whole surface green. It is something less than a quarter of a
                    mile in breadth. When I discovered <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">my error</hi> I was still descending with the <placeName ref="pl3167">River Colwyn</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName>.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>From the moment we enter <placeName ref="pl2855">Bettws</placeName> there is no
                    losing the way, no turning to the right or left. It is a continued defile
                    between two ranges of mountains, that I believe never recede from each other
                    half a mile. At the upper end of <placeName ref="pl1526">Cwellyn</placeName>
                    there is a pass on the right called <placeName ref="pl3093">Drws y
                        Coed</placeName>, but it is so insignificant I did not see it. It leads
                    through the Nant or <placeName ref="pl3168">Vale of Nantlle</placeName>, passes
                    by two small lakes in the vale, called <sic>Llyniau</sic> Nantlle, and ends at
                    the village of <placeName ref="pl2034">Llanllyfni</placeName>, in the road from
                        <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1670">Penmorfa</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1594">Criccaeth</placeName>. I
                    believe it can only be explored on foot. In this unfrequented and almost
                    inaccessible <placeName ref="pl3168">Vale of Nantlle</placeName> is a farm so
                    considerable that it keeps three hundred goats, two thousand sheep, and a dairy
                    of thirty cows; besides fourscore head of other cattle. It produces oats, but
                    neither wheat nor barley will ripen.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName> is the first visible opening in
                    the mountains. It is the junction of three vales. The rivers <placeName ref="pl3167">Colwyn</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl3205">Glaslyn</placeName> make each one, and they join together to form a third.
                    Two or three miles below, the united waters rush into the sea, at <placeName ref="pl1524">Traeth Mawr</placeName>.</p>
                <pb n="p57"/>
                <fw>p.57</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName> is beautifully situated among a
                    few fertile meadows, embosomed in lofty mountains. It contains a church and
                    several houses, one of which is a decent inn. As I contemplated the tombstones
                    in the churchyard, and considered the age of man, I found that, among the
                    mountains, as in populous cities, his term is limited; the number of his years,
                    which he cannot pass, and I have not been able to ascertain that local
                    circumstances materially shorten or extend his days. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The origin of the name <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName> has been
                    detailed in verse and prose. Such places are probably not to be found in
                        <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> alone; for I remember meeting with
                    a similar story in the studies of my infancy. I think, in that famous book, The
                    Seven Wise Masters.<note type="editorial">A widespread text originally deriving
                        from India, which included the story of the faithful greyhound. There were
                        several C18th editions which Hutton could have read, including <hi rend="italic">The Famous history of the seven wise masters of Rome</hi>
                        (Printed and sold in Aldermar Church Yard, Bow-Lane, London [?1750]). It is
                        also known as ‘The Seven Sages of Rome’.</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>A Prince of <hi rend="superscript">Wales</hi>, on his return from hunting, was
                    met by his favourite dog, who had been left behind: the <hi rend="superscript">animal</hi> expressed his joy, on seeing his master, by every means that
                    eyes, and paws, and tail could devise. Not so the master. He observed that the
                    dog was covered with blood, and he saw that the cradle of his only son was
                    overturned on the floor. "Wretch!" cried he, "thou hast killed my son!" He drew
                    his sword, and, as retributive justice demanded, killed the dog. He then did
                    what he might as well have done before - he took up the cradle to examine into
                    the particular circumstances of the fact, and found the boy unhurt, and a dead
                    serpent lying near him. Concluding that the dog had slain the serpent in the
                    child's defence, and touched with remorse for having destroyed the dog, he
                    resolved to make him all the amends now in his power. He interred him
                    honourably, and erected a church over his remains. It was called <hi rend="underline">Bedd</hi>, which to this day in Welsh signifies <hi rend="underline">Grave</hi>; and <hi rend="underline">Gelert</hi> was the
                    name of the dog. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>From <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName> I walked to <placeName ref="pl1525">Pont Aber Glaslyn</placeName>, a mile and a half </p>
                <pb n="p.58"/>
                <fw>p.58</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>distant, which is reckoned one of the wonders of <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>. The bridge itself is not particularly striking, but the
                    scenery above it forms the grandest spectacle I ever saw. The river descends in
                    perpetual cascades, and foams among enormous rocks, through a chasm [-----]
                    between mountains of a stupendous height. It fills the whole space, at the
                    bottom; the road being cut out of the rock, a little above it. When I looked up,
                    scarcely could my aching eyes reach the tops of the mountains; yet halfway up.
                    On one side, was a man, reduced to a puppet, burning fern; a more dreadful trade
                    than gathering samphire on Dover Cliff.<note type="editorial">‘Half way down/
                        Hangs one that gathers samphire, dreadful trade’. Shakespeare, <hi rend="italic">King Lear</hi>, IV:vi. Bracken was used as animal bedding,
                        and the ash in soap-making.</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>If I were to form a comparison between <placeName ref="pl1525">Pont
                        Aberglaslyn</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl2829">Pont y Glyn</placeName>,
                    I should say, that one was wildly grand, the other exquisitely beautiful. The
                    first is a dashing river, and the look <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">up</hi> is tremendous; the second is a smaller river, and
                    the look down is to its narrow rocky channel, sprinkled, and sometime almost
                    hidden, by wood.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I stood upon <placeName ref="pl1525">Pont Aber Glaslyn</placeName> and
                    congratulated myself on having seen that, and <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y
                        Bwlch</placeName>, without either passing the seven miles of rock road
                    above, or fording the Traeth below, which divides them. [----] From the bridge I
                    saw the beginnings of the sands of <placeName ref="pl1524">Traeth
                        Mawr</placeName>. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName> begins the <placeName ref="pl2901">Nant Gwynan</placeName>, from which the <placeName ref="pl3205">Glaslyn</placeName> comes down from its source on <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>. It is reckoned the most picturesque vale in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>, and contains two lovely lakes. It is with
                    sorrow I say I have not seen it. I would willingly have walked a few miles up
                    it, but I was informed the beginning was not worth my pains, and the <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">beautiful</hi> part was out of my reach. The lakes are
                    six or seven miles a</p>
                <pb n="p.59"/>
                <fw>p.59</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>bove <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName>. I just looked into
                        <placeName ref="pl2901">Nant Gwynan</placeName>, and saw a narrow glen
                    between the mountains, with a road paved with stones from the size of an orange
                    to that of a flag, laid in all directions, hills, and hollows, and grass growing
                    out of every crevice. The Welsh horses travel it in safety, and I saw a man ride
                    along it with a composure that I envied; but I believe no Englishman would even
                    walk it, without looking, where he must next place his foot.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>A very worthy and intelligent <hi rend="superscript">gentle-</hi>man of
                        <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>, whose profession leads him
                    all over the county, and who never went the same road twice, while another
                    remained that led to the same place, allows the road up <placeName ref="pl2901">Nant Gwynan</placeName> to be very bad, but says there is one over the
                    mountains to the right of that vale, which goes to <placeName ref="pl3169">Dolwyddelan</placeName>, which is the worst he ever saw. On my return from
                        <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName> I saw <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName> in perfection; every atom of his vast surface was
                    visible, and, to make amends for my former neglect, I looked at him as if I
                    would get acquainted with every atom. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I hope you are not so much fatigued with my excursion as I was. I was ten hours
                    out, nine of which I was on foot, or on horseback. My stockings were shattered,
                    my feet were blistered, and I was almost ready to prove, according to the
                    opinion of some great philosophers, that man is a quadruped, by crawling on all
                    fours. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> Letter 14 </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p style="right"><placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>, Sept 29, 1797</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>My Dear Brother,</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>This is a gala day at <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>; a kind of
                    city feast, at chusing the magistrates. But the city is saved the expence of it,
                    by the liberality of a neighbouring nobleman, who out of gratitude for their not
                    voting in direct opposition to his wishes at an election, indulges about a
                    hundred Welshmen, once a year, with as much good eating as</p>
                <pb n="p.60"/>
                <fw>p.60</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>they can cram, and more good drinking than they can carry. The ladies have a
                    ball.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The shore at <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> is pebbles; but, as
                    the descent is pretty quick, the bathers are soon in the water. What are called
                    bathing machines on the English part of the coast are here, as well as at
                        <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName>, with strict propriety, called
                    bathing houses: for if the term machine imply motion, which I apprehend it does,
                    these have no title to the name, though they have wheels. They are merely used
                    for dressing and undressing, and the bathers have to walk from them <hi rend="underline">to</hi> the water, and <hi rend="underline">into</hi> the
                    water, be the same more or less. On the flat shore of <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName>, it could not well be more, if one bathed at low
                    water. At both places the nothing is regulated by the tide, to prevent the
                    inconvenience of a long promenade. At <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName>, the sea-guide gives you a total immersion, if you
                    chuse it, by pouring on your head a bucket full of salt water. I shall never
                    forget my feelings on the occasion. I would have cried out for mercy, but I
                    could not speak; and I would have run away but I could not move. I could only
                    stand still and sob <del>violently</del> piteously.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>In fine weather the Welsh ladies frequently prefer undressing in the open air to
                    being shut up in a bathing house. They sit down on the shore, and exchange their
                    cloaths for the bathing dress, and the bathing dress for their cloaths, with a
                    decency and dexterity that leaves them nothing to fear; as they do not fear
                    catching cold.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The civility of the Welsh bathing women it is unnecessary to mention. It is the
                    trade of these people, everywhere, to be civil. And as most females look up to
                    them for protection when they have their powerful element to contend with, it
                    gives them an opportunity to throw in a little kindness. At <placeName ref="pl0043">Scarborough</placeName> they carry this to such a pitch that
                    they call you my lady, my love, and my honey, in the same breath. </p>
                <pb n="p.61"/>
                <fw>p.61</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName> I asked our sea-guide,
                        Gwinnah,<note type="editorial">Gwinnah appears as a character in Hutton’s
                            novel,<hi rend="italic"> The Welsh Mountaineer</hi> (1817).</note> how
                    old she was? She could have told me in Welsh, in a moment, but the question
                    puzzled her English arithmetic. She hesitated, and answered: “Twelve above
                    twenty, and two above that.” </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Accidents appear to me frequent at <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>. During my short stay, I have seen a mother led along
                    the street, in agonies for her drowned child; and a number of sailors searching
                    the sands, at low water, for the body of their drowned comrade. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The <placeName ref="pl2020">church</placeName> at Llanbeblic is crowded with
                    tombs, almost every poor person affording a slate, laid flat upon a little brick
                    and mortar, to tell the passenger he lived and died. I saw only two inscriptions
                    at all remarkable, and these only as they related to particular customs. The
                    first was:</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Here lieth the body of Robert Ap Richard of <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>, Glazier, who died the 5 day of June 1703. Aged 44
                    years.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>This was before the Welsh had fully obeyed the order to assume sirnames. <hi rend="underline">Ap</hi> Richard was the <hi rend="underline">son</hi> of
                    Richard, and <hi rend="underline">his</hi> son probably took the sirname of
                    Pritchard.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The other was exactly as follows.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Underneath</p>
                <p>Lie the remains of Elizapeth</p>
                <p>Piter wife of Ropert Rowland</p>
                <p>Who departed this life April the 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1790 </p>
                <p>Aged 80</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>It should seem by this that the Welsh women, like the Scotch, do not always go by
                    the names of their husbands. Elizabeth Peter was still so called, though the
                    wife of Robert Rowland. Whether this is a general custom among the lower sort of
                    people I know not.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I do not give the latter inscription as a specimen of common Welsh orthography;
                    for I have not, in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>, seen anything like
                    it.</p>
                <pb n="p.62"/>
                <fw>p.62</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The profession of the bard is not extinct in <placeName ref="pl1221">north
                        Wales</placeName>; though I believe some other occupation is generally
                    annexed to it, to procure a livelihood. The Welsh still have Bards, who compose
                    extempore verses, and sing them to the harp; and, as one of the most celebrated
                    of ancient times was denominated, <persName ref="pe2211">Rhys Coch yr
                        Eiryri</persName>, Rhys the Red, of <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>, so one of the most celebrated of the present day is
                    called <persName ref="pe2212">Dafydd Dû</persName>, yr Amlwch, <hi rend="superscript">David the Black, of Amlwch</hi>;<note type="editorial">David Thomas (Dafydd Ddu Eryri, 1759-1822). In 1796 he had obtained the
                        post of ‘Coal-Meter’ (measuring coal) at Amlwch copper mines on Anglesey;
                        Hutton’s reference to him as Dafydd Du ‘of Amlwch’ is thus highly topical,
                        since he did not remain in this role for long.</note> from their respective
                    complexions, and places of residence. These Bards form themselves into
                    societies, and elect a president; who, at their meetings, gives a subject, upon
                    which each man present makes verses, without hesitation. Those which the
                    president deems the best are intitled to a prize. The Welsh say, that some of
                    these compositions of the moment have great merit; but that they lose much on
                    being translated into English.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>On the opposite side of the river at <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> is a summer house, which crowns the top of a steep
                    hill, covered with wood. It is, itself, a distinguished object and commands an
                    extensive view both of sea and land. [xxxxxxxxxxxx].<note type="editorial">Seven
                        lines are scored through here, and are illegible.</note> The place is called
                    Coed Ellen, the Wood of Helen. If you have any desire to become acquainted with
                    this female saint, the lady patroness of both wood and river, I must inform you
                    that she is Helen, the mother of Constantine.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>But ask me no further I beseech you, lest I betray my ignorance; for though I
                    have read</p>
                <pb n="p.63"/>
                <fw>p.63</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I think of Helen, mother of the Emperor Constantine, I never heard of her travels
                        <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>.<note type="editorial">Helen
                        mother of the Emperor Constantine, (246/248-c. 330) is frequently conflated
                        with 'Elen Luydawc' ('Elen of the Hosts'), who appears in the Welsh medieval
                        legend 'Macsen Wledig' as a princess of Segontium (Caernarfon), wife of
                        Magnus Maximus (fourth century ruler of Britain).</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I have walked from the quay at <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>, by
                    the side of the river, up to <placeName ref="pl3140">Pont Saint</placeName>, and
                    from thence have accompanied it to <placeName ref="pl3139">Pont
                        <sic>Newyd</sic></placeName>. I endeavoured to trace it up to <placeName ref="pl3138">Pont Rûg</placeName>, but bogs and impenetrable brushwood
                    compelled me to return. Its banks are generally steep and woody, with now and
                    then a meadow. A carriage road runs along the <placeName ref="pl2022">Coed
                        Ellen</placeName> side of the river, and joins the <placeName ref="pl3213">Pwllheli</placeName> road at <placeName ref="pl3140">Pont
                    Saint</placeName>. The end of the avenue is closed by a mill which is an object
                    truly picturesque.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We leave this place next Wednesday, and leave it with the pleasant conviction
                    that <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> is not always so inhospitable as
                    we first found it. Settled fair weather is settled here also, but stormy weather
                    falls with a tenfold vengeance. Numberless are the people that go to see
                        <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>; but it is the lot only of a few
                    favoured mortals to say they <hi rend="underline">have</hi> seen it. Many, in
                    climbing it, have been overtaken by torrents of rain and gusts of wind that have
                    obliged them to creep on their hands and knees; or cling to the rock, or their
                    guide, to prevent their being blown down the precipices. I believe the reasons
                    of the imperfect accounts given of <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>
                    are, first, because few can see it when they get there; and, secondly, because
                    the few that can think of nothing but how they can get down.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> Letter 15 </p>
                <p style="right"><placeName ref="pl1477">Denbigh</placeName>, Oct 6th, 1797</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>My Dear Brother,</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Our road as far as <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName> was the same that
                    brought us to <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>. At <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName> we exchanged our accommodation for the
                        <placeName ref="pl3124">Harp</placeName>, where we met with good
                    accommodation and civil treatment from the honest Innkeeper, +its master.<note type="authorial">+ He was afterwards drowned in crossing his own
                        river</note> The best Harper I have heard in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> made me afraid to use my teeth at dinner, lest they
                    should interrupt the office of</p>
                <pb n="p.64"/>
                <fw>p.64</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>my ears. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We intended yesterday morning to have sent our horses four miles higher up the
                    river to the Pont at <placeName ref="pl1596">Tal y Cefn</placeName>, rather than
                    have had them dragooned into the ferry boat at <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName>, as they were wholly unaccustomed to the water. But
                    moderate measures succeeded; they entered the ferry without much difficulty, and
                    we followed in the mail boat.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The mail boat is moored with a running rope, and is always afloat. The passengers
                    cross the river in all weathers and at all tides, but persons who can wait
                    seldom chuse to go at less than half flood, or more than half ebb, on account of
                    the wet sands they would have to walk over.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I look with admiration on the mechanism of the mail-coaches. Not on the
                    construction of their wheels and springs, <del>though the motion produced by
                        these is as easy as anything, except sailing</del>, but on the whole,
                    considered as one grand machine, pervading every part of the kingdom, and
                    governed by invariable laws. As an individual, I never tried them but once. I
                    was then struck with the singularity of finding the horses or the dinner waiting
                    our arrival at the different inns, according as we were to proceed, or refresh
                    ourselves, instead of having them to bespeak. It reminded me of those scenes of
                    enchantment, where the castle door stands open, and the table is spread, before
                    the stranger has even time to signify his wishes. I own I was also struck with
                    another circumstance – as decent people do, sometimes, travel in stage-coaches;
                    and as all, probably, pay for what they eat and drink, I was surprised that they
                    should be regarded, at inns, as vagrants, who were whipped from town to
                    town.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The <placeName ref="pl1018">Holyhead</placeName> mail-coach leaves <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> at seven o clock in the evening, and reaches
                        <placeName ref="pl1018">Holyhead</placeName> about the same hour next
                    morning but</p>
                <pb n="p.65"/>
                <fw>p.65</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>one; performing a journey of two hundred and eighty two miles in forty-eight
                    hours. The fare is five guineas each person for the whole way, or sixpence per
                    mile for any part. Each passenger pays a shilling at <placeName ref="pl3075">Conwy ferry</placeName>, and the same at <placeName ref="pl1563">Bangor
                        ferry</placeName>. The packets from <placeName ref="pl1018">Holyhead</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1673">Dublin</placeName> are fine
                    sloops of 70 tons burthen. I saw one at <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>, wainscoted with mahogany, elegantly fitted up and
                    furnished. They can carry a hundred persons each, but they only have sixteen
                    beds. They are each allowed fourteen hands, though four would be sufficient to
                    navigate the vessel. They are fast sailors, and will live in any sea, provided
                    they have room. Indeed I was told there never was an instance of one being lost.
                    For if it happened that they could not make the post for which they were bound,
                    they were always bound to run into some other. They undergo a thorough
                    examination once a year, when every failing is repaired, and as far as possible,
                    prevented. The passage to or from <placeName ref="pl1673">Dublin</placeName>, is
                    a guinea.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>But I forget I had just crossed the river <placeName ref="pl2384">Conwy</placeName>.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We rode a short way along the Denbighshire bank of the river, and then turned to
                    the left, up a narrow marshy road. [<del>xxxxxx</del>] The old road continued
                    along this vale till it ended in the Irish Sea, and then bore to the right,
                    along a great promontory called <placeName ref="pl3170">Penmaen
                    Rhos</placeName>, where it was more terrific and dangerous than over <placeName ref="pl1338">Penmaen Mawr</placeName> itself.<note type="editorial">Cf
                        Thomas Pennant, ‘In my memory the traveller went along a narrow path cut on
                        its front, like the road on Penmaen Mawr, but infinitely more terrible and
                        dangerous; a fine coach-road has of late been formed far behind this
                        precipice.’ <hi rend="italic">Tour in Wales</hi> (1784) II, 334.</note>
                    Fortunately for us, the new <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">road</hi> turned to the right before we reached it. We
                    wound round the hills, and crossed them at what might be termed a miniature
                    bwlch, and reached the sea by a shorter, as well as an easier way.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I believe <placeName ref="pl3170">Penmaen Rhos</placeName> to have been the place
                    where the unfortunate <persName ref="pe2268">Richard the second</persName> was
                    betrayed by the Earl of Northumberland, because I know no other [<del>xxx</del>]
                    that answers that description.</p>
                <p>History says that when Henry Duke of Hereford, who then assumed the</p>
                <pb n="p.66"/>
                <fw>p.66</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>title of Duke of Lancaster, and soon after, that of <persName ref="pe0667">Henry
                        the fourth</persName>, had proceeded as far as <placeName ref="pl0002">Chester</placeName>, and when <persName ref="pe2268">Richard the
                        second</persName>, abandoned by his troops and [xxx] followers, had fled for
                    refuge to <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName> castle; that <persName ref="pe2268">Richard</persName> sent two noblemen to Henry, offering to
                    resign his crown, and retire to private life, if his person might be safe. His
                    ambassadors were not suffered to return. The Archbishop of Canterbury
                    represented to Henry that it would be very difficult to take the King in such a
                    country as <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> where the mountains
                    afforded numerous retreats inaccessible to an army; and advised that he should
                    decoy his fallen sovereign by treachery. The Earl of Northumberland was sent to
                        <placeName ref="pl1530">Conwy Castle</placeName>, where he obtained an
                    audience of the King, and swore, upon the sacrament, that if he would dismiss
                    his evil counsellors, whom he named, and accompany him to <placeName ref="pl0002">Chester</placeName>; the Duke of Lancaster would fall on his
                    knees and ask for mercy. He assured him also that the Duke had taken the same
                    oath.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>In an evil hour <persName ref="pe2268">Richard</persName> quitted his castle,
                    deemed impregnable, and his vessels, which might have conveyed him out of the
                    reach of his revolted subjects, and crossed the <placeName ref="pl2384">Conwy</placeName>, with only sixteen followers. He had not ridden more than
                    four miles when he saw a body of armed men under a rock. The King perceived the
                    snare into which he had fallen, and upbraided Northumberland with the breach of
                    his oath. The Earl endeavoured to excuse himself by saying he had appointed the
                    soldiers to meet them, only to guard the king’s person. The king replied there
                    needed not so many; and that by his oath he was bound not to have more than the
                    five who had accompanied him to <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName>.
                    Northumberland then threw off the mask, and told the king that since he had him,
                    he would keep him.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The sea beat on one side of the ill-advised and ill-fated monarch; impenetrable
                    rocks rose on the other; a thousand lances and archers stood before him; and to
                    return was impossible. He came down from the rock</p>
                <pb n="p.67"/>
                <fw>p.67</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>and surrendered himself to the traitor, who obliged him to take a little wine and
                    bread; took him to <placeName ref="pl1978">Rŷddlan castle</placeName> to dinner,
                    and to <placeName ref="pl2418">Flint castle</placeName> to lodge; where, the
                    next morning, he was met by his adversary. – My indignation is roused by the two
                    first peers of the realm, spiritual and temporal, the one contriving, and the
                    other executing, so base a trick!</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>From the time we reached the sea till we arrived at <placeName ref="pl1203">Abergeleu</placeName>, our road was that of <persName ref="pe2268">Richard</persName>. I saw no rock likely to have been the scene of this
                    infamous transaction. On the contrary, we had fields of corn and grass, and even
                    trees, which did not seem to suffer by the sea breezes. <placeName ref="pl3170">Penmaen Rhos</placeName> is such a rock. There, the sea would beat on the
                    king’s left, the mountain would rise on his right, and the soldiers might be
                    hidden from his view, till they were just under him, by the projection of the
                    rock.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>After passing over a steep hill the country diminished in beauty and at eight
                    miles from <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName> we came to a village, the
                    name of which I inquired. The man answered, in English, "Black-and-Blue." We
                    concluded that he was a Welsh wit, who had a mind to divert himself at our
                    expence, and rode on. Not quite satisfied, however, we repeated our question to
                    the next man, who answering <placeName ref="pl3171">Llandûlas</placeName>, we
                    were convinced of the ingenuity of our first informer. On mentioning the
                    circumstance at <placeName ref="pl1203">Abergeleu</placeName>, we were told that
                    the name of the place was really <placeName ref="pl3171">Llandûlas</placeName>,
                    the signification of which in English was the Parish of Black and Blue.<note type="editorial">‘Du’ is black; ‘glas’ is blue. Dulas appears relatively
                        frequently in Welsh place-names, and can also mean dark blue or blackish
                        blue.</note> We then found our Welshman, instead of his wit, only shewed his
                    learning. If the village takes its name from a patron saint, as most of the
                    Welsh villages do, it is reasonable to suppose that Dûlas must have been some
                    distinguished pugilist.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At eleven miles from <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName> we came to
                        <placeName ref="pl1203">Abergeleu</placeName> situated in a flat country,
                    backed by hills that have lost all title to the name of mountains. The town is
                    poor, but must be pleasant enough </p>
                <pb n="p.68"/>
                <fw>p.68</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>when enlivened by sea-bathers. The sea is a mile distant. The shore is low, but
                    the view is grand. One seems to look upon the unlimited ocean from the centre of
                    a capacious bay, formed by <placeName ref="pl3170">Penmaen Rhôs</placeName> on
                    one hand and a headland which shoots out from the <placeName ref="pl1443">Vale
                        of Clwyd</placeName>, on the other. The <placeName ref="pl1305">town</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1978">castle</placeName> of Rhyddlan
                    are plainly seen, under the latter, at the distance of four or five miles. The
                    town looks pitiful, the castle respectable. Its circular towers resemble those
                    of <placeName ref="pl1521">Harlech</placeName>.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At <placeName ref="pl1203">Abergeleu</placeName> we quitted the coast, and passed
                    through the village of <placeName ref="pl3172">Llansansior</placeName>, or Llan
                    St George; the first English saint I have met with in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>. The Welsh have a calendar of their own. Soon after, we
                    rode by <placeName ref="pl1976">Kinmael</placeName>, the seat of <persName ref="pe2165">Mr Hughes</persName>, beautifully situated on the side of a
                    hill, and commanding half the <placeName ref="pl1443">Vale of
                    Clwyd</placeName>.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The <placeName ref="pl1443">Vale of Clwyd</placeName> is about twenty-six miles
                    long, and six wide. It is bounded, at the upper end, by the mountains of
                        <placeName ref="pl1211">Yale</placeName>, which separate it from the parish
                    of <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName>. At the lower, it is open to the
                    sea. On each side it is inclosed by a continued chain of hills, not divided,
                    like the mountains of <placeName ref="pl1234">Caernarvonshire</placeName>, but
                    rising from one base, though with different summits. I am told that the whole
                    eastern side has only one narrow outlet, without climbing the hills. There are
                    four market towns in the <placeName ref="pl1443">Vale of Clwyd</placeName>: -
                        <placeName ref="pl1305">Rhyddlan</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1371">St
                        Asaph</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1477">Denbigh</placeName>, and
                        <placeName ref="pl1246">Ruthin</placeName>. The remains of castles are still
                    seen at all, except <placeName ref="pl1371">St Asaph</placeName>. The villages I
                    cannot enumerate. Gentleman's houses, some of which wear the appearance of
                    palaces, meet the eye every moment; and the dwellings of the farmers look
                    comfortable and convenient. The fields are beautiful, the woods are fine; the
                    surface of the ground is variegated, the soil is a rich dark mould.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I am told that land in the <placeName ref="pl1443">Vale of Clwyd</placeName>
                    lets, on an average, at 2l. [£2] an acre; that one large farm is even let for
                    3l. 10s. and the occupier has made a fortune. Bold<note type="editorial">Reading
                        uncertain.</note> pieces of land are frequently let as high as 6l. an acre;
                    and when land of any description is to be let, it is sought after </p>
                <p> </p>
                <fw>p.69</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>with avidity, and obtained with difficulty. The inhabitants of the Vale [xxxx]
                    consume about a sixteenth part of its produce. the hills that inclose it are
                    cultivated to nearly two-thirds of their height. In one point only the
                        <placeName ref="pl1443">Vale of Clwyd</placeName> is deficient, and in all
                    other parts of <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> that I have seen that
                    deficiency is an exuberance; the vale itself is scantily watered, and the towns,
                    being built on hills rising out of it, have no water at all.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1305">Rhyddlan</placeName> I have seen only at a distance.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1371">St Asaph</placeName> is the seat of an episcopal see; and
                    poorer, and even smaller, than <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName>. The
                        <placeName ref="pl1561">cathedral</placeName> is full as good, and the choir
                    neatly fitted up.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1477">Denbigh</placeName>, the capital of the county, is a
                    tolerably large and decent looking town, on the side of a steep rock. The
                        <placeName ref="pl1880">castle</placeName> formerly occupied the summit, but
                    part of the area is now a bowling green, from whence the view, comprehending all
                    the lower, and much of the upper part of the <placeName ref="pl1443">Vale of
                        Clwyd</placeName> is magnificent. The castle is in a very ruined state, but
                    from the shapeless mass that remains, and the walls of prodigious thickness, it
                    appears to have been a place of great strength. The entrance, a grand arch, is
                    still intire, with the figure of <persName ref="pe1340">Henry Lacy</persName>,
                    the founder, sculptured over it. A noble building, of slighter mould, and later
                    date, with ten or twelve fine arched windows on each side, is said to have been
                    intended for a church in the days of <persName ref="pe0357">Elizabeth</persName>, but never finished. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Letter 16</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p style="right">
                    <placeName ref="pl0002">Chester</placeName>, October 7th, 1797</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>My dear Brother,</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At three miles beyond <placeName ref="pl1477">Denbigh</placeName> we passed
                    through the village of Llanrhaiader, where a flaming King’s Head, a very
                    uncommon object in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>, was placed against
                    the wall of a <placeName ref="pl3173">house</placeName>. As I rode along I read
                    the following lines, which I had no difficulty in remembering.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.70"/>
                <fw>p.70</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Within this place there is a vault</p>
                <p>Where such good liquor’s fix’d</p>
                <p>You’ll say that water, hops and malt</p>
                <p>Were never better mix’d. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><del>These lines recalled to mind several other invitations to ale-houses, which
                        I have met with in other parts of England; for, if I see two lines hang over
                        my head, I always read them as I [run?], though I believe none will dispute
                        the laurel with the Welsh poet. You would think me very vulgar if I were to
                        repeat such compositions, perhaps? Never mind, you shall have them. The
                        first is a sprightly widow in Yorkshire who cries:</del></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>
                    <del>Look up, Gentlemen, what do you think?</del></p>
                <p><del>The Widow Waddington sells you drink!</del></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><del>The two next are found upon their respective signs.The first is the sign of
                        the shoemaker’s last, and the motto:</del></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><del>All the long day I have sought for good ale</del></p>
                <p><del>And at the last I’ve found it.</del></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><del>The other is the sign of the Moon, and underneath is written</del></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><del>Come in, my friends, and take a sup </del></p>
                <p><del>And go home while the moon is up.</del></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><del>The last I shall give you is in the style of my Welsh friend in
                        Llanrhaiader:</del></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><del>Halliday’s ale is stout and fine</del></p>
                <p><del>Much care and pains he takes to brew it</del></p>
                <p><del>If to taste it you incline</del></p>
                <p><del>Turn down this lane, you’ll soon come to it.</del></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Pardon me for detaining you [<del>xxx</del>]at <hi rend="superscript">an</hi>
                    ale-house door. We will now get on to <placeName ref="pl1246">Ruthin</placeName>.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1246">Ruthin</placeName> is the last town in the <placeName ref="pl1443">Vale of Clwyd</placeName>, and the most flourish</p>
                <pb n="p.71"/>
                <fw>p.71</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p> ing. It consists of three streets running up a hill, two along its top, and one
                    down on the other side. They all meet in the centre, where an ancient, clumsy
                    market house obstructs the way. But time has given it a kind of prescriptive
                    right, which I should feel some scruples to invade. The left [<del>xx</del>]
                    street at the top of the hill leads to the church. [<del>xxxxxx</del>]. The
                    right [<del>xx</del>] street leads to the castle, of which little now remains
                    but broken detached pieces of thick wall. When <persName ref="pe0495">Owen
                        Glyndwr</persName> lived in <placeName ref="pl1258">Glyndwrdy</placeName> or
                    the Vale of Dee, here lived <persName ref="pe1035">Lord Grey</persName> of
                    Ruthin, and though ten miles distant, and separated by a natural barrier of
                    mountains, the two chiefs were too powerful to be friends.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The mountains which inclose the <placeName ref="pl1443">Vale of Clwyd</placeName>
                    are respectable, though not sublime. Over the eastern range, and towards the
                    head of the vale, we now had to climb, on our way to <placeName ref="pl1857">Mold</placeName> and in all my mountain hunting, such an escalade never
                    fell to my lot. The ascent is two miles and very steep; it is cultivated high
                    up, and there is even a gentleman’s house and park in a place where no wheel
                    once set a-going could be stopped. Yet this is the road on which coal is carried
                    to <placeName ref="pl1246">Ruthin</placeName>, and on it we met two loaded
                    carts. The manner of conducting them is ingenious, but, to me, not very
                    satisfactory; and they approached so near to ungovernable, that I was glad when
                    they had passed. They were small and not heavily laden, drawn by one horse, in
                    the shafts, led by a boy, and stopped by two horses, behind, pulled back by a
                    man; and with all their holding back, crossing the road, and dexterity of
                    steerage, I expected every moment that the carts and horses would escape from
                    their pilots, and overwhelm men, horses, and everything else they found in their
                    way.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I rode up till I was not without some fears of sliding down over my horse’s tail;
                    I then walked. The road now overhung a chasm or bwlch, called Bwlch Pen Barras;
                    and, with much toil, I reached the top. On the right rose </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.72"/>
                <fw>p.72</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>the summit of the mountain, Pen Barras, from which the pass takes its name, and
                    on the left, beyond the gulph, that of the still higher mountain, <placeName ref="pl3175">Moel Famma</placeName>. </p>
                <p>From the top of <placeName ref="pl3174">Bwlch Pen Barras</placeName>, the sun
                    shining in our faces, and the haziness of an October sky, prevented our seeing
                    the whole of the <placeName ref="pl1443">Vale of Clwyd</placeName>, and, over
                    the tops of its western hills, the towering mountains of <placeName ref="pl1183">Snowdonia</placeName>. We knew that such things were, but they were not for
                    us. Our climate altered, as we travelled upwards. In the Vale, <del>it</del>
                    <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">the air</hi> was calm and warm, but, before we gained the
                    top of the pass, <del>the air</del>
                    <hi rend="superscript">it</hi> was piercing, and the wind was high. When I hear
                    the beating rain and roaring blast in my [<del>xxx</del>] chamber at home, I
                    shall congratulate myself that I am not at top of <placeName ref="pl3174">Bwlch
                        Pen Barras</placeName>. Indeed, I can conceive of nothing on land so
                    dreadful, in a storm, as these Welsh bwlchs in the mountains.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>On the other side, the descent was trifling, but we had not only another climate;
                    we had another world. We exchanged, in a moment, the rich landscapes of the
                        <placeName ref="pl1443">Vale of Clwyd</placeName> for mountains covered with
                    heath no longer purple, and fern already brown.</p>
                <p>The cottages and their inhabitants partook of the poverty of the soil. We pursued
                    our way, still environed by mountains, which now were rocky; one before us
                    singularly so; rows of stone, one above another, encircling it round like walls.
                    All was wild and dreary, and we could not guess, round, or over, which mountains
                    our road must lie; when at a sudden turn, our man exclaimed, ‘There’s <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>!’ I turned <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">my head</hi> and, between an opening of two mountains
                    saw, <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">at a distance, and far below me</hi>, a level country,
                    with inclosed fields. Though glad of such a prospect for my lodging, I looked
                    with regret on the country I was leaving, perhaps for ever. One small scene of
                    enchantment only remained; the village of <placeName ref="pl3176">Llanverras</placeName>, with a river, a bridge, and a mill, surrounded by
                    mountains and hanging woods.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>If I had one spark of poetry within me, I would here address a pathetic far<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>well ode to the mountains, rocks, and glens of
                        <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>. In vain! I can feel; but I cannot
                    write verse! My plodding, groveling genius can</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.73"/>
                <fw>p.73</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>not even reach the sublime heights of prose, for which some ladies are so much
                    admired.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Rugged hills brought us to a stone that divides the parishes of <placeName ref="pl3176">Llanverras</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1857">Mold</placeName>, and the counties of Denbigh, and Flint, and a long
                    descent brought us to the town of <placeName ref="pl1857">Mold</placeName>,
                    situated <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">on a small hill</hi> in the flat country we had seen from
                    the moun<hi rend="superscript">tains</hi>, and, like <placeName ref="pl1477">Denbigh</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1371">St Asaph</placeName>,
                    fetching all its water from the plain below. <placeName ref="pl1857">Mold</placeName> is a neat little town, less Welsh than English. Here has
                    been a castle; the mount on which it stood is all that remains; and we were not
                    allowed to visit it. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Both the ancient and modern limits of <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>
                    and <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> appear to me altogether arbitrary;
                    they were probably fixed by the sword. The ancient dyke is about a mile and a
                    half beyond <placeName ref="pl1857">Mold</placeName>; the stone that now marks
                    the boundaries of the counties of Flint and Chester, and consequently the
                    kingdom of <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> and the principality of
                        <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>, is about a mile and a half before
                    we reach <placeName ref="pl0002">Chester</placeName>, <del>that is, nine miles
                        further</del> but the natural barrier is Mold Mountain. The last of our
                    journey, and that we descended to <placeName ref="pl1857">Mold</placeName>.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The twelve miles between <placeName ref="pl1857">Mold</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl0002">Chester</placeName> is over a flat, uninteresting country and a
                    bad road one part of which is so notorious it is called the Dirty mile.<note type="editorial">A section of the A549 between Lane End and Dobs Hill is
                        still called ‘Dirty Mile’.</note> The only objects worth notice were
                        <placeName ref="pl0788">Hawarden castle</placeName>, and the estuary of the
                        <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName>, with a multitude of vessels at
                    anchor. The last mile and half of road, which was our entrance into <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>, was the worst that ever <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> offered to my view: it was spacious enough,
                    but of soft sandy rock, that the coal carts had worn into holes sufficiently
                    large to bury themselves in. We were frequently surrounded by a dozen, and
                    sometimes by twenty of these carts; with each driver leading and pushing his
                    draft horse, and exerting all his skill in cartmanship to avoid the holes. Had a
                    wheel gotten into one of them, neither praying to </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.74"/>
                <fw>p.74</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Hercules, as the carter did of old, or putting his shoulder to the wheel, as
                    Hercules recommended, could have relieved him.<note type="editorial">Hercules
                        and the Waggoner is a fable recorded towards the end of the first century
                        AD, and later credited to Aesop. When the driver’s cart gets stuck, usually
                        in mud, he calls on the god to help him. Hercules tells him to put his own
                        shoulder to the wheel before asking for help, and the man frees the cart by
                        himself.</note> His cart must have <hi rend="superscript">been</hi> dashed
                    to pieces, in spite of men or gods. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We crossed the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName> into <placeName ref="pl0002">Chester</placeName>, which instead of the solemn, decayed city
                    I expected to find it, looks busy, populous, and flourishing. Though as it is
                    the eve of the fair, it may probably be raised something above its natural
                    pitch.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> Letter 17 </p>
                <p/>
                <p style="right"><placeName ref="pl1361">Nantwich</placeName>, Oct 9, 1797</p>
                <p>My Dear Brother, </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Do not be alarmed at seeing <placeName ref="pl1361">Nantwich</placeName> at the
                    top of a letter, when only letters from <placeName ref="pl1221">North
                        Wales</placeName> were promised you; or fancy that, like certain shy singers
                    who cannot be stopped when they are once set a-going, I may continue writing
                    across the island of <placeName ref="pl0777">Great Britain</placeName>. I give
                    it under my hand and seal, that you shall be fairly quit of me at this place. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The wall that surrounds <placeName ref="pl0002">Chester</placeName> is intire,
                    and is one mile, three quarters, a hundred and one yards in circumference. Its
                    top is a public walk, from four to six feet in width, paved with flat stones,
                    and secured by a parapet, on each side, about four feet high. Where it crosses
                    the principal outlets of the city, it runs over gateways, and the parapet walls
                    have given way to iron rails. The views from hence down into the busy streets
                    are singular. In some parts of the wall the prospect is excluded by buildings,
                    which rise on either side the path; but where it is open to the river and the
                    Welsh hills, it is delightful. The castle stands on a steep red rock, without
                    the walls. It has a new appearance, though in the old style; and exhibits a pair
                    of little cannon, to terrify whom they may concern. A row of paltry brick houses
                    have had the assurance to place themselves; and a pompous <placeName ref="pl3177">prison</placeName> is rearing its head hard by.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>On each side the principal streets of <placeName ref="pl0002">Chester</placeName>
                    are two <placeName ref="pl1537">rows</placeName> of shops, one above the other.
                    Those level with the street project from the houses and their</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.75"/>
                <fw>p.75</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>flat roofs form a gallery which is the street to the shops above. It is a
                    constant thoroughfare and communicates with the street below by flights of steps
                    and the shopkeepers display their wares on its walls and balustrades. But
                        <del>the shops must be dark and</del> I cannot conceive of the reason for
                    placing the<del>m</del> shops on one another’s shoulders when God Almighty <hi rend="superscript">there is</hi> has given room enough for them all to stand
                    on the ground – at least, if the security derived from the city walls was a
                    reason it exists no longer.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The most impressive object in <placeName ref="pl0002">Chester</placeName> is the
                        <placeName ref="pl1853">Cathedral</placeName> which is massive and grand. It
                    was originally built in the year 660, but as it now appears it is too wonderful
                    a monument of wealth and taste for that early age. I did not go in at the
                    principal entrance but at a smaller one, and found myself in a complete church,
                    dirty, dark and shabby, with a carpet on the communion table that looked as if
                    it had been several years trodden under foot at an inn. I exclaimed, what a
                    cathedral! But observing a partition with a fastened door, I went out in search
                    of another entrance and found that the precept in holy writ which enjoins us to
                        <hi rend="underline">enter in at the strait gate</hi> does not apply to
                        <placeName ref="pl1853">Chester cathedral</placeName>. I now entered in at
                    the <hi rend="underline">wide gate</hi>, and saw a noble church, divided into
                    three aisles, by two rows of pillars. The ornaments of the choir are extremely
                    fine, but the Bishop’s throne, a curious kind of stone pulpit, adorned with
                    arches, pinnacles, and small gilt statues of kings and queens of Mercia,
                    particularly attracted my notice. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I stayed the service in the <placeName ref="pl1853">cathedral</placeName>.
                    Living, as I do, in a retired place <del>xxxx</del>
                    <hi rend="superscript">in the country</hi>, the paraphernalia of religion was
                    new to me, and impressed my mind with awe. The grandeur of the place, and above
                    all the solemn sweetness of the voices, raised to celebrate the praise of
                    Almighty God, elevated my soul to him, and my emotions bordered on tears. But
                    when I saw the Dean, cloathed in scarlet</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.76"/>
                <fw>p.76</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>and fine linen, and <sic>preceeded</sic> by a silver mace, stalk along the
                    cloisters, enter a door, and become invisible to a bowing and admiring crowd,
                    the charm dissolved, and I perceived, with some indignation, that the creator
                    was lost in the creature.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The annual fair at <placeName ref="pl0002">Chester</placeName> lasts three weeks;
                    but the principal business is transacted in one. As it is the great mart to
                    which the Irish bring their linens, so it is their opportunity to supply
                    themselves with the cottons of <placeName ref="pl1044">Lancashire</placeName>,
                    the woolens of <placeName ref="pl0770">Yorkshire</placeName>, and the hardwares
                    of <placeName ref="pl1293">Birmingham</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl2523">Sheffield</placeName>. I was told that Irish linens are sold at one fair to
                    the amount of half a million sterling; and that a hundred thousand pounds worth
                    have been sold in one day. During the fair, a glove is hung out at an ancient
                    building called the <placeName ref="pl3179">Pentise</placeName>, to invite all
                    strangers to bring their goods; and the concourse of people is so great, that
                    most of the private houses let lodgings. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The day the Mayor of Chester goes out of office is a day of anarchy. His
                    authority is understood to cease in the morning; a bull is baited, all sorts of
                    petty excesses are committed; and the greatest blackguard is master. At night
                    the authority of the new mayor is acknowledged and all things are restored to
                    order.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl0002">Chester</placeName> is forty miles from <placeName ref="pl0723">Liverpool</placeName> by land, as the first bridge over the
                        <placeName ref="pl2906">Mersey</placeName> is at <placeName ref="pl0265">Warrington</placeName>. By water is a voyage of only three hours, with a
                    favourable wind. A covered boat, with a cabin, sets out every day, and conveys
                    passengers by a canal cut between the <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName>
                    and the <placeName ref="pl2906">Mersey</placeName>, and a packet waits to carry
                    them on to <placeName ref="pl0723">Liverpool</placeName> by sea.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The whole country from <placeName ref="pl0002">Chester</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1361">Nantwich</placeName>, a distance of nineteen miles, is a
                    continued plain; but a considerable range of hills from a back ground to the
                    left. For the first five miles, to the village of <placeName ref="pl0003">Tarvin</placeName>, the country is poor, and road a wretched pavement.
                    Beyond through</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.77"/>
                <fw>p.77</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>the villages of <placeName ref="pl3180">Duddon</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl3181">Clotton</placeName>, I was gratified with the sight of fine
                    pastures, variegated with wood, and large and neat balck and white farm houses
                        [<del>xxxxx</del>]. Every thing wore the aspect of abundance. About three
                    miles, on our right, stood <placeName ref="pl1536">Beeston Castle</placeName>,
                    on the summit of a tall insulated rock, rising abruptly out of the plain, and
                    said to be 365 feet in height. A number, perhaps, too singular to be exactly
                    true.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>In answer to my enquiries concerning the dairies of <placeName ref="pl1362">Cheshire</placeName>, I was informed they are generally from thirty to
                    sixty cows, and there are a few of fourscore. A dairy of fifty cows will make
                    two cheeses a day, of fifty or sixty pounds weight each. Farms are let from
                    thirty shillings to three pounds an acre, and the candidates for them are so
                    numerous, that they are commonly let by auction. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At ten miles from <placeName ref="pl0002">Chester</placeName> we came to
                        <placeName ref="pl3182">Tarporley</placeName>, a small Market Town. I saw on
                    a tomb, in the church, two ladies of the Crewe family, in the dress of the time
                    of King William, whose towers<note type="editorial">OED sv ‘Tower’ (n.6.b) ‘A
                        very high head-dress worn by women in the reigns of William III and Anne. It
                        was built up in the form of a tower of pasteboard, muslin, lace, and
                        ribbons’.</note> the statuary had plaited as neatly, in beautiful white
                    marble, as it was possible for their own tire-women to have done, in fine
                        lace.<note type="editorial">These are Jane Done (d. 1662) and Mary Crewe (d.
                        1690), and her granddaughter Mary Knightley who died as a child in 1674. The
                        monument comprises three figures in white marble on a black base, the women
                        recumbent and the child with flowers standing.</note>
                </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1361">Nantwich</placeName> is a large town, and contains a
                    greater number of fine old half-timbered houses, of about the days of Elizabeth,
                    than I have remarked in any one place. The <placeName ref="pl3183">church</placeName>, both within and without, is in the cathedral style; and
                    much it grieved me to see a part of it going to decay. The houses surround the
                    churchyard, without any fence to make them keep at a proper distance, and the
                    consequence has been that on one side they <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">have</hi> encroached on the view of this noble edifice;
                    and on the other there is only a very narrow passage between.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>In the body of the <placeName ref="pl3183">church</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl1361">Nantwich</placeName> is a curious antique stone pulpit not now
                    made use of; and two old carved pews, mounted up aloft. In one of the transepts
                    is a coffin, without a lid, hollowed out of a solid block of wood, into the form
                    of the body which has been placed in it. It </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.78"/>
                <fw>p.78</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>was found under the chancel, when the pavement was taken up to repair a drain. In
                    the other transept is an unheeded, mutilated figure of a knight, perhaps a hero
                    of the crusades;<note type="editorial">This may be the alabaster effigy of Sir
                        David Craddock, (d. ca 1384), in the south transept.</note> a proof, if any
                    proof were wanting, that men must die, and their productions must follow. The
                    choir is very beautiful; its stalls are ornamented with carving.<note type="editorial">The church contains some 20 intricately carved misericords
                        of the early C15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</note> The roof exhibits,
                    among its gothic ribs, a number of small tablets of stone, on which is
                    sculptured the history of our Saviour; the floor is paved with little square
                    bricks, that appear to have been painted. But Peter and Paul block up the
                    window, and keep out the light; an office those worthy apostles were certainly
                    never designed for. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The people of <placeName ref="pl1361">Nantwich</placeName> take more care of
                    their churchyard than of their <placeName ref="pl3183">church</placeName>. While
                    the beautiful roof, and carved ornaments of the one are mouldering away, every
                    grave that is made in the other is instantly levelled, so that it has no
                    appearance of a cemetery. </p>
                <p> </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>