<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0031">
    <teiHeader type="w">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Catherine Hutton’s Tour of Wales: 1799
                    <date>1799</date></title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Edited with an introduction by Mary-Ann Constantine</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                        <idno>MS 19079C</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p> Letter 18 </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p style="right"><placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> Aug 20 1799</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>My Dear Brother,</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We have made our third sally into <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>, but
                    as we are come here by the same route as we did two years ago, I have little to
                    trouble you with, except the weather and [<del>xxxxx</del>] this <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">subject</hi> will hardly have novelty to recommend it;
                    for you must have been singularly fortunate if it has not troubled you before.
                    Our share <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">however</hi> has been so extraordinary that you must be
                    content <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">to</hi> bear a part of it with your own.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><del>The fine old windows and door of the Abbey Church at <placeName ref="pl0740">Shrewsbury</placeName>, with the figure of Roger de Montgomery, kinsman
                        of the Conqueror and one of his commanders at the Battle of Hastings, high
                        above, had always attracted my admiration. I determined now to see the
                        inside but found nothing to repay my pains, except a very ancient statue of
                        the same Earl, who was the founder of the Abbey, and died there,</del>
                </p>
                <pb n="p.79"/>
                <fw>p.79</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p><del>one of its monks, in 1094. The legs are broken, the face is a shapeless
                        blank, but the right arm is visibly drawing the sword. “And did this repay
                        your pains?” I hear you say. I think it did, but its age was its sole
                        merit.</del></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> the waiter, who is the first
                    personage in the house and minds everybody’s business but his own, overwhelmed
                    us with civility and gave us nothing to eat. Instead of setting the machine in
                    motion, and letting it move by its own impulse, he is pushing here, driving
                    there, shouting every where, and fancies that not an atom can stir without
                    him.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We passed Owen <persName ref="pe0495"/>Glyndwr at <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName>, regardless of the intreaties of our horses, who,
                    remembering the rest and refreshment it had twice afforded them, were very
                    desirous to enter its stable, but I was determined to try the <placeName ref="pl2463">Druid</placeName>, a true Welsh inn, about two miles and half
                    further, in preference to stopping at one of the mongrel posting inns on this
                    great road. I had no reason to repent my choice. We had a good parlour, a good
                    fire, and a good dinner. The furniture of my bed was modern printed cotton, and
                    all the royal family, with many of the saints, arrayed in the brightest scarlet
                    and the deepest blue, ornamented the walls of my chamber. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I have formerly told you that the munificence of English tourists, as far as it
                    extended, has spoiled the Welsh, and I cannot help reflecting now, that it is
                    very difficult not to spoil them, since we, who are neither immensely rich, nor
                    extravagantly generous, could scarcely refrain from contributing to it! I told
                    the good woman at the <placeName ref="pl2463">Druid</placeName> she charged too
                    little for our mutton chops and chickens, and obliged her to be paid for a slice
                    of bread and butter she wished to give me, at setting out. Such conduct must, in
                    the end, cure people of moderation and hospitality.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I was desirous of going from the <placeName ref="pl2463">Druid</placeName> to
                        <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName>, and from thence to</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.80"/>
                <fw>p.80</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>, the mountain road, by <placeName ref="pl1523">Festiniog</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y
                        Bwlch</placeName>, and the rock road to <placeName ref="pl1525">Pont Aber
                        Glaslyn</placeName>. I consulted our landlord on the subject, and asked,
                    “What sort of road from here to <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName>?”</p>
                <p>“Up an town roat, put very coot” </p>
                <p>This I had travelled, and knew the <hi rend="underline">up and down</hi> to be
                    true; though I differed a little in opinion, with regard to the <hi rend="underline">very good</hi>. </p>
                <p>“What from <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1523">Festiniog</placeName>?”</p>
                <p>“Mountain, put very coot roat”</p>
                <p>“From <placeName ref="pl1523">Festiniog</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y Bwlch</placeName>, and <placeName ref="pl1525">Pont Aber
                        Glaslyn</placeName>?”</p>
                <p>“All up and town, put very coot road”</p>
                <p>I found that, to the honest Welshman, who had never been out of his own country,
                    all its roads were good; and as the weather was now become very bad, I resolved
                    to keep the high road, through <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName> and
                        <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName>, which had the suffrages of other
                    people.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The rain <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">had</hi> begun as we were ascending the mountain from
                        <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName>, and it continued without
                    intermission for twenty four hours. While we were detained at the <placeName ref="pl2463">Druid</placeName>, our landlord produced his library, to amuse
                    us. It consisted of a treatise against popery, of six hundred pages, dedicated
                    to James the second, when Duke of York; the Causes of the Decay of Christian
                    Piety, four hundred and fifty pages;<note type="editorial">Richard Allestree,
                            <hi rend="italic">The causes of the decay of Christian piety, or, An
                            impartial survey of the ruines of Christian religion, undermin'd by
                            unchristian practice written by the author of The whole duty of man</hi>
                        (1667).</note> and an old Geographical Dictionary. You will, perhaps,
                    imagine that when I had made myself mistress of the title pages, and quantity, I
                    took up my netting; and if [<del>xxx</del>] <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">such is your conjecture</hi>, you will not be
                    mistaken.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At one o’clock the rain abated and we took leave of our worthy host and hostess,
                    but it increased gradually, and from <placeName ref="pl1576">Cerniogeu</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>, was
                    a second deluge. The beautiful Vale of Llanrwst was half under water, <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">and</hi> the corn that, two years ago, was a bright
                    yellow, was now green [<del>xxx</del>]. I entered the inn as wet as before.</p>

                <pb n="p.81"/>
                <fw>p.81</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We had the good fortune to reach <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName> the
                    next day in dry weather, but we passed through the remains of a great flood that
                    had swept down hedges, rails, and banks; and as we were told, a house.<note type="editorial">In a letter from Beaumaris, 18 August 1799, the Welsh poet
                        Edward Williams (Iolo Morganwg) wrote, ‘A continual rain for three weeks has
                        occasioned such dreadful floods in north Wales that it is truly lamentable
                        to see how the country has been torn by them; cattle, hay &amp;c in
                        abundance lost; hares and foxes found amongst the drowned; cows, sheep,
                        horses &amp;c in the Menai houses swept away, corn laid flat on the ground;
                        and what is worse, people drowned in their houses. Amongst the many bridges
                        carried off is that ornament of our country, the beautiful bridge of
                        Llanrwst. I could weep for the loss of it. Hay carried down by the flood
                        stopt up the arches till the pressure of the accumulating flood became so
                        great as to thrust the bridge from its rocky foundation whereon the great
                        Inigo Jones had laid it in 1636. The damages done by the floods in the Vale
                        of Conwy are very great, as they also are in many other places. A set of
                        pretty milkmaids were swept by the flood into the Menai, but their lives
                        were saved. Geraint Jenkins, David Ceri Jones and Ffion Jones (eds), <hi rend="italic">The Correspondence of Iolo Morganwg Volume II
                            (1797-1809)</hi>, 220. The bridge at Llanrwst did not sustain lasting
                        damage.</note> At <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName> it rained
                    throughout the night, and till five o clock the following afternoon. We were
                    safe under the shelter of the <placeName ref="pl3124">Harp</placeName>. We were
                    informed that this irresistible flood had carried away the bridge at <placeName ref="pl1595">Aber</placeName>, and enquired of the guard who brought the
                    mail from thence of it were true. He gave us small encouragement to proceed. He
                    said one end of the bridge hung by about a foot, and <hi rend="underline">we</hi> might pass it, but he did not know how our horses could be got
                    over. Stones, he added, came rolling down the torrent, from the mountains, like
                    thunderbolts. Though it is probable he never heard the noise of a thunderbolt,
                        <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">any more than myself</hi>, it was not difficult to guess
                    his meaning.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I wished myself at <placeName ref="pl1595">Aber</placeName>, on the other side of
                    the bridge. How I should have enjoyed this tremendous mountain scene! Being at
                        <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName>, however, we thought it best to
                    stay there, till the next morning, when we mounted our horses and rode away. At
                    the pass of <placeName ref="pl2400">Sŷchnant</placeName>, the wind was terrible,
                    and we were obliged to tie our hats on with our pocket handkerchiefs. At the
                        [<del>xxxxx</del>] foot of <placeName ref="pl1338">Penmaen Mawr</placeName>,
                    we dismounted, and sent our horses round to <placeName ref="pl1595">Aber</placeName> by the sands. I had a walk before me of four miles. I
                    crept slowly up the mountain, and tripped down it as lightly as feather. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>By this time it rained, <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">though moderately</hi>, and I was obliged to put on my
                    great coat, and beat up against the stormy blast [xxxxxx] till I got to
                        <placeName ref="pl1595">Aber</placeName>. I had resolved not to murmur at
                    fatigue – if I could help it. But I could no longer help it. I thought, with the
                    force of the wind, the flowing of my drapery, and the weight of my wet coat, I
                    should have sunk to the ground! I turned my back to the wind for a moment and
                    with a deep sigh, and a low voice, said ‘Oh! This is hard work!’ </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.82"/>
                <fw>p.82</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The bridge at <placeName ref="pl1595">Aber</placeName> afforded us just safe
                    footing and no more, but the torrent had so far subsided that our horses might
                    have forded it [<del>xxx</del>] above, and I, had we known it, might have been
                    spared this cruel walk. Such a season has not been known in the memory of man. I
                    have borne it with patience, when exposed to it, and been grateful for the
                    houses which sheltered me from it; but I am glad I did not come by <placeName ref="pl1523">Festiniog</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y
                        Bwlch</placeName>; for I believe my fortitude, if not my reason, would have
                    forsaken me, in such weather, among the mountains.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At <placeName ref="pl1595">Aber</placeName> we were again confined the whole day
                    by rain. In the evening I was fortunate enough to get a peep at <placeName ref="pl3146">Rhaiader Vawr</placeName>, <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">the Great Waterfall</hi>. The fall itself was
                    inaccessible, as the approach to it lay on the opposite side the river, and the
                    two bridges which crossed it were one broken and the other swept away. The first
                    was a modern bridge of stone, on the mountain road leading to <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>; the other, higher up, was of wood, for
                    the convenience of the peasants. We advanced nearly to the place where the
                    latter had stood, and from thence, at the distance of about a mile, saw the
                    river pouring down a hollow in the mountain, from a prodigious height, a cloud
                    resting on its top. A noble sight, but at too great a distance! Chrystal streams
                    ran over our road; the river rolled over huge stones at the bottom of the glen;
                    and we found, at the village of <placeName ref="pl1595">Aber</placeName>, its
                    rapid course had carried away a small field of barley, and making itself a new
                    channel, had left a mill stream empty.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Yesterday morning, having made all tight for foul weather, we determined to stop
                    no more till we reached <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>. Our
                    precautions were needless; for the weather proved fine, and we arrived here in
                    safety at eleven o’ clock.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>This morning I have been dusting the furniture of my chamber, and</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.83"/>
                <fw>p.83</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>putting all things in order. I might, it is true, have called up the housemaid
                    and desired her to be the operator; but, besides that Welsh ideas of cleanliness
                    do not accord with mine, I thought it less trouble to do it myself. My <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">employment</hi> brought to mind Madame Roland in the
                    prison of the Abbaye. I resemble her in my taste for neatness, books, and
                    flowers; and though I am more weak and timid I might, perhaps, resemble her in
                    resolution if a great occasion called it forth; but that occasion would have no
                    connexion with politics. I have several loves stronger than the love of my
                        country.<note type="editorial">This intriguing reference to Manon Roland,
                        executed in Paris in 1793, and the plight of the Irish refugee mentioned
                        below, are explored further in Constantine, <hi rend="italic">Curious
                            Travellers; Writing the Welsh Tour 1720-1820</hi> (forthcoming). A
                        second edition of the English translation of Roland’s memoir came out in
                        1796.</note>
                </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> Letter 19 </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p style="right"><placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> Aug. 30 1799</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>My Dear Brother,</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> is not the same place it was two
                    years ago. I then took my solitary walks, unseen by any, but the blue cloaks of
                    the country; the streets now present, continually, elegant women in fashionable
                    dresses. In this Emporium of Tourists I have already met with two families that
                    I know. These are birds of passage; but there are many others, like ourselves,
                    resident here for some time. Four ladies and two gentlemen, who are on what is
                    called a party of pleasure, lodge in the same house with us. They are one day
                    driving about in an Irish car; the next at the Lakes of Llanberis; and the next
                    at <placeName ref="pl1525">Pont Aber Glaslyn</placeName>. They play at cards
                    before and after supper, and when not at cards, are talking, three or four at a
                    time. They might each be agreeable if separate, but as our dining rooms and
                    sleeping rooms join, they are, all together, terrible neighbours to one. I
                    should prefer the house of mourning to such mirth as theirs.
                    [<del>xxxxxx</del>]</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I have made another acquaintance, directly opposite. Pity for her forlorn
                    situation attaches one to her. She is an unmarried woman, turned of thirty, of a
                    noble family in Ireland, whom the troubles there have driven</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.84"/>
                <fw>p.84</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>into <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>. She has not been in any personal
                    danger; but her brother’s house has been plundered by the rebels, and his
                    domestics threatened with instant death. Such is her terror at these
                    proceedings, that she declared to me she would not have slept another night in
                    his house for a thousand guineas; and I am told, that here she sleeps in her
                    cloaths. She is at <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> without either
                    friend or servant. The people here have a notion she is a little deranged. This,
                    however, is not the case. She appears to me not only rational but sensible. She
                    is so grateful for my attention, and her manner is so affecting, that sometimes
                    I can hardly refrain from tears.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I was so unfortunate as to take a cold when I first came here, which brought on a
                    slow fever. I struggled against it with all my might, but at length lost all
                    hopes of shaking it off, without the advice of the physician of the place. I was
                    informed that morning was the time to get him; for that his intellects were then
                    generally unclouded by the fumes of wine. I sent twice yesterday morning,
                    without success. I suppose he had taken a double dose of his own prescription
                    the night before, and took a longer time than usual to recover it. He was in
                    bed, and could not come. I then ordered my horse, rode out, and was better. I
                    have done the same today, with the same effect. If I keep mending, I shall think
                    the Doctor the best physician I ever knew, for not coming when he was sent for;
                    and will endeavour to get a diploma for my horse.<note type="editorial">In <hi rend="italic">The Welsh Mountaineer</hi> (1817) the heroine Dorothy
                        Penrose persuades her cousin to take the same medicine: “I dare not sit out
                        of doors” said Bridget; “and you know I cannot walk.” “Try my Taffy”, said
                        I; “I will warrant him an able physician.” (<hi rend="italic">WM</hi>, 1817
                        III, 219). </note>
                </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p style="right">
                    <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">see page 51 &amp; page 62</hi>
                </p>
                <p>I have had the pleasure of seeing the devotion of the Methodists, if not at its
                    highest pitch, at a degree of extravagance sufficiently striking.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>When I entered the crowded chapel, the service was almost ended, and the preacher
                    was pronouncing short sentences, with the greatest energy of voice and violence
                    of gesticul<hi rend="superscript">ation</hi>, which the congregation repeated,
                    in a murmuring cadence. When his part was finished, theirs began. At first the </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.85"/>
                <fw>p.85</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>roar was universal, but it subsided by degrees, and the multitude became
                    spectators, while eight or ten of the most inspired were actors. Each of these
                    repeated some particular sentence that he had caught, and all roared out the
                    same monotonous tune, till they had worked themselves up into a frenzy; flinging
                    about their arms, clapping their hands, rolling their heads and bodies from side
                    to side, and at intervals, jumping, at least a dozen times together. The jumpers
                    were chiefly in pairs, and held each other by both hands. I observed, that the
                    women pair with women; and men with men. It would not have been quite decorous
                    to have done otherwise, as some of their gestures were very familiar. When a
                    couple of men came across a couple of women, they shook hands, as brothers and
                    sisters in the Lord Jesus; but I believe their heavenly love was so sincere, at
                    the moment, that no other sentiment could find a place in their breasts. The
                    friends of the females were very careful to adjust their garments, when they
                    became a little disordered.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>When I first witnessed this scene I felt amazed, mixed with horror. The yell was
                    insupportable; I seemed surrounded by lunatics, in their most outrageous
                    paroxysm. These feelings, in some degree, yielded to pity; and my next concern
                    was for my watch and my purse. Recollecting, however, that I was in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>, I did not trouble myself to feel if they
                    were safe. My ignorance of the language added to the strangeness of the scene. I
                    at first imagined, from the hideous tones, that touched with remorse they were
                    bewailing their sins, and imploring forgiveness of Almighty God; but I after<hi rend="superscript">wards</hi> understood that they were chaunting songs of
                    triumph, believing themselves his favourite children.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The preacher sat some time with a handkerchief thrown over his head, to prevent
                    his taking cold, (for his exertions had thrown him in a bath) viewing the pranks
                    of the demon he had raised; and then stole silently off. The friends of the
                    performers, when they thought they had displayed </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.86"/>
                <fw>p.86</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>sufficient proofs of inspiration, led them to his house; where I was told he
                    would spend some hours in bringing them to their senses. It is not often that
                    the Methodists are raised to this degree of frenzy; but the present orator was a
                    very popular man, and had spared no pains to work upon their passions.<note type="editorial">Methodists (often called ‘Jumpers’) were another perennial
                        source of interest to tourists in this period. See Michael Freeman <ref type="http" target="https://sublimewales.wordpress.com/what-they-wrote-about/perceptions-of-wales/religion-in-wales/jumpers/">here.</ref> William Hutton gives a lively account of this meeting in
                        Caernarfon, and makes some observations on Methodism, in <hi rend="italic">Remarks upon north Wales</hi> (1803) 94-101.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The <placeName ref="pl1564">straits of Menai</placeName>, which divide the county
                    of <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> from the Isle of <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName>, may be crossed at five different ferries.
                    The first is from <placeName ref="pl1595">Aber</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName>, fifteen miles from <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>. The second is at <placeName ref="pl1563">Bangor</placeName>, nine miles from <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>. It is about half a mile in breadth, at high water,
                    and sixteen fathoms in depth. The third is called <placeName ref="pl2853">Moel y
                        Don</placeName>, Hill of the Waves, from a large round rock which there
                    shoots out into the sea. This is four miles from <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>, the water is there three quarters of a mile, when
                    the tide is in; and eleven fathoms deep. The fourth ferry is at <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> itself, and is called <placeName ref="pl2097">Tal y Foel</placeName>. It is about two miles across. The fifth
                    is that of Aber Menai about three miles beyond <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>, where the straits open to the sea. There is also a
                    ford, I believe, opposite <placeName ref="pl1595">Aber</placeName>, where, when
                    the tide retires, the greatest part of the channel is dry sands; but I would not
                    be one who should cross it.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Notwithstanding the fever I mentioned, I have made a trip to the <placeName ref="pl1093">Island</placeName>, urged by an ardent curiosity to see the
                        <placeName ref="pl3188">Carnedd</placeName> and the <placeName ref="pl3189">Cromlech</placeName>.<note type="editorial">For a discussion of the
                        responses of both Huttons to the prehistoric monuments on Anglesey see
                        Constantine, ‘Celts and Romans On Tour: Visions of early Britain in
                        eighteenth-century travel literature’, in Francesca Kaminski-Jones and Rhys
                        Kaminski-Jones (eds), <hi rend="italic">Celts, Romans, Britons: Classical
                            and Celtic Influence in the Construction of British Identities</hi>
                        (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2020), 117-39.</note> We rode to
                        <placeName ref="pl2853">Moel y Don ferry</placeName>, and sent our horses
                    on, to that of <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName>, chosing to walk along
                    the opposite shore of <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName>. We sailed
                    across the <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai</placeName> in ten minutes; we then
                    pursued a path along two charming fields, to the church of <placeName ref="pl3187">Llanedwin</placeName>, and entered the park of <persName ref="pe1230">Lord Uxbridge</persName>. I thought myself here on hallowed
                    ground, and looked around me with a scritinizing eye, expecting every moment to </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.87"/>
                <fw>p.87</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>see some monument of the religion of my ancestors rise before me. We had walked
                    through the woods, perhaps, a quarter of a mile, when pointing to a hill on our
                    left I cried, What’s that? My father went to see, and I, who durst not make one
                    step in vain, sat down under a tree. He beckoned and I sprung up. It was the
                        <placeName ref="pl3188">Carnedd</placeName>, the sepulchre of some
                    distinguished Briton. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The <placeName ref="pl3188">Carnedd</placeName> is <hi rend="superscript">a
                        circular hill</hi>, about four hundred feet in circumference, and about
                    fourteen in height. It is composed of the stone of the country, hewn into small
                    angular pieces. The whole surface is so covered with grass, that the stones
                    would pass unnoticed, without attention; and the interstices are now filled with
                    earth to such a depth, that it affords nutriment to four or five moderate oaks,
                    which grow on one side. The <placeName ref="pl3188">Carnedd</placeName> has <hi rend="superscript">been</hi> formerly opened, and a part of the stones
                    carried away. In the area thus formed stands, now exposed to view, a stone six
                    feet in length and breadth and one in thickness, supported by others set on end,
                    and leaving a hollow underneath, probably for the body.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>From hence we continued our way through the wood, until we came to the house of
                        <placeName ref="pl1965">Plas Newydd</placeName>, on which it is said
                        <persName ref="pe1230">Lord Uxbridge</persName> has expended £60,000. The
                    principal front commands the <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai</placeName>, and the
                    grand range of <placeName ref="pl1234">Caernarvonshire</placeName> mountains.
                    Our road lay at the back, and we did not go out of it, for fear of being deemed
                    impertinent. The stables, which are newly erected, are an imitation of a castle,
                    adorned with battlements, and turrets; and, I suppose, are much admired. I like
                    them not. I would never build castles for horses. No person is a greater admirer
                    of real castles than myself. Nobody one has viewed those of <placeName ref="pl1521">Harlech</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1530">Conwy</placeName>
                    and <placeName ref="pl1566">Caernarvon</placeName>, with more veneration and
                    pleasure. But bulk and strength are so essential to these kind of buildings,
                    that all imitations of them are paltry.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Nearly opposite the stables is the <placeName ref="pl3189">Cromlech</placeName>;
                    I believe, <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">one of</hi> the most perfect re-</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.88"/>
                <fw>p.88</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>maining in <placeName ref="pl0777">Great Britain</placeName>. Is one huge, rude
                    stone, twelve feet in length, nine in breadth, four and half in thickness at one
                    end and three and half at the other; supported by five stones, which raise the
                    underside four feet above the ground. One or two other supporters now lie
                    prostrate on the earth. Adjoining to the Cromlech is another, of the same kind,
                    but smaller. The soil has accumulated in the hollows of both, till they are in
                    several places covered with fern, wild geranium, and other plants.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>While I looked with awe on the works of man that had lasted, perhaps two thousand
                    years, and figured to myself the white-robed Druids and their smoaking fires; my
                    heart recoiled at the idea that, on this very altar, my fellow-creatures,
                    possibly my progenitors, had been sacrificed by the dictates of a barbarous
                    religion.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The scenery, a venerable wood, is proper for the subject; but the predecessors of
                        <persName ref="pe1230">Lord Uxbridge</persName> committed a grand mistake,
                    in planting ashes rather than oaks; and his lordship, instead of lamenting the
                    error, has planted sycamores. By oaks, the native produce of our islands, and
                    their pride, these sacred remains of antiquity were once surrounded; and I still
                    consider, as an appendage to the Cromlech, all other wood prophane. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I left this interesting spot with reluctance, and cast many a longing, lingering
                    look behind. My only comfort was the <placeName ref="pl1234">Caernarvonshire</placeName> mountains. They were indeed a noble
                    consolation, not only for the curious relics I had left behind [<del>me</del>],
                    but for many a weary step I had before me. Never did I see them look so sublime.
                    On their own shore one is too near them: here the eye takes in the whole range
                    at once; with their different summits, rising above and between each other.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Our road led us through a village called <placeName ref="pl3190">Llanfair</placeName>, and between two hills of disjointed pieces of rock,
                    many of which were ready formed by nature for the slab of a cromlech, and
                    required only to be loosened on one side. I believe the cromlech, itself, grew
                    there.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.89"/>
                <fw>p.89</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>In the small part of <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName> I saw, the
                    roads were good, and the lands poor, with some exceptions in favour of the
                    latter. The country is well inhabited, and the cottages are decent.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We crossed the <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl1563">Bangor ferry</placeName>, and took some refreshment at the inn,
                    where we found our horses waiting for us. It is beautifully situated on the
                    steep bank of the <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai</placeName>, and is,
                    undoubtedly, the first inn in the Principality. </p>
                <p> </p>

                <p> Letter 20 </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p style="right"><placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> Sept 10 1799</p>

                <p> </p>
                <p>My Dear Brother,</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>In spite of fever, medicines and apothecary <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">all which I have at present and</hi> which last, by the
                    way, is a very worthy, skillful man, I have this day been at <placeName ref="pl1527">Llanberis</placeName>. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The road from the inclosures to the foot of the mountains, that two years ago was
                    the worst of the way, is now <del>mended and</del> become some of the best. Each
                    year does something to facilitate travelling in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Having deposited out horses in a barn, at <placeName ref="pl3141">Cwm y
                        Glo</placeName>, we entered the boat of Richard Williams,<note type="editorial">‘R. Williams’ is one of four independent boatmen at Cwm y
                        Glo paid by the Dinorwic slate quarry company for services in 1787 and 1789.
                        J.S. Illsley and O.T.P. Roberts provide an interesting account of the
                        development of boating activities on lakes Padarn and Peris in ‘An 18th
                        century boat in Lake Padarn, North Wales’, <hi rend="italic">The
                            International Journal of Nautical Archaeology and Underwater
                            Exploration</hi> (1979), 8.1:45-67.</note> who, as well as his wife, was
                    armed with a pair of oars. I felt some difficulty in trusting myself to the care
                    of the female rower, but the man assuring me that she was as strong and as
                    skillful as himself, which I had no reason to doubt from her appearance; and
                    recollecting <persName ref="pe0232">Pennant</persName>'s Margaret Evans, who
                    used to wrestle and hunt on these mountains, and fiddle and row on these lakes,
                    I concluded myself safe in her care and keeping.<note type="editorial">Although
                        Pennant did not meet her on his visit to Llanberis, the ‘Amazon’ Margaret
                        Evans (Marged ach Ifan) became well known to later tourists through his
                        vivid description in his <hi rend="italic">Tour in Wales</hi> II,
                        158-59.</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The first lake of Llanberis is, at the beginning, little <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">more than a</hi> marsh, with one channel just deep enough
                    to carry a boat. But having gone half a mile <del>and doubled</del>
                    <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">and passed</hi> some rocks which jut out, <del>and</del>
                    a sheet of water opens two and half miles in length, and nearly a mile in
                    breadth. This fills the whole space between the mountains. They are inaccessible
                    rocks</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.90"/>
                <fw>p.90</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>which rise from its very edge, and no doubt, from beneath it. In a small hollow,
                    on the left, is a green patch and cottage where lived Margaret Evans, the
                    above-mentioned amazon of the lakes. But death has put an end to her exploits
                    long ago.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At the end of the first lake the lands project again, and form a narrow channel
                    for the water, not more than fifteen or twenty yards across, over which is
                    thrown a neat, light, wooden bridge, resting upon four piers of slates, and
                    secured with railing. We passed under the centre, now higher than the man,
                    standing upright in his boat. But he passed it after the late flood, when he was
                    not only obliged to sit, but to stoop. Beyond the bridge, the water was now so
                    shallow that he got out to lighten the boat, and haul it up against the
                    current.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>About the division of the two lakes is an opening, between the mountains on the
                    right, cultivated and sprinkled with cottages and trees; though this, after
                    having displayed a waterfall, terminates in a mountain. On the left, also, in
                    two different hollows, are cottages, with each a tree or two and a small spot of
                    green. One of these is a farm, for which the tenant used to pay thirty shillings
                    a year; but <persName ref="pe0944">Ashton Smith</persName>, Esqr , his landlord,
                    has raised his rent to five pounds, and it is said the man will be ruined. Sheep
                    and goats were basking on the rocks; but these goats are never milked. They are
                    wild, and yield their owner no other advantage than their flesh and skins - when
                    he can catch them. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We now entered the upper lake, which is a mile and half long, and about three
                    quarters of a mile broad; but deeper than the lower, being in the deepest part
                    twenty fathoms, while that is only fourteen. At the end of the second lake, on a
                    high, round projecting rock, partly covered with heath and moss, stands
                        <placeName ref="pl1309">Dolbadern Castle</placeName>. At a distance it had
                    the appearance of a prodigious stone, but nearer it look</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.91"/>
                <fw>p.91</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p> ed more important. It is a large, round ivy-mantled tower, having many windows,
                    of varying sizes. What could have been its use, it is difficult to conceive! It
                    is too small to have defended this pass into the mountains; and as to a
                    watch-tower, it is secluded from all created objects [<del>xxxx</del>] by the
                    mountains above and the lakes below! I wished to visit the castle, and our
                    boatman offered to set us on shore; but I was obliged to hoard my little
                    strength, and give up something, that I might be enabled to do the rest. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The mountains which inclose the upper lake are higher than those of the first.
                        <placeName ref="pl3191">Crib Coch</placeName>, one of the mighty sons of
                        <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>, forms the right boundary of
                    that and the vale beyond it; and along his side lies the ascent from <placeName ref="pl1527">Llanberis</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl2862">Y
                        Wyddfa</placeName>, which I traced, with aching eyes. <placeName ref="pl3191">Crib Coch</placeName>, is not, however, his tallest son. The
                    highest, and almost the rival of his father, is <placeName ref="pl3192">Crib y
                        Distil</placeName>. I think I am now acquainted with the whole family. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I saw, on the left, a slate quarry, high up the mountain, and the road by which
                    the slates are brought down to the lake. The method of conveying them
                        [<del>xxx</del>] is by small carts, with one horse before, and another
                    behind. To me the destruction of the poor animals seemed inevitable; I could not
                    conceive how they could not escape being precipitated into the lake: but it
                    seems a different fate awaits them—they are only killed by the labour.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>On the right, near the top of the second lake, are two copper mines, one of which
                    runs nine score yards under the mountain. We landed at the extremity of the
                    lake, on the opposite side, where are machines for breaking the ore, and a
                    succession of pits, where the earth is washed from the copper. I might have seen
                    the whole process, but I have no fancy for metals or minerals, and an utter
                    abhorrence of ill smells.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The space between the mountains, which was now reduced to half a mile in breadth,
                    and extended about the same distance in length </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.92"/>
                <fw>p.92</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>is meadow, as level as the water we had quitted. At the end of this is the
                    village of </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1527">Llanberis</placeName>, consisting of eight houses
                    intermixed with trees, and a church.<note type="editorial">This refers to the
                        settlement now known as Nant Peris; modern Llanberis developed in the C19th
                        further down near the lake.</note> Above the village, the mountains approach
                    each other so as to leave only a narrow glen; a horrible bwlch is then to be
                    climbed, after which the road divides, that on the right leading round
                        <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>, and through <placeName ref="pl2901">Nant Gwynan</placeName>, to <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName>; that on the left through <placeName ref="pl3193">Dŷffryn Mŷmbr</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel
                        Cerig</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>. Farther
                    than <placeName ref="pl1527">Llanberis</placeName> I saw not, <del>but did</del>
                    <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">for</hi> my strength <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">did not</hi> equal my inclination, <del>I would see
                        it</del>. We have all a certain portion of curiosity; that of many persons
                    lies in their ears, and inclines them to listen to small matters of fact
                    regarding their neighbours. Mine is seated in my eyes, and <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> is the place to gratify it.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The church of Llanberis<note type="editorial">St Peris’ Church, Nant Peris. For a
                        print of the area by Moses Griffith (1810), see <ref type="http" target="http://hdl.handle.net/10107/1130713">here.</ref>
                    </note> is lowly without, and gloomy within. Not, however, owing to the
                    proximity of the mountains, as I had been informed, but to the smallness of the
                    windows. We entered it, and found it was the parish school. About a dozen boys
                    were reading Welsh. The clergy<hi rend="superscript">man</hi> followed us
                        <del>in</del>, and began a conversation, by observing, that it was an old
                    church. I beg his pardon—not suspecting his profession, by his blue coat, silk
                    handkerchief, and brown stockings; we made some slight assent to his remark, and
                    he retired. I feel both remorse and regret at this circumstance; remorse, for
                    having failed in the respect due to his situation; and regret, at having missed
                    the information he could have afforded us.<note type="editorial">This may well
                        be Peter Bailey Williams (1763-1836), rector of Llanrug and Llanberis from
                        1792 until his death. A graduate of Jesus College Oxford, he was an
                        enthusiastic educator, opening Sunday schools in the area. He was also an
                        adventurous mountaineer. In 1798 he acted as a guide for the botanist (and
                        fellow clergyman) William Bingley, making the first recorded ‘rock-climb’ in
                        Britain on the east face of Clogwyn Du’r Arddu. In 1821 Williams published
                        the <hi rend="italic">Tourist's Guide to the County of Caernarvon</hi>, a
                        detailed account of many key sites in Snowdonia which knowledgeably
                        references and updates Pennant’s Tours. See <ref type="http" target="https://www.gutenberg.org/files/45865/45865-h/45865-h.htm">here.</ref></note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Having looked with great satisfaction at this humble village, almost cut off by
                    lakes and mountains from communication with the rest of the world, we entered
                    its principal inn; for there are two.<note type="editorial">Cf P.B. Williams,
                        ‘Persons going up the Lake may be landed either near the New Inn, or on the
                        Meadow below Mr. Smith’s Cottage, or they may proceed to the extremity of
                        the upper Pool, and walk from thence to the Village, which is about a
                        quarter of a mile distant, and procure refreshment at Robert Closs’s, who
                        keeps a small Inn there; the Landlord of this House, as well as Pierce
                        Jones, who lives at the other Inn, are both very civil and obliging men, and
                        will either act as Guides themselves, or will procure persons to attend any
                        Gentlemen up Snowdon, or to any of the neighbouring Villages.’ <hi rend="italic">Tourist’s Guide</hi>, 1821), 113-14. Robert Closs took
                        over Tŷ’n Llan from his father John Closs (1725-1799), who had moved from
                        Flintshire to work for the Llanberis Mine Company. Thomas Pennant stayed
                        there before climbing Snowdon in 1781 (<hi rend="italic">TiW</hi> 1784, II,
                        168) as did William Bingley some years later.</note> As guests above the
                    common rank, we were shewn into the parlour—a parlour, whose walls and floors
                    were of black, rugged stone; whose top was rafters; whose only light came
                    through a dozen very small panes of glass; </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.93/"/>
                <fw>p.93</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>whose partition wall was a mat; and whose furniture, one <del>small</del> table,
                    two <del>small</del> benches, and a plank, supported by slates. The good woman
                    of the house repeated the word ‘Welcome!’, spread a table-cloth; brought a jug
                    of <hi rend="underline">cwrw</hi> out of an adjoining pantry, (for cellar she
                    had none;) shewed us butter and brown bread, and by the boatman, our
                    interpreter, offered us eggs. We declined her civility, though we paid her for
                    it; having brought wine and cold provisions of our own.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>After this refreshment we set out on our return, and after a pleasant voyage,
                    arrived in safety at the bottom of the lakes.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We were much pleased with Richard Williams, our rower. He speaks English, a rare
                    qualification, and we found him very civil and intelligent. His civility was of
                    the true Welsh sort, and would be better understood by the term kindness. Seeing
                    me look ill, he offered me <del>a little of</del>
                    <hi rend="underline">something, <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                        <hi rend="superscript">that</hi> the gentleman <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                        <hi rend="superscript">had</hi> left with him</hi>. That <hi rend="underline">something</hi>, I dare say, was brandy – a treasure he
                    could not possibly replace.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The general road between <placeName ref="pl3141">Cwm y Glo</placeName> and
                        <placeName ref="pl1527">Llanberis</placeName> is on the lakes, and slates
                    are daily carried along them in boats; but there is another, which instead of
                    winding down <placeName ref="pl3141">Cwm y Glo</placeName>, keeps on the side of
                    the mountain, on the right of the lake, at a frightful height above the water.
                    It then descends and goes over rocks near the shore, passes behind <placeName ref="pl1309">Dolbadern Castle</placeName>, and through the cultivated
                    opening between the mountains; becomes a terrace just above the lakes, and in
                    one place runs close to the water’s edge. I took the pains to trace it the whole
                    way. This road is so improved that I saw a gig travel along it; but, till
                    lately, it was terrible, even to the Welsh. It was, sometimes up or down steps
                    of native rock, and sometimes so narrow, that, when one horse met another, the
                    two riders were obliged to dismount; and one hauled his horse up <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">the side of</hi> the mountain, while the other passed. An
                    English horse has been seen to stop and tremble before he could be made to
                    venture along it. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.94"/>
                <fw>p.94</fw>
                <p> </p>

                <p>Two years ago I was told that on a dreadful windy day, in the
                        <sic>preceeding</sic> winter, a poor woman left <placeName ref="pl1527">Llanberis</placeName> on horseback, to go to Caernarvon market, and that
                    neither she nor her horse were ever heard of more. It was supposed they were
                    blown down one of the precipices, into the lake, and swallowed up for ever. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p/>
                <p> Letter 21 </p>
                <p style="right">
                    <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> Sept 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1799</p>
                <p>My Dear Friend,</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I will take this opportunity of assuring you, once and for all, that it is my
                    sincere desire to speak the truth, and that only; but at the same time I will
                    not venture to affirm that I have always done so. I saw the Lakes of Llanberis
                    two years ago, as I then informed you. I even went more than half a mile upon
                    them in a boat, which I had the discretion not to tell you; for though I might
                    have made a flourishing description of what I heard, saw and conjectured, it
                    would have had one fault at least – it would not have been a true one. Some
                    obvious reflections occurred to me on my second visit to the lakes – How much I
                    had been deceived in the first! How could I blame travellers for differing from
                    reality and from each other, when I, who meant to tell no falshood, who wished
                    to make no system, could not hear the same tale twice over, or see the same
                    thing twice in the same light! Well might I forgive a recent tourist for making
                    the river <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName> rise at <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName>! I therefore would not be understood to make
                    positive assertions, but to stipulate for such a share of your credence only, as
                    the best exertions of my senses and my memory deserve. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Public weddings are the universal custom throughout the principality among the
                    common people. <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">Here</hi>, if the father of the bride can afford it, he
                    provides the marriage feast and it is her portion. If he cannot, or if she have
                    no parents, she is trusted by some friend, or obtains credit at some public
                    house; and, after repaying the money out of what is left by the guests, the
                    remainder is her own. Every man who dines pays a shilling; every woman sixpence; </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.95"/>
                <fw>p.95</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>though many chuse to give a shilling; every person who drinks tea sixpence. Every
                    pint of ale is scored up to the person who calls for it, each comes and goes as
                    he pleases, and many come only to drink and dance. 1 <hi rend="superscript">[A
                        poor]</hi>
                </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> 2 In <placeName ref="pl1245">south Wales</placeName>, when a poor couple marry,
                    they send a printed hand-bill to every person by whom they are known, signifying
                    that they mean to be married on such a day, and to keep their wedding at such a
                    place, where they hope to see the person to whom it is addressed. This is called
                    a <hi rend="underline">bidding</hi>. On the day appointed, after the ceremony is
                    performed, the new married couple, attended by the bridemaid and brideman,
                    repair to the house fixed upon, which is always a public one, and sit, from
                    eleven o'clock in the forenoon till seven in the evening, to receive the
                    contributions of their friends. Their equals give half-crowns, the better sort
                    crowns, or even pounds, according as they are esteemed and respected. If either
                    of them have been a servant, it is said, in the bidding, late servant to Such a
                    one, and all the friends and visitors of the family shew their generosity on the
                    occasion. Every donation is registered by the clerk of the parish, who attends
                    for that purpose; and when the giver marries, [<del>xxxx</del>] it becomes a
                    debt. No person ever fails to pay at the wedding of another what he received at
                    his own; except through absolute inability. The same obligation prevails in the
                    higher class:- I always give at the wedding of your servant, what you give at
                    the wedding of mine; or more, if I think she deserve it better, or have lived
                    longer in her place. The money thus raised amounts commonly to from twenty to
                    fifty pounds, and sometimes reaches a hundred. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The young people of the better sort scamper away <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">on horseback</hi>, in parties of twenty, at a bidding.
                    After having made their presents, the men treat the girls with cakes; load them
                    with as many as they can carry, and then they gallop off <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">together</hi>, and try who shall be first home. Such as
                    chuse it stay to dance in the evening.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The poor people regale at the expence of the new-married pair, who </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.96"/>
                <fw>p.96</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>provide bread, butter, a cheese, and sweet drink (that is ale with sugar and
                    spice) in another room. [3, when a common man dies &amp;c].</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> 1 A poor man, in the hollow of the mountains, has married his daughter since I
                    have been here. He brewed a quarter of malt for the occasion. The cloth was laid
                    out of doors; for his house consisting of one room, could not contain the
                    company. Forty persons sat down at once, and as soon as they had dined, forty
                    more took their places. My father who gave me the account, remained there not
                    quite two hours; and saw about a hundred and fifty people, two only of whom
                    could speak English.<note type="editorial">William Hutton has a lively verse
                        description of the festivities held at Cwm y Glo in ‘The Welch Wedding
                        (September 13, 1799)’, <hi rend="italic">Remarks upon North Wales</hi>
                        (1803), 87-93. </note> The bride, her father and mother, waited on the
                    guests. The banquet resembled that prepared by Esop for his master, except that
                    instead of tongues, tongues, tongues, it was beef, beef, beef.<note type="editorial">In ‘Aesop’s Feast’ he serves tongue to his master Xanthus
                        at every course, claiming that the tongue encompassed the full range of
                        human emotion.</note> Five rounds were ready to succeed each other; the
                    variations were bags of peas and mountains of cabbage: but these were delicacies
                    to people accustomed to live on oatmeal and buttermilk. The <hi rend="underline">cwrw</hi> was good, the man having done justice to his malt. The company
                    ate off wooden trenchers, and sat on wooden planks, supported by slates.<note type="editorial">From which William Hutton and two young women tumbled:
                        ‘When the board which we sat on too feeble was found/To support Wales and
                        England—we fell to the ground!’ (p. 90) </note> A harper made one of the
                    party; and another was expected. The desert was butter and cheese. The house
                    served for an occasional drawing-room; and two beds that were in it supplied the
                    place of sophas. Not a female appeared in anything other than woolen, which some
                    had fashioned into gowns, and others into bedgowns, nor one without the beaver
                    hat except the mother of the bride, who being cook, might be obliged to take it
                    off. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I saw a sailor married to the daughter of a shoemaker at <placeName ref="pl2020">Llanbeblic</placeName>, the parish church of <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>. The bridegroom marched first with his bridemen; or,
                    as they were here called, his <hi rend="underline">servants</hi>, one on each
                    side. The rest of the men followed, three abreast. Then came the intended bride,
                    between her servants, and the rest of the women, in the same order,</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.97"/>
                <fw>p.97</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>closed the procession. These town ladies were not clad like the mountaineers, in
                    woolen, but in flowered cotton gowns, white petticoats, and white stockings. The
                    bride and her maids wore white satin ribbands in their caps; the beaver hat is
                    ever the same, but these were ornamented with a smarter bow than those of the
                    rustics. Part of their finery, however, the morning being rather cloudy, was
                    eclipsed by their blue cloaks, which nothing but the hottest sunshine <del>ever
                        tempts them to lay by</del>, and sometimes not even that, can tempt them to
                    lay by. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>When the clergyman came to a certain part of the service, he stopped and the
                    sailor stepped forward, and laid four shillings on his book. The parson very
                    quietly gave one to the clerk, pocketed the other three himself; and thus sure
                    of his reward, proceeded to make the <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">lovers</hi> man and wife. The ceremony ended, the two
                    bridemen flew at the two poor defenceless maids; and after some struggling, each
                    ravished a kiss. This is an established custom among all ranks, and also between
                    Godfathers and Godmothers, at a christening. If the lady leaves the church
                    unsaluted, she claims a pair of gloves: if the gentleman succeed, she is
                    supposed to be satisfied.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The new-married couple kept their wedding at a public-house, not far distant from
                    our lodgings, where they dined, and two of their female friends sat making tea
                    from three o'clock in the afternoon till seven. At seven the next morning, I saw
                    many of the company, <del>women as well as men</del>, mounting their horses to
                    return home. </p>
                <p>[<del>xxxx</del>] Every person acquainted with either of the families makes it a
                    point of honor to attend the wedding feast. A considerable sum is thus
                    collected, for the benefit of the young couple beginning the world; and each,
                    receiving it in his turn is only laying up a fund against his own marriage, or
                    paying a debt contracted at it. 2 In South Wales </p>
                <p>------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</p>
                <p> 3 When a common man dies at <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>, a
                    small bell is rung about </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.98"/>
                <fw>p.98</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>the streets, as an invitation to all persons to attend the funeral. Those who
                    arrive first fill the house, the others crowd about the door, and each is
                    presented with a small cup of <hi rend="underline">cwrw</hi>, holding about a
                    quarter of a pint; they all accompany the corpse to the church, singing psalms
                    by the way. Should any person acquainted with the deceased fail in his
                    attendance, it would be construed as an affront; but the clergyman would have
                    the most solid reason to resent it.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Having provided for our own table, I can give you the present prices of
                    provisions here. If you have no occasion for such information yourself, it may
                    be amusing to your grandchildren, when you have any, to compare it with the
                    prices of their day; if they should chance to visit <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>
                    <hi rend="superscript">see page 52</hi></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Mutton and beef are sixpence a pound, veal, five pence, salmon five pence and
                    sixpence., flour threepence halfpenny, butter eight pence halfpenny to nine
                    pence halfpenny, and potatoes two pounds and a half for a penny. Chickens are
                    from four pence to eight pence a piece, ducks from eight pence to ten pence,
                    rabbits sixpence, and eggs a halfpenny. But the difficulty is to get these
                    things. Meat is plentiful on a Saturday, but is scarcely to be had on any other
                    day. Poultry is scarcely to be had on any day. Rabbits can only be had by
                    chance. Fish depends on an uncertain element; and most of the poultry and all of
                    the rabbits depend on the facility of crossing it; as they come from <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName>. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Entering upon our lodgings at the beginning of a week, famine stared us in the
                    face, and I thought myself very fortunate in being able to seize upon a set of
                    calves’ feet and a piece of ham. Hearing <del>by good luck</del>
                    <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">accidentally</hi> that a sheep was killed, I sent and
                    secured a quarter of it, for the next day. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Not one of the market people understand a word of English. If you send a servant
                    to market, he must find an interpreter in the street; </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.99"/>
                <fw>p.99</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>and if provisions are offered at the door, he must call up one of the maids of
                    the house to transact the business. Many of the <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">country people</hi>, are not ignorant, however, of the
                    practice, common to every tongue and kindred, of extorting a higher price from
                    strangers than the current value of the thing to be sold. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We are preparing to leave <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>, and my
                    own next letter will be addressed to you from some place on my way home. With a
                    small degree of lurking fever, I am going to attack the rock road between
                        <placeName ref="pl1525">Pont Aber Glaslyn</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y Bwlch</placeName>, so long the object of my curiosity and
                    dread. A road that every mountain hunter goes once, but I never heard of any
                    Englishman going it twice except my father. This will be his third time.<note type="editorial">For the notorious ‘rocky road’ from Beddgelert to
                        Tan-y-Bwlch see Richard Moore-Colyer, <hi rend="italic">Roads and Trackways
                            of Wales</hi> (2nd ed. Ashbourne: Landmark, 2001), 164.</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> Letter 22 </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p style="right"><placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName>, Sept 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, 1799</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>My Dear Brother,</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="superscript">See p 54</hi> The road as <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">far as</hi>
                    <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName> presented nothing new, except the
                    ravages of the overwhelming flood that we had our share of on the way to
                        <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>. Lying close under the
                    mountains it was, at first, impassable in places and is still covered in earth
                    and stones deposited there by the torrents. In one place a breach is made in the
                    wall which divides the road from the mountains, and the road is raised to the
                    level of the wall, when standing. At <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName> the water ran over the causeway on which the inn
                    stands; but did not enter the house. At a house below, a young man saw it
                    rushing in, and shut the door. The water forced it open. He then opened an
                    opposite door, to give it vent; but before he could escape, the current jammed
                    him in between the door and the door case, and he was squeezed to death.<note type="editorial">Tŷ Isaf, Beddgelert (also known as Llewelyn Cottage) is now
                        a National Trust property; the young man was apparently Robert Jones, aged
                        21. See <ref type="http" target="https://britishlistedbuildings.co.uk/300003679-llewelyn-cottage-also-known-as-ty-isaf-beddgelert">here</ref> and <ref type="http" target="https://coflein.gov.uk/en/site/16957/details/ty-isafllewelyn-cottage-beddgelert">here.</ref>
                    </note> The mother of the man that keeps the inn, a cheerful pleasant old woman
                    of ninety two years of age, who has lived in that house sixty five years, never
                    saw such a flood.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.100"/>
                <fw>p.100</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Having armed myself with an unusual quantity of excellent cold roast beef, I rode
                    to <placeName ref="pl1525">Pont Aber Glaslyn</placeName>, and entered upon the
                    celebrated road from thence to <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y Bwlch</placeName>.
                    To give you a general idea of this road I must tell you, that between the
                        <placeName ref="pl3205">Glaslyn</placeName>, whose estuary is called
                        <placeName ref="pl1524">Traeth Mawr</placeName>, and the river which flows
                    through the Vale of Tan y Bwlch, whose name I unfortunately do not know,<note type="editorial">Afon Dwyryd.</note> and whose estuary is called Traeth
                    Bŷchan, is a tract of high, rocky land, the refuse of the mountains. It is seven
                    miles across, and universally acknowledged to be the worst carriage road in
                        <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>; but, as it is the grand pass from
                        <placeName ref="pl1234">Caernarvonshire</placeName> into Merionethshire and
                    is travelled by gigs, curricles, post chaises and gentlemen’s carriages. The
                    Welsh, themselves, say, that the only way to pass it in safety or pleasure is on
                    foot, and accordingly, if their business can be made to suit the tide, they
                    always go by the sands, and ford the traeths; but strangers, not so well knowing
                    how to escape the dangers of the water, generally encounter the inconvenience of
                    the rocks.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>After going up and down several short steeps, from <placeName ref="pl1525">Pont
                        Aber Glaslyn</placeName>, we climbed a long hill, so steep that it required
                    my utmost efforts to keep my seat upon my horse. Time was, when we would have
                    divided the toil, but now I was obliged to save myself for walking <hi rend="underline">down</hi> hills. The summit is a gap between two rocks; and
                    the descent, which begins immediately, made all I had ever seen appear trifling.
                    It is native rock, in steps and ledges; huge stones, in holes and ridges, and so
                    steep, that it shook my</p>
                <p>whole frame to walk down them, though I leaned half my weight on my father. I
                    wondered that the horses could keep on four legs so unequally placed; as I saw
                    them led down before me. In short the</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.101"/>
                <fw>p.101</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>road is all that is bad, except dirty. That it can never be; for there is not a
                    particle of soil, or any material, of which dirt can be composed.</p>
                <p>There are only two descents of this description, which succeed each other, down
                    from the gap: a few more, of less consequence, brought us to the bottom. We then
                    entered on another hill, steep at intervals, rugged without intermission, and
                    toiled up it for an hour, on foot (for having left half my journey behind me, I
                    felt more confidence for the rest) we looked back, and were surprized to see our
                    old friend the gap not far behind us. Our road now became tolerably level,
                    though still rugged, till we came to a second gap; from whence the descent was
                    not so rapid as the first. It is then as fine a road as can be imagined, and
                    winds down the steep of <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y Bwlch</placeName>; the
                    charming woods of <persName ref="pe0939">Mr Oakley</persName> on the right, with
                    squirrels leaping from tree to tree; and the beautiful Vale of Tan y Bwlch and
                    Festiniog below. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The sum total of the country between <placeName ref="pl1525">Pont Aber
                        Glaslyn</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y Bwlch</placeName> is a
                    high, rugged rock, divided into two distinct hills with a vale running along it,
                    and subdivided into many ups and downs, as they were called by the good man at
                    the <placeName ref="pl2463">Druid</placeName>. We crossed the vale towards the
                    top, mountains rising on our left; but we saw it expanding towards the sea, on
                    our right, and containing the village of <placeName ref="pl3203">Llanfrothen</placeName>, <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">with</hi> a church, and a gentleman’s house. From the
                    heights we had constantly a view of <placeName ref="pl1524">Traeth
                        Mawr</placeName>, and, latterly, of both traeths at once. They seemed near
                    each other; the land which separates the rivers growing narrower, as it
                    approaches the sea. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>For six miles we saw neither horses, cattle, nor houses, except in our look down
                    the vale of <placeName ref="pl3203">Llanfrothen</placeName>. The country is, in
                    some places, bare </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.102"/>
                <fw>p.102</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>rock; in others it is covered with heath and moss, intermixed with blades of
                    grass, affording subsistence for a few straggling sheep. Yet even this is
                    private property, divided by stone walls; and we should have had the trouble of
                    opening eight or ten gates, if a party of boys had not walked by the side of our
                    horses, and rendered us that service. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>With something like the sensation one finds at meeting with an old friend, I saw
                    the castle at <placeName ref="pl1521">Harlech</placeName>; the woods of
                        <placeName ref="pl3100">Maesyneuadd</placeName>; the hills of <placeName ref="pl3099">Llantegwyn</placeName>; and that on which I took my first view
                    of <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y Bwlch</placeName>. Near the bwlch we passed a
                    cottage. Exhausted by fatigue, and parched with thirst, I shewed a piece of
                    silver and pronounced the word <hi rend="underline">cwrw.</hi> In vain! The
                    inhabitants possessed no such luxury; and I gave them, from compassion, what I
                    would have given for a draught of beer.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The green fields, green hedges, winding river, and good road of the Vale of Tan y
                    Bwlch appeared, as it has been called, a terrestrial paradise. <persName ref="pe0939">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Oakley</persName>, situated in a
                    fine wood, near the bottom of the bwlch, commands it all, in every sense of the
                    word.</p>
                <p>We passed the inn, crossed the vale, rode upwards of a mile on the opposite side,
                    and mounted a cultivated steep to <placeName ref="pl1523">Festiniog</placeName>,
                    which is situated in a flat on the side of a mountain. We were five hours in
                    coming from <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName> hither; only eleven
                    miles, and I never toiled so hard in any five hours of my life. At <placeName ref="pl1523">Festiniog</placeName> I could neither eat nor rest; but I drank
                    milk like a calf.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The situation of <placeName ref="pl1523">Festiniog</placeName> is beautiful; on
                    the top of one of the steeps [<del>xxx</del>] which surround the vale; and
                    mountains behind rising far above it. It is a neat compact village, and for this
                    country, a large one, contain</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.103"/>
                <fw>p.103</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>ing a church, two inns, and several creditable houses.<note type="editorial">See
                        Moses Griffith’s view in Thomas Pennant’s Extra-Illustrated <hi rend="italic">Tours in Wales</hi> (NLW), <ref type="http" target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Category:A_Tour_in_Wales_by_Thomas_Pennant#/media/File:Festiniog_02386.jpg">here.</ref>
                    </note> The lands about it are fruitful, and the women not less so; for I was
                    informed, that they seldom bring fewer than a dozen or fourteen children each,
                    and sometimes, five and twenty.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Village as it is, <placeName ref="pl1523">Festiniog</placeName> may be called the
                    metropolis of the mountains. In a circumference of more than a hundred miles
                    about it, there are nowhere so many houses assembled together. It is
                    twenty-three miles distant from <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>;
                    eighteen from <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>, eighteen from
                        <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName>; twenty from <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelleu</placeName>, twenty two from <placeName ref="pl1519">Barmouth</placeName>; and twelve from the little town of <placeName ref="pl1520">Harlech</placeName>; and the whole road to every one of these
                    places is over, or between, or under, mountains. The people of <placeName ref="pl1523">Festiniog</placeName> go to market to <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName>, and fetch their wheat from <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>. The latter road is supremely bad, and never marked
                    with English footsteps.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I have been more unsuccessful in my designs on water-falls than any other
                    subjects in this country. I was told there was a water-fall half-a-mile from
                        <placeName ref="pl1523">Festiniog</placeName>
                    <note type="editorial">Possibly Rhaeadr Cymerau, on the river Goedol, close to
                        Llan Ffestiniog.</note> with two singular rocks starting up in it, called
                    the Parson and Clerk; but I was so far from making one of the congregation, as I
                    ardently wished, that I had great difficulty in walking downstairs, from the
                    distension of the muscles of my legs on the ups and downs of the <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y Bwlch</placeName> road. I was told that there was another
                    waterfall about three miles on our way to <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName>, and only a quarter of a mile from the road.<note type="editorial">Rhaeadr Cynfal, which contains a rock also known as ‘Huw
                        Lloyd’s Pulpit’, is off the modern B4391 </note> To make myself some amends
                    I determined to see this, and, for fear we should miss it, took one of the
                    inn-keeper’s sons, a boy of ten or twelve years of age, for our guide. It is
                    true the boy could not speak a word of English; but he had often, as his father
                    told us, shewn the waterfall to ladies and gentlemen; and we were sensible it
                    did not need an invocation in that language to make itself visible. The father
                    made a long oration to his son, in Welsh, and the boy trudged on before our
                    horses.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.104"/>
                <fw>p.104</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>When we had gone three miles, by our own computation (for there were no
                    mile-stones) we had a deep glen on our right, and fancied we heard the sound of
                    water. We could not communicate our ideas to the boy, who still marched on
                    before us; we stopped, however, and pointed to the right. He beckoned us
                    forward, and we obeyed. The sound ceased; the glen grew narrower; it ended; and
                    a small river appeared in view. The boy stopped at a cottage to make enquiries,
                    and we passed him; as we had done the waterfall. He then beckoned us to return,
                    but this was too much, in a stage of eighteen miles, and he no longer found us
                    obedient. We pursued our journey, without seeing the cascade, and he returned
                    home without his reward.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>From <placeName ref="pl1523">Festiniog</placeName> our road ascended gradually
                    about four miles, when we reached the top of the mountain. The descent is about
                    three or four more. In this space there is no house, except the cottage where
                    the boy learned that we had passed the waterfall, and the whole country is peat
                    and bog; though the road is good. From the foot of this mountain our road lay,
                    for two or three miles along a narrow rocky vale: we then skirted and wound up
                    another mountain; and a descent of four miles brought us to <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName>: so that the whole eighteen miles from
                        <placeName ref="pl1523">Festiniog</placeName> to this place, is composed of
                    one mountains at each end, and a vale in the middle. No part of the road is very
                    steep. In the last mile and a half, three lovely fertile vales open to the view,
                    in the junction of which <placeName ref="pl1669">Bala</placeName> is
                    situated.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>During this mountain ride my father [<del>xxx</del>] told me that I mended a
                    guinea a mile. True it is that I now found myself, for the first time of almost
                    a month, totally free from fever.</p>
                <p> </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>