<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0032">
    <teiHeader type="w">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Catherine Hutton’s Tour of Wales: 1800
                    <date>1800</date></title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Edited with an introduction by Mary-Ann Constantine</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                        <idno>MS 19079C</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <pb n="p.105"/>
                <fw>p.105</fw>
                <p/>
                <p> Letter 23 </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p style="right"><placeName ref="pl1246">Ruthin</placeName> Aug 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, 1800</p>
                <p>My Dear Brother,</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We are now on our fourth equestrian expedition into <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>, intending once more to shake hands with the mountains,
                    and then take leave of them for ever.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>How changed is the appearance of the country we have travelled through! Green has
                    vanished from the face of the earth, and rests only on some of the trees whose
                    roots draw nurture far beneath. The wet sands are reduced to powder, and a great
                    part of them covers the neighbouring hedges. Last year the ground was under, or
                    mixed with, water; this, it reflects everlasting sunshine. If it be true, as the
                    old adage says,</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Nothing pays so just a debt</p>
                <p>As wet to dry, and dry to wet<note type="editorial">A letter to the <hi rend="italic">Farmers’ Magazine</hi> written in August 1879 quotes a
                        version of this: ‘There’s ne’er so justly paid a debt/ As wet to dry, and
                        dry to wet’ (Vol 56, Series 3, p. 213).</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The proof of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Dry’s punctuality may rest upon the
                    present season. Now I am quoting proverbs, I will give you another: <hi rend="underline">Too much of one thing is good for nothing.</hi> I do not
                    mean to infer from this that the beautiful Vale of Llangollen is good for
                    nothing. I only wish you to understand, that, having seen its beauties so often,
                    we rather chose a worse landscape which we had not seen at all. Instead,
                    therefore, of proceeding up the vale, as heretofore, we crossed the lower end of
                    it, and climbing a steep hill, rode by the side of Sir Watkin’s <placeName ref="pl0761">park</placeName>, to <placeName ref="pl1199">Ruabon</placeName>, a large and pleasant village. Three miles farther we came
                    to <placeName ref="pl0792">Wrexham</placeName>, the first town in <placeName ref="pl1221">North wales</placeName> for size and population. The tower
                    steeple of the <placeName ref="pl1983">church</placeName> is very fine. The
                    country around is beautiful and fertile, rich in corn and woods; and doubtless
                    in verdure, when it is any where to be found. The mountains were left behind, to
                    guard Llangollen Vale.</p>
                <p>We took the road to <placeName ref="pl1246">Ruthin</placeName>, and three miles
                    beyond <placeName ref="pl0792">Wrexham</placeName>, quitted the swelling hills
                    and waving grain, for a barren common</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p106"/>
                <fw>p.106</fw>
                <p>and a most execrable stoney road. <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">A new set of</hi> mountains now rose on our left, with
                    mines of coal and iron, and works for refining the ore. The place is called
                    Minera; I suppose from the <placeName ref="pl1210">mines</placeName>. After
                    three or four miles our road mended; <del>and</del> our scenery became more
                    wild. <del>We were fairly among the mountains, and breathed the pure air which
                        removed my fever</del>
                    <hi rend="superscript">And I inhaled with pleasure the mountain breeze which
                        restored to me to health</hi> last year. We travelled between two rows of
                    mountains, along a narrow elevated vale, adorned, not with yellow wheat, like
                    the rich slopes about <placeName ref="pl0792">Wrexham</placeName> but with
                        <del>here and there</del> a <hi rend="superscript">few scattered</hi>
                    patches of green oats. When one <del>passes</del>
                    <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">enters</hi> the barrier of the mountains the difference
                    is immediate and astonishing.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At nine miles from <placeName ref="pl0792">Wrexham</placeName> we quitted the
                    Ruthin road, and toiled up a dreary hill, on the left, to a house where we meant
                    to sleep. It is the <placeName ref="pl3207">Cross Foxes</placeName>, but whoever
                    seeks it by that token will seek in vain, for the Foxes, instead of giving
                    intelligence at the door, are placed over the parlour chimney, and the house is
                    generally known by the name of <placeName ref="pl3207">Tavarn
                        Dowyrch</placeName><note type="editorial">Tafarn Dywyrch, ‘the turf tavern’
                        would also be visited by George Borrow, in 1854 (<hi rend="italic">Wild
                            Wales</hi>, Chapter XV).</note>. It is in the parish of Llanarmon in
                    Yale: but three miles distant from the church.</p>
                <p>We entered the only parlour, which was dark and superlatively dirty. Nobody came
                    to disturb us. I proceeded to the kitchen, where, in a corner, by a roasting
                    fire, though the heat of the weather was insupportable, sat a female Falstaff,
                        <persName ref="pe2283">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Davies</persName>,
                    the governess of the mansion. Neither she nor her chair were moveables. From the
                    spot where they were fixed, she might have laid her hands upon the fire; but she
                    was defended from part of its heat by two old pans, or pot-lids. This lady
                    received me with all the state of a Duchess, and from her I learned that she had
                    no meat, no porter, no oats, </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="p.107"/>
                <fw>p.107</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>no straw. I asked if she had any beds? She answered she could make up eighteen. I
                    sought no farther. The maid was baking thin cakes of flour on an iron plate. I
                    desired to have some of them buttered; and with three successive pints of milk,
                    two glasses of brandy, and some lump sugar, twice renewed, in an old broken
                    tea-cup, we made a most delicious repast. I believe we should have committed an
                    excess, and indulged ourselves with another pint, if we had dared; but when we
                    sent our man out for the last, <persName ref="pe2283">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Davies</persName> asked him if he thought the river ran
                    milk?</p>
                <p>Bread, I thought, would be a good substitute for corn for our horses <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">as fern, she said, would be for straw</hi> and I asked if
                    they could have a loaf? She answered in a very decisive and laconic manner,
                    “No”. But, she observed, they would do very well without. I had not foreseen she
                    had no bread; though that was actually the case, and our consumption of the
                    cakes had caused a famine in the family.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>As the dust in the kitchen was sometimes removed, and our habits brought up more
                    from the parlour than they could have found on the turnpike road: as the kitchen
                    was lighted by a blazing fire, while we did not know but a solitary candle might
                    be esteemed a favour: and, as it was a trouble to get anything where the
                    mistress could not move, and the maid could not understand: we sat an hour after
                    supper with <persName ref="pe2283">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                        Davies</persName>.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The woman had been handsome, and did not want understanding, and her manner would
                    have done honour to an Empress. She told us she had <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">been</hi> afflicted with the stone <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">during</hi> twenty nine years; that the pain had become
                    intolerable; and about three years ago a gentleman from <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> slept at her house, to whom she mentioned her case. He
                    promise</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>108 </p>
                <p>ed to send her something which should cure her, and <del>she gave him</del>
                    <hi rend="superscript">demanded</hi> half a crown <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">for his remedy, which she gave him</hi>. A packet of
                    medicines arrived soon after, with directions for taking them. She doubled the
                    dose, as she said she always did of everything that Doctors sent her. For five
                    hours she was in such exquisite pain, that she thought her inside, and even her
                    flesh, were being torn to pieces; and she bid her maid not to leave her, for she
                    believed she should die. I suppose, if she had not been stronger than a horse,
                    she must have died. But, at the end of that time, the stone came from her,
                    broken into thirteen pieces, weighing, altogether, an ounce and a quarter. She
                    was then easy and went to bed. Half a year later, a fragment of the stone, about
                    the size of a pea, worked out at her loins. She has had no return of her
                    complaint; but she was so weakened with the operation <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">of the medicine</hi> that she has never been able to move
                    since, except twice, in the twenty four hours, between her bed and her kitchen
                    fire. This has made her grow to such an enormous bulk. She does not sleep well,
                    but in remembrance of her former suffering, she blesses God, as she lies awake,
                    that the Queen of England is not happier than she: for she is free from
                    pain.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Having listened to the extraordinary case of <persName ref="pe2283">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Davies</persName>, we desired her to make out
                    our bill; which she did, with chalk, on the table before her; and retired. She
                    and her family (a man and maid servant) supped on potatoes and buttermilk after
                    we left them. My bed was the best of the eighteen, and had red and white checked
                    curtains, half way round; an inferior stood in my room; four, still worse, in
                    another room that I saw, and a miserable pallet, in a hole, at the top of the
                    stairs. The other eleven remain unaccounted for to this hour. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="109"/>
                <fw>p.109</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>My dormitory was worthy of the other accommodations that I saw, at <placeName ref="pl3207">Tavern Dowyrch</placeName>. A lumpy flock bed covered with a
                    rug, no pillow, and the grease of twenty Welsh heads <hi rend="superscript">of
                        hair</hi> marking the place where it should have lain. I got into it with
                    reluctance. But either finding or fancying that I was damp, I stripped it of its
                    dirty linen, and slept between the blankets; which, for the honour of the Welsh,
                    I must say are always clean and were so in this, the dirtiest and poorest of
                    their inns. <hi rend="underline">That</hi> was more than I could say of myself,
                    after passing through the dust of the preceeding day; but as only the maid was
                    visible this morning, and I did not know what was Welsh for a towel, I carried
                    my dirt away with me to <placeName ref="pl1246">Ruthin</placeName>.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p/>
                <p> Letter 24 </p>
                <p style="right">
                    <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>, Aug 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1800</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>My Dear Brother, </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> It is impossible in this country to steer clear of public meetings; we meant to
                    have gone by <placeName ref="pl0741">Pool</placeName>, but hearing it was the
                    Assizes there, we went to <placeName ref="pl1260">Oswestry</placeName>, where we
                    found it was the wake. At <placeName ref="pl1246">Ruthin</placeName> we met the
                    Assizes, and at <placeName ref="pl1203">Abergeleu</placeName> we came in for the
                    fag end of the fair. The street was in an uproar, and Mr and Mrs Davies, at the
                        <placeName ref="pl3208">Bee</placeName>, were pushing drunken Welshmen out
                    of their house, by the head and shoulders. In setting out from <placeName ref="pl1371">St Asaph</placeName>, we took a wrong road, which brought us to
                        <placeName ref="pl1268">Bodelwyddan</placeName>, the seat of <persName ref="pe1364">Sir John Williams</persName>. I took the liberty to ride up to
                    the house, and enquire the way; and the servant was so civil as to walk by my
                    horse, till he had conducted us into the high road. When I gave him something at
                    parting, he said ‘God bless you’, which is the Welsh mode of saying, Thank-you
                    Ma’am.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We arrived at the shore of the <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName>, <hi rend="superscript">just as</hi> the mail boat was putting</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="110"/>
                <fw>p.110</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>off, and I begged the people to take us in. But every one to his business—theirs
                    was to make haste—so they refused my petition. We waited near two hours for high
                    water, and then crossed the river in the common ferry, in company with our own
                    horses. We were forty three minutes on our passage, exposed to a violent storm
                    and a rough sea: safe enough, I suppose, but I liked neither my situation nor my
                    companions; the four footed ones, at least; for though I am fond of them on
                    shore, I did not like to see them so near me on the water. I wrapped myself
                    close in my greatcoat, however; sat on the floor, for the ferry affords no other
                    seat; held down my head against the pelting wind and rain, and expressed none of
                    my dislikes to my fellow travellers. The horses had the same discretion. They
                    trembled, and said nothing, but I believe they were as glad as myself, when we
                    set our feet on the shore of the town of <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName>. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We reached <placeName ref="pl1595">Aber</placeName> while <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">we hoped</hi> light enough remained for us to walk to
                        <placeName ref="pl3146">Rhaiader Vawr</placeName>; and, that we might lose
                    none of it, we set out immediately, without entering the inn. We marched up the
                    deep, sequestered glen, the river still running at our feet; but no longer a
                    foaming torrent. We met a traveller on horseback; for, as far as <placeName ref="pl3245">Pont Newyd</placeName>, a horse road from <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName> goes up the glen. His appearance announced that he
                    could speak English. “How far to the water-fall?” “Three miles” we met another,
                    and repeated our question. “A great way, I am sure you cannot see it tonight”.
                    Though a little discouraged, and passed by <placeName ref="pl3245">Pont
                        Newyd</placeName>, which is now repaired. From thence, the road being still
                    on the side of the mountain, and no longer intended for a horse, became so
                    narrow that it required all my [<del>xxx</del>] strength of head to pass it. We
                    soon came <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="subscript">near</hi> to a new wooden bridge; but the river was now so
                    low, that we crossed it on huge stones, of which its bed is full. The mountains </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="111"/>
                <fw>p.111</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>here recede so far as to leave a meadow, by the side of the river, considerably
                    elevated above its banks. This might be very fertile, if the husbandman chose to
                    scatter the manure over it, which at present adorns the cow-path. As it is, it
                    is beautiful; and is enlivened by a cottage, and a score of black cattle. A
                    flock of ten domestic goats we saw come down the mountain to be milked; and we
                    observed that they stopped at the door of a shed used for that purpose, as
                    mechanically as a horse would have done at the door of his stable.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We walked up this narrow vale, on a path so little worn by human footsteps, that,
                    at times, it was scarcely discernible: till, as nearly as we could compute it,
                    we were two miles and a half from the entrance, when the broad face of a
                    mountain shut it up at the end, and seemed to say “Thus far shall ye go, and no
                    further”. Down a hollow in this mountain falls the river; from the height, as we
                    conjectured, of two hundred feet. There are two falls; the upper one sloping and
                    short, the lower perpendicular, and occupying four fifths of the height. We saw
                    it at the greatest disadvantage: at a time when large streams are diminished and
                    small ones dried up: but even so it was majestic; not dashing and foaming, but
                    falling in an even placid manner, down the smooth surface of the rock, itself
                    had worn; and breaking and sprinkling over every inequality it had not been able
                    to subdue.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I could have spent a day in this solitary glen, with such a magnificent object
                    before <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">me</hi> and not known how the hours had passed; but day
                    was almost gone, and I did not wish night to overtake me here. I therefore
                    walked back with hasty strides, till I reached the wooden bridge, which, in a
                    fit of heroism, I determined to cross, instead of going over on the stones
                    below: but my short-lived bravery could scarcely carry me to the end, and had
                    the river been bold and rapid, I must either have gone</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="112"/>
                <fw>p.112</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>back or gone in. The bridge is what <persName ref="pe0232">Pennant</persName>
                    calls an Alpine bridge. Its construction is very simple. Two thin poles are laid
                    across the river, the ends resting on piles of stones. Across these, at
                    intervals, are nailed small narrow planks to step on; and a third pole, above
                    the others, serves as a rail to hold by. I was glad when I quitted it; and glad
                    that we reached the place where we crossed the river, in going up, while a
                    glimpse of light remained; for, in the intermediate space, the path was so
                    narrow I could hardly set two feet abreast, and was obliged to hold by the heath
                    and furze of the mountain, to keep myself from falling.</p>
                <p/>
                <p>The river comes down the glen with a rapid descent; consequently the upper part,
                    though still a deep glen, is high ground. From thence, through the opening at
                    bottom, we caught a beautiful view of the north east part of <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName>. It was dark before we arrived at the inn
                    at <placeName ref="pl1595">Aber</placeName>; but we were both charmed with our
                    expedition.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>People must certainly die and marry among the mountains, as well as in the great
                    world; but we have had two unexpected instances of it since last year. <persName ref="pe2219">Richard Williams</persName>, the worthy boatman of <placeName ref="pl3141">Cwm y Glo</placeName>, has exchanged his own [<del>xxx</del>]
                    boat for that of Charon, and the Lakes of Llanberis for the river Styx, <hi rend="superscript">according to the creed of Grecian poets, and their
                        imitators to the present day</hi>. And the sprightly old hostess of
                        <placeName ref="pl1527">Llanberis</placeName>, who had just English enough
                    to bid us welcome, has become a widow and is married again.<note type="editorial">John Closs of Tŷ’n Llan, Nant Peris (now the Vaynol Arms)
                        died in 1799; his first wife Jane Roberts apparently died in 1773; this must
                        be Elin Griffith, whom he married in 1780. See Margaret Wyn Roberts, <ref type="http" target="https://ecorwyddfa.co.uk/downloads/papurau/2007/342_3_2007.pdf">'Cofeb Griffith Ellis'</ref>.</note> Her second husband, who had been
                    her former lover, [<del>xxxx</del>] hearing of her lonely situation, brought his
                    horse and pillion, and bore her off, in triumph.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Roads perish as well as men! We saw that from <placeName ref="pl1525">Pont Aber
                        Glaslyn</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y Bwlch</placeName> at
                    its last gasp. A new one has been opened since that time, which runs nearer the
                    sea; where, [<del>xxx</del>] the larger rocks are lessened and the smaller are
                    extinct. I am glad I saw the rough old gentleman, before his departure.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="113"/>
                <fw>p.113</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We are very fortunate in having made the acquaintance of the son of an Irish
                    nobleman; a soldier, open, bold, and brave: a man of good sense and great
                    reading; and his wife, a sweet, amiable young woman. Their politeness is of no
                    common kind. I have often met with persons, who, under the mask of obliging
                    others, have sought only to please themselves: persons who, like Mr Smith in
                        <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0108">Evelina</title></bibl> are for
                        <hi rend="underline">whatever the company chuses, but they like <placeName ref="pl2644">Vauxhall</placeName> best:</hi><note type="editorial">‘Mr
                        Smith’ is a minor character in Frances Burney’s, <hi rend="italic">Evelina,
                            or the History of a Young Lady's Entrance into the World</hi>
                        (1778).</note> but, though we are together every day, we cannot get this
                    gentleman and lady to let us understand that they have a wish of their own.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> Letter 25 </p>
                <p/>
                <p style="right"><placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> Sept 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> 1800</p>
                <p>My Dear Brother,</p>
                <p/>
                <p>I have made an excursion to <placeName ref="pl3212">Clŷnnog</placeName>, a
                    village ten miles south west from this place, lying between the mountains and
                    the sea. A little beyond the third mile stone, the road divides; that on the
                    left, having run nine miles farther, divides again, one branch of it leading to
                        <placeName ref="pl1594">Criccieth</placeName>; the other to <placeName ref="pl1670">Penmorfa</placeName> (the Head of the Marsh); and from thence,
                    across the traeths, into <placeName ref="pl1235">Merionethshire</placeName>. We
                    took the right hand road, which goes through <placeName ref="pl3212">Clynnog</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl3213">Pwllheli</placeName>. Till
                    the division, our road had been stoney, and we had met carts innumerable
                    conveying slates from the mountains. We here quitted slates and stones, and the
                    road became as fine as I ever travelled; and so, I am told, it continues to
                        <placeName ref="pl3213">Pwllheli</placeName>.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We left the little rural church of <placeName ref="pl3214">Llanwnda</placeName>
                    on our right; and farther on, that of <placeName ref="pl3215">Llandwrog</placeName>; no doubt under the patronage of the same kind St
                    Twrog to whom is dedicated the <placeName ref="pl3157">church</placeName> of
                        <placeName ref="pl1522">Maentwrog</placeName>, near <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y Bwlch</placeName>. On our left was the house of <placeName ref="pl3331">Glynllifon</placeName>, the seat of <persName ref="pe0153">Lord
                        Newborough</persName>. The entrance [<del>xxx</del>] and the woods we saw,
                    but the mansion kept so close among the trees, that it was with difficulty we
                    could discern the smoak of its chimnies. The whole road is near the coast; never
                    more than a mile from the sea, on one hand, or more than four from the mountains
                    on the other. The country is a plain, made up</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="114"/>
                <fw>p.114</fw>
                <p>of round hills, some of them sufficiently steep; but it is better cultivated and
                    better wooded than any part of <placeName ref="pl1234">Caernarvonshire</placeName> I have seen.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I could not help noticing, as we passed, the Welsh mode of getting in
                        harvest.<note type="editorial"> On this theme, of perennial interest to
                        tourists who often travelled in late summer, see the examples noted by
                        Michael Freeman <ref type="http" target="https://sublimewales.wordpress.com/material-culture/occupations/agriculture/harvesting/">here.</ref>
                    </note> In a field of wheat were the farmer, his wife and three children. They
                    had three drags, each with one horse, and each horse mounted be a boy or girl.
                    The woman laid nine sheaves upon a drag; the man raked, the children drove. When
                    the woman had loaded a drag, she stood still, till another came. When the man
                    had raked the ground occupied by the last nine sheaves, he stood still, till his
                    wife had moved out of his way. The children always <hi rend="underline">sat</hi>
                    still, for they had nothing to do but hold a halter, and let the horse carry
                    them. And so the whole family would go on, soberly; till by the blessing of God,
                    and continuance of fine weather, they might in time, have carried all their
                    wheat.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>A few miles to the left, within the mountains, I had, before, seen a lazy fellow,
                    in a hay field, loading two women alternately with hay. They carried it home, on
                    their backs, while he rested on his fork, till each returned for another
                    load.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The road from <placeName ref="pl3331">Glynllifon</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl3212">Clŷnnog</placeName> is remarkably straight. In returning we
                    traced it the whole way to the woods of <placeName ref="pl3331">Glynllifon</placeName>: a distance of nearly five miles. About two miles
                    before we reach <placeName ref="pl3212">Clŷnnog</placeName>, <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">we have</hi> a charming view of <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>, through the opening of <placeName ref="pl3168">Nant
                        Nanlle</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl3093">Drws y Coed</placeName>. It
                    is the vista from which <persName ref="pe1109">Wilson</persName> took his view
                    of that mountain [<del>xxxx</del>].<note type="editorial"> Richard Wilson,
                        ‘Snowdon from Llyn Nantlle’, Walker Art Gallery, National Museums Liverpool;
                        see <ref type="http" target="http://interactive.britishart.yale.edu/wilson-in-wales/103/snowdon-from-llyn-nantlle">here.</ref></note> We saw the whole breadth of <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>, and it exactly filled the opening; but <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">a</hi> rising hill intercepted its base. This, also, is
                    best seen in returning from <placeName ref="pl3212">Clŷnnog</placeName>.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl3212">Clŷnnog</placeName> is a lowly, retired village, with a
                    tower steeple rising out of a grove of trees. It is not more than five or six
                    hundred yards from the sea; though it is totally hidden from it. <placeName ref="pl3212">Clŷnnog</placeName> is about three miles from <placeName ref="pl3246">the Rivals</placeName>, the grand termination of the mountains:
                    but not more than one from Gwern Coch,<note type="editorial">Gyrn Goch and Gyrn
                        Ddu are hills on the Llŷn Peninsula just south of Clynnog Fawr. </note> the
                    nearest. The chain seems here to prohibit human</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="115"/>
                <fw>p.115</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>progress, and one would imagine that only birds or fishes could penetrate
                    further; but I was told that the road to <placeName ref="pl3213">Pwllheli</placeName> winds among the mountains, and after four miles,
                    leaves them behind. From the shore the great three headed promontory of
                        <placeName ref="pl3246">the Rivals</placeName> is a most noble object.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We dined at the <placeName ref="pl3333">New Inn</placeName>, which is the older
                    of the two at <placeName ref="pl3212">Clŷnnog</placeName>. Its mistress, the
                    widow of a former curate of the parish, we found a very intelligent woman, and
                    her moderate charge and [<del>xxx</del>] kindness, proclaimed her truly
                        Welsh.<note type="editorial">She appears (later in the text) to be a Mrs
                        Jones.</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We were conducted to the church of Clŷnnog by the clerk’s wife, without
                        [<del>xxx</del>] shoes or stockings. But she had a worse deficiency: she
                    neither spoke nor understood one word of English, and vain were my enquiries
                    after St Beuno, his chapel and his chest.<note type="editorial">Beuno, thought
                        to have died in the mid-seventh century, was widely revered as a saint
                        across north Wales. A C14th Welsh-language Life, Buchedd Beuno, recounts a
                        range of events and miracles which correspond to sites of his cult; he also
                        appears in the Life of his niece St Gwenfrewi or Winefrede of Holywell, near
                        Thomas Pennant’s home at Downing. See Patrick Sims-Williams, <hi rend="italic">Buchedd Beuno: The Middle Welsh Life of St Beuno</hi>
                        (Dublin: Dias Texts, 2018) and ODNB.</note> In this distress I sent our
                    servant for Mrs Jones, our landlady; who shewed us, on the right side of the
                    altar, the chest of St Beuno: a log of wood, made hollow within, and covered
                    with a lid; with strong iron hinges, and a chink, to receive money.<note type="editorial">At Clynnog both the chapel and the distinctive ash chest
                        (‘Cyff Beuno’) mentioned by Hutton survive: for a mid-nineteenth-century
                        watercolour of the latter see Frances Wynne (1835-1907) ‘Scraps ancient and
                            modern’<ref type="http" target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:DV307_no.150_St_Beuno%27s_Chest,_Clynnog_Aug_8_1866.png">National Library of Wales Drawing Volume DV 307.</ref>
                    </note> The chest is secured by three locks, and is opened only once a year,
                    when the contributions of the Pious, amounting to about thirty or forty
                    shillings, are distributed among the poor. It was whispered that another motive,
                    than piety, had sometimes a share in the donations – that if a young woman had
                    committed a fault, for sixpence, the saint would kindly interpose, and prevent
                    her becoming a mother, without being a wife.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>An ancient vaulted passage was the communication between the church and the
                        <placeName ref="pl3334">chapel of St Beuno</placeName>. It may still be
                    entered from the church, but the door next to the chapel is stopped up, and, to
                    enter that, we are obliged to go round to its outer door. In this small cloister
                    was formerly found the statue of Winifred, the celebrated saint of <placeName ref="pl0702">Flintshire</placeName>, who was the niece of Beuno. It lies
                    there still, and the discovery of whom it represents does great credit to the
                    penetration of the discoverers, for it has neither head nor arms.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The <placeName ref="pl3334">chapel of St Beuno</placeName> is large and lofty,
                    and if the saint himself erec </p>
                <pb n="116"/>
                <fw>p.116</fw>
                <p/>
                <p>ted it for his mausoleum, he must have had at least as much vanity as devotion.
                    His remains were deposited in the centre of the chapel, and worked miracles for
                    ages. They healed the sick and, particularly, cured rickety children: but it
                    must be owned, by the most rational method that ever saint invented. The
                    patients were dipped in a well hard by; wrapped in blankets, and laid all night
                    on the tomb. Instances of this have occurred within these very few years. But
                    the sacrilegious <persName ref="pe0153">Lord Newborough</persName> (whether he
                    thought like the boy whose goose laid golden eggs, I know not) employed workmen
                    to take down the tomb, and dig up the body.<note type="editorial">Thomas Wynn of
                        Glynllifon (1736-1807) decided to excavate the site in 1793; several later
                        tourists note this, such as Richard Ayton and William Daniell, <hi rend="italic">A voyage round Great Britain undertaken in the summer of
                            the year 1813</hi>, 8 vols (London: Longman, 1814-25) I, 179. I have yet
                        to find it noted in an archaeological report.</note>The first they did
                    effectually, for they broke up the tomb into a hundred pieces: luckily, they
                    failed in their second purpose, for by the time they had dug about three feet in
                    depth, they were become so completely drunk that they were obliged to give up
                    the enterprize; which was never resumed. The stones are piled carefully in a
                    heap, and mark the place where the saint reposes; but he has been robbed of his
                    heavenly diploma, and cures the sick no more.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The skill of St Beuno as a surgeon, was far more extraordinary than his practice
                    of physic. It is well known that he took the head of his niece, Winifred, after
                    it had been severed from her body, and placed it again on her shoulders; where
                    it lived and flourished fifteen years, having no other mark of the injury it had
                    sustained, than a small white circle around the neck.<note type="editorial">The
                        legend of the decapitation and miraculous recovery of St Winifred, niece of
                        St Beuno, became widely known to tourists through Pennant’s <hi rend="italic">Tour in Wales</hi>, I, 31-34.</note>
                </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The well of St Beuno is inclosed by a quadrangular stone wall; but it has always
                    been open up top. Within are two heights of benches, built all round in the
                    walls, which narrow the masonry down to the well. These, I suppose, were for the
                    convenience of the bathers; as four small recesses, at the back of the seats,
                    were for their cloaths. The spring has been much injured by the alteration of
                    the road to <placeName ref="pl3213">Pwllheli</placeName>. The well is now not
                    more than eighteen inches deep; but woe be to him that approaches it without
                    caution; for it is surrounded by </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="117"/>
                <fw>p.117</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>offerings more likely to be acceptable to the heathen Goddess Cloacina,<note type="editorial">A delicate way of putting it: Cloacina was the Roman
                        goddess of sewers.</note> than to a Christian Saint.</p>
                <p>I thought of the maxim, <hi rend="underline">Truth will prevail in the end.</hi>
                    The church that Beuno erected for the worship of Almighty God is clean, and in
                    perfect repair. The chapel he erected for the worship of himself is the
                    receptacle of rubbish; and his well is marked by the filth of half the
                    parish.</p>
                <p>The Welsh had many Holy Wells, beside that of <placeName ref="pl1979">St
                        Winifred</placeName>, still so called; and the common people have great
                    faith in them to this day. Another proof of my maxim, and of the good sense of
                    the Welsh; who made their saints cure diseases by fine, clear, springs of cold
                    water; while every other people ascribed that virtue to dry bones; the decayed
                    remnants of the human body.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p/>
                <p> Letter 26 </p>
                <p style="right">
                    <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>, Sept 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1800</p>
                <p>My Dear Brother,</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>In another excursion I have been making to the Isle of <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName>, I crossed the <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl1563">Bangor Ferry</placeName> and
                    began where I left off before. We turned to the right, along a narrow, rocky
                    road, where it was just possible for our horses to follow us. This having taken
                    us, some time, close to the water’s edge, led us up a steep rock high above it;
                    from whence the views of the <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai</placeName> and the
                    country above it were charming. After we had gone about four miles, we came into
                    the high road. Our descent into <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName>
                    was one of the steepest I ever saw marked by wheels. At the bottom is the
                    harbour. A row of houses, on the left, commands the whole bay; now a glassy
                    surface enlivened by a number of vessels. Beyond this is the town, most
                    beautifully situated; washed by the sea on one side, and sheltered by steep,
                    wooded hills on the other; but in the principal street, which is</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="118"/>
                <fw>p.118</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>broad, straight, and not ill-built, shut out by the houses from both. It contains
                    a good inn, and many good lodging houses, for the Irish, having made <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> dear and saucy, are flocking to
                        <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName>. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At the farther end of this street is the <placeName ref="pl1968">castle</placeName>, separated from the sea by a lovely green, which is the
                    public promenade of the town.<note type="editorial">For an image of Beaumaris
                        Castle by Moses Griffith, see <ref type="http" target="https://www.watercolourworld.org/painting/beaumaris-castle-anglesea-tww02210e?page=1">here.</ref></note> As the castle had no steep rock for security, it was
                    surrounded by a deep ditch, which could occasionally be filled from the water.
                    The <placeName ref="pl1968">castle of Beaumaris</placeName> is reckoned less
                    beautiful than those of <placeName ref="pl1530">Conwy</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1566">Caernarvon</placeName>. Its towers are round, and not so lofty,
                    and the elegant turrets are wanting; but it is more regular than either. It has
                    a singular and massive appearance, and much would have been said of it, if the
                    peerless castles of <placeName ref="pl1530">Conwy</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1566">Caernarvon</placeName> had not been its neighbours. It is also
                    less known. Nobody goes <hi rend="underline">through</hi>
                    <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName>, and few go <hi rend="underline">to</hi> it.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The court of the <placeName ref="pl1968">castle</placeName>, enlarged by some of
                    the buildings having totally vanished, though still surrounded by others, is now
                    a bowling green. I will not affirm that tall grass and weeds, through which one
                    might with difficulty make one’s way, might not be more appropriate: I can only
                    say, that neatness, even as an attendant upon ruins, did not offend me.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Opposite the entrance is the state chamber, presenting a front of five regular
                    windows. It has one gothic fire place in the middle, and one at each end. But we
                    can only look up into it, the floor, having been of wood, is gone. Here</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Princes sat, where nettles grow!<note type="editorial">[Anon] <hi rend="italic">A
                            journey to the Highlands of Scotland. With occasional remarks on Dr.
                            Johnson's tour: by a lady</hi> (1776) contains a poem ‘by a gentleman’
                        on ‘Rosline Castle’. ‘Where bats now rest their smutty wings / Th’impurpled
                        feast was wont to flow / And Beauty danced in graceful rings / And princes
                        sat, where nettles grow. (p. 75)</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Here, for a short time, sat the unfortunate <persName ref="pe2268">Richard the
                        second</persName>. It is remarkable that of the four castles built in this
                    country by his great great grandfather, three served him for an asylum, and one
                    for a pri</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="119"/>
                <fw>p.119</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>son. He fled successively to <placeName ref="pl1530">Conwy</placeName>,
                        <placeName ref="pl1968">Beaumaris</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1566">Caernarvon</placeName>, and <placeName ref="pl1530">Conwy</placeName>
                    again; and he was taken to <placeName ref="pl2418">Flint</placeName>.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>On the right is the chapel, the ribbed stone roof of which is entire, and
                    deservedly admired. On each side the chapel, at a considerable height, is a
                    window, communicating with a closet. Whether these were confessionals, or places
                    where the principal inhabitants of the castle might join in the devotion,
                    without mixing with the crowd, I am too ignorant to say. Underneath the chapel
                    is a dungeon, which we went into. It is now no more than a vault, admitting
                    light at the entrance; but in its perfect state, not a ray could penetrate. I
                    shuddered at the thought! And pitied, while I blamed, those mistaken christians
                    who could supplicated pardon for their sins from the God of mercy; whilst they
                    obliged their fellow creatures to languish under their feet, deprived of the
                    common benefits of light and air!</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>A gallery formerly ran all round the castle, with recesses for the soldiers, on
                    one hand, and doors to the apartments on the other. We walked along the whole of
                    one side the square, and part of two other sides. What more remains I know not.
                    The gallery is narrow; some of the arched door-ways are too low even for me to
                    pass through, without stooping; and it is lighted only by the chinks through
                    which the soldiers reconnoitered the country, and discharged their arrows. There
                    is a space all round the outside of the castle, bounded by a high stone
                    wall.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>From the <placeName ref="pl1968">castle of Beaumaris</placeName>, we mounted
                        <placeName ref="pl1964">Baron Hill</placeName>, and walked through the
                    beautiful woods of <persName ref="pe1232">Lord Bulkeley</persName>, to the <hi rend="underline">cist faen</hi>, or stone coffin of <persName ref="pe2285">Joan</persName>, natural daughter of <persName ref="pe2049">John</persName>, King of England, and wife of <persName ref="pe2047">Llywelyn</persName>, Prince of Wales.<note type="editorial">The carved lid
                        of the stone coffin, with its effigy thought to be Joan, was kept in the
                        church of St Mary and St Nicholas and reunited with the ‘cattle trough’ on
                        the suggestion of the poet Richard Llwyd; Lord Bulkeley built a mausoleum
                        for it in his grounds in 1808. The coffin was moved to the church in
                        Beaumaris in the 1920s. See Ramage, <hi rend="italic">Portraits of an
                            Island</hi>, 7-8. For a photograph of the carved lid, see <ref type="http" target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan,_Lady_of_Wales#/media/File:Eglwys_y_Santes_Fair,_Biwmares,_Ynys_Mon,_Church_of_St_Mary_and_St_Nicholas,_Beaumaris,_North_Wales_61.jpg">here.</ref>
                    </note> This princess came down from the Welsh camp on the mountains, and had
                    the inexpressible pleasure of making peace between her father and her husband.
                    What a glorious prerogative of woman is that of making peace! She died in 1237,
                    and it is said <persName ref="pe2047">Llywelyn</persName> built the monastery of
                        <placeName ref="pl3248">Llanfaes</placeName> over her grave. After</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="120"/>
                <fw>p.120</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>the destruction of the abbey, the coffin became a watering trough for cattle, at
                    a farmhouse. <persName ref="pe1232">Lord Bulkeley</persName> has rescued it from
                    this ignoble situation, and given it a place in his park; though he does not
                    seem yet to have determined how to dispose of it, and in the meantime it lies
                    neglected. I am afraid his lordship will never consult me on the subject; or I
                    should counsel him to beg the coffin of <persName ref="pe2047">Llywelyn</persName> from the <placeName ref="pl1879">church of
                        Llanrwst</placeName>, if possible; and if not, to present that of <persName ref="pe2285">Joan</persName> to it; for it is a little singular that the
                    coffin of the husband should have remained above ground, ever since the
                    destruction of the Abbey of Maynan;<note type="editorial"><persName ref="pe2047">Llywelyn</persName>’s coffin was moved to Maenan Abbey near Llanrwst
                        after the Dissolution; it can now be seen in the church at Llanrwst. </note>
                    as that of the wife has done, since the destruction of <placeName ref="pl3248">Llanfaes</placeName>. In their resurrection I would not divide them.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>From the <hi rend="underline">cist faen</hi> we ascended to the fort, a small
                    castellated building, rising out of the woods, and mounting ten or a dozen
                    peaceable little guns, whose only business is to announce days of
                        rejoicing.<note type="editorial">One of several follies and buildings in the
                        grounds, this tower does not seem to have survived.</note> Notwithstanding
                    my general contempt for modern antiques, this commanded my respect, from its
                    situation. In <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName> it looks down on the
                        <placeName ref="pl1486">town</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1968">castle</placeName> of Beaumaris, and the north east part of the island;
                    beyond this <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">on</hi> the sea, <placeName ref="pl1959">Priestholm
                        Island</placeName>, the <placeName ref="pl1564">Straits of
                    Menai</placeName>, and the City of <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName>.
                    The view is terminated by the chain of majestic mountains, which form the
                    boundary of all the prospects of this country. I left this spot, where so much
                    of the world was spread before me, with reluctance; but a more humble matter was
                    become interesting – the dinner that waited for us at the inn.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We left <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName> by another road, to avoid
                    the hill, going along a hollow way, and under the arch of an elegant bridge that
                        <persName ref="pe1232">Lord Bulkeley</persName> has thrown over it, to
                    connect his lawns above. [<del>xxxxxxx</del>]. Here, as I sat silent on my
                    horse, I had nothing to do but</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="121"/>
                <fw>p.121</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>contemplate the mountains. Hitherto I had seen but in part, and known but in
                    part; I now considered them as a grand whole.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The chain of mountains begins at the <placeName ref="pl1958">Great Orme’s
                        Head</placeName>, and ends at <placeName ref="pl3246">the
                    Rivals</placeName>, about thirty eight or forty miles distant. These points, and
                    one other between, which is <placeName ref="pl1338">Penmaen Mawr</placeName>,
                    touch the sea. But the general line of the mountains receeds inwards, leaving a
                    space [<del>xxxx</del>] of what, in comparison [<del>xxxxx</del>] may be called
                    level ground; but whoso travels it will find, to his cost, that it is a
                    succession of steep, rocky hills. Perhaps it is nowhere more than five miles in
                    breadth. This district is called Arfon, and <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>, being seated in it, is no more than the city or
                    castle of Arfon.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>There are but three openings by which one can penetrate into the recesses of the
                    mountains. </p>
                <p>The first and grandest of these is <placeName ref="pl1529">Nant
                        Francon</placeName> [<del>xxxxxxx</del>]; the second of <placeName ref="pl3135">Llanberis</placeName> [<del>xxxx</del>] the third is of
                        <placeName ref="pl1526">Cwellyn Pool</placeName>.[xxxxxx]</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Each of the stupendous masses of earth and rock has a name; but I am acquainted
                    with only the principal of them. [<del>xxxxx</del>] They rise in the following
                    order:</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The <placeName ref="pl1958">Great Ormes Head</placeName></p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1338">Penmaen Mawr</placeName></p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl3249">Carnedd Llewelyn</placeName>. Inferior only to <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>, being 3330 feet above high water mark;
                    while <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName> is but 3568 feet above the
                    quay at <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl3250">Carnedd Dafydd</placeName>. The twin brother of
                        <placeName ref="pl3249">Carnedd Llewelyn</placeName>.</p>
                <p>[<del>xxxxx</del>] </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="122"/>
                <fw>p.122</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The <placeName ref="pl3251">Trefaen</placeName>. A scalloped mountain, perhaps
                    taking its name from that circumstance.</p>
                <p>The two Glyders, <placeName ref="pl3154">Vawr</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl3232">Bach</placeName></p>
                <p>The two Lleders, <placeName ref="pl3253">Vawr</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl3254">Bach</placeName></p>
                <p>[<del>xxxxx</del>]</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName></p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl3126">Moel Elian</placeName></p>
                <p>[<del>xxxx</del>]</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl3164">Mynydd Vawr</placeName>
                </p>
                <p>The <placeName ref="pl1866">Cader</placeName>, or Chair. A long, flat, huge
                    mountain.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl3255">Cilgwyn</placeName></p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl3246">Yr Eifl</placeName> mountains; or, as we call them,
                        <placeName ref="pl3246">The Rivals</placeName></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At first my view was obstructed by clouds, but they travelled by degrees down the
                    sides of the mountains, and lay on the vales, like whipped syllabub. <placeName ref="pl3249">Carnedd Llywelyn</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName> alone were capped, but their caps were like thin
                    muslin, through which the shape of the head was seen. After we had crossed
                        <placeName ref="pl1563">Bangor Ferry</placeName>, <hi rend="underline">The
                        glimmering landscape faded on the sight</hi>,<note type="editorial">From the
                        second stanza of Thomas Gray’s ‘Elegy Written in a Country Churchyard’
                        (1751): see <ref type="http" target="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=elcc">here.</ref></note> and we rode to <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName> by the light of a charming moon. That I was
                    fatigued, as usual, or more than usual, you will not wonder at, when you are
                    told that my day’s journey was thirty three miles; out of which I had walked
                    full ten. A more extraordinary performance, as, at home, I have no pedestrian
                    atcheivements to boast. But I was literally run away with, by old castles and
                    cist faens.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> Letter 27 </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p style="right">
                    <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel Cerig</placeName>, Sept 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1800.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>My Dear Brother,</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We intended to have returned home by the new road to <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan
                        y Bwlch</placeName>, and from thence to <placeName ref="pl1517">Dolgelleu</placeName>, a part of the country we had never seen; but a paper
                    had been put into our hands at <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName>,
                    containing a printed plan and description of a new and shorter road from
                        <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName> to</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="123"/>
                <fw>p.123</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl3119">Capel Voelas</placeName>, which would leave out
                        <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>.<note type="editorial">For the new road and the
                        coaching inn at Capel Curig, built by Lord Penrhyn (1737-1808), see accounts
                        collected by Michael Freeman, <ref type="http" target="https://sublimewales.wordpress.com/practicalities/accommodation/inns/capel-curig-inn/">here.</ref>
                    </note> I had some fear of an unfinished road; and especially of one part of it
                    which was said to climb a rock two hundred feet above a river and to be without
                    a fence: but I was assured it was every where passable for horses. The names of
                        <placeName ref="pl1529">Nant Ffrancon</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel Cerig</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl2851">Rhaiader y
                        Wenol</placeName>, and <placeName ref="pl3143">Pont y Pair</placeName>, were
                    music to my ears. I had been taught by <persName ref="pe0232">Pennant</persName>
                    to consider them as classic ground and <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">we</hi> determined to visit them. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Possibly you may wonder at the word <hi rend="underline">I;</hi> and think that I
                    should say <hi rend="underline">we</hi>, if not <hi rend="underline">he</hi>:
                    knowing I have a companion whose wish ought to go before my own. If I were to
                    speak in common terms, I should say, my <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">father’s</hi> only wish is to oblige me. But he has no
                    wish. It is an innate principle of his mind, which operates invariably, before
                    he has time to form a wish. In return, I hope I have another innate principle,
                    which would teach me, without reflection, to avoid every thing that might be
                    really disagreeable to him. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We breakfasted in a circular room at the <placeName ref="pl3151">Penrhyn
                        Arms</placeName>, an inn erected by <persName ref="pe1198">Lord
                        Penrhyn</persName>, beyond <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName>.
                    Perhaps the view from its windows may surpass that of any room in <placeName ref="pl0777">Great Britain</placeName>.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The peasants of the eastern part of <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName>
                    call <placeName ref="pl1529">Nant Ffrancon</placeName>, <hi rend="underline">Cegin y Cythraul</hi>, the Kitchen of the Devil; for there, they say, he
                    brews the storms. We had some reason to believe his cauldron was boiling now, as
                    a terrible steam hovered over <placeName ref="pl1529">Nant Ffrancon</placeName>.
                    However that might prove, I rejoiced at the opportunity of seeing the old
                    gentleman’s kitchen; having hitherto only seen his cooks: but the mist dispersed
                    and he put off his brewing, in our favour.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At <placeName ref="pl3149">Llandegai</placeName> we turned to the right and
                    entered the grand portal of the mountains. We rode along the cultivated side of
                    a broad vale, with the river <placeName ref="pl2415">Ogwen</placeName> roaring
                    over its stoney bed at the bottom. The road was wide, and the carts, and even
                    waggons, that were perpetually moving along it gave it the appearance of a
                    turnpike road in England. At five miles from Llande</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="124"/>
                <fw>p.124</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>gai we came to the slate quarries, where the vale contracts, but the dreary
                    aspect of the mountains is animated by a multitude of little fanciful white
                    cottages, built by <persName ref="pe1198">Lord Penrhyn</persName> for his
                    workmen. It were to be wished his Lordship had seen the cottages erected by Lord
                    Scarsdale at <placeName ref="pl1544">Kedleston</placeName>.<note type="editorial">Nathaniel Curzon, Lord Scarsdale inherited the estate at
                        Kedleston and built a new house and developed the grounds in 1759,
                        relocating the public highway and the entire village in the process. </note>
                    Local circumstances would have compelled him to substitute slates for their neat
                    thatch; but their chaste simplicity might have served him for a model. <persName ref="pe1198">Lord Penrhyn</persName> employs many hundred workmen in these
                    quarries, and we were informed that he cleared last year £8,000 by their
                        labours.*<note type="authorial"> *I have since been told that in 1805 Lord
                        Penrhyn cleared £20,000.</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>On a green bank above a river, stands an elegant cottage called <placeName ref="pl1579">Ogwen Bank</placeName>, built by <persName ref="pe2195">Lady
                        Penrhyn</persName>, and surrounded by a flower garden; a thing utterly
                    unknown before, in these desart wilds. Her ladyship frequently brings cold
                    provisions, and dines in this retreat.<note type="editorial">This paragraph has
                        been inserted on a separate page. For Lady Penrhyn’s ferme ornée see Bettina
                        Harden, <hi rend="italic">The Most Glorious Prospect: Garden Visiting in
                            Wales 1639-1900</hi> (Graffeg: Llangennech) 140-43.</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Beyond the slate quarries carts are seen no more. <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">Even travellers disappear</hi>. The road and the country
                    were our own. Here [<del>xxxx</del>] begins [<del>xxxx</del>] a vale of starved
                    meadows, about three miles in length, and half a mile in breadth. The north west
                    end, at which we entered, is open to the sea and the Isle of <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName>; the upper end is closed by a wall of very
                    high rocky ground, called the <placeName ref="pl3256">Benglog</placeName>, and
                    behind that the <placeName ref="pl3251">Trefaen</placeName>, a lofty mountain,
                    whose summit is a round, indented rock. Between these two is a horrid chasm
                    called <placeName ref="pl3257">Cwm Idwal</placeName> with a lake in its bottom.
                    The boundary of <placeName ref="pl1529">Nant Ffrancon</placeName> on the left,
                    is the vast <placeName ref="pl3250">Carnedd Dafydd</placeName>, the base of
                    which fills the whole side. On the right we rode over the foot of a mountain,
                    rent and torn by some tremendous flood. Huge broken rocks lay on the right of
                    the road; and, on the left, torrents of stones that had rolled over it..</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The only exit from the upper end of <placeName ref="pl1529">Nant
                        Ffrancon</placeName> was, in <persName ref="pe0232">Pennant</persName>’s
                    time, by a road up the <placeName ref="pl3256">Benglog</placeName>, which he
                    calls “the most dreadful horsepath in Wales”.<note type="editorial">‘The way
                        from that place into the valley, or rather chasm, of Nant Frankon, is called
                        The Ben-Glog, the most dreadful horsepath in Wales, worked in the rudest
                        manner, into steps, for a great length’. <hi rend="italic">Tour in
                            Wales</hi>, II, (1784) 161.</note> The road now keeps ascending up the
                    side of the mountain on the right, till it reaches the level of the <placeName ref="pl3256">Benglog</placeName>, on which it crosses the head of the vale,
                    and is by no means difficult. It then turns to the right, and burst upon
                        <placeName ref="pl3148">Ogwen Pool</placeName>.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="125"/>
                <fw>p.125</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>On the <placeName ref="pl3256">Benglog</placeName> I saw the path which led to
                        <placeName ref="pl3257">Cwm Idwal</placeName>. It was such as I should not
                    dare to climb.<note type="editorial">For the pioneering climb of this chasm and
                        the surrounding peaks by Peter Bailey Williams and William Bingley see Simon
                        Bainbridge, <hi rend="italic">Mountaineering and British Romanticism: The
                            Literary Cultures of Climbing 1770-1836</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University
                        Press, 2020) 59-63. </note> The appearance of this black hollow is terrible.
                    It must be surrounded by walls of rock; and that on the side of the <placeName ref="pl3251">Trefaen</placeName> must be lofty and perpendicular. The river
                        <placeName ref="pl3258">Idwal</placeName> tumbles out of the lake, and joins
                    the <placeName ref="pl2415">Ogwen</placeName> below.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We conjectured <placeName ref="pl3148">Llyn Ogwen</placeName> to be two hundred
                    feet higher than the river, below the <placeName ref="pl3256">Benglog</placeName>; about a mile and a half in length, including its
                    curvature (for in one place it becomes narrow, and then opens again); and half a
                    mile in breadth, in the widest part. It is skirted by mountains down to the
                    water’s edge; mountains which suffered no sensible diminution of their height,
                    from the two hundred feet we had ascended. As the side of the stupendous
                        <placeName ref="pl3250">Carnedd Dafydd</placeName> had formed the left
                    boundary of <placeName ref="pl1529">Nant Ffrancon</placeName>, so its end formed
                    the left boundary of the lake. [<del>xxxxx</del>]. Our road was cut in the
                    rocks, under the <placeName ref="pl3251">Trefaen</placeName>, on the margin of
                    the water.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We travelled four or five miles along <placeName ref="pl3256">Nant y
                        Benglog</placeName>, the elevated valley which succeeds <placeName ref="pl3148">Ogwen Pool</placeName>; first up a river that discharges itself
                    into it, till it disappeared among the bogs; and then overtaking another,
                    running in the opposite direction. The country was barren and the ground was
                    peat. We had a most alarming proof of its unsoundness. In opening a gate, my
                    father’s horse slipped off the causeway on his hind legs, sunk up to his
                    haunches; and could not extricate himself till his rider had jumped from his
                    back.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>This country, though dismal, is not absolutely uninhabitable. We saw, now and
                    then, a cottage, with a small stack of hay, and numbers of black cattle were
                    grazing in different spots on the sides of the mountains. Our vale terminated in
                    the descent to <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel Cerig</placeName>, situated in the
                    lower vale of <placeName ref="pl3193">Dŷffryn Mŷmbyr</placeName>, which runs
                    across it.<note type="editorial">For an evocative print of this landscape see:
                            <ref type="http" target="https://www.peoplescollection.wales/items/19884">here.</ref></note> This descent was formerly a bwlch, but our road, which
                    from <placeName ref="pl3149">Llandegai</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel Cerig</placeName>, a distance</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="126"/>
                <fw>p.126</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>of fifteen miles, is a new one, made solely at the expence of <persName ref="pe1198">Lord Penrhyn</persName>, wound down it with ease. Here we were
                    charmed with the sight of wood.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The <placeName ref="pl1891">inn</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel
                        Cerig</placeName> is lately erected by <persName ref="pe1198">Lord
                        Penrhyn</persName>, and is occupied by two of his former servants; happily
                    for their business, English and Welsh. It smells a little of the embattled
                    cottages, but one is thankful for good accommodations in so remote a place.
                    Before it was built, sorry<hi rend="underline"> cwrw</hi>, milk, butter and
                    oaten bread was all that money could purchase, at a hut called a public house,
                    in <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel Cerig</placeName>.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The <placeName ref="pl3259">chapel</placeName>, from which the place takes its
                    name (Chapel of the Rock) is said to be the oldest in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>; it is certainly, one of the poorest, and would any where
                    else be mistaken for a barn.<note type="editorial">This is now known as the
                        church of St Julitta. See <ref type="http" target="http://www.stjulittas.org/english/about.html#History">here.</ref></note>
                    <persName ref="pe1198">Lord Penrhyn</persName> means to build another; but I am
                    pleased to hear he has so much reverence for antiquity, that he will not destroy
                    this.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><persName ref="pe1198">Lord Penrhyn</persName> is the <persName ref="pe0941">Sir
                        Watkin</persName> of the country. The domain of a great <sic>chieftan</sic>,
                    formerly divided among his family, is again united in him, by his marriage to
                        <persName ref="pe2195">Lady Penrhyn</persName>.<note type="editorial">Richard Pennant inherited property through his marriage to Ann Susanna
                        Warburton (1745-1816); his father John Pennant, a Liverpool merchant, had
                        been General Hugh Warburton’s business partner.</note> We have trodden on no
                    ground but his, from <placeName ref="pl0799">Bangor</placeName>. And it extends
                    two miles further up <placeName ref="pl3193">Dŷffryn Mŷmbyr</placeName>, where a
                    small river divides it from the lands of <persName ref="pe0944">Mr
                        Smith</persName>. <persName ref="pe1198">Lord Penrhyn</persName> is a proof
                    of Pope’s assertion, that</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>True self love, and social are the same <note type="editorial">Alexander Pope,
                            <hi rend="italic">Essay on Man</hi> (1733): ‘That reason, passion,
                        answer one great aim / That true self-love and social are the same /
                        Self-love forsook the path it once pursu’d / And found the private in the
                        public good.’</note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>He has made a port on the <placeName ref="pl1564">Menai</placeName>, at the mouth
                    of the <placeName ref="pl2415">Ogwen</placeName>, to carry off the productions
                    of his estate, and he is improving his possessions, and his country, at the same
                    time by farming, fishing, mining, digging quarries, making roads, and every
                    other method that wisdom can suggest, and wealth can execute. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p/>
                <p> Letter 28 </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p style="right">
                    <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel Cerig</placeName>, Sept 19, 1800 </p>
                <p>My Dear Brother,</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>I have fancied <placeName ref="pl1183">Snowdonia</placeName> a city not made with </p>
                <p/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">[Map inserted here]</hi>
                </p>
                <pb n="127"/>
                <fw>p.127</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>hands, whose Builder and Maker is God.<note type="editorial">‘an house not made
                        with hands, eternal in the heavens’ (<hi rend="italic">2 Corinthians</hi>
                        5:1); Hutton’s map is reproduced <ref type="http" target="https://blog.library.wales/lovemaps-mary-ann-constantine-4">here.</ref></note> I have bounded my fancied city by the district of
                    Arvon; an imaginary line drawn from <placeName ref="pl3246">the
                        Rivals</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1525">Pont Aber Glaslyn</placeName>;
                    the vale beginning at <placeName ref="pl1525">Pont Aber Glaslyn</placeName>, and
                    ending at <placeName ref="pl3143">Pont y Pair</placeName>, and the Vale of
                        <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName>, from <placeName ref="pl3143">Pont
                        y Pair</placeName> to the sea.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Arvon, in front of the city, and open to the <placeName ref="pl1564">Straits of
                        Menai</placeName>, I have called the Grand Parade. This, from <placeName ref="pl1338">Penmaen Mawr</placeName> at one end, to <placeName ref="pl3246">the Rivals</placeName> at the other, is thirty three miles in length.</p>
                <p>Parallel with the Parade, and at the distance of from eight to twelve miles
                    behind it, runs a street which divides the buildings <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">of <placeName ref="pl1183">Snowdonia</placeName></hi>
                    from those of <placeName ref="pl1235">Merionethshire</placeName>. This, from
                        <placeName ref="">Pont Aber Glaslyn</placeName>, at one extremity, to
                        <placeName ref="pl3143">Pont y Pair</placeName> at the other, is about
                    twenty four miles in length. But, as a continuation of the same street in
                        <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> is known by several names, of
                    Ludgate Hill, Fleet Street and the Strand, so this is distinguished by the
                    different appellations of <placeName ref="pl2901">Nant Gwynan</placeName>,
                        <placeName ref="pl3193">Dŷffryn Mŷmbyr</placeName>, and Glyn Llugwy. Nant,
                    correctly speaking, signifies vale, and dŷffryn a wider, and glyn a narrower
                    vale.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>The interior of my city is crossed, at right angles, by three grand avenues,
                    which communicate both with the Parade and the long street behind it. These are
                    the passes of Cwellyn, <placeName ref="pl3135">Llanberis</placeName> and
                        <placeName ref="pl1529">Nant Ffrancon</placeName>. The three cross streets
                    are each so narrow. in one part, as to be wholly filled </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="128"/>
                <fw>p.128</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>by a lake. These are the pools of <placeName ref="pl1526">Cwellyn</placeName>,
                    Llanberis and <placeName ref="pl3148">Ogwen</placeName>. [<del>xxxxx</del>]</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>, the magnificent temple of the city,
                    touches three streets; the long one, at <placeName ref="pl2901">Nant
                        Gwynan</placeName>; and two of the cross ones, at <placeName ref="pl1526">Cwellyn pool</placeName>, and the upper lake of Llanberis.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>From the back of <placeName ref="pl1527">Llanberis</placeName> the Almighty
                    Architect seems to have judged it proper to strengthen his stupendous works. As
                    if a vale of twenty four miles in length, bordered by such powerful neighbours,
                    might stand in need of some support, he has run out a bulwark in the middle
                    which connects both sides. This divides <placeName ref="pl2901">Nant
                        Gwynan</placeName> from <placeName ref="pl3193">Dŷffryn Mŷmbyr</placeName>,
                    and from this the vales and waters descend opposite ways.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Besides these principal streets is the collateral one of <placeName ref="pl3168">Nant Nanlle</placeName>, which commences, like the other cross streets, at
                    Arfon but ends at the foot of <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>. There
                    is also a [<del>xxxx</del>] street parallel with <placeName ref="pl2901">Nant
                        Gwynan</placeName>, and behind it, called the vale of <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y Bwlch</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1523">Festiniog</placeName>. The space between this and <placeName ref="pl2901">Nant Gwynan</placeName> includes great mountains, such as <placeName ref="pl3262">Moel Siabod</placeName> and the two Moel Wynns; but I do not
                    think it properly belongs to <placeName ref="pl1183">Snowdonia</placeName>.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Farther this deponent sayeth not. I believe here are no more grand divisions
                    among the mountains, and whoso travels other roads must get over them.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">[unnumbered half-page]</hi>
                </p>
                <p>I have annexed a sketch of <placeName ref="pl1183">Snowdonia</placeName>, from
                    Evans’s map,<note type="editorial">For John Evans’ maps of north Wales, see <ref type="http" target="https://blog.library.wales/lovemaps-mary-ann-constantine-2/">here.</ref></note> which will explain my ideas better than all the
                    words I could use.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>For the first time in my life I had now turned the mountains.<note type="editorial">Not clear: possibly ‘toured’?</note> At <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel Cerig</placeName> I found myself in the long street which
                    runs at the back of <placeName ref="pl1183">Snowdonia</placeName>. To remain in
                    the house was impossible. I planted myself on a small wooden bridge between the
                    two upper and the lowest lakes of <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel
                        Cerig</placeName>. [<del>xxxxx</del>]. <placeName ref="pl3193">Dŷffryn
                        Mŷmbyr</placeName>
                    <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">was</hi> before <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">me</hi>, terminated by the mortify <hi rend="subscript">^</hi><hi rend="superscript">ing</hi> outwork that shut me out of
                        <placeName ref="pl2901">Nant Gwynan</placeName>. On my right were the
                    Glyders, the black chasm of Llanberis, and <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName>; on my left rose the crooked mountain <placeName ref="pl3262">Moel Siabod</placeName>. The summit of this last seems easy of
                    access; and, if I could scale mountains, it should be my first. From its top a
                    great part of the city I have been describing; a city beyond the work of mortal
                    hands, and almost beyond the reach of human imagination, would strike the eye at
                    once. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Verso of inserted half page</hi>] </p>
                <p>The scenery around me was beautiful, but unassuming, and formed a happy contrast
                    to the sublimity of the more distant objects. The small lakes of <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel Cerig</placeName>; a few green meadows intermingled with
                    wood; the chapel and the inn; were all that hills and mountains left visible. My
                    taste would have led me to consider the inn as an intruder in such a prospect,
                    had I not reflected that without the comforts it afforded I could never have
                    visited the spot. <persName ref="pe0232">Pennant</persName>’s view of <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName> is taken from a rising ground, about a
                    quarter of a mile below.<note type="editorial">Peter Bishop discusses Moses
                        Griffith’s picture ‘The Summit of Snowdon from Capel Cerig’ from Pennant’s
                            <hi rend="italic">Journey to Snowdon</hi> (1781), as an early example of
                        a much-painted view: see <ref type="http" target="https://www.cnp.org.uk/blog/snowdon-capel-curig-classical-viewpoint">here.</ref></note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>If you will allow the trifling transition from <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName> to a fungus. I shall conclude my account of <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel Cerig</placeName> by informing you that I never saw so
                    many mushrooms, or so fine <del>growing</del> as at this place, and that we
                    carried the sauce to our chickens back with us to the inn. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="129"/>
                <fw>p.129</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>[<del>xxxxxx</del>]</p>
                <p>As our next stage, to <placeName ref="pl1576">Cernioge</placeName>, was sixteen
                    miles and a half, and as the first five, to <placeName ref="pl3132">Bettws y
                        Coed</placeName> (the Bead house of the Wood) was the part ^ of the road not
                    yet completed, I determined to take a guide, not only to point out the way, but
                    to shew us <placeName ref="pl2851">Rhaiader y Wenol</placeName>, and <placeName ref="pl3143">Pont y Pair</placeName>, and render us any service we might
                    stand in need of. I requested the master of the house to provide one. “Yes
                    Ma’am, I shall”. I repeatedly asked, “Have you spoken to the guide?” “No Ma’am,
                    but you may depend upon him”. This morning came, and I found our innkeeper, who
                    promises all things, and does as few as he can, had engaged no guide. An
                    Englishman in the kitchen, who was walking our road, was extremely anxious to
                    conduct us. Though he could walk much faster than we travelled, he would go our
                    pace. I rejected his offer, for two reasons; the one I did not chuse to accept
                    of services we were not to pay for; the other, that he was a stranger to the
                    road, as well as ourselves. It is true he was sure he could find it, which we
                    were not. Finding he could not fasten himself upon us, with all his rhetoric, he
                    brandished his cudgel, and set off at a great rate. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At length our innkeeper has given us his hostler as our guide to <placeName ref="pl3132">Bettws</placeName>. He knows no English; but he knows the
                    country, and can open a gate, or lead a horse.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> Letter 29 </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p style="right">
                    <placeName ref="pl0740">Shrewsbury</placeName>, Sept 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 1800</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>My Dear Brother, </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>On leaving the inn at <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel Cerig</placeName>, we passed
                    the humble chapel, interesting as a picture of the poverty and simplicity of
                    ancient days. We then crossed the river Llugwy, which comes down from the
                    mountains on the left, and having received the water of the Lake of Ca</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="130"/>
                <fw>p.130</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>pel Cerig, runs down to the <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName>, and gives
                    its name to the glen through which it passes. Our road was old Welsh: a lane,
                    between two hedges, just wide enough to admit a pair of wheels; though seldom
                    called upon to do it; sometimes of shivery gravel, sometimes paved with huge
                    stones; and, not unfrequently, native rock. But the scenery was inexpressibly
                    grand. The river hemmed in by lofty mountains, and rolling among gigantic rocks;
                    its banks, not watery meadows, but the cultivated base of mountains, besprinkled
                    with wood, and animated with scattered dwellings. How charming after the
                    houseless, leafless, <placeName ref="pl3256">Nant y Benglog</placeName> and
                        <placeName ref="pl3193">Dŷffryn Mŷmbyr</placeName>!</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>About a mile brought us to a narrow pass, where the river and the road fill the
                    vale. Even they have some difficulty to get along; for enormous rocks endeavour
                    to stop the water, and the road lies on its brink. At the end of this pass
                    stands the rock of two hundred feet. Future travellers will avoid it, as a
                    bridge is already built, and the road is to run along a meadow on the opposite
                    side. We had to get over it; but as I always chuse to walk over rocks that are
                    two hundred feet above rivers, I was not terrified. It is said a gig and a
                    curricle have once passed this way; it may be possible, the horses running
                    tandem. But I think they would not persuade other gigs and curricles to
                    follow.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>After we had descended our rock, the river assumed a more placid form. At two
                    miles from <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel Cerig</placeName>, we forded it, and
                    going up a steep hill, were proceeding towards <placeName ref="pl3169">Dolwyddelan</placeName>, when our guide opened a gate on the left, and we
                    turned suddenly back to the water’s edge, and travelled more than a mile on the
                    new road.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Our landscapes yesterday were magnificent, but savage: to-day they were more
                    beautiful and picturesque. We had now a narrow vale</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="131"/>
                <fw>p.131</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>with limits less grand, but we had verdant fields <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">and</hi> varied woods, with rocks starting up, sometimes
                    as big as a house.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Goats have not been frequently seen in our journeying in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>. In Glyn Llugwy we met one family – the father and mother
                    chained together with a cord of rushes – No bad emblem of matrimony – Though I
                    believe the restraint in the present instance, was not so much intended to
                    prevent their running away from each other, as their running away together.
                    Their offspring needed no other tie than filial affection.<note type="editorial">For tourists’ interest in the iconic Welsh mountain goats see Michael
                        Freeman, <ref type="http" target="https://sublimewales.wordpress.com/what-they-wrote-about/perceptions-of-wales/goats/">here.</ref></note></p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At three miles from <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel Cerig</placeName> the sound of
                    falling water gave notice that we were in the neighbourhood of <placeName ref="pl2851">Rhaiader y Wenol</placeName>; and our guide taking us down to a
                    field, to the river side, I could several views of this celebrated waterfall. I
                    saw it rushing down stupendous clefts of solid rock, and dashing round immense
                    stones; every where adorned with wood; though, in many places, it was difficult
                    to conceive how wood could grow: but, to have seen it in perfection, I should
                    have been at the bottom; a descent to which neither my strength nor my nerves
                    was equal.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>When our new road deserted us, we ascended a hill, covered with wood, almost
                    intirely birch. From the top of this, a steep descent of nearly a mile, and a
                    causeway on the river’s brink, of half a mile, brought us to <placeName ref="pl3132">Bettws y Coed</placeName>; one of the few Coeds that still
                    deserve the name; for it is still surrounded by wood. <placeName ref="pl3262">Moel Siabod</placeName> terminated the view behind us all the way, soaring
                    above every winding of the vale, and even at <placeName ref="pl3132">Bettws</placeName>, seeming near.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At <placeName ref="pl3132">Bettws</placeName> is <placeName ref="pl3143">Pont y
                        Pair</placeName>, a bridge of five arches, thrown from rock to rock over the
                    Llugwy; and every pier, if I right <hi rend="superscript">-ly remember</hi> is
                    the native rock of the torrent. It is reckoned one of the wonders of <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>. [<del>xxxxx</del>] It appeared to me
                    romantic, but not so striking as <placeName ref="pl1525">Pont Aber
                        Glaslyn</placeName>, at the other</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="132"/>
                <fw>p.132</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>end of these continued vales; or even as <placeName ref="pl2829">Pont y
                        Glyn</placeName>. Here, the mountains round off to the right and left, and
                    the river and glen of the Llugwy end in those of the <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName>, which run across. We were now only three miles above
                        <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>. The road over <placeName ref="pl3143">Pont y Pair</placeName> on the left, leads to that place. The
                    character of Nant Conwy changes here. From hence to the spot where it finishes
                    in the ocean, it presents all the comforts of civil life; society, that greatest
                    of all, included. From hence till it ends in the moorish mountains where the
                    river has its source, it is wild and solitary.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Arrived at the banks of the <placeName ref="pl2384">Conwy</placeName>, from
                    whence we had been told the road was open for carriages, and there was no losing
                    our way, we dismissed our guide. The man had been very serviceable, and very
                    civil; for civility needs not words to make itself understood: the best desire
                    to oblige is shewn by actions. Our gratitude at parting was also displayed in a
                    manner too unequivocal to be mistaken.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>We turned to the right up the <placeName ref="pl2384">Conwy</placeName>; our road
                    being on the <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">brink of</hi> its waters, and from three to ten feet
                    above them. At about a mile and a half we came to<placeName ref="pl3264"> Pont
                        yr <sic>Lleder</sic></placeName>, a bridge over the river <placeName ref="pl3263">Lleder</placeName>, which comes down through an opening in the
                    mountains on the right, and joins the <placeName ref="pl2384">Conwy</placeName>.
                    The <placeName ref="pl2384">Conwy</placeName> had been, till now, a sullen,
                    silent stream; I dare say, very deep. Just before <placeName ref="pl3264">Pont
                        yr Lleder</placeName>, we lost it, behind some rocks; and moment after, saw
                    a great chasm, down which it poured. We began a steep ascent, which soon became
                    a precipice, high above the rover; and never shall I forget, though I can ill
                    describe, the scenes which then presented themselves to my view! I was come,
                    without expecting it, to the celebrated falls of the <placeName ref="pl2384">Conwy</placeName>! I had heard, in a confused manner, at <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>, of grand falls, up the river, and of
                    adventurous knights, and fortunate la-</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="133"/>
                <fw>p.133</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>dies, who had visited them from thence; but I never hoped to see them myself, and
                    still less imagined they lay in my way.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Our steep ascent continued more than a mile, the river ascending with us, though
                    always far below. The glen was no more than its bed; for our road was cut in
                    rocks that were immediately above it; and rocks rose on the other side,
                    inaccessible even to a mountain goat. The road was good, and wide enough for a
                    carriage; though, as it is without a fence towards the precipice, I should
                    shudder to see a carriage roll along it. I saw no regular water-fall; but a
                    succession of broken falls, for more than a mile. A river rushing down a
                    tremendous fissure in the rocks, torn and split into a thousand pieces, by
                    opposing masses of singular shapes, and foaming, and struggling, and fight<hi rend="subscript">^</hi><hi rend="superscript">ing</hi> its way to the
                    bottom! </p>
                <p>Having gained the summit of the rock, we came to a rustic mill, from whence we
                    saw the convulsions of the <placeName ref="pl2384">Conwy</placeName>, in all
                    their grandeur. Had we pursued the same road, we should still have gone up the
                    river, and about two miles farther should have reached <placeName ref="pl2852">Penmachno</placeName>; and leaving Llyn <sic>Conway</sic> among moorish and
                    barren mountains on the left, in nine or ten miles more, it would have carried
                    us to <placeName ref="pl1523">Festiniog</placeName>. But, about three miles from
                        <placeName ref="pl3132">Bettws y Coed</placeName>, we turned suddenly to the
                    left, crossed the <placeName ref="pl2384">Conwy</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl3265">Pont Rhyd Llanfair</placeName>; quitted <placeName ref="pl1234">Caernarvonshire</placeName>, and its magnificent scenery, and exchanged
                    lofty mountains, rapid rivers, and romantic glens, for an insipid sameness,
                    bleak hills, and a bad road.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Five miles and a half of wearisome hills, and sterile commons, brought us into
                    the high way from <placeName ref="pl0740">Shrewsbury</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1018">Holyhead</placeName>, a mile short of <placeName ref="pl3119">Capel
                        Voelas</placeName>, and three of <placeName ref="pl1576">Cernioge</placeName>. Twice </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="134"/>
                <fw>p.134</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>had I passed these dreary heights before, in my way from <placeName ref="pl1576">Cernioge</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>, and
                    both times in heavy rain. I had always an idea that, if the clouds had not
                    interposed, I should have seen the towering mountains of <placeName ref="pl1183">Snowdonia</placeName>: but I had no conception they were so near, or
                    afforded so glorious a sight. I now beheld them, piled one upon another, in all
                    their various forms [<del>xxxx</del>] <placeName ref="pl2862">Snowdon</placeName> alone was capped. I cannot express to you my feelings,
                    while my eyes rested on them, as long as a glimpse remained; believing, as I
                    still believe, that I shall see them no more!</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Such is the road from <placeName ref="pl3149">Llandegai</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl3119">Capel Voelas</placeName>; and such the road that is to
                    supercede the present route of the mailcoach from <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1018">Holyhead</placeName>.<note type="editorial">On Lord Penrhyn’s road from Llandegai through the mountains
                        see Richard Moore-Colyer, <hi rend="italic">Roads and Trackways of
                            Wales</hi> (2nd ed. Ashbourne: Landmark, 2001) 154-60.</note> When I
                    first heard of it, I longed to see the sublime mountain scenes it would unfold;
                    but I believed it would be impracticable in bad weather; and that storms, in the
                    defiles of such mountains, would even overset a coach.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>In this opinion I was confirmed by the people of the towns of <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName>, whose towns it will almost annihilate; but I no longer
                    apprehend this danger at any time. The paper given us at <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName> was fabricated by persons interested in the success
                    of the new road, and somewhat shortened the distance. In those parts stated to
                    be already open for carriages, carriages may, indeed, pass; but one contingency
                    is frequently forgotten to be provided for – how they may pass one another. Much
                    remains to be done, before it can be made a post road; but it stands in no need
                    of misrepresentation to recommend it; and will certainly be, one day, the high
                    road through North <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>.*<note type="authorial"> [------------line in darker ink, and then inserted:] The
                        mail coach to Holyhead travelled this way, for the first time, Sept
                        1808</note> Other branches are proposed to be made from it which will
                    disclose the now hidden beauties of Nant Beris and <placeName ref="pl2901">Nant
                        Gwynan</placeName>. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="135"/>
                <fw>p.135</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Between <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> and Chirk, our <hi rend="superscript">English-</hi>man of <placeName ref="pl1528">Capel <hi rend="subscript">^</hi><hi rend="superscript">Cerig</hi></placeName>,
                    who was so desirous of shewing us the way to <placeName ref="pl1576">Cernioge</placeName>, passed us on the roof of the stage coach. Hey! called
                    out my father [<del>xxxx</del>]. I thought you were to have been far before us!
                    Aye, cried he, but I turned to the left, and got to <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName>.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Three miles short of <placeName ref="pl1260">Oswestry</placeName>, we took the
                    road to the village of <placeName ref="pl3266">Whittington</placeName>. We
                    enquired at the turnpike of there was any inn there, likely to accommodate us
                    and our horses. The woman said “Yes, there’s two, and they both sell every
                    thing, but that by the church is best”. I asked what was the sign? She hesitated
                    a moment and then called out, “Sall, what is the sign of the <placeName ref="pl3267">Boot Inn</placeName>?”, but recollecting herself, “Oh dear”,
                    said she. “I believe it’s the Boot.” With this information we proceeded and
                    found <placeName ref="pl3266">Whittington</placeName> a very pleasant village,
                    ornamented with fine trees, and that the <placeName ref="pl3267">Boot</placeName> actually sold everything – we wanted.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>At <placeName ref="pl3266">Whittington</placeName> are some round towers
                    remaining of an old castle, and a manor house adjoining, of the days of
                        <persName ref="pe1091">Queen Elizabeth</persName>.<note type="editorial">For
                        a lovely image of the castle by Moses Griffith, see <ref type="http" target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Whittington_Castle#/media/File:Whitington_Castle.jpg">here.</ref></note> The place appeared to me so likely to be the resort
                    of spectres, that I could not forbear asking the woman who shewed it, if it were
                    not haunted. She assured me, with great earnestness, that it was; and told
                    several stories to confirm it. She said one old woman lived in it, but she did
                    not care for spirits. I wondered the creators of the ghosts had not dubbed this
                        <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">singular</hi> old woman a witch. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Our mode of travelling places us in rather equivocal light at inns. Without the
                    sound of wheels to announce us, and often without even the trampling of horses’
                    feet (for we frequently chuse to walk through a paved town) <hi rend="underline">we come in such a questionable shape that they will not speak to
                        us</hi>.<note type="editorial">Hamlet to the ghost of his father: ‘Thou
                        comest in such a questionable shape / That I will speak to thee’. <hi rend="italic">Hamlet</hi>, Act 1, iv. On some innkeepers’ lack of
                        enthusiasm for pedestrian customers see Michael Freeman <ref type="http" target="                             https://sublimewales.wordpress.com/practicalities/travel/pedestrian/">here.</ref></note> An instance of this has occurred at the place where
                    we now are at <placeName ref="pl0740"><hi rend="superscript">Shrewsbury</hi></placeName> which was recommended to us as a comfortable
                    second rate inn. We</p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="138"/>
                <fw>p.138</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>entered the house. No one came. We advanced to the bar, where the mistress was
                    sitting, and asked her if we could have a room with a fire, supper, and beds.
                    She surveyed us from head to foot. “Why <hi rend="underline">yes</hi>, said she,
                    you may have a room and I will order a fire in it”. I told her my cloaths were
                    wet. She gave me permission to stand by her bar fire, till the other was ready,
                    and then left us to our own reflections, which were not much in her favour. We
                    saw fire carried along the passage; and, having allowed it a reasonable time to
                    burn, we followed it; but it was as cold as its mistress; a few great black
                    pieces of coal, that disdained to burn. I rang the bell and told the girl who
                    entered that if we gave too much trouble, we would remove to the <placeName ref="pl1610">Lion</placeName>, where we had been accustomed to go. She then
                    bustled about got us a cheer<hi rend="superscript">ful</hi> fire, and brought in
                    a couple of candles. This lighted up my good humour: but a moment after, she
                    came in again, took up one of the candles, hunted round the room for something
                    she could not find; and at last, fairly marched off with it. I rang the bell a
                    second time. “Young woman”, said I “you are an excellent servant. No girl could
                    have better obeyed her mistress’s orders, or taken our candle with more
                    dexterity. If your mistress has any occasion for the other, I beg you will take
                    that too, for we asked only for fire.” Whether this reproof had its effect; or
                    whether they perceived, by this time, that our man’s livery and laced hat were
                    of the party, and that our horses were at supper in the stable, I know not; but
                    the master brought in our first <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">dish</hi> and behaved with a degree of civility that
                    would have recommended his house to us; if it had been exercised a little
                    earlier. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Before I take my leave of travelling in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>, I will observe, that the more I <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">have</hi> seen of the country, the more I <hi rend="subscript">^</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">have</hi> had to admire; and that </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="137"/>
                <fw>p.137</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>no tourist, except <persName ref="pe0232">Pennant</persName>, has seen <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>.<note type="editorial">Much of this final
                        section (with its interesting overlap between tourist and military routes in
                        the years of the Irish Rebellion) appears in a letter written in December
                        1799 to Hutton’s close friend Mrs André. The letter finishes a little less
                        graciously: ‘The common people do not understand English, and they know
                        nothing’. Catherine Hutton Beale, <hi rend="italic">Reminiscences of a Gentlewoman of the Last
                        Century: Letters of Catherine Hutton</hi> (Birmingham, 1891) 131-32. </note> To
                    travel post in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName> is to fly. The life of
                    a post horse is every where miserable, here, if I may be allowed the expression,
                    it is certain death. The mistress of the inn at <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName> who had seen our horses one, [<del>xxx</del>] three
                    and four years before, looked at them and shook her head. “Ah!” said she, you
                    can keep your horses, and make them look well! No horse lasts me above a year
                    and half!” Along the whole road from <placeName ref="pl0740">Shrewsbury</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1018">Holyhead</placeName>, the
                    horses are knocked up. The innkeepers lament it - but in consideration of their
                    own loss - no idea of the sufferings of the poor animals ever enters their
                    minds.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>This hurry has been occasioned by the perpetual intercourse between the two
                    kingdoms, during the troubles in <placeName ref="pl0889">Ireland</placeName>.
                    Men have gone upon business, and <hi rend="underline">must</hi> make haste.
                    Others have followed and <hi rend="underline">would</hi> make haste. Irishmen
                    have curst the post boys; and, presenting their pistols, have bade them drive to
                    the devil; and threatened to shoot them if they dared to disobey. To this fury
                    of expedition the example of the mail coach has contributed. It is obliged, by
                    profession, to fly; and all post boys endeavour to fly after it. The horses are
                    allowed to pull up steep hills, but they gallop up common ones, and down all.
                    When they return empty, they are made to gallop; whether they deserve it or no,
                    they are flogged; and at the end of their journey, there commonly stands some
                    little dirty boy, to whip them into the stable.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>Travellers at this rate cannot see <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>But a great number of persons of fortune, of both sexes, travel through
                        <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>, on purpose to see its beauties.
                    These have their own carriages and frequently their own horses. They enter
                        <placeName ref="pl1221">North Wales</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl3069">Chirk</placeName>. They pass through <placeName ref="pl0793">Llangollen</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName>,
                        <placeName ref="pl1533">Llanrwst</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1049">Conwy</placeName>; and take a dinner at <placeName ref="pl1563">Bangor
                        Ferry</placeName> in their way to <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>. From <placeName ref="pl1565">Caernarvon</placeName>
                    they make an excursion to the Lakes of Llanberis; and, perhaps, to <placeName ref="pl1183">Snowdonia</placeName>. </p>
                <p> </p>
                <pb n="138"/>
                <fw>p.138</fw>
                <p> </p>
                <p>They then proceed to <placeName ref="pl1518">Beddgelert</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1571">Tan y
                    Bwlch</placeName>, and, by the nearest way, home; and having done all this, they have seen
                        <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>. So they have; the grand outline;
                    and enough to wonder at, and admire. But to find out all its beauties, a man
                    must travel on foot; or at least on a Welsh Keffil. He must be acquainted with
                    the Welsh gentry and clergy, and travel with a pass from one of their houses to
                    another. So might he learn what was worth seeing, and where to find it. </p>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>