<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0051">
    <teiHeader type="s">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Anonymous, Tour in Scotland August 1794
                    <date>1794</date></title>
                <author>Anonymous</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Edited with an Introduction by Alex Deans</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
                <date when="1794"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
                        <idno>Acc.8278</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab>
                            <locus>1-86</locus>
                        </ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <additional>
                        <p>For ease of reading the author's unpaginated notes, given at the end of
                            the manuscript journal, have been linked in this document to the
                            passages to which they refer. The journal bears a bookplate with the
                            name Leonard Clark. Folio numbers have been added to the journal in a
                            modern hand. Some punctuation and corrections appear to have been
                            inserted in a different ink; it is unclear whether these are later
                            corrections by the original author or additions by a separate hand.</p>
                    </additional>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gd">Gaelic</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="it">Italian</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p><pb n="f.1v"/> Tour in Scotland August 1794.</p>
                <p><quote>
                        <l>“Care Selve beate,</l>
                        <l>E voi solinghi, et taciturni Horrori,</l>
                        <l>Di Riposo e di Pace Alberghi veri,</l>
                        <l>O quanto volontieri</l>
                        <l>A rividervi I’ torno: e se le Stelle-</l>
                        <l>M’ havesser dato in sorte</l>
                        <l> viver à me stessa, e di far Vita</l>
                        <l>Conforme a le mie voglie:</l>
                        <l>Io già co’ Campi Elisi</l>
                        <l>Fortunato Giardin de’ Semidei,</l>
                        <l>La vostr’Ombra gentil non cangerei”</l>
                    </quote><bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0163">Pastor Fido</title></bibl>
                    Scena V.</p>
                <p><quote>
                        <l>“A tale of the Times of old! The Deeds of Days</l>
                        <l>“of other Years. The murmur of thy Streams O</l>
                        <l>“Lora brings back the memory of the past.</l>
                        <l>“The sound of thy Woods, Garmallar, is loudly</l>
                        <l>“in mine Ear.”</l></quote> Ossian’s Carthorn.<note type="editorial"><bibl>James Macpherson, <title ref="bi0569"><hi rend="italic">Fingal,
                                    an ancient epic poem, in six books: together with several other
                                    poems, composed by Ossian the son of Fingal</hi></title>
                            (London: 1762), <biblScope unit="page">p.127</biblScope></bibl>.</note>
                </p>
                <p><pb n="f.2r"/>Thursday, <lb/>August 1<hi rend="superscript">st.</hi> Left
                        <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> at 1. O. clock in the afternoon,
                    and were set down in <placeName ref="pl0253">Carlisle</placeName> on Saturday at
                    2 P.M. This City is small, dirty and ill built: the Castle, in one of the Towers
                    of which <persName ref="pe0527">Mary Queen of Scots</persName> was confined, is
                    strong, but irregular, and without any Dignity or Symmetry of Parts; and the
                    ramparts which surround the Town are of the same Description. The Town appears
                    not to be populous or Commercial.</p>
                <p>We left <placeName ref="pl0253">Carlisle</placeName> on Sunday 4<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi>, and soon came in sight of the Bor-<pb n="f.2v"/> ders form’d by an immense chain of Mountains, beginning at the West with the
                    lofty hill of <placeName ref="pl1096">Scrawfell</placeName> rival of <placeName ref="pl1097">the great Skiddaw</placeName>, which with the range of
                    Mountains bounding the Lakes of <placeName ref="pl0800">Cumberland</placeName>
                    appear’d in view to a vast distance. We pass’d over <placeName ref="pl1098">the
                        extensive Plain of the Solway</placeName>, formerly the Theatre of mutual
                    Devastation, and the scene of many a bloody Encounter between the two Hostile
                    Nations now so happily united. This Plain is celebrated for the extraordinary
                    Eruption of the Moss. It issued from an aperture no larger than the Mouth of a
                    common well. Being a solution of the Mossy Pulp in water, no obstacle which
                    might have stopp’d or retarded <pb n="f.3r"/>the progress of a Solid Body could
                    withstand it’s Course. This inconsiderable spring poured forth it’s Contents
                    with such Copiousness and Rapidity, that in an Hour’s time it overwhelmed a
                    Track of Country many Miles in all Directions, completely burying it under this
                    extraordinary Lava. Many People were surprised in their Houses, and narrowly
                    escaped with their Lives. It cover’d the Bridges and roads, and stopp’d the
                    Course of a number of rivulets, rendering all communicati<add place="above">o</add>n between the different Parts of the Country impracticable. In the
                    Course of Years it has been removed and thrown into the <pb n="f.3v"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0556">River Eske</placeName>, and so carried into the Sea, but
                    there still remain many prominent Marks of the Devastation.<note type="authorial">In the Eruption of the Solway Moss a Cow-house in which
                        there were 6 Cows was overwhelm’d, 5 of which perish’d. The other remain’d
                        sunk up to the Head for 60 Hours without food. When liberated She ate
                        heartily but shew’d the utmost horror when water was set before Her; until
                        at length time or necessity cured her of this Aversion.</note>
                    <note type="editorial">This account of the eruption of the Solway Moss appears
                        to be based on that given by Thomas Pennant in <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0008">A tour in Scotland 1772, part I</title></bibl> (1774),
                        pp.75-76. Pennant gives the year of the eruption as that previous to his
                        tour: 1771.</note> On passing <placeName ref="pl0557">the River
                        Sark</placeName> we enter’d <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> by
                        <placeName ref="pl0558">the celebrated village of Greatney</placeName>, and
                    went on to <placeName ref="pl0587">Douglas Mill</placeName> where we slept.</p>

                <p>Mnday 5<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> Walked to <placeName ref="pl0590">Lanark</placeName> along a dreary and uncomfortable Country. Here we
                    visited the Cotton Mills belonging to <persName ref="pe0528">Mr.
                    Dale</persName>, in which no less than 1700 Persons are employ’d. There is an
                    Institution forming part of this extensive Scheme which does Honour to the
                    Proprietor, and which cannot be contemplated without Pleasure and Admiration.
                    This Benevolent and truly Patriotick Man employs no less than 300 Boys and
                    Girls, all of indigent Parents, who are brought <pb n="f.4r"/> up in the Mills,
                    and are taught the art of spinning in the Cotton and the other branches of the
                    Business. They are fed and cloath’d by Him for a certain term of Years, which
                    being expired, He gives to each a Suit of Cloaths and 20 S. in money: and then
                    they are at liberty to seek new Masters, or to remain in his service. But while
                    they are thus acquiring early Habits of Diligence and Industry, and attaining
                    that Skill in the Manufacture which is the Foundation of their future
                    Independance in Life their Minds are by no means neglected. This munificent
                    Patron maintains no less than 11 Masters for their Instruction in those useful
                        <pb n="f.4v"/> Parts of Knowledge that are most appropriate to their
                    situation in society; such as Reading, Writing and Arithemik; which are taught
                    after the Termination of their daily Occupations in the Mills. We saw there 300
                    sit down in a large Room each with his Cogue or Bason (no small one) of
                    excellent Scotch Broth and their respective Rations of Oatmeal Bread. They
                    appear’d to be stout, healthy children. In another large Room exceedingly well
                    ventilated they sleep in large Beds containing 3 a piece. So extraordinary and
                    ingeniously contrived is the Machinery of the Mills that all the operations,
                    which are of amazing Variety and Complication, are perform’d by children under
                    the age of 12 Years. <persName ref="pe0528">Mr. Dale</persName> the Proprietor
                        <pb n="f.5r"/> is a singular Instance of the Effect which Industry and
                    Prudence aided by Fortune may produce. Although some Years ago He was only a
                    Journey-man weaver, He now gives bread to between 6 or 7000 People employ’d in
                    the various Departments of his Business.</p>
                <p>The Mills are situated about 2 Miles up the River from <placeName ref="pl0590">Lanark</placeName> and their first Appearance is very striking. They are
                    built in a deep or rather profound Glen close to the <placeName ref="pl0600">Clyde</placeName>, which is hemm’d in on both sides by high and rugged
                    Precipices, ---- rolling over 2 or 3 little Falls, and again broken by detach’d
                    Fragments of Rock producing and Agitation attended with a continual murmuring
                    Noise. The main Body of <pb n="f.5v"/> the Building is <sic>parallell</sic> to
                    the River, and there is a large detach’d Wing to the westward of it: and in the
                    middle is a very fine spacious Area. At a little distance from the Mills stands
                    a small neat and regularly built Village belonging to <persName ref="pe0528">Mr.
                        Dale</persName>, and built by Him for the residence of his Mechanics. At the
                    brow of the Hill by which it is approach’d from <placeName ref="pl0590">Lanark</placeName> this whole scene suddenly opens to view: the first
                    Object which immediately <add place="above">arrests</add> our attention is the
                    Building of the Mills which <add place="above">being</add> very lofty, regular
                    and entirely of Stone together with it’s Extent and the stature of it’s
                    Situation, impresses <add place="above">us</add> with the Idea of the retreat of
                    a Great Monarch rather than of a Place destin’d for the Exercise of mechanical
                        <pb n="f.6r"/>Industry: and indeed the whole corresponds with every
                    Suggestion which could proceed from the warm Imagination of a Poet.</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe0528">Mr. Dale</persName> politely shew’d us the Works: but it
                    is difficult to convey to those who have not seen them any precise Acquaintance
                    with their Structure, the various Parts or their general Cooperation.</p>
                <p>The whole is set in motion by one Wheel of amazing Dimensions suspended in the
                    Center of the Building, it’s Axis on each side resting on the solid Rock, in
                    which is cut or blown a chasm large enough to permit the Revolution of the
                    wheel. The Stream which drives it runs through the Perforation of a solid <pb n="f.6v"/> Rock some hundred yards in length and it ends on a level with
                    that part of the River’s Surface from which the Current into it is powr’d. The
                    channel of this current runs <sic>parallell</sic> to the Course of the River
                    with considerable rapidity: the Elevation from which it proceeds being about 50
                    Feet above the bed of the Water at the Mills as the River descends from the
                    aperture by 3 Falls: and it is made with that degree of declension requisite to
                    give the Water it’s necessary proportion of Velocity and Force. In the center of
                    the area there is a receptacle for the water of a circular Form, and being here
                    collected, by means of sluices which can be raised and depress’d, is regulated
                        <pb n="f.7r"/>the Quantity of Water which turns the great Wheel, and
                    consequently the Quickness of Motion in the whole Machinery. This is measur’d by
                    means of the Dial Plate of a Clock, the Hands of which are turn’d by the
                    Revolutions of the great Wheel, which is compared with a Common Clock placed in
                    the same Room (Counting House) : 20 Revolutions being fix’d as the Standard of a
                    Minute, and occasionally as it becomes slower or faster the water is so
                    regulated as to bring it within that medium.</p>
                <p>The 1<hi rend="superscript">st.</hi> Operation is that of carding the Raw Cotton.
                    It is placed on a flat Frame of Wood under a long round Piece of polish’d Iron:
                    in this situation it is <pb n="f.7v"/>gradually taken in by the Revolution of a
                    Cylindrical Carding Brush: from this it is caught by another of finer and closer
                    Wires, and being brought up in the Course of the Revolution it is intercepted by
                    the repeated and regular strokes of a straight single row of Teeth supported
                    upon and acting by 2 Levers, which strikes it off the Cylinder, whence it is
                    transmitted between two plain Pieces of wood which being round and continually
                    revolving draws it out in shape of a long narrow Train of Cotton, and in this
                    manner it is lodg’d in a Tin Case. By the same operation it is afterwards
                    gradually reduced to a size fit for the Bobbin.</p>
                <p>The fine Thread is produced by a curious Process. A Leathern strap attached to
                    some of the larger secondary <pb n="f.8r"/> wheels which are put in motion by
                    the Primary Movement goes round a certain number of smaller Dimensions ranged
                    along a Frame: these last again have another strap each going round a certain
                    number of Bobbins. — Large Bobbins of the coarse <del rend="overstrike">Thread</del> Thread being placed on the Top of the Machine arranged in a
                    straight Line standing perpendicularly, and turning loosely on their axes the
                    Thread is introduced: 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> between a wooden plain
                    small Cylinder, and under it a fluted metal one, both turn’d by brass Wheels,
                    which reduces it to a particular Size: 2<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> it then
                    succeeds to another viz: a Cylinder cover’d with fine Leather and another of
                    Metal finer than the first and brought closer together, in order still farther
                    to attenuate <pb n="f.8v"/>the Thread: 3<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> it’s
                    ultimate <sic>Finess</sic>
                    <add place="above">is produced</add> by a third of the same Description,
                    bringing out a Thread as even and uniform as that of a silk-worm. In this last
                    stage it is wound round the lower set of Bobbins mention’d above: then are
                    placed in 2 Rows (as likewise the larger ones) on a Frame, which in order that
                    the Thread may be equally distributed along them is rais’d and depress’d by the
                    revolution of a plain Elliptical Wheel: thus lifting up the Bobbins along with
                    it, &amp; gradually letting them down again, so that every part has it’s due
                    proportion of the Thread.</p>
                <p>About ¾ of a Mile above the Mills are the two stupendous <placeName ref="pl0591">Falls of the Clyde</placeName> call’d the <placeName ref="pl0593">Bonniton-Lyn</placeName> and the <placeName ref="pl0592">Corallyn</placeName>. To these we are led by a walk in the <pb n="f.9r"/>
                    Park of <persName ref="pe0512">Lady Ross</persName>, romantically winding along
                    the Bank of the River, and awfully looking down on it’s deep dark and rug--ged
                    Bed, flanked on each side by high and perpendicular Rocks. Of these Cascades the
                        <placeName ref="pl0592">Corallyn</placeName> is by far the most
                    considerable.</p>
                <p>The Water is first collected in a round Bason in a vast Inclosure of the Rocks on
                    each side, from which it moves with Majestick Slowness ‘till pitching on a
                    craggy Bottom immediately below the Line of the Bason it is instantly broken and
                    throw’n into the most furious Violence and Ebullition. It is carried on in this
                    manner foaming and agitated for some way over a nearly horizontal surface, until
                    it arrives at the brink of the first Fall <pb n="f.9v"/> (for there are properly
                    two) over which it is precipitated with great force, and plunging into the Flood
                    below, by the Rebound throws up it’s water in Pyramidical Columns to a
                    considerable Height. Being here in a manner collected for the greatest onset it
                    soon arrives at the last Fall which is much higher and of greater Expanse that
                    the first: it rolls it’s mighty Volume over the shapeless Precipice with a
                    resistless Force and thundering Sound, it’s terrifick appearance and the solemn
                    Grandeur of the scene which surrounds it suspending every Power of the Mind in
                    Astonishment and Awe. The Spray, at the same time, ascending like Clouds of
                    Smoke to a vast Height <add place="above">and illuminated with the rays of the
                        Sun</add> flings into the atmos-sphere all the vivid Clours of the Prism,
                        <pb n="f.10r"/>
                    <pb n="f.10v"/>
                    <pb n="f.11r"/> and they are <del rend="overstrike">sometimes</del>
                    <add place="above">often</add> exhibited in a circular Form, some Parts of the
                    spray near the surface being thrown into a Revolutionary Motion. When it falls
                    on the Rock below the foaming Whiteness immediately ceases as if the whole Body
                    of the Water were swallow’d up in a gulf. When the Sun shines upon it, the Light
                        <del rend="overstrike">from</del> on it’s surface is so strong as scarcely
                    to be sustain’d by the Eye, and it gives to all the neighbouring Objects a
                    sombrous and melancholy Aspect. Behind is seen the calm and glassy Surface of
                    the Bason from which this tumultuous Scene proceeds buried in a deep and
                    cavernous Obscurity; presenting to us the contrasted Representation of the most
                    placid Tranquillity, and the most ungovernable Violence &amp; Disorder. <pb n="f.11v"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0593">Bonniton-Lyn</placeName> is much inferior to the last,
                    and consists of one Stream thrown over a Rock.</p>
                <p>At about 4 Miles down the River is the <placeName ref="pl0594">Fall of
                        Stone-Byers</placeName>: it consists of 3 distinct Columns of Water, one
                    above the other, thrown each from an amazing Height, in an immense Mass, and it
                    exceeds by far the other two in Magnitude and Grandeur.<note type="authorial">On
                        the 26<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> January 1787. <placeName ref="pl0600">the Clyde</placeName> became suddenly dry above <placeName ref="pl0590">Lanark</placeName>, and stopp’d the Mills for 2 hours and afterwards
                        flowed on as usual. This curious Phenomenon has happen’d to many other
                        Rivers in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> at different
                        times.</note></p>

                <p><placeName ref="pl0590">Lanark</placeName> is a pleasant little Town and situated
                    in a charming Country.</p>
                <p>Tuesday 6<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> August. We walk’d from <placeName ref="pl0590">Lanark</placeName>, and arrived in <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> late in the Evening after a fatiguing. March of 36
                    Miles, and render’d vexatious by some cross accidents. The Road lay along the
                    Banks of the <placeName ref="pl0600">Clyde</placeName>, and the country appear’d
                    well cultivated and <pb n="f.12r"/> finely wooded. We stopp’d at <placeName ref="pl0597">Hamilton</placeName>, and saw <placeName ref="pl0232">Chatelherault</placeName><note type="authorial"><handShift/><placeName ref="pl0231">the Palace at H.</placeName></note> the residence of
                        <persName ref="pe0250">the Duke of Hamilton</persName>. It is an old
                    Mansion, &amp; has nothing to the exterior to recommend it, nor can much be said
                    for the Furniture and internal Decorations. The grand room the only one worthy
                    of remark is long and well proportion’d, but it is furnish’d in a manner which
                    seems to betray the perverted Taste of a Voluptuary. In different Places there
                    are Setees on the Floor “a la Turque”: in other <sic>Mattrasses</sic> and sofas
                    with arm-chairs and Reading Desks so confusedly arranged as to give it strongly
                    the air of an Upholsterer’s Warehouse. It contains however one invaluable
                    Curiosity, <rs type="art" ref="ar0076">the Painting of Daniel in the Lions’ Den
                        by Rubens</rs>. <pb n="f.12v"/> The Figure of Daniel in the middle is
                    exquisitely painted. The admirable attitude, the exact anatomy, the Inflexions
                    and Indentures of the Muscles so excellently express’d, and the clean fleshy
                    colouring, all conspire to render it a perfect Production of Art. In the Eyes
                    and Face turn’d up to Heaven we could almost imagine that we discern’d the
                    carious Emotions then working on his Mind, were we not certain that it exceeds
                    the Province of Painting to express at the same instant any Variety or
                    Combination of them. The Lions are all admirably drawn, in different attitudes,
                    and by their manner strongly impress us with the Idea of being restrain’d by a
                    supernatural Power. In one of the rooms there is an Original <rs type="art" ref="ar0246">Painting of Mary Queen of Scots</rs>: it corresponds <pb n="f.13r"/> with the Testimony of Historians relating to the Beauty of that
                    Unforunate and misguided Princess.</p>
                <p>After leaving <placeName ref="pl0597">Hamilton</placeName> we pass’d over
                        <placeName ref="pl0230">Bothwell Bridge</placeName> celebrated for the
                    Defeat of the Covenanters by the <persName ref="pe0605">Marquis of
                        Montrose</persName>. We visited the remains of <placeName ref="pl0599">the
                        Castle</placeName> which is a Noble Ruin, standing on the Top of a Hill high
                    and steep, and at the foot of it the <placeName ref="pl0600">Clyde</placeName>
                    rolls it’s troubled Flood.</p>

                <p>August 7<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> and 8<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi>
                    Stopp’d at <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName>. This large Commercial
                    and Populous City is the best built of any in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>: the Fronts of the Houses are chiefly of Stone, many
                    of them having Collonades and Porticcos with other architectural ornaments; and
                    being mostly detach’d from each other they have more the appearance <pb n="f.13v"/> of little Palaces than the Residence of Private Citizens. The
                    High Street in particular is very magnificent, being built in a straight Line
                    running to a great length, and the Houses on each side having regular and lofty
                    Fronts. At the Top of it is the Toll-Booth and the Exchange, and under it the
                    spacious and elegant Coffee House of the Tontine, to which the Merchants resort
                    to transact Business.<note type="authorial"><placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> contains by the last Estimate 61,945 Inhabitants or
                        about ¾ of the Population of <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName>,
                        to which in the Course of some Years it will probably be superior. It may be
                        called the Capital of the West as <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName> is of the East of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>.</note></p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1059">The Cathedral</placeName> is a superb Gothick Struc-ture
                    situated on the summit of an Eminence North of the City, and can be seen on all
                    sides at a great Distance from <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName>. It
                    is divided into 3 Parts the one Wing being set apart for the service of the
                    Parish in which it stands: the other is call’d the Low-church: <pb n="f.14r"/>
                    <pb n="f.14v"/>
                    <pb n="f.15r"/> and the center is dignified with the Name of the High-Church.
                    This Part is spacious, lofty, well-lighted, and the cluster’d Gothick Columns
                    with their corresponding Arches are in the best proportions of that grand stile
                    of architecture. That Aisle which is with great propriety call’d <add place="above">low</add> is exceedingly dark, and has more the appearance of
                    the Dungeon of a Prison than a Place destined for the Exercise of a Religion
                    which inspires Comfort, and awakens us to pleasing and serene Enjoyments. At the
                    End of it there is a Cymetry a Place where is <q>no Light but rather Darkness
                        visible</q><note type="editorial">John Milton, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0567"><hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi></title><biblScope unit="line"/></bibl></note> and painted black in order to aggravate
                    the Gloom: <pb n="f.15v"/> in short in every respect calculated to render our
                    instinctive Dread of Death more horrible. These many leading Families in the
                    Town have their particular Vaults.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1061">The College </placeName>is by no means remarkable: they
                    have however begun a new Quadrangle which is to be built in consequence of a
                    bequest of <persName ref="pe0529">John Hunter</persName> the late eminent
                    Surgeon, and for the reception of his valuable Anatomical Preparations, which He
                    has left to the society.</p>
                <p>There is a singular Piece of Convenience which the People of <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> enjoy, and to which I have seen nothing
                    similar elsewhere. In a large Meadow extending along the <placeName ref="pl0600">Clyde</placeName>, called <placeName ref="pl1099">the Green</placeName>,
                    there stands a low Quadrangular Building, in the <pb n="f.16r"/> inside divided
                    into equal Portions or Compartments by means of small wooden Pillars, giving it
                    the appearance of a small Piazza: in the middle is a large reservoir of water
                    brought from the River and thrown into this Bason by forcing Pumps: in the
                    Corners are Boilers for heating the water. All the washing Work of <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> is perform’d in two Places of this kind,
                    each of those Portions being let out indiscriminately to a certain Number of
                    washer-women, who have the Advantage of being supplied with Hot and Cold water,
                    and of drying their Linen on <placeName ref="pl1099">the Green</placeName> at
                    the Rate of 3<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> a day. We saw 200 Acres of Ground
                    cover’d with <pb n="f.16v"/> washing Articles of every Description. <placeName ref="pl0600">The Clyde</placeName> where it runs by <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> is broad but not navigable, being very shallow and it’s
                    course broken by Fragments of the rock, over which it goes with a continual
                    Noise. There are two light and elegant Bridges thrown over it here. Owing to
                    this Impossibility of navigating the River so high the Trade of <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> is carried on at <placeName ref="pl0603">Greenock</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl0602">Port Glasgow</placeName>
                    near the Mouth of the River.</p>
                <p>At 4 Miles from <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> is the <placeName ref="pl1100">Vale of Kelvin</placeName> celebrated for the <placeName ref="pl1101">Stupendous Aqueduct</placeName> which conveys over it Part of
                        <placeName ref="pl1102">the Grand Canal joi<add place="above">n</add>ing the
                        Firths of the Forth and the Clyde</placeName>. It consists of 4 arches, the
                    span of each appearing to be about 50 or 60 Feet <pb n="f.17r"/> and the Height
                    including the Parapet between 70 and 80. The Descent of the Canal to it is by 5
                    Locks closely succeeding each other, every one of them having under it a large
                    circular Bason to supply the necessary waste of water. The Cut from the main
                    Body to <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> is 3 Miles in length: it is
                    conducted over 3 Bridges of amazing Strength and Solidity, each consisting of a
                    single Arch of about the same Dimensions as those of the Aqueduct: and ends at a
                    Place called <placeName ref="pl1103">Port Dundass</placeName> greatly above the
                    level of the Town. The great Level is 156 Feet above the Sea, and it descends on
                    one side by 19 on the other by 20 Locks. It carries <pb n="f.17v"/>Vessels of
                    150 Tons Burden being 8 Feet deep. The Expence of constructing it is stated at
                    £250,000.</p>

                <p>Friday 9<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> August.</p>
                <p>Sailed from <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> down <placeName ref="pl0600">the Clyde</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0226">Dunbarton</placeName>, and saw on each side a pleasant Country, but not
                    striking or picturesque. <placeName ref="pl0226">The Town of
                        Dunbarton</placeName> is built on a Flat, close to <placeName ref="pl1063">the River Leven</placeName>. It is a small Town and carries on an
                    inconsiderable Trade with <placeName ref="pl0889">Ireland</placeName>. The Rock,
                    on the Summit of which <placeName ref="pl1104">the Castle</placeName> is built,
                    stands perfectly insulated on a Plain extending 2 Miles on all sides, exhibiting
                    the curious and almost unparallell’d Phenomenon of a Height or Mountain totally
                    aloof from any other Eminence. From the River or the Plain, even at <pb n="f.18r"/>a small distance it appears diminutive and almost contemptible,
                    nor is but by a near Approach that we discover it’s great Extent, it’s Height
                    and impracticable Abruptness. It is naturally divided into 2 Parts or Rocks
                    nearly equal, between which in the inside there is a Passage by a Flight of
                    Stairs overhung by large Pieces of the Rock which seem to be critically
                    poised.</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe0530">Captain Robertson</persName> a Brave Veteran, and a Man of
                    the most obliging Politeness conducted us over <placeName ref="pl1104">the
                        Castle</placeName>. From Him we learnt that it is 1 English Mile in
                    Circumference, and the Rock 567½ Feet high. He shew’d us a spring almost at the
                    highest Elevation suffici<hi rend="superscript">ent</hi>
                    <pb n="f.18v"/> in case of a Siege to supply 1500 Men. In a Cistern supplied by
                    another spring He shew’d us a Trout which has lived there for 20 Years. In a
                    late repair order’d by Government in digging to the Foundation a small Piece of
                    Artillery was discover’d of a singular Make. It is of a Calibre of 1 Pound, but
                    in stead of Trunnions to mount it on a Carriage it has a long Handle each End of
                    which joins the Barrel, and is just of Weight enough to be carried by a Strong
                    Man according to the suppos’d Intention. In service it was most probably placed
                    on the Ground or any other casual support that might offer itself. <add place="above">We saw here</add> the Sword of S<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                        W<hi rend="superscript">m.</hi> Wallace, <pb n="f.19r"/>justly esteem’d the
                    Greatest of those Heroes whom Scotland has produced, and to whom the fond and
                    hyperbolick Admiration of his Countrymen has ascribed Qualities which exist only
                    in Fiction.</p>
                <p>Some Parts of this Rock seem to possess a magnetical Property, for by making an
                    Experiment with a Needle the North Pole was sometimes attracted and sometimes
                    repell’d, and according to different Positions pointed to all <sic>Qarters</sic>
                    of the Horizon: and this Variety of Effects took place within the Compass of a
                    Yard.</p>
                <p>To the North of the Castle there lies a Fragment fallen from the Rock for a time
                    immemorial, the size of which <pb n="f.19v"/>is astonishing. It appears in bulk
                    equal to the Hull o a 1<hi rend="superscript">st.</hi> Rate Line of Battle Ship,
                    and the surface of it next to the Castle is an exact Duplicate of the
                    perpendicular Face of the Rock at the foot of which it lies. Fragments of the
                    Rock frequently loosen and are precipitated, and <placeName ref="pe0530">Captain
                        Robertson</placeName> related to us two Accidents of that Kind, which were
                    nearly attended with fatal Consequences. <persName ref="pe0531">Lord
                        Cassilis</persName>, who was Governor about 60 Years ago, intending to take
                    an Airing in his Carriage had it drawn up in the usual Place: (where the Rock is
                    perfectly perpendicular): the servant had open’d the Door, and was holding it in
                    that manner ready for his Lordship to enter, <pb n="f.20r"/>who was at the
                    Instant at a small distance giving some Instructions to the People around Him,
                    when in the Interval a prodigious Fragment flew from the summit of the Rock, and
                    pitching on the Top of the Carriage dash’d it in pieces, the servant escaping
                    unhurt. The second Instance is of his own Daughter, a Beautiful Young Woman, who
                    passing near the same spot about 20 Pieces of Stone of the size of a Man’s Head
                    came thundering down about 3 or 4 Yards behind Her.</p>
                <p>The importance of his impregnable Rock during the Civil Discords in Scotland is
                    sufficiently known, and <pb n="f.20v"/> accordingly it became the scene <add place="above">of one</add> of the most gallant Enterpri<del rend="overwritten">z</del>
                    <add>s</add>es recorded in History.</p>
                <p>When <persName ref="pe0532">Lennox</persName> was Regent of Scotland during the
                    Minority of <persName ref="pe0533">James 1<hi rend="superscript">st.</hi></persName> and Deposition of <persName ref="pe0527">his
                        Mother</persName> this Castle was then in the Hands of the Queen’s Partizans
                    and <persName ref="pe0534">Lord Fleming</persName> was Governor. <persName ref="pe0535">Cap<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Crawford of Jordan
                        Hill</persName> a Man of invincible Resolution and Enterpize form’d the
                    desperate and seemingly impracticable Scheme of taking it by Surprize, being in
                        <persName ref="pe0532">the Regent’s</persName> Interest. The Plan and
                    Practicability of the Attempt were explain’d to Him by a Soldier who having
                    serv’d in <pb n="f.21r"/> the Garrison was acquainted with it’s accesses, and
                    was urged to this Piece of Treachery by Disgust and resentment arising from some
                    ill wage which He had experienced in the Garrison. Accordingly towards the
                    Evening of the 24<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> March 1571 <persName ref="pe0535">Capt. Crawford</persName> left <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> with a small by determind Band and reach’d <placeName ref="pl1104">the Rock</placeName> towards mid-night: the Moon was up but
                    overcast with clouds and afforded them just light enough to lead them to their
                    dreadful Purpose without hazard of Discovery. After having surmounted incredible
                    Difficulties, and vanquish’d many unforeseen Accidents with great Presence of
                    mind they arriv’d at the foot <pb n="f.21v"/> of a Pa<add place="above">r</add>apet wall 10 or 12 Feet high closer to the Guard House (<sic>whic</sic>
                    is still standing) and which it was their Chief object to surprize when a
                    trifling Accident had nearly disconcerted this daring Plot. The 1<hi rend="superscript">st.</hi> Man who ascended was seiz’d with a Fit while yet
                    on the Ladder, but <persName ref="pe0535">Capt. Crawford</persName>, one of
                    those whose Faculties are only sharpen’d by Danger tied Him fast and then turn’d
                    up the other side. He led the way was seen by the Centinel as He mounted, whom
                    He instantly cut down: his gallant Companions enter’d <placeName ref="pl1104">the Castle</placeName> with triumphant Shouts where they met with no
                    resistance. He accomplish’d his Purpose without the Loss of a single man, and
                    was rewarded with the Command of it. <persName ref="pe0534">Lord
                        Fleming</persName> had just time to escape half naked in a Boat across the
                        <placeName ref="pl0833">Clyde</placeName>.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.22r"/> It may be mention’d among the Curiosities of this that <persName ref="pe0530">Cap<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Robertson</persName> who at
                    present has the Command is in Countenance and Person extremely like <persName ref="pe0465">the Present King</persName>, and He tells a pleasant Story of
                    his having been saluted by the Guard of <placeName ref="pl1105">S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> James’s</placeName> in consequence of being
                    mistaken for Him.</p>

                <p>Saturday 10<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> August.</p>
                <p>Walk’d to the delightful and romantick Village of <placeName ref="pl0224">Luss</placeName>, situated on <placeName ref="pl0223">Loch-Lomond</placeName> in a beautiful little Valley, having behind it a
                    fine Skreen of Hills, exhibiting from the water a most lovely Scene. We walk’d
                    for about 5 Miles along the Banks of the pleasing <placeName ref="pl1063">Stream
                        of the Leven</placeName>, running through a <pb n="f.22v"/>rich verdant
                    Valley which it fertilizes &amp; embellishes. All along this Track to the Mouth
                    of the River issuing from <placeName ref="pl0223">L. Lomond</placeName> the
                    Country is wonderfully pleasant, highly cultivated, and abounds with fine
                    Plantations. The Road to <placeName ref="pl0224">Luss </placeName>is excellent
                    being well shaded having the Appearance for some Miles of a delightful Avenue.
                    About 2 Miles from <placeName ref="pl0226">Dunbarton</placeName> we meet with a
                        <placeName ref="pl1064">Pillar</placeName> erected, at a Village called
                        <placeName ref="pl1106">Rantyn</placeName>, by <persName ref="pe0537">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Smollet of Bonhill</persName> to the memory
                    of the Celebrated <persName ref="pe0536">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                        Smollet</persName> who was born on this spot, so elegantly described by Him
                    in <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0568">one of his last Poetical
                            Productions</title></bibl>. In this Vale and along the River’s side lies
                    the pretty <placeName ref="pl0225">Village of Bonhill</placeName>, built in <pb n="f.23r"/> detached <sic>Clustres</sic>, and extending almost the whole
                    length of the River: the Houses are small but neat and have slated roofs: close
                    to them are numerous Bleaching Greens and other Indications of Population and
                    Industry; and the whole Scene seems to be peculiarly the Seat of Competence and
                    Ease. Near <placeName ref="pl0224">Luss</placeName> we pass’d by <placeName ref="pl1065">the Seat</placeName> of <persName ref="pe0508">S<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> James Colquhoun</persName> standing in a most
                    elegant Situation on the borders of <placeName ref="pl0223">the
                    Loch</placeName>, and commanding and extensive View of it’s surface, many of
                    it’s Islands, and the distant mountainous Boundaries. <placeName ref="pl0223">This Loch</placeName> is 35 English Miles in length: it’s greatest breadth
                    is 8: but about 5 Miles from <pb n="f.23v"/><placeName ref="pl0224">Luss</placeName> it becomes very narrow, and continues so for 20 Miles. It
                    is bounded on all sides by high Hills, and towards the North is seen the
                    towering Height of <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben Lomond</placeName>: there are 24
                    Islands, some of them 2 or 3 Miles in circumference, extremely well wooded, and
                    adding greatly to the Beauty and Richness of the Scenery.</p>
                <p>It is impossible by words to convey an adequate Idea of this enchanting
                    Landscape: the Eye is bewilder’d in it’s numerous Mazes, and almost fatigued
                    with the Variety of Objects presented to it, while the Fancy pleasingly
                    exercised in contemplating the different Scenes exhibited to it is lost in <pb n="f.24r"/>their endless, and inexhaustible Combinations. Sometimes we see a
                    broad Expanse of water with Rich and Verdant Isles beautifully grouped, and
                    floating on the Surface of the Lake: at other times the Landscape covers almost
                    it’s whole surface, which is only seen by glimpses, defining with it’s Silvery
                    touch the Boundaries of the different Islands and Objects that enter into this
                    grand Composition. — Sometimes when the Sun is setting behind the Mountains we
                    see their shadows projecting to the very Verge of the Horizon &amp; spreading a
                    dark Veil over the whole Landscape: and sometimes when his Rays shoot through
                    the Vallies <pb n="f.24v"/>it gilds the Sides of the Mountains, shewing by
                    contrast their black contiguous Ridges: and it terminates in the distant Hollows
                    of the Mountains discovering their deep Defiles, their vast Cavities and
                    immeasurable Bulk: but this Light is beautifully soften’d and diversified when
                    it flows smoothly over the level Surface of the Scene, shedding a lambent Smile
                    on the whole Face of this lovely Groupe.</p>

                <p>I ascended to the Top of <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben Lomond</placeName> and saw a
                    most extensive Prospect, from <placeName ref="pl1107">the German
                        Ocean</placeName> at the Mouth of the <placeName ref="pl0083">Firth of
                        Forth</placeName> to the <placeName ref="pl1108">Irish Sea</placeName>. The
                    View was great, but not so pleasing as might be conjectur’d: for at that height
                    all the <pb n="f.25r"/>
                    <pb n="f.25v"/>
                    <pb n="f.26r"/> Objects are too much under the Eye, and lose their grouping and
                    comparative Dignity. It had more the appearance of a Map than a Landscape. I
                    could trace the <placeName ref="pl1063">River Leven</placeName> from it’s Source
                    at <placeName ref="pl0223">L. Lomond</placeName>, with all it’s Inflexions,
                    until it falls into the <placeName ref="pl0600">Clyde</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl0226">Dunbarton</placeName>. The Day was in general very fine, but
                    now and then a Mist or Scud passed over the Mountain, so that I saw this wide
                    Prospect with alternate Splendor and Gloom. I could distinctly count all the
                    Islands of the Loch the most considerable of which are <placeName ref="pl1109">InchMain</placeName>; <placeName ref="pl1110">Inch Calloch</placeName>,
                    Carlin’s (Old Mans) Island so called from being the Burying Place of the M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Grigors;<note type="editorial">Possibly a
                        mistranslation of the Island's Gaelic name <placeName ref="pl1110">Inchcailleach</placeName> (the island of the old women) — a reference
                        to a community of nuns supposed to have inhabited the island.</note>
                    <pb n="f.26v"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl1112">Inch Lonach</placeName>, entirely cover’d with Yew Trees
                    about 1500 in number: <placeName ref="pl1113">Devannah or Monk’s
                        Island</placeName> where formerly there was a Monastery; and another call’d
                    for what reason I know not, <placeName ref="pl1114">Luss Prison</placeName>.
                        <placeName ref="pl0223">The Loch</placeName> itself was diminish’d in
                    appearance to the size of a Pool, and it required my former Experience of it’s
                    dimensions to assign it its proper rank in this grand assemblage. Towards the
                    side of <placeName ref="pl0818">Argyleshire</placeName> I saw nothing but
                    immense Ranges of Mountains hiding the champain Country from view. East-ward
                    close to the Foot of the Mountain runs the Water of Alloa<note type="editorial">There is no river called Alloa — the author may be referring to the
                            <placeName ref="pl1116">River Forth</placeName> or the <placeName ref="pl1115">River Teith</placeName>, both of which flow east from the
                        base of <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben Lomond</placeName>.</note> through the
                        <placeName ref="pl1117">Vale of Monteith</placeName>; a Region</p>
                <p><quote><l>“Forlorn and Wild,</l>
                        <l>“The Seat of Desolation void of Light”:</l></quote>
                <note type="editorial">John Milton, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0567"><hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi></title>, <biblScope unit="book">Book I</biblScope>, <biblScope unit="line">ll.180-81</biblScope></bibl>.</note></p>
                <p><pb n="f.27r"/> and seemingly more fit for the Haunt of Dæmons and Wild Beasts
                    than for the comfortable Abode of Human Beings. This Place was formerly the
                    Residence of the murderous and vindictive Clan of the M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Grigors, a Name detestable to every Lover of Humanity. The opposite
                    side of the Lake was inhabited by the Colquhouns, and between these and the M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Grigors there subsisted a mutual Jealousy &amp;
                    perpetual Warfare. The Murder of the Colquhouns the fatal catastrophé that
                    terminated those bloody Feuds is known to Every one the least conversant in
                    Scotch History. It seems that the immediate Cause of this Massacre was owing to
                        <pb n="f.27v"/> the Colquhouns’ having inflicted summary Execution on one of
                    the M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Grigors who was detected in stealing a sheep.
                    A Meeting was appointed to adjust this and various other Differences, to which
                    the M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Grigors under their chief <persName ref="pe0538">Rob Roy M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Grigor</persName> came
                    armed, surprised the Colquhouns, and made an undistinguishing Slaughter of Them:
                    and to consummate this horrible Cruelty, they pursued and murder’d in cold <add place="above">blood</add> a number of People, chiefly Young Men from the
                    College of <placeName ref="pl0226">Dunbarton</placeName> who were standing on
                    the Top of a Hill, (which I saw) innocent spectators of the scene.</p>
                <p>This infamous Atrocity was retaliated by a signal Act of Vengeance, and of a <pb n="f.28r"/> nature unprecedented in the History of Man.</p>
                <p>No Decree ever issued by any Human Power was more severe, or follow’d up with a
                    more merciless and merited Execution. All sympathy with Them as partaking of a
                    Common Nature was declared to be dissolv’d: they were pronounced to be Enemies
                    to their Species: their very Name as abhorrent to Human Nature was extinguish’d,
                    and it was made Felony in any Clergyman to give it in Baptism. Orders were
                    issued to pursue Them in all Directions and fall on them without mercy whereever
                    they could be found, and the Murder of a M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi> Grigor
                    was not a Crime <pb n="f.28v"/>but a Merit. Such of Them as attempted to save
                    Themselves by flying to the Hills which were inaccessible to Men, were track’d,
                    hunted down like Wild Beasts, and tak’n or torn in pieces by Dogs of
                    extraordinary Fierceness and Strength. The miserable Remnant who succeeded in
                    saving Themselves went into the different Parts of the Country, and assumed the
                    prevalent names in those Places where they settled. This salutary Act of Justice
                    produced many beneficial Consequences by restraining that bloody Spirit of
                    Revenge, the Consequence of Hereditary Feuds which had always actuated the
                    Highland Clans.</p>
                <p>Monday 12<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> August walk’d to <placeName ref="pl1008">Araquhar</placeName>: <pb n="f.29r"/>
                    <pb n="f.29v"/>
                    <pb n="f.30r"/> on <placeName ref="pl0221">Loch Long</placeName>, and next Day
                    to <placeName ref="pl1069">Cairndow</placeName> on <placeName ref="pl1070">L.
                        Fine</placeName>.<note type="authorial">From the Window of the Inn at
                            <placeName ref="pl1008">Arroquhar</placeName> there is seen at a small
                        Distance a huge bare Rock on the Top of a Mountain called <placeName ref="pl1171">the Cobler</placeName>, from it’s whimsical and striking
                        Resemblance of a Cobler working at his Stall.</note></p>
                <p>The approach to this Place lies through the tremendous Defiles of <placeName ref="pl1068">Glencro</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1118">Glenkinglass</placeName>: one of the grand and aweful Passes into
                    Highlands. For about 12 Miles this Glen which is hemm’d in on both sides by
                    amazing high, and craggy <add place="above">Rocks</add>, exhibits a savage
                    Grandeur truly dreadful; nor is there any symptom of Vegetation or Track of a
                    Dwelling to check the unabating Horror of the scene.</p>

                <p>Wednesday 14<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> Walk’d to <placeName ref="pl0217">Inverary</placeName>.About 2 Miles from <placeName ref="pl0217">Inverary</placeName> a noble Prospect opens to view. The Centre Object is
                        <placeName ref="pl0217">the Duke of Argyle’s Castle</placeName> situated <pb n="f.30v"/> on a fine Lawn, and having behind it a Majestick Amphitheatre of
                    Wood: on the left is <placeName ref="pl1072">the neat Town</placeName>
                    charmingly built on the Edge of the Lake which presents a Wide Expanse of Water
                    cover’d with hundreds of Herring Boats, animating the Place, and giving it an
                    appearance of lively Industry: and on the right hand rises the lofty Cone of
                        <placeName ref="pl0218">Dunecoich</placeName> surmounted with Wood.</p>
                <p>The Castle is built in the Gothick Stile with 4 flanking Towers like Bastions
                    with Battlements on the Top, and a Square Tower in the middle: a mode of
                    Architecture incapable of the Noble Elevation, the regular Proportions, and the
                    rich and dignified Elegance of <pb n="f.31r"/> a Grecian Front. The Inside with
                    a few exceptions is very fine. The Dome over the Vestibule is too high, and is
                    almost lost to the Eye on entering the House. The Dining and Drawing Rooms are
                    particularly worthy of Notice, the Paintings and Gildings with the other
                    Decorations being executed in the highest Stile of Elegance and Taste. In the
                    Drawing Room there are some <rs type="art" ref="ar0079">Pieces of Gobelin
                        Tapestry</rs> which are exquisite. The Subjects are Pastoral and truly in
                    the Taste of the French, a People who, although they have excell’d almost in
                    every Art and Science, have by a strange Fatality been marked by a wide
                    Departure <pb n="f.31v"/>from Nature both in Fiction and Philosophy. Here we saw
                    Parisian <sic>Sheperds</sic> with “Chapeau bras” and Coats of Courtly Cut, silk
                    stockings and neatly pointed shoes, approaching in Opera attitudes to ravish
                    Kisses from tonish sprightly Milliners, who seem not very solicitous to repel
                    these bold advances. The Flocks which are feeding around them, and whose silent
                    Indifference is the very Essence of such a scene, are unnaturally made to cast
                    sympathyzing looks on these amorous Couples. But amidst this absurdity the
                    Workmanship challenges our admiration, and is superior to all criticism. The
                    Figures are finely drawn, <pb n="f.32r"/>
                    <pb n="f.32v"/>
                    <pb n="f.33r"/> the Colours are beautifully bright, and the Shading manages with
                    such Delicacy and Softness, that it is necessary sometimes to approach them in
                    order to be satisfied that it is not Effect of the Pencil.</p>
                <p>The Herring Fishery is the great Support of this Country and it’s Neighbourhood.
                    There are about 3000 Boats employ’d on the Loch, each carrying 4 Men. At Sunset
                    they set sail and assume their different Stations; for the Fish can only be
                    taken in the Night: they then let down their Nets which are more than 100 Yards
                    long to the depth of 50 to 60 Fathoms, which they draw up towards the morning,
                    and Instances have been of a single Net’s enveloping 10,000 Fishes. <pb n="f.33v"/> About 60,000 Barrels are salted and sent to <placeName ref="pl0704">the West Indies</placeName> as Food for the Negroes, besides
                    the immense Quantity which the Country People lay in for Winter Stock, and the
                    great Consumption of the fresh Fish; for the chief sustenance of the People in
                    this Quarter of the Kingdom consists of Herrings and Potatoes, which last are
                    accordingly much cultivated here. The Average Price is about 10 a Penny. August
                        15<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> Walk’d to <placeName ref="pl0214">Dalmalie</placeName> along a most barbarous Country. This delightful
                    Village is situated near the Head of <placeName ref="pl0269">Loch
                        Awe</placeName>:<note type="authorial">The Fable relating to the Formation
                        of <placeName ref="pl0269">Loch Awe</placeName> is thus beautifully told by
                            <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian</persName>: (Not publish’d by <persName ref="pe0558">M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>Pherson</persName>) <p><quote>
                                <l>“<persName ref="pe0562">Bera the Aged</persName> dwelt in the
                                    Cave of the</l>
                                <l>“Rock. She was the Daughter of Griannan</l>
                                <l>“the Sage: long was the Line of her Fathers</l>
                                <l>“and She was the last of her Race. Large</l>
                                <l>“and fertile were her Possessions: Her’s the</l>
                                <l>“beautiful Vales below, and her’d the Cattle</l>
                                <l>“which roam’d on the Hills around. To</l>
                                <l>“<persName ref="pe0562">Bera</persName> was intrusted the Charge
                                    of that</l>
                                <l>“aweful Spring which by the Appointment</l>
                                <l>“of Fate was to prove so fatal to the In-</l>
                                <l>“-heritance of her Fathers, and to her</l>
                                <l>“Fathers’ Race.</l>
                                <l>“Before the Sun should withdraw his</l>
                                <l>“Beams She was to cover the Spring</l>
                                <l>“with a Stone on which sacred and mys-</l>
                                <l>“-terious Characters were written. One</l>
                                <l>“Night this was forgotten by the un-</l>
                                <l>“-happy <persName ref="pe0562">Bera</persName>. Overcome with the
                                    Heat</l>
                                <l>“and Chace of the day, She was seized</l>
                                <l>“with Sleep before the usual time of</l>
                                <l>“Rest. The confin’d Waters of Moun-</l>
                                <l>“-tains burst forth into the Plains be-</l>
                                <l>“-low, and cover’d that large Expanse</l>
                                <l>“now Known by the Name of the Lake</l>
                                <l>“of <placeName ref="pl0269">Aw</placeName>. The third morning
                                        <persName ref="pe0562">Bera</persName></l>
                                <l>“awak’d from her sleep. She went to</l>
                                <l>“remove the Stone from the spring</l>
                                <l>“but behold no Stone was there. She</l>
                                <l>“look’d to the Inheritance of her Tribe</l>
                                <l>“She shriek’d! The Mountain shook</l>
                                <l>“from it’s base! Her Spirit retired to the</l>
                                <l>“Ghosts of her Fathers in their light and</l>
                                <l>“airy Halls.</l></quote></p>
                        <p>The Mountain mention’d here is <placeName ref="pl0831">Ben
                                Cruachan</placeName>. It is 1130 Yards above the level of the Sea
                            and 20 Miles in Circumference <placeName ref="pl0269">the
                                Loch</placeName> is 30 Miles long and ¾ broad: it is 36 Yards above
                            the level of the Sea. The History of <placeName ref="pl0272">Fraochyn</placeName>, the Hesperides of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> is given by the same Poet:</p>
                        <p><quote>
                                <l>“The fair <persName ref="pe0563">Mego</persName> longed for the
                                    delicious</l>
                                <l>“Fruit of the Isle guarded by a</l>
                                <l>“a dreadful Serpent. <persName ref="pe0564">Fraoch</persName> who
                                    long</l>
                                <l>“had loved the Maid goes to gather</l>
                                <l>“the Fruit. By the rustling of the</l>
                                <l>“Leaves the Serpent was awaked from</l>
                                <l>“his sleep: he attack’d the Hero, who</l>
                                <l>“perish’d in the Conflict. The Mon-</l>
                                <l>“-ster was also destroy’d: <persName ref="pe0563">Mego</persName>
                                    did</l>
                                <l>“not long survive the Death of her</l>
                                <l>“Lover.”</l>
                            </quote></p></note><note type="editorial">This account of the formation
                        of Loch Awe matches verbatim that given by John Lettice in <hi rend="italic">Letters on a Tour Through Varous Parts of Scotland, in the Year
                            1792</hi>, (London: 1794), pp.256-257. Lettice attributes this rendition
                        of the legend to <persName ref="pe0158">Joseph MacIntyre</persName>,
                        minister of Glenorchy. The Hesperidean tale of Fraoch Eilean given
                        subsequently is similar to that found in Thomas Pennant, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0001">A tour in Scotland
                            1769</title></bibl> (1771), p.188. The source for both may be John
                        Smith's English translation in <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0648">The Death of Artho and the Death of Fraoch. Two Ancient Poems,
                                Translated from the Galic.</title></bibl> (Glasgow: 1769).</note>
                    and about 2 Miles distance from it on the Border of the Loch are the remains of
                        <placeName ref="pl0215">Kilchurn Castle</placeName>, formerly the Residence
                    of the Earls of Breadalbane and built by <persName ref="pe0539">S<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Colin Campbell</persName> Founder <pb n="f.34r"/> of that Family. It was built by Him in the Year 1440, after his
                    Return from the Crusades: it is in the Saracenic Stile of Architecture, which He
                    introduced into <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>. The Principal
                    Tower <sic>next the front</sic> of the Building is square and high, having
                    Turrets at each Angle most beautifully rounded at the Bottom, appearing as
                    entire and fresh as in a Modern Building, and indeed all the architraves of the
                    Windows and the <sic>Coign</sic> Stones of the Tower had the same appearance. It
                    is one of the finest Ruins which I have ever seen. It is sufficiently
                    dilapidated to give it the venerable air of antiquity, but we can exactly trace
                    out the original Design of all its Parts. There is something singularly
                    melancholy in viewing the prostrate <pb n="f.34v"/>Remains of these Edifices,
                    not intended merely as the Residence of Grandeur and Festivity, but likewise
                    constructed for Protection and Defiance: it reminds us solemnly of the
                    Transition of Human Greatness, and the uncontroulable changes which take place
                    not only in Men but in Ages themselves. The appearance in the Inside brought
                    forcibly on my Memory the affecting Passage of Ossian in Carthon one of his most
                    pathetic Compositions: <quote><l>“I have seen the Walls of Balclu-</l>
                        <l>“tha, but they were desolate. The Fire had resoun-</l>
                        <l>“ded in the Halls: and the Voice of the People is</l>
                        <l>“heard no more. The Stream of Clutha roll’d mur-</l>
                        <l>“muring over the fallen Walls. The Thistle</l>
                        <l>“shook it’s lonely head: the Moss whistled to the</l>
                        <l>“Wind. The Fox look’d out from the Windows:</l>
                        <l>“the long Grass of the Wall waved round it’s</l>
                        <pb n="f.35r"/>
                        <l>"it’s Head. Desolate is the Dwelling of Moina,</l>
                        <l>“Silence is in the House of Her Fathers.”<note type="editorial">James
                                MacPherson, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0569"><hi rend="italic">Fingal, An Ancient Epic Poem</hi></title>,
                                    (London: 1762) <biblScope unit="page">p.132</biblScope></bibl>.</note></l></quote></p>
                <p>At the distance of about 3 Miles from <placeName ref="pl0215">Kilchurn</placeName> on an Island in the Lake call’d <placeName ref="pl0272">Fraochlyn</placeName> (Heath Island) stand the massy remains of
                    another Castle in an impregnable Situation; but with regard to it’s Founder, and
                    the Purpose for which it was built, Tradition is silent.</p>

                <p>August 17<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> Walked to <placeName ref="pl0212">Tayndrum</placeName>. It is a dreary, miserable Place. I here view’d the
                    Inside of a Highland Hut: at the door there were an Old Man and his Wife, each
                    past 80, assisting a Young Couple in shearing the Sheep. The Old People look’d
                    healthy and active. There was no accom<add place="above">modation</add> in it
                    beyond the reach of the Scanty means, <pb n="f.35v"/>and uninventive <del rend="overstrike">
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" quantity="2"/>
                    </del>
                    <add place="above">Ge</add>nius of a savage: in Nakedness and Misery it could
                    not be exceeded by the wigwam of a Hottentot. It’s Economy is simple and soon
                    described. There is only one Division or Partition in it: by it a small Portion
                    is set off for the Accommodation of the Family: the Fire is in the middle of
                    this Part, and above it an aperture in the Roof serving as a chimney, but the
                    Windows are occasionally used for the same purpose. Over the Fire is suspended a
                    chain with Hooks (call’d in the Lowlands a Crook) on which they hang their Pots
                    for boiling Meat; Roasting being necessarily unknown among them. The Beds are
                    ranged along the Wall each Department of this little Society, having according
                    to Circumstance a particular one assign’d to it. The other <pb n="f.36r"/>Part
                    of the Hut which is by far the greatest is used to stow their Feuel, their
                    Instruments of Trade, Culinary Utensils, Food for their cattle, and occasionally
                    in severe weather the Cattle themselves. In these uncouth Dwellings to use the
                    Words of Tacitus applied to the Germans</p>
                <p><quote>“In hos Artus et haec Corpora quae <lb/>“<unclear reason="illegible">miramur</unclear> excrescunt.”<note type="editorial">Tacitus, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0342"><hi rend="italic">Germania</hi></title>, <biblScope unit="chapter">XX</biblScope></bibl>. In <hi rend="italic">The Agricola and
                                Germania of Tacitus</hi>, trans. by K.B. Townshend (London: Methuen,
                            1894), the entire sentence is translated as: 'In every household the
                            naked, dirty children develop the mighty limbs and frames that we see
                            with so much admiration.'</note></quote></p>
                <p>Nations in a Civilized State are constantly and progressively making
                    Improvements, and changing the Structure of their Habitations, the Nature of
                    their Food, the Habits of their Life, and even their National character itself:
                    but Pastoral Tribes, living in a State of Simplicity, and scatter’d thinly over
                    a vast but unproductive Country, are in all those Particulars doom’d to a
                    Stationary Sameness: <pb n="f.36v"/>the Arabs and Tartars will a thousand Years
                    hence be the same they were a thousand Years ago: and it is probable that about
                    the middle of last Century the Scotch Highlanders were not very different from
                    those who lived in the Days of <persName ref="pe0540">Fingal</persName>.</p>

                <p>August 18<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> Walk’d to <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName>. this word signifies in the Gaëlic a Burying Place: as
                    it was here that <persName ref="pe0540">Fingal</persName> was interr’d whose
                    Tomb is still shew’n. The Entrance into this very pleasant Village is singularly
                    Romantick. It is situated on a Peninsula on one side of which runs the
                        <placeName ref="pl0995">River Dochart</placeName>, a broad and copious
                    Stream, and on <add place="above">the</add> other the <placeName ref="pl1003">Lochay</placeName>, both falling into <placeName ref="pl0104">Loch
                        Tay</placeName> a Mile below <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName>. The
                        <placeName ref="pl0995">Dochart</placeName> close to the Bridge of
                        <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName> by which we enter the place is
                    broken by numberless Rocks, twisting and eddying through <pb n="f.37r"/>a vast
                    number of Channels, and hurrying over the rugged Fragments in hundreds of Rills
                    and Cascades. About 3 Miles from <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName> we
                    saw two <placeName ref="pl1119">Falls of the Lochay</placeName>, which are very
                    grand and little if at all inferior to <placeName ref="pl0591">those of the
                        Clyde at Lanark</placeName>.</p>
                <p>The Parish of <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName> extends 30 Miles, and
                    the whole Duty of it is perform’d by one Pastor, and his assistant.</p>
                <p>The Country from <placeName ref="pl0212">Tayndrum</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName> is the Highest in Scotland; it is therefore
                    by the Highlanders call’d <placeName ref="pl0813">Braid Alba or
                        Albin</placeName>: Braid signifies Head, Albin <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>. At the <placeName ref="pl1121">Half-way House between
                        Tayndrum and Killin</placeName> the Top of a Crozier was shew’n to us, which
                    the owner ignorantly called a Medal, of <pb n="f.37v"/> Rich Workmanship, in the
                    possession of <persName ref="pe0541">a poor Man of the Name of Dewar</persName>,
                    certified under a Writing or Probate, sign’d by <persName ref="pe0542">James
                        1</persName><hi rend="superscript">st.</hi> of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> to have been in the possession of his Family since the
                    time of <persName ref="pe0544">Robert Bruce</persName>, and mention’d there as a
                    Sacred Relique of <persName ref="pe0543">S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi>
                        Fillan</persName> who first converted the <placeName ref="pl0744">County of
                        Perth</placeName> to Christianity.</p>

                <p>August 20<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> Walk’d to <placeName ref="pl0103">Kenmore</placeName> or <placeName ref="pl0107">Tay-mouth</placeName>: the
                    course lay along the Banks of <placeName ref="pl0104">Loch-tay</placeName>.</p>
                <p>We began about 5 O Clock in the morning: the Dawn was clear and silvery: the Lake
                    was perfectly smooth, and an even mild Light being universally diffused over it,
                    the Face of it appear’d as if it had been polish’d and reflected the opposite
                    Country, <pb n="f.38r"/> which was High and sloped down regularly to the Outline
                    of the Lake, with all it’s Fields, Woods and the surmounting Hills with as clean
                    and precise a Definition as could have been produced by a Mirror. The Loch is on
                    all sides surrounded with Greatness. Towards <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName> we saw it magnificently terminated by <placeName ref="pl0815">the Hill of Benmore</placeName>, one of the Highest in
                        <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>, rising in Elevation to the Eye
                    as we encreas’d our Distance from it, and sinking the scenery approximate to it
                    in proportion, an appearance familiar to those who have travell’d in mountainous
                    Countries. We visited in our way <placeName ref="pl1122">L<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> Breadalbane’s Hermitage</placeName>, from a Window of which,
                        <pb n="f.38v"/> contrived on purpose, there is seen a Cataract 140 Feet high
                    rushing down from the muddel of an amphitheatre of Wood at about 60 Yards
                    distance. <placeName ref="pl0101">L<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> Breadalbane’s
                        Seat</placeName> here is admirably situated: there is a very broad walk or
                    rather Terrace in his Park running 3 Miles along <placeName ref="pl0096">the
                        Tay</placeName> particularly entitled to Admiration.<note type="authorial">On the 12.th Sept<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> 1784 at 9 O Clock in the
                        Morning <placeName ref="pl0104">Loch Tay</placeName> suddenly left the East
                        End 300 Feet dry; it roll’d on 300 Feet farther, and met another wave
                        rushing in a Contrary Direction. The Collision rais’d them to the Height of
                        6 Feet: the whole Body then took a compound or lateral Direction Southward,
                        and went 4 Feet beyond the highest Watermark. — It ebb’d and flow’d every 7
                        Minutes for 2 Hours until it recover’d it’s Station.</note></p>
                <p>August 21<hi rend="superscript">st.</hi> Parted with my Friend <persName ref="pe0545">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Booth</persName>.</p>
                <p>I walk’d to <placeName ref="pl0099">Dunkeld</placeName> along <placeName ref="pl0096">the Tay</placeName>: on both sides of which I observ’d a great
                    Number of Gentleman’s seats with their Policies (Plantations): and abundance of
                    Farm Houses neatly built, and around them a fruitful and highly cultivated
                    Country, giving Employment to a numerous Peasantry at that time employ’d in <pb n="f.39r"/>
                    <pb n="f.39v"/>
                    <pb n="f.40r"/>getting in the Harvest.</p>
                <p>Some way beyond the 7<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> Mile Stone I was surprised
                    at the Appearance of 4 stones standing perpendicularly in a Field near the Road
                    upon a small Hillock.<note type="editorial">Possibly the stone circle at
                            <placeName ref="pl1123">Croft Moraig</placeName> between <placeName ref="pl0107">Taymouth</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1124">Aberfeldy</placeName></note> On going up and examining it, I found it
                    to be the remains of Druidical Temple, and could trace the Situation of the
                    other stones, and even the Vestiges of the Entrance very distinctly, according
                    to the perfect Model discover’d a few Years ago at <placeName ref="pl1125">Jersey</placeName>, and now erected in <persName ref="pe0546">General
                        Conway’s</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl1126">Grounds at Henley</placeName>. It occurs to me at this
                    moment, as a singular Circumstance, that having formerly walk’d about 50 Miles
                    in different Directions in <placeName ref="pl1093">the Island of <pb n="f.40v"/>
                        Anglesey</placeName> the Chief Seat of the Druids, and of consequence the
                    Emporium of their superstition, I met with no Monument of a similar Kind. — The
                    highest Stone in this was 10 Feet from the Ground, about 4 in breadth and 6
                    Inches in thickness.</p>
                <p>The Access to <placeName ref="pl0099">Dunkeld</placeName> is thro’ a deep Glen
                    guarded on each side by high Hills of steep Ascent, cover’d with Pine Woods
                    through which we sometimes see the Rocks looking down majestically on <placeName ref="pl0096">the River Tay</placeName>. This Scene continues for about 3
                    Miles. <placeName ref="pl0099">Dunkeld</placeName> stands close to the River,
                    embosom’d in Woods and Eminences that surround it, exhibiting a beautiful Coup
                    d’œil, and singular in that Beauty. It has the Depth of <persName ref="pe0509">Salvator Rosa </persName>without his Horror: it has the Richness and <pb n="f.41r"/> chastity of <persName ref="pe0547">Claude Lorrain</persName>
                    though not his Extent and Variety.</p>
                <p>In looking down upon <placeName ref="pl0099">the Town</placeName> from Hill to
                    the Westward of it, the Buildings appear without any Exception regular and
                    uniform: The Walls are all white: the Roofs are slated, and as the streets run
                    in straight lines, the Houses appear from that view arranged in even Rows. Here
                    the <persName ref="pe0548">Duke of Athol</persName> has a seat: <placeName ref="pl1127">his House</placeName> is commodious but no ways remarkable. It
                    was here that <persName ref="pe0087">the late Duke</persName> in a fit of Fury
                    and Derangement, the Effect of a Fever, eluded his Keepers and drown’d Himself
                    in the River. He is universally spoken of in this Country as having been a Man
                    of the most amiable character.</p>

                <p><pb n="f.41v"/> August 22<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> Walk’d to <placeName ref="pl0110">Blair</placeName>.</p>
                <p>The Castle at this Place which is well Known to have stood a Siege in the Year
                    1746 is now modernized, and is a Residence of <persName ref="pe0548">the Duke of
                        Athol</persName>.</p>
                <p>In this route I went through the famous <placeName ref="pl0112">Pass of
                        Killycrankie</placeName>. It has infinitely more Grandeur with a less
                    mixture of the Horrible than any of the numerous Defiles which I have as yet
                    seen in the Highlands. I must not omit to mention that near the
                        <sic>begginning</sic> of it I met with <placeName ref="pl1128">another
                        Cromleach </placeName>with 6 of the Stones standing and unbroken.</p>
                <p>August 23. Went from <placeName ref="pl0110">Blair</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0112">Killycrankie</placeName> and view’d the Field of Battle fought
                    between <persName ref="pe0549">Lord Dundee</persName> and <persName ref="pe0550">General M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Kay</persName>, on July 7<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> 1789.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.42r"/> From examining the Nature of the Ground <persName ref="pe0549">Dundee’s</persName> Disposition appears to have been as masterly, as that
                    of his opponent was weak and injudicious. His first Position was on the Face of
                    a very extensive Hill which in a manner flanks the Pass: at the Foot of it there
                    is a Plain bounded by a Bank towards the River, and the Flat of the Defile. On
                    the appearance of <persName ref="pe0550">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Kays</persName> Army He descended, and ranged his Troops on the
                    Plain. By this measure He secured an advantageous Ground, and an excellent
                    Retreat in case of a Disaster; as he could easily retire to his former
                    impregnable Situation.</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe0550">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Kay</persName> drew up his
                    Men close to the Bank upon a narrow Plain, a choice of situation subject to
                    innumerable Inconveniences without a single Advantage. <pb n="f.42v"/> In the
                    first place his Retreat in consequence of a Discomfiture was cut off by the
                    Rivers <placeName ref="pl1129">Gary</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl0096">Tay</placeName>. His Horse and Artillery were absolutely useless, there
                    being no Room for either to act on the Front of the Highlanders. As the Plain
                    was so narrow He could not change his Line of Battle, and was therefore exposed
                    to being outflanked by <persName ref="pe0549">Dundee’s</persName> Army, who
                    could choose their mode of fighting; and which actually took place. As the Pass
                    was close to the Scene of Battle, it encreas’d the Confusion when an impetuous
                    Enemy poured down upon them and broke their Ranks.</p>
                <p>The unfortunate Event might have been prevented in two ways. He might have pass’d
                    the <placeName ref="pl1129">River Gary</placeName> immediately on leaving the
                    Defile, when He could have drawn up his Army on a Rising Ground with the River
                        <pb n="f.43r"/> in their Front, and so render’d the attack of the
                    Highlanders, who depended on their broad swords, useless and dangerous: by
                    keeping them for a long time expose to a galling and destructive Musquetry, in
                    which his Men must have been superior, as more steady and practiced.</p>
                <p>The other Mode was to have maintaind a running Battle on the same Plain where the
                    Struggle took place, and in the Course of 2 Miles’ March He would have arriv’d
                    on a level Ground, with sufficient space for 50,000 men to act. This was the
                    last of the great Actions perform’d by the Highlanders, as <persName ref="pe0549">Dundee</persName> is the last of those Heroes whose memory they
                    cherish with a fond and superstitious Veneration. <pb n="f.43v"/> Tradition has
                    here conferr’d on one man at least a local Immortality. His Name was <persName ref="pe0551">Donald Gorme</persName>: it appears that He was a Man of great
                    bodily Strength, as well as of Courage: during the Flight of <persName ref="pe0550">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Kay’s</persName> Men across the
                    River He planted himself in the place where there was the greatest Press, and
                    was observ’d to cut down 13 Men with his Claymore: but a Horseman from the
                    opposite side who had recover’d from his Pannic took a fatal aim at Him, and
                    shot him dead.</p>
                <p>August 25<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> Walked to <placeName ref="pl1130">Dalnacardoc</placeName>
                    <lb/>26<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> To <placeName ref="pl1131">Dalwhinie</placeName> by the <placeName ref="pl1132">Glen of
                        Dramoochquhar</placeName>. <lb/>27<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> To
                        <persName ref="pl0198">Fort Augustus</persName> over the tremendous
                        <persName ref="pl1133">Mountain of Corriaarack</persName>, and crossing
                        <placeName ref="pl0143">my Native River the Spey</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl1134">Garviemore</placeName>. These 3 Stages and particularly <pb n="f.44r"/>the last are over a wild and barbarous Country: the Road from
                        <placeName ref="pl1131">Dalwhinie</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0198">F.
                        Augustus</placeName> is shocking.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl0198">The Fort</placeName> is in a beautiful situation at one
                    end of the <placeName ref="pl0193">Loch Ness</placeName>: the Garrisoning of it
                    is now a mere Formality</p>
                <p>August 28. Walk’d to the <placeName ref="pl0196">Fall of Fyers</placeName> the
                    greatest in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>. The whole Body of the
                        <placeName ref="pl1660">River <unclear reason="illegible">Fechloyn</unclear></placeName> is confin’d at the Top between two Rocks,
                    forming a very narrow Passage for the Water, which is precipitated from this
                    Place to an amazing Depth<hi rend="superscript">x</hi><note type="authorial">(x
                        200 feet.)</note> below, and enlarging it’s Dimensions at it descends; until
                    it is plunged and swallow’s up in a deep Gulf, the water of which is so
                    infuriated, and throws up such Volumes of spray, that it’s surface cannot be
                    seen. <pb n="f.44v"/>As far as I could judge by the Eye it was double the Height
                    of the three Columns that compose <placeName ref="pl0594">the Fall at
                        Stone-Byers</placeName>.</p>
                <p>This Night I slept at a miserable Hut on a Bed of Straw and Pillow of Fern, with
                    a Coarse Blanket under me, and two by way of Cover: I could in the Morning see
                    Parts of the Landscape through many a cranny in the walls, and there was
                    abundance of Light from above. It was however the ordinary Repose of a Celtick
                    Beauty, Daughter of the woman of the House, who probably was better accommodated
                    than thousands of her Countrywomen. Fatigue like Virtue is its Reward for I
                    never slept sounder.</p>
                <p>August 29. Walked to <placeName ref="pl0156">Inverness</placeName> along
                        <placeName ref="pl0193">the Loch</placeName>, which was uniformly grand: the
                    Road in general good, and <sic>semingly</sic>
                    <pb n="f.45r"/>made with prodigious Difficulty, running over solid Rock for a
                    great way, blown and levell’d on purpose. — Arrived in <placeName ref="pl0156">Inverness</placeName>.</p>
                <p>This Place may be stiled the Capital of <placeName ref="pl0711">the
                        Highlands</placeName> as it takes the lead of every other in this District
                    of the Country in Population, in Trade and in Fashion. The Number and Burden of
                    the Shipping in the Harbour did not seem to indicate any considerable Commerce,
                    and I believe the chief Article of Export if Salmon of which they send a great
                    Quantity to <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> and Foreign
                    Countries</p>
                <p>The Country around <placeName ref="pl0156">Inverness</placeName> is beautiful and
                    fertile; they were going on briskly with their Harvest at this time <pb n="f.45v"/>and had gotten the start of their Southern Neighbours by a
                    Fortnight. This superior Earliness of the Harvest is owing to their dry
                    Situation and Proximity to the Sea. — The Town itself is neither large, nor well
                    built, nor very clean owing to it’s being in a low Situation. There is a
                    singular Hill called the <placeName ref="pl0822">Tomanewry</placeName> which is
                    a great ornament to it’s Neighbourhood. It is completely detached from any other
                    Eminence, is cover’d with a beautiful Wood, and exactly resembles a Ship’s Hull
                    with the Keel uppermost. Between <placeName ref="pl0198">F<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> augustus</placeName> and this Place I saw a Hill not a little
                    resembling <placeName ref="pl1104">the Rock of Dunbarton</placeName>, much of
                    the same size and like it completely insulated.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.46r"/><placeName ref="pl1135">The Castle of Inverness</placeName> is now
                    completely ruined, and it’s Fate was rather singular; for it did not perish by a
                    gradual decay, but fell by the Effect of a Frost in one enormous Mass. in it
                        <persName ref="pe0552">Duncan King of Scots</persName> was murder’d by
                        <persName ref="pe0553">the Usurper M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>Beth</persName>, an Event immortalized in <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0570">one of the most exalted Productions of Human
                            Genius</title></bibl>.</p>
                <p>As this place is well calculated as a Resort for Education to the Young Highland
                    Gentry, an Academy has lately been endow’d here by Subscription, where the same
                    mode of Education is pursued which prevails in the Scotch Colleges. I should
                    regard the Man who would found a College in this Remote Corner of <placeName ref="pl1136">the United Kingdoms</placeName> as entitled to the Veneration
                    and Gratitude of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>, <pb n="f.46v"/>and an essential Benefactor to the whole Island.</p>
                <p>Aug<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> 31<hi rend="superscript">st.</hi> Left
                        <placeName ref="pl0156">Inverness</placeName> on my Route to <placeName ref="pl0153">Fort George</placeName>, passing over a most dreary Region of
                    Silence, Barrenness and Horror. About 4 Miles from the Fort I met with a
                    Curiosity the chief perhaps of it’s kind in <placeName ref="pl0777">the Island
                        of Great Britain</placeName>. It is a Cromleach composed of two Concentric
                    Circles, the exterior of which measured in Diameter 35 of my Paces or 83 feet:
                    the Stones, of which there was a prodigious number, were of incredible size, and
                    must have been brought from a considerable distance, for I could see no Place in
                    the Neighbourhood where it was likely that they were produced.<note type="editorial">Possibly a description of the stone circles and chambered
                        cairns at <placeName ref="pl1661">Balnuaran Of Clava</placeName>, near Fort
                        George.</note> Surely we are accustom’d to hold distant Ages in excessive
                    and undeserv’d Contempt; for the <pb n="f.47r"/>Mechanical Skill required in
                    this Erection must have been very great, &amp; perhaps could not be exceeded in
                    modern times. — It was mention’d to me that in those Places of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> where Cromleachs are found the Inhabitants
                    in the Neighbourhood can assign by tradition a Name to every Stone, which is a
                    Designation of it’s particular Purpose or use in the general assemblage: such as
                    the Stone of Sacrifices (which were unquestionably Human): Stone of the Altar
                    &amp;c.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl0153">Fort George</placeName> in which I slept this Night is a
                    beautiful, regular and strong Fortification, and constructed according to the
                    System of <persName ref="pe0554">Vauban</persName>. The Barracks are built in 3
                    Quadrangles inside of the Fort and under cover, their Roofs <pb n="f.47v"/>being
                    no higher than the Ramparts, and the Casemates and Magazines are Bombproof.
                    There is a most delightful Walk round the Ramparts.</p>
                <p>The 3 Forts along the Lochs were at first intended to repress the disaffected
                    spirit of the Highlanders, by introducing a Military Force into the very Vitals
                    of their Country, and cutting off the Communication between the Northern and
                    Western Clans: but soon after this Scheme was executed, there arose a Man who
                    went far beyond the Views of Vulgar Politicians, and knew that the mind was not
                    to be subdued by external Force.<persName ref="pe0245">Lord Chatham</persName>
                    in the War which He so successfully conducted against <placeName ref="pl0925">France</placeName> would not allow the martial Disposition of the
                    Highlanders to lie dormant and <pb n="f.48r"/> useless, but gave Commissions to
                    their Chiefs who accordingly brought their adherents into the Army, and ever
                    since they have been as zealous in the Service of the House of Brunswick as they
                    were formerly in their Devotion to the Stuarts.</p>
                <p>On my way to <placeName ref="pl0153">Fort George</placeName> I view’d <placeName ref="pl0155">the Scene of Battle fought on Culloden Moor</placeName> on
                        16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Apl 1764: a Day which annihilated the Glory
                    of one of the most illustrious Families that Europe had ever known, over which
                    Fortune had exercis’d a Capricious and Tyrannical Sway: the Individuals as well
                    as the whole Race having <add place="above">alternately</add> enjoy’d her
                    Smiles, and been subject to her Scourge; and as the Morning of their Lives rose
                    with Transcendant Splendor, so it was <pb n="f.48v"/>generally overtaken by a
                    premature and disastrous Obscurity.<note type="authorial">After the Battle of
                            <placeName ref="pl0155">Culloden</placeName>
                        <persName ref="pe0559">the defeated Prince</persName> was guarded by
                            <persName ref="pe0560">a Highlander of the Name of McKian (or
                            Kennedy)</persName>. This Man’s Conduct affords a most illustrious
                        Example of Highland Courage and Fidelity. He expos’d his Life in every shape
                        to maintain Him in his concealment: He stole plunder’d and robb’d for this
                        pupose, when He Knew that by betraying his trust He could gain £30,000. At
                        last after He had effected his Escape, being impell’d by the direst
                        Necessity, in order to maintain his Family, He stole a Cow for which He was
                        tried and hang’d at <placeName ref="pl0156">Inverness</placeName>. <persName ref="pe0561">George the II<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi></persName> who
                        could prize this Man’s Qualities. although an Enemy, declared if He had
                        known the Circumstances sooner He would have placed Him beyond the Reach of
                        Poverty. Before his Execution He made a Declaration which seems to be equal
                        to any thing ever utter’d by a dying Hero or Philosopher in Ancient or
                        Modern Times. He took off his Bonnet, and said He thank’d God that <p><quote>
                                <lb/>“He never betray’d a Trust, never injured the <lb/>“Poor, and
                                never refused a Share <lb/>“of what He had to the Stranger <lb/>“and
                                Helpless”. </quote></p></note></p>
                <p>It may be safely pronounced that the Issue of that Rebellion was highly
                    beneficial to <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>. The Mortification of
                    the severe Defeat which they had sustain’d sunk deeply in the Minds of the
                    Highland Clans, and made them regard all further Resistance to the Establish’d
                    Government as desperate and unavailing. An arm’d Force was introduced into their
                    Country and for the first time a standing Army watch’d all their Motions, and
                    render’d any Combination among them impossible. The Legislature had a Pretence,
                    and possess’d the Abiltiy to crush those Allodial Jurisdictions exercised by the
                    Chieftans of the <pb n="f.49r"/>different Clans, which made every one of them
                    regard it’s own Head as their only Legitimate Ruler; and their Duty to Him often
                    superseded every Obligation of Loyalty and Justice. As soon as this Power was
                    withdrawn ––––– the spirit of Clanship and enthusiastick atttachment to their
                    Hereditary Leaders immediately began to decay: for although the Indigenous
                    Spirit of every Tribe, and it’s separate and exclusive Union together with their
                    general Love of Ancestry still remain’d, yet their Chiefs thus stripp’d of
                    Authority could no longer inspire Terror, the commanding Principle of Political
                    Obedience, and even of affection among Men. This Constitution of Clanship was
                    very inconsistent, or rather <pb n="f.49v"/>absolutely incompatible with Civil
                    Government, every Part in such a System having <sic>irreconcileable</sic>
                    Prejudices, and considering it’s own Interests as totally separated from the
                    General Welfare. It besides nourish’d a martial or rather a ferocious
                    Disposition among the Highlanders, being the source of numberless &amp; immortal
                    Broils, which were continually calling forth their Exertions against each other.
                    But this Disposition became extremely formidable when, as was frequently the
                    case, it was exercised in Rebellion against the Sovereign Power of the Country:
                    it was for centuries the Scourge and Terror of the Government in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>, nor can we regard the Highland Clans as
                    forming a united and effective Branch of the Scottish Nation under it’s Old
                    Kings.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.50r"/> Now that these Mountaineers enjoy a Community of Privileges with
                    their Fellow Subjects, and as their Ancient Habits decline they discover every
                    day a greater Aptitude for Civil Government &amp; Society. It makes People of
                    inferior Understanding Smile to observe, that so great a Genius as <persName ref="pe0127">Lord Kaimes</persName> should lament the decay of their Warlike
                        Disposition,<note type="editorial">Probably a reference to Kames's <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0571"><hi rend="italic">Sketches of the
                                    History of Man</hi></title>, <biblScope unit="volume">Volume
                            </biblScope>, <biblScope unit="page">p.</biblScope></bibl>.</note> and
                    consider that part of their Character as most meritorious which for Ages
                    involved themselves and their Country in perpetual Confusion: but they still
                    retain Qualities which constitute them excellent Soldiers, Courage, Obedience,
                    Fidelity and Perseverance.</p>
                <p>The Battle which seems for ever <add place="above">to have</add> decided their
                    Fate was fought <pb n="f.50v"/> on <placeName ref="pl0155">an extensive
                        Moor</placeName> open in all directions for many Miles; a fair Field of
                    Contention where there was neither Advantage to the Victors nor Retreat for the
                    Vanquish’d. It was fought in a manner characteristick of the different Qualities
                    of the two Contending Nations; on the part of the Highlanders with a generous
                    &amp; impetuous Valour, opposed by the other army with a cool and determin’d
                    Bravery.</p>
                <p>In this route through the <placeName ref="pl0711">Highlands</placeName> beginning
                    at <placeName ref="pl0226">Dunbarton</placeName> &amp; ending at <placeName ref="pl0156">Inverness</placeName> the Roads are excellent with the
                    Exception of that from <placeName ref="pl0212">Tayndrum</placeName> to
                        <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName>, and from <placeName ref="pl1134">Garviemore</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0198">F<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Augustus</placeName>, the first 22 the other 18 Miles. These
                    are called <pb n="f.51r"/> Military Roads, having been executed by the different
                    Regiments stationed in the Country after the Rebellion. The Expence was defray’d
                    out of the Income of the Forfeited Estates and a Sum has been funded, annually
                    producing £5000, at the disposal of Commissioners, for their Repair. They were
                    intended for the wise purpose of facilitating the Intercourse between Remote
                    Country and the other Parts of the Island, and perhaps to make it more
                    accessible in case of Rebellion. How far this Measure may tend to produce an
                    Identity of Language, Manners, and Modes of Thinking between the Highlanders and
                    their Southern Neighbours it is not easy to ascertain: but it certainly will
                    require <pb n="f.51v"/>a great length of Time, perhaps Ages, for that purpose.
                    It is amazing over what a Tract of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>
                    the Gaëlick Language still extends. The Line of Demarcation between the two
                    Tongues seems to begin from <placeName ref="pl0153">S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> George,</placeName> going by <placeName ref="pl1137">Nairn</placeName>, and then South East 20 Miles West of <placeName ref="pl0145">Elgin</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl0144">Fochabers</placeName> thence by <placeName ref="pl0116">Bremar</placeName>
                    on the <placeName ref="pl1138">River Dee</placeName>, from thence all along the
                    Western Boundary of <placeName ref="pl0733">Angus Shire</placeName>, and then in
                    a Straight line to <placeName ref="pl0226">Dunbarton</placeName>; a Tract equal
                    to two thirds of the whole Extent of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>: all to the North and West of this Boundary speak
                    Gaelick.</p>
                <p>along this Route we found the People universally attentive, civil, and obliging,
                    with something of a Gentility of Manner <pb n="f.52r"/>and Behaviour not to be
                    met with in the <placeName ref="pl1139">Lowlands</placeName>. Indeed from the
                        <placeName ref="pl1140">Borders</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0226">Dunbarton</placeName> they seem’d to possess little of the Character of the
                    North: they were sullen, sulky and uncivil; a character which I am afraid is too
                    just when applied to most of the Southern Scots. From <placeName ref="pl0226">Dunbarton</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0156">Inverness</placeName> by a
                    Route 251 Miles in length I was never once solicited for charity although I met
                    Multitudes of needy Objects. Many of Them who have come a very considerable
                    Distance (sometimes about 2 Miles) to point out the way would not accept of
                    money when offer’d to them; which I believe would rarely occur south of the <pb n="f.52v"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0727">Tweed</placeName>. I have a pleasure in bearing this
                    Testimony to the Character of a Peo<add place="above">ple</add> who among us are
                    prejudg’d, and look’d on as a race of Savages and Enemies to every Civil Virtue.
                    Whoever can travel in this Country with Indifference has neither Eyes to see,
                    nor a Heart to feel. Great Caution is to be observ’d in taking the Report of the
                    Highlanders and Lowlanders relating to each other: there prevails between them
                    an inveterate &amp; illiberal Antipathy, similar to Protestants and Roman
                    Catholicks in <placeName ref="pl0889">Ireland</placeName>, nor do I know of any
                    other Parallell in this respect of the three Kingdoms.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.53r"/> September 1<hi rend="superscript">st.</hi> Walk’d to <placeName ref="pl0148">Forres</placeName>. It is a neat clean Town, and situated in a
                    Rich and Delightful Country. The View from some Eminences in the Neighbourhood
                    extends over almost the whole Rich and Productive Plain of <placeName ref="pl1141">Murray Shire</placeName>, the Granary of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>, and the finest Corn Country in <placeName ref="pl0777">the Island of Great Britain</placeName>: we saw a most
                    extensive Range of dry and level Country cover’d with Fields of Wheat, Oats, and
                    Barley and deficient in Nothing by Pasturage which seems to be comparatively
                        trifling.<note type="authorial">Many Years ago the Estate of <placeName ref="">Culbane</placeName> extending many miles along the Sea Coast from
                            <placeName ref="">Findhorn</placeName> to <placeName ref="">Nairn</placeName> was completely overwhelm’d with Sand by a Tempest in
                        the Sea.</note><note type="editorial">The 'inundation' of coastal land by
                        sand dunes was noted by travellers as a cause for environmental concern.
                        Thomas Pennant describes the appearance of this phenomenon at Findhorn in
                            <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0001">A tour in Scotland
                                1769</title></bibl> (1771), pp.131-32.</note> An English Spectator
                    would be very much deceiv’d in estimating the Riches of this fine Province: for
                    altho’ the whole surface of the Soil which is <pb n="f.53v"/> deep and
                    luxuriant, is cover’d with the most abundant Crops, yet, owing to the want of
                    Hedges and Inclosures as in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> where
                    they sometimes disguise a natural Sterility of the Country, the Prospect has a
                    bare and naked Aspect. This View comprehends the Hills of <placeName ref="pl1142">Rossshire</placeName>, the Entrance of the Famous <placeName ref="pl1143">Bay of Cromarty</placeName>; the Country in the Neighbourhood
                    of <placeName ref="pl0156">Inverness</placeName>, and <placeName ref="pl0153">S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> George</placeName>; the <placeName ref="pl1144">Town &amp; Harbour of Findhorn</placeName>, and the bold
                    Promontory of <placeName ref="pl1145">Brough Head</placeName>. This last is the
                        <placeName ref="pl1010">Gibraltar</placeName> of <placeName ref="pl1141">Murray-Shire</placeName>. As this Part of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> was the chief Theatre of the Ravages of the Danes they
                    fortified this Peninsula very strongly on the Landside, and towards the Sea it
                    was naturally impregnable, being <pb n="f.54r"/> surrounded with deep water with
                    an excellent Harbour that afforded Shelter to the Ships which transported those
                    destructive Hordes of Free-booters. This was always their last refuge in case of
                    Misfortune and Defeat: as they were Masters of the Sea it was impossible for the
                    Scots to cut off their Retreat, or prevent their landing in that way. West of
                        <placeName ref="pl0148">Forres</placeName> stand the <placeName ref="pl1146">Remains of a Palace</placeName> of <persName ref="pe1015">King
                        Duffus</persName>.</p>
                <p>About ¾ of a Mile E. from <placeName ref="pl0148">Forres</placeName> there is a
                    singular Curiosity, which has generally attracted the Notice of Travellers, and
                    long employ’d the Conjectures of Historians and Antiquaries. It is a <placeName ref="pl0147">Stone Column</placeName> of the amazing Height of 23 Feet and
                    an <pb n="f.54v"/>Experiment having been made some Years <add place="above">ago</add> to ascertain the Foundation, they dug to the Depth of 14 Feet
                    finding the Stone still entire, when the Attempt was given up. The Pillar is
                    about a Yard broad, and about 9 Inches in thickness. The Surface towards the
                    North is cover’d with sculpture merely ornamental, without any particular
                    Design. The opposite or South Side seems intended to convey the Historical
                    Design of the Erection. It is divided into 3 Partitions or compartments. The
                    lowest contains on the right hand side some Human Figures, and on the left 3
                    Lions passant: the 2<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> is the most inexplicable: on
                    the right hand are a <pb n="f.55"/><note type="editorial">An engraving of the
                        Pillar of Forres with a maid milking a cow and the town in the distance is
                        pasted into the journal here with the print partly visible through the
                        verso-side of the folio it is attached to. The publication from which the
                        image has been taken has not been identified. The printed title of the image
                        is ‘FORRES’; below the image are the names of the artist and engraver: ‘A.
                        Grant del.’ and ‘F.Cary.Sculp’.</note>
                    <pb n="f.56r"/>number of Arm’d Men; on left an equal Number lying as if dead; in
                    the middle Representation of a Tower or Castle with two Figures like Lions
                    attempting to enter it’s Gate: in the middle of the highest Division there
                    stands a supereminent Figure of a larger Size, and seemingly better executed
                    than the Rest in a complete Highland Garb. This circumstance determines me to
                    believe that it is a Scottish, and not a Danish Monument, notwithstanding many
                    Opinions to the contrary. This Part of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> was the Scene of such a multitude of interesting
                    Events, that, if we pretend to assign the precise Circumstance which it is
                    intended to <pb n="f.56v"/>commemorate, we must depend entirely on arbitrary and
                    lawless Conjecture.</p>
                <p>On my way to <placeName ref="pl0148">Forres</placeName> I stopt at <placeName ref="pl1147">Calder</placeName>, and saw <placeName ref="pl0152">the
                        Castle</placeName>. In the Inside and Center of the Building there stands
                    the stem of a Thorn Tree, said to be coeval with the Foundation of the Castle;
                    but by what whim it was placed there, is not precisely known. On the Top of this
                    Castle there is a Room to which we ascend by a Ladder over the Roof where
                        <persName ref="pe0154">Simon Lord Lovat</persName> was concealed after the
                    Battle of <placeName ref="pl0155">Culloden</placeName>.</p>
                <p>In one of the Rooms is preserv’d the Bed on which <persName ref="pe0552">Duncan</persName> was murder’d by <persName ref="pe0553">MacBeth</persName>: the Sculpture of it is Rich but artless, and very much in
                    the Stile of that <pb n="f.57r"/>on the <placeName ref="pl0147">Pillar at
                        Forres</placeName>: the ornamental part especially, where there were no
                    Figures, was exactly the same in both, nor do I know what Inference to draw from
                    the similarity.</p>
                <p>Sept<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> 3<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> Walk’d to
                        <placeName ref="pl0145">Elgin</placeName>. This Place is but the Shadow of
                    what it was.<note type="authorial">There are various Conjectures concerning the
                        Derivation of <placeName ref="pl0145">Elgin</placeName>. The most probable
                        seems to be that it was named after <persName ref="pe1022">Helgey</persName>
                        General of <placeName ref="pe1023">Sigurd King of Norway</placeName> who
                        conquer’d <placeName ref="pl1141">Murrayshire</placeName> in 927. and is
                        said to have built a Town in the Southern Part of it. It was anciently
                        written <placeName ref="pl0145">Helgeyn</placeName> or <placeName ref="pl0145">Helgun</placeName>.</note><note type="editorial">For a
                        similar etymology of Elgin see Sir John Sinclair's <bibl type="editorial">
                            <title ref="bi0169"><hi rend="italic">Statistical Account of
                                    Scotland</hi></title> 21 vols (Edinburgh: 1791-1799), <biblScope unit="volume">v</biblScope>,<biblScope unit="page">
                            p.2</biblScope>.</bibl></note> The great number of Remains of Ancient
                    Buildings which it contains give it a melancholy Aspect, but sufficiently
                    indicate what it was in the flourishing Days of it’s Wealth and Splendor. It has
                    greatly declined in consequence and Population; for about 40 Years ago it had
                    6306 Inhabitants, at present it has only 4534. The Country in it’s Neighbourhood
                    is exceedingly rich, and well cultivated. <pb n="f.57v"/>Here I view’d
                        <placeName ref="pl1148">the Magnificent Ruins of the
                    Cathedral</placeName></p>
                <p>The Western Front or Grand Entrance consists of two Square Towers, and between
                    these there is a Door with fine cluster’d Gothick Pilasters, supporting a Rich
                    and corresponding Arch. Half way between these Towers and the Eastern End, or
                    Termination of the Chapel, there are two others facing the North and South
                    projecting to a small distance on each side, so as to form a Cross with the Body
                    of the Cathedral, and their Fronts appear to be double of those of the Western
                    Entrance. Beyond these it narrows considerably forming the chancel which is the
                        <pb n="f.58r"/>most entire Part of the Building: it’s Eastern Extremity has
                    5 large Windows in the lower part, as many smaller over them, the whole
                    surmounted by a noble and circular one.</p>
                <p>Between the middle Towers and the End of the Chancel there is a Projection on
                    each side of a singular kind, which when entire, must have been very grand. One
                    of these is no more, and can only be known to have existed by Analogy from
                    seeing the other, which is in a tolerable State of Preservation. It consists of
                    a straight Part issuing at Right Angles from the Body of the Chancel, and
                    terminating in an Octagon Tower; in the inside of which there is a Masterly
                    Achievement <pb n="f.58v"/>of Gothick architecture, which is a Massy Dome of
                    Stone centrally supported by a single slender and beautiful Pillar, similar to
                    that which supports the Lobby of <placeName ref="pl1149">Christ Church Hall in
                        Oxford</placeName>. The Windows and ornaments in the Inside of the
                    Cathedral, and especially the Chapel are of the most beautiful, chaste and at
                    the same <add place="above">time</add> fanciful Designs; and the trifling
                    Remains of the Arches are just sufficient to inform us what they have been.</p>
                <p>The View of these Ruins as associated with a Retrospect of the Past presents one
                    of the most afflicting spectacles. This magnificent Temple, dedicated to
                    Religion, the Boast of a Kingdom, and the Wonder of Ages, lies now a most
                    deplorable <pb n="f.59r"/> Wreck. — The two Towers on the West Entrance are so
                    loose, broken and disjointed that it appears with difficulty they can support
                    themselves, and I believe that a few Shocks of a Cannon Ball would hurl them
                    both in Ruins. On the North side, intervening between the Western Extremity and
                    the Chapel only one solitary Pillar remains. In the Inside huge Masses of the
                    fallen Walls, some of them equal to the Burden of a large Ship lie heap’d on
                    each other with the most ruinous Confusion. The Churchyard is cover’d with
                    Showers of Fragments that have fallen from time to time, some of which have
                    broken through large Grave Stones and buried themselves in the Earth. It appears
                    fast approaching the Verge of Annihilation <pb n="f.59v"/>and that no Part of it
                    can stand for many Years.</p>
                <p>This Cathedral was first built in 1224, but was destroy’d by a Goth named
                        <persName ref="pe0555">Alexander Lord of Badanoch</persName>, I suppose an
                    Ancestor of <persName ref="pe0088">the present Duke of Gordon</persName>. It was
                    rebuilt in 1414. It is 260 Feet in Length by 34.</p>
                <p>About 6 Miles from <placeName ref="pl0145">Elgin</placeName> stand <placeName ref="pl1163">the Ruins of Pluscardine Abbey</placeName>, which are very
                    grand. it is situated on a small Eminence. The Body of the Building runs North
                    and South, the chapel or church projecting Eastward from it, and terminated on
                    the West Side by a Square Tower. To the North and South a Part of the Main Body
                    of the Building is set off, and joins the Tower, ––––– equal to <pb n="f.60r"/>the Chapel in Elevation and considerably higher than the other Parts, so that
                    assuming the Tower is the Center It has the appearance of 3 Sides of a Maltese
                    Cross, and forms no bad Effect. The Rest of the Ruins seem to bespeak it
                    formerly to have been a Place of considerable Beauty and Consequence.</p>
                <p>About a Mile and a half eastward from <placeName ref="pl0145">Elgin</placeName>
                    we come to <placeName ref="pl1150">the Beautiful Loch of Speynie</placeName>, on
                    the Borders of which there stand <placeName ref="pl1151">the massy Remains of a
                        Palace</placeName>, improperly call’d a Castle, the residence formerly of
                    the Bishops of <placeName ref="pl1141">Murray</placeName>. The Loch is many
                    Miles in Extent, and is cover’d with Wild Ducks and Geese: and is remarkable for
                    being the Resort <pb n="f.60v"/>of the Wild Swans which generally come here
                    about the latter End of September to winter on the Lake. In the Neighbourhood
                        <del rend="overstrike">some</del> some Parts of the Soil are so excellent,
                    that they appear equal if not superior to that of <placeName ref="pl1172">the
                        Vale of White Horse in Berkshire</placeName>, supposed to be the finest in
                        <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Sept<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> 4<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> Pass’d
                        <placeName ref="pl0143">the Spey</placeName> within Gunshot of the Place,
                    celebrated for two great &amp; similar Events; where <persName ref="pe1016">Malcolm Kanmore, King of Scotland</persName>, cross’d the River to subdue
                    the Rebellious Clans of the North; and where the <persName ref="pe0556">Duke of
                        Cumberland</persName> pass’d in 1746 to a similar Encounter. Close to this
                    Passage stands <placeName ref="pl0144">the Village of Fochabers</placeName>,
                    built within 10 Years past upon a regular Plan, and very neat. At a small
                    distance stands <pb n="f.61r"/>the superb Edifice of <placeName ref="pl0142">Gordon Castle</placeName> with it’s fine Grounds and Romantick Walks. About
                    4 Miles East of <placeName ref="pl0144">Fochabers</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl0143">the Mouth of the Spey</placeName> there is a Dock or Harbour
                    call’d <placeName ref="pl1152">Kingston Port</placeName>, where shops are built
                    of as large a Size as any in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> and
                    entirely of Firs floated down the River from <placeName ref="pl1153">the Forest
                        of Glenmore</placeName>. There was one upon the stocks at this time of 700.
                    Tons burden. The Forest has been purchas’d by an English Company for a certain
                    Term of Years, and it is calculated that they float down 12,000 Pieces in a Year
                    for sale independant of the Timber employ’d in Ship building.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.61v"/>
                    <pb n="f.62r"/>
                    <pb n="f.62v"/> Walk’d to <placeName ref="pl0128">Aberdeen</placeName> by
                        <placeName ref="pl0141">Cullen</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl0139">Portsoy</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl0136"><sic>Bamff</sic></placeName>,
                        <placeName ref="pl1154"><unclear>Turreff</unclear></placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1155">Old-Meldrum</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1156">Peterhead</placeName>.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl0141">Cullen</placeName> is a small Place of inconsiderable
                    Population or Trade. A Manufacture of Linen was establish’d and encouraged here
                    by <persName ref="pe1017">the late Earl of Findlater</persName>, but It has
                    never arrived to any Extent.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl0136">Banff</placeName> is pleasantly situated on the Sea Side
                    round a capacious Harbour, and carries on a comparatively considerable Trade.
                    The Country in this Quarter, and especially about <placeName ref="pl0141">Cullen</placeName>, is pleasant and cultivated.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1154"><unclear>Turress</unclear></placeName> is a small and
                    mean Place, and <placeName ref="pl1155">Old-Meldrum</placeName> the most <pb n="f.63r"/>wretched, to deserve the Name of a Town, which I have seen in the
                    North.</p>
                <p>This Part of <placeName ref="pl0732">Aberdeenshire</placeName> looks bare and
                    miserable; and still more so as we exchange the fertile Plains of <placeName ref="pl1141">Murray</placeName> for this uncouth and sterile Scene. The
                    Country is by no means deficient in Natural Advantages, the soil appearing to be
                    good and practicable, although much neglected. The Lands and Farms are laid out
                    in a slovenly manner, and betray in the Owners a Want of Capital or
                    Encouragement; or shameful Negligence and Ignorance of Agriculture; or perhaps
                    all these <pb n="f.63v"/>Disadvantages united</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl0128">Aberdeen</placeName> in point of Size, Population and
                    Trade is rank’d as the third City in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>. It is divided into 2 Parts the Old and New Town which
                    taken together extend from the mouth of <placeName ref="pl1157">River
                        Don</placeName> on the North to that of <placeName ref="pl1138">the
                        Dee</placeName> on the South about 2 Miles Distance, and within this compass
                    there are calculated to be 30,000 Inhabitants. The Town stands on a Hill which
                    slopes gradually towards the west and terminates suddenly and abruptly <del rend="overstrike">
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" quantity="1"/>
                    </del>on the Eastern side, on which stand the remains of <placeName ref="pl1158">the Castle</placeName>.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.64r"/>The Harbour is capacious but somewhat difficult of Access and does
                    not admit Vessels of more than 500 Tones burden.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.64v"/>
                    <pb n="f.65r"/>
                    <pb n="f.65v"/>
                    <pb n="f.66r"/>
                    <pb n="f.66v"/>
                    <pb n="f.67r"/></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Journal of the Prince’s Escape after the Battle of Culloden.
                        –––––</hi></p>
                <p>16<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> April 1746.</p>
                <p>Was taken off the Field by <persName ref="pe0560">Major Kennedy</persName>, while
                    the French &amp; scotch Troops Kept <persName ref="pe0556">the Duke of
                        Cumberland</persName> at bay Here He gave Orders for his Army to disperse.
                    17. Went to <placeName ref="pl1159"><unclear>Tordarack</unclear></placeName>, 9
                    miles from <placeName ref="pl0156">Inverness</placeName>. To <placeName ref="pl1160">Aberardar</placeName> in M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>In<unclear reason="illegible">tosh’s</unclear> Country 3 Miles.
                        <placeName ref="pl1662">Farlone</placeName> in Lovat’s Country &amp; thence
                    1 Mile more to <placeName ref="pl1663">Castlelaige or Gortulaige</placeName>,
                    where They met <persName ref="pe0154">L<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi>
                        Lovat</persName> &amp; drank a few Glasses of Wine. The Persons who
                    accompanied were; <persName ref="pe1018">Sir Thomas Sheridan</persName>;
                        <persName ref="pe1020">Sir David Murray</persName>; <persName ref="pe1019">Alexander M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Leod</persName>: <persName ref="pe0107">John Hay</persName>; <persName ref="pe0186">Edward
                        Burk</persName>; <persName ref="pe1021">Allan M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald</persName><note type="editorial">This appears to be a precis
                        of <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0167"><hi rend="italic">A Plain,
                                    Authentic and Faithful Narrative of the Passages of the Young
                                    Chevalier &amp;c.</hi></title> (London: 1750)</bibl>.</note></p>
                <p><pb n="f.67v"/>
                    <pb n="f.68r"/>
                    <pb n="f.68v"/>
                    <pb n="f.69r"/>
                    <pb n="f.69v"/>
                    <pb n="f.70r"/>
                    <pb n="f.70v"/>
                    <pb n="f.71r"/>
                    <pb n="f.71v"/>
                    <pb n="f.72r"/>
                    <pb n="f.72v"/>
                    <pb n="f.73r"/></p>
                <p>Length of the Journey. Miles.</p>
                <p><list>
                        <item>August 1. <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0253">Carlisle</placeName> . . . . . 301</item>
                        <item>4. <placeName ref="pl0253">Carlisle</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0587">Douglas Mill</placeName></item>
                        <item>Walk’d. 5. <placeName ref="pl0587">Douglas Mill</placeName> to
                                <placeName ref="pl0590">Lanark</placeName> . . 9. <lb/><placeName ref="pl0591">Falls of Clyde</placeName> ……………. 8. <lb/><placeName ref="pl0590">Lanark</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0597">Hamilton</placeName> &amp;c. 21.</item>
                        <item>6.{<placeName ref="pl0597">Hamilton</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> by <lb/><placeName ref="pl0230">Bothwell Bridge</placeName> } 15.</item>
                        <item>8. To <placeName ref="pl1101">Kelvin Aqueduct</placeName> &amp; back .
                            . . 8.</item>
                        <item>9. <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0226">Dunbarton</placeName> . . . . 14.</item>
                        <item>10. <placeName ref="pl0226">Dunbarton</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0224">Luss</placeName> . . . . 13.</item>
                        <item>12. Ascent of <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben-Lomond</placeName> &amp;
                            down 6. <placeName ref="pl0224">Luss</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1008">Araquhar</placeName> . . . . . . 12.</item>
                        <item>13. <placeName ref="pl1008">Arroquhar</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1069">Carndoo</placeName> . . 12.</item>
                        <item>14. <placeName ref="pl1069">Carndoo</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1072">Inverary</placeName> . . .7.</item>
                        <item>15. <placeName ref="pl1072">Inverary</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0214">Dalmallie</placeName> . . 16.</item>
                        <item>16. To <placeName ref="pl0215">Kilchurn</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl0272">Fraöchlyn Castles</placeName> 10.</item>
                        <item>17. <placeName ref="pl0214">Dalmallie</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0212">Tayndrum</placeName> .. 12.</item>
                        <item>18. <placeName ref="pl0212">Tayndrum</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName> . . . 22.</item>
                        <item>Carried over . . . . . . 185</item>
                        <pb n="f.73v"/>
                        <item>August 1794. Bro<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> over . . . . . . . . .
                            . 185.</item>
                        <item> Walk’d. 19. To <placeName ref="pl1119">Lochay Falls</placeName> and
                            back. 6.</item>
                        <item>20. <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0103">Kenmore</placeName> . . . . . 16.</item>
                        <item>To <placeName ref="pl1122">L<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi>
                                Braidalbane’s Hermitage.</placeName> 4</item>
                        <item>21. <placeName ref="pl0103">Kenmore,</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0099">Dunkeld</placeName> . . . 24.</item>
                        <item>22. <placeName ref="pl0099">Dunkeld</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0110">Blair</placeName> . . . . 20.</item>
                        <item>23. To <placeName ref="pl0112">Killycrankie</placeName> . . . . .
                            7.</item>
                        <item>24. To <placeName ref="pl1130">Dalnacardoc</placeName> . . . . .
                            11.</item>
                        <item>25. To <placeName ref="pl1131">Dalwhinie</placeName> . . . . . .
                            13.</item>
                        <item>26. To <placeName ref="pl0198">F<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi>
                                Augustus</placeName> . . . . . . 31.</item>
                        <item> 27. To <placeName ref="pl0195">General’s Hut</placeName> . . . .
                            14.</item>
                        <item>28. To <placeName ref="pl0156">Inverness</placeName> . . . . . .
                            18.</item>
                        <item>31. To <placeName ref="pl0153">F<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi>
                                George</placeName> by <placeName ref="pl0155">Culloden</placeName>
                            16.</item>
                        <item>365.</item>
                        <item>September. <lb/>1. <placeName ref="pl0153">F<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> George</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0148">Forres</placeName> . . . . 24.</item>
                        <item>3. To <placeName ref="pl0145">Elgin</placeName> . . . . . . . .
                            12.</item>
                        <item>Carried over . . . . . . . . . 401.</item>
                        <pb n="f.74r"/>
                        <item>Bro<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> over . . . . . . . . 401.</item>
                        <item>4. To <placeName ref="pl0144">Fochabers</placeName> . . . . .
                            9.</item>
                        <item>6. To <placeName ref="pl1161">Walkerdale</placeName> . . . . .
                            6.</item>
                        <item>7. To <placeName ref="pl0144">Fochabers</placeName> . . . . . .
                            6.</item>
                        <item>To <placeName ref="pl1162">Garmouth</placeName> &amp;c.
                            ......10.</item>
                        <item>To <placeName ref="pl2496">Elchies</placeName> . . . . . . 12.</item>
                        <item>To <unclear reason="illegible"><placeName ref="pl0145">Elgin</placeName></unclear> by <placeName ref="pl1163">Pluscardine</placeName>. 24.</item>
                        <item><placeName ref="pl0144">Fochabers</placeName> . . . . . . . .
                            9.</item>
                        <item>To <placeName ref="pl0141">Cullen</placeName> . . . . . . 12.</item>
                        <item>To <placeName ref="pl0136">Banff</placeName> by <placeName ref="pl0139">Portsoy</placeName> . . . . .12.</item>
                        <item>To <placeName ref="pl1154">Turreff</placeName> . . . . . . . . .
                            10.</item>
                        <item>To <placeName ref="pl1155">Old Meldrum</placeName> . . . . .
                            18.</item>
                        <item>To <placeName ref="pl0128">Aberdeen</placeName> . . . . . . 17.</item>
                        <item>Total Walk’d on this Route . . . 546.</item>
                    </list>
                    <pb n="f.74v"/>
                    <pb n="f.75r"/>
                    <pb n="f.75v"/></p>
                <p>Notes &amp;c:</p>
                <p><pb n="f.76r"/> The Highlanders call <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0705">Alpin</placeName>, whc. signifies a Mountainous Country,
                    and was probably the original Name of the whole Island from which the Romans
                    deriv’d their <placeName ref="pl0777">Albion</placeName> The Name of that chain
                    of Mountains dividing <placeName ref="pl0925">France</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1164">Italy</placeName> viz: <placeName ref="pl1165">Alps</placeName>
                    is plainly of Celtick Extraction and synonimous with <placeName ref="pl0705">Alpin</placeName>. It is probable that the word <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> was originally <placeName ref="pl0705">Schôtte-land</placeName> which is tantamount in meaning to <placeName ref="pl0705">Alpin</placeName> for it is an obsolete German Vocable
                    signifying a Hill. It is not likely according to <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0569">Ossian McPherson’s</title></bibl> Supposition that it is
                    derived from Scuyth a Celtick word signifying a Wanderer, because it is uncommon
                    to incorporate Words of different Languages (Land being undoubtedly Saxon) and
                    because it is unnatural for any People to impose on their Country a Name
                    involving <pb n="f.76v"/>a stigma or reproach. <placeName ref="pl0700">The
                        Shetland Isles </placeName>(or Scotland Isles) still retain the old
                    Pronunciation.</p>
                <p>Most Names of Places in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> are Gaelick
                    Viz:</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1166">Grampian Hills</placeName>: from Grant, Great and Beinn
                    or Bean or Ben a Hill — <placeName ref="pl0815">Benmore</placeName> is the Great
                    Hill: <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben-lomond</placeName>, Bare green Hill:
                        <placeName ref="pl1167">Ben-ledy</placeName>, Holy Hill; <placeName ref="pl1168">Ben-venue</placeName>, small Hill.</p>
                <p>Dun is probably a Heap of Buildings or a Town thus we have <placeName ref="pl0076">Dun-Edin</placeName> or <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName>: <placeName ref="pl0226">Dun-barton</placeName>:
                        <placeName ref="pl0316">Dun-dee</placeName>: <placeName ref="pl0371">Dun-fermline</placeName> &amp;c.</p>
                <p>Don signifies a deep River.</p>
                <p>Glean or Glen signifies a valley open at both Ends: Strath a Valley through wc. a
                    River runs: Ach (Haugh) an extensive Flat.</p>
                <p>Crom is a Circle, Cromleach a Circle of Stones or Druidical Temple: The
                    Expression in Erse “are You going to <pb n="f.77r"/>Church”? signifies literally
                    “are You going to the stones.”?<note type="editorial">The source for this
                        translation is probably Pennant <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0001">A
                                tour in Scotland 1769</title></bibl> (1771), p.188, or Lachlan Shaw,
                            <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0081">The History of the Province
                                of Moray</title></bibl> (Edinburgh: 1775), p.230.</note> — I imagine
                    that the Devotion of the Druids consisted in Solar Worship: it is the most
                    natural of all superstitions. There is one Relick of it remaining in <placeName ref="pl0711">the Highlands</placeName> to the present Day called Baaltein
                    which signifies the Fire of Baal or the Sun. It is a ceremony perform’d on the
                        1<hi rend="superscript">st.</hi> of May. A number of People assemble and
                    bake a Cake in the open Air which they break into small bits, one of which is
                    blacked: they are put into a Bonnet, and every one draws one by chance, the
                    Person to whom the black Piece falls is obliged to jump 3 times over the Fire
                    but formerly it is probable, was consign’d to that Element as a Sacrifice to
                    their Deity <q>Tantum potuit Religio suadere malorum.</q><note type="editorial">Lucretius, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0638"><hi rend="italic">De
                                    Rerum Natura</hi></title><biblScope unit="book">I</biblScope>,
                                <biblScope unit="line">l.101.</biblScope></bibl> Translated as 'So
                        great the power religion had for evil', in Lucretius, <hi rend="italic">On
                            the Nature of the Universe</hi>, trans. by Ronald Melville (Oxford:
                        Oxford University Press, 1997).</note></p>
                <p><pb n="f.77v"/> Aber signifies Mouth: thus <placeName ref="pl0128">Aberdeen</placeName> means <placeName ref="pl1138">Mouth of the
                        Dee</placeName>: <placeName ref="pl0347">Abernethy</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1664">Abergeldy</placeName> &amp;c.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl0077">Leith</placeName> signifies Mouth of the Water.</p>
                <p>Ross means promontory: <placeName ref="pl0085">Kinross</placeName> Head of the
                    Promontory: <placeName ref="pl0323">Montrose</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl0323">Moin-ross</placeName>, Fenny Promontory.</p>
                <p>The Derivation of the Name of <placeName ref="pl1072">Inverary</placeName> is
                    very curious. It is Ion-ar-as-reidh in the Gaelick. Ion-ar (Inver) worthy of
                    Tillage from Ion-worthy and ar, to Till as-reidh (dh is pronounced as y) Mouth
                    of a Rough River: so that this Word has the very comprehensive signification of
                    “a Fertile Piece of Ground at the Mouth of a Rough River” which gives us a high
                    Idea of the power of Combination in the Erse Language.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl0590">Lanark</placeName>, contracted for Lav-ri-uisg (g is
                    pronounced as K) A Place near Water. <placeName ref="pl0143">Spay
                        River</placeName> (Spadha, a Long Stride) <pb n="f.78r"/> in Reference to
                    the Length of that Turbulent Stream. Most of the Names of Rivers in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> are Celtick Words simply signifying Water
                    and I believe this to be the case in all Languages.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl0683">Morvern</placeName> a Hilly Country. General Term for the
                        <placeName ref="pl0711">Highlands</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Spaut, Speat or Swelling of a River.</p>
                <p>Logie, A Low, flat Country.</p>
                <p>Drum, An Eminence, <placeName ref="pl0212">Tayndrum</placeName> Hill of
                        <placeName ref="pl0096">the Tay</placeName>.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl0122">Tulloch</placeName>, a small Hill or Knock.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl0405">Melrose</placeName>, pronounced by the Scotch <placeName ref="pl0405">Mullross</placeName>, a bare Promontory.</p>
                <p>Stron, a Nose or Promontory.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl0755">Clunee</placeName>, a Pasture among Woods.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.78v"/>
                    <pb n="f.79r"/>
                    <pb n="f.79v"/>
                    <pb n="f.80r"/>
                    <pb n="f.80v"/>
                    <pb n="f.81r"/>
                    <pb n="f.81v"/>
                    <pb n="f.82r"/>
                    <pb n="f.82v"/>
                    <pb n="f.83r"/>
                    <pb n="f.84r"/>
                    <pb n="f.84v"/>
                    <pb n="f.85r"/>
                    <pb n="f.85v"/>
                    <pb n="f.86r"/></p>
                <p><pb n="f.86v"/>
                    <list>
                        <item>Vol. Pen<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> __ ___ 2</item>
                        <item>Carys Map — 1</item>
                        <item><unclear>Scone</unclear> — 1</item>
                        <item><bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0081">Murray</title></bibl> —
                            1</item>
                        <item>Gent<hi rend="superscript">s</hi> Tour</item>
                        <item>1 <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0649">Scotland
                                delin</title></bibl>. 1</item>
                        <item>Roads – – 1</item>
                        <item><bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0277">Anislye</title></bibl> —
                            1</item>
                        <item><unclear reason="illegible">Sketches</unclear> — 1</item>
                        <item><unclear reason="illegible">Nonni</unclear> — 3</item>
                        <item><bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0650">Gilpin</title></bibl> —
                            1</item>
                        <item>Map of Scot</item>
                        <item><gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/> S</item>
                        <item>Compass</item>
                        <item>Mirror</item>
                        <item>Coloured Glass</item>
                        <item><unclear reason="illegible">Brymen</unclear> 1</item>
                        <item><unclear reason="illegible">Memorand</unclear> 1 </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>