<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0052">
    <teiHeader type="s">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>A Tour through part of England and Scotland By Eliza Dawson in the
                    Year 1786
                    <date>1786</date></title>
                <author>Eliza Dawson</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Edited with an Introduction by Alex Deans</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
                        <idno>Acc.12017</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>ff.1-79</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <additional>
                        <p>Transcribed from a photocopy with each MS side reprinted on a separate A4
                            sheet and ring-bound. There is an orange slip in the folder that reads:
                            ‘ELIZA FLETCHER (MSS of autobiography)’.</p>
                    </additional>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p/>
            </abstract>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p><pb n="1"/></p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">A Tour through part of England and Scotland</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">By Eliza Dawson in the Year 1786.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It is natural to suppose a Girl of sixteen, who has never been above thirty miles
                    from home, should form sanguine expectations from a journey of eight hundred. as
                    for me who answer that description, I anticipate a prodigious deal of pleasure
                    from it — and therefore have determin’d to set down every trifling circumstance,
                    that affords me the least momentary entertainment, — two good reasons induce me
                    to do it — first as they might probably slip my memory, and by that means I
                    should lose the satisfaction of reciting them to those from whose indulgence
                    every pleasure I experience is deriv’d, — and surely our enjoyments would be all
                    imperfect were we denied the superior gratification of communicating them to
                    others. — The second inducement is, that doubtless in course of time, Fortune
                    may be less lavish of her favours than she has been hitherto, and as we are too
                    apt to lose all remembrance of the former bounties we have enjoy’d. — I may cast
                    an eye upon this journal and recollect I have no reason to repine, since this
                    will prove I have had my portion of happiness ––––– These reasons I flatter
                    myself are not bad ones, — and with these ideas I will avail myself of every
                    opportunity.</p>
                <p>Set off from <placeName ref="pl2039">Oxton</placeName> July the 23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> about seven o clock having travell’d the road
                    before as far as <placeName ref="pl2040">Broughbridge</placeName>, I found
                    nothing remarkably striking; — one object present’d itself that rather excited
                    our compassion which was: about half way between <placeName ref="pl2041">Wetherby</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl2040">B<add place="above">o</add>roughbridge</placeName> we observed several Boys assembled; and
                    when we drew nearer discover’d a cart had been thrown over by the negligence of
                    one of them, — from negligence it must have been since it had run off the road,
                    we had not occasion long to examine the <pb n="2"/> countenances before we found
                    out which was he, — he seem’d about twelve years old, and never was sorrow more
                    strongly delineated in any face whatever. — he had been exerting all his
                    strength, and skill to raise it up again. — but finding his efforts fruitless,
                    was standing over it — in an attitude of utter stupefaction, - what would I have
                    given to have help’d him. – it might have been a matter of ridicule to some —
                    yet who knows but that poor lad might so far incur the displeasure of his master
                    as to be <sic>dismissed his service.</sic> — perhaps he had no home to go to.
                    ––––– when we consider these things which are very possible, — sure pity must
                    intrude upon our feelings, — We arrived at <placeName ref="pl2040">B<add place="above">o</add>roughbridge</placeName> about ten and after having
                    order’d breakfast we desired the waiter to show us to the <placeName ref="pl2042"><hi rend="underline">Devils</hi>
                        <hi rend="underline">Arrows</hi></placeName>. indeed they may deservedly be
                    reckon’d great curiosities. — there are three almost in a direct line. the first
                    is by far the largest in circumference. my Uncle, and Cousin, took the
                    dimensions. Towards the base it is twenty four feet and appears to be about
                    twenty one feet high, — the other is considerably higher and of a pyramidical
                    form, the last resembles it, only not quite so high, it is very remarkable there
                    is not tradition to be found concerning them. — they are of a gritty nature
                    resembling fitt’ring stones — I was curious to know what were the ideas of the
                    common people as I supposed their conjectures would be nearly as <hi rend="underline">wonderful</hi> as the cause which excited them, —
                    accordingly I ask’d the waiter what was the general Idea of them. “Ma’am
                    (replied he making an obsequious bow) <hi rend="underline">They</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">say</hi> they were shot from <placeName ref="pl2043"><hi rend="underline">Hamilton</hi>
                        <hi rend="underline">hills</hi></placeName>.” What makes them entertain that
                    notion, said I? — “ Because Ma’am (<hi rend="underline">bowing</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">again</hi>) they are the same kind of stone that is found
                    there — this was a more reasonable answer than I expect’d — Some of the most
                    superstitious assert <pb n="3"/> that they have been shot by the Devil when he
                    was in a pet with <placeName ref="pl2040">B<add place="above">o</add>roughbridge</placeName>. — certainly he might have chosen a more
                    eligible situation than <placeName ref="pl2043">Hamilton Hills</placeName> to
                    have discharg’d them from, — as I fancy <add place="above">those hills are</add>
                    above twelve miles from the <hi rend="underline">illfated</hi> town. however
                    whomever they were shot by they surely must have been, of the family of the <hi rend="underline">Armstrongs</hi>, — The most likely conjecture is that they
                    are a composition, and have been erected to commemorate the actions of some
                    Great Men. ––––– When breakfast was over, we proceeded on our route — we were
                    much pleas’d with a small village call’d <placeName ref="pl2044">Aizenby</placeName> situated on the banks of the <placeName ref="pl2045">river Swale</placeName>, — a charming view from the north side of
                        <placeName ref="pl2046">Topcliff</placeName> down the valley it commands a
                    good prospect of <persName ref="pe1289">Lord Grantham’s</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl2047">house</placeName>, and the Vale is pleasantly decorated
                    with <add place="above">the</add> windings of the river, the banks of which are
                    cover’d with fine trees. — The road to <placeName ref="pl2048">Northallerton</placeName> extremely agreeable from the quantity of small
                    Villages and thatch’d huts, the inhabitants seem’d busily employ’d spinning
                    worsted, and the children (with countenances that indicate inward serenity and
                    rosy health) playing at the door, give the whole an air of content extremely
                    pleasing. — We arrived at <placeName ref="pl2048">Northallerton</placeName>
                    about three, order’d dinner and in the mean time went to see the Sessions Hall,
                    which they are building it will be an excellent room 60 feet by 32, they are
                    also building a gaol, and some excellent apartments beneath the spacious Hall, —
                    for the Governor to reside in this will be a great addition to the town as the
                    Old Hall is the meanest looking place imaginable. nothing else remarkable at
                        <placeName ref="pl2048">Northallert</placeName> it’s a well built town
                    consisting <add place="above">chiefly</add> of one long and spacious street. —
                    Left it at five, and arrived at <placeName ref="pl2049">Darlington</placeName>
                    by eight. <persName ref="pe1290">My Uncle</persName> sent <pb n="4"/> for
                        <placeName ref="pe1291">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Richardson</placeName>, and order’d supper. <persName ref="pe1291">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> R —</persName> came, spent <add place="above">the</add> evening with us, was as <hi rend="underline">jocose</hi> as ever,
                    and ask’d us to breakfast with him the next morning — we part’d about twelve,
                    each happy to retire to our several apartments. ––––– Slept well at <placeName ref="pl2049">Darlington</placeName> then went to <persName ref="pe1291">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Richardson’s</persName> w<add place="above">h</add>ere we met with a very agreeable reception, both from <persName ref="pe1293">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Mowbray</persName> and himself.
                    — the former seems to be very conversable and extremely good temper’d,.
                        <persName ref="pe1292">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Mowbray</persName> was
                    from home but she introduced us to her young family, which consists of a fine
                    looking boy about 12 years old and two sweet little Girls. — we stay’d there
                    till ten which was longer than we intended, but could not resist their pressing
                    solicitations — (so powerful is persuasion,) — We left <placeName ref="pl2049">Darlington</placeName> about eleven, and after some hilly road (in which
                        <persName ref="pe1290">my Uncle</persName> compassionat’d the poor horse so
                    much as frequently to alight) we reach’d <placeName ref="Durham">Durham</placeName> about two, and a <hi rend="underline">Grand</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Solemn</hi> procession we made the streets being so uneven
                    and illpaved as to oblige us to go as slow as possible, — we proceeded to
                        <placeName ref="pl2050">the Wheat Sheaf</placeName> (<persName ref="pe1294">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Shuttons</persName>) recommended to us
                    by <persName ref="pe1295">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forster</persName>, it
                    is a most elegant house. was formerly the habitation of a x x x x gentleman
                    call’d <persName ref="pe1296">Reed</persName>, it is in a dull part of the Town
                    but has the advantage of a garden, from which there is a pleasant view of the
                        <placeName ref="pl0934">Castle and Cathedral</placeName> — We order’d dinner
                    after which we took a walk to <placeName ref="pl0934">the Minster</placeName>.
                    There is a most delightful view from <placeName ref="pl2051">Fromergate
                        bridge</placeName> to Newbridge<note type="editorial"><placeName ref="pl1727">Prebend's Bridge</placeName> further down the River Wear,
                        built in the 1770s after an older bridge was destroyed by flooding.</note>
                    on the West side are sloping gardens, and on the East a high and rugged rock —
                    on which stands the <placeName ref="pl0934">Castle and Minster</placeName> — the
                    Mill and dam, are nearly between the two Bridges, and add greatly to the beauty
                    of the charming prospect — this walk led us to the <placeName ref="pl0934">Cathedral</placeName> — after having seen <placeName ref="pl0932">S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Peter’s</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl0763">York</placeName> this appears but trifling <pb n="5"/> and tho’
                    considerably smaller it is exactly the same plan, the pillars are heavy and shew
                    a wretched taste for architecture, whereas those at <placeName ref="pl0932">York</placeName> are remark’d for the contrary, — a woman conducted us to
                    see the curiosities, we were shown five very ancient robes, one was given by
                        <persName ref="pe0600">Charles the first</persName>, it’s red velvet
                    curiously inwrought with gold, it has been intended for a cloak, and on the hood
                    is the figure of <persName ref="pe1297">David</persName>, with <persName ref="pe1298">Goliah’s</persName> head in his hand: the other four are said
                    to have been here ever since the church was founded, they are different colour’d
                    velvets cover’d with emblematical figures taken from scripture, inwrought with
                    gold, silver, and various colour’d silks, — there is an ancient manuscript
                    (concerning the founding of this Cathedral) which I copied literally it was as
                    follows. —</p>
                <p><quote>“The Bishops See of <placeName ref="bi0084">Durham</placeName> was first
                        placed at <placeName ref="pl2052">Lindisfarn</placeName>
                        <lb/>“now <placeName ref="pl2052">Holy-Island</placeName>, on the sea coast
                        of <placeName ref="pl2053">Northumberland</placeName>. but both the
                        <lb/>“Bishops and Monks being driven from thence by the Danes about
                        <lb/>“the year 800, they wander’d up, and down, for about 200 years, till
                        <lb/>“in the end they <hi rend="underline">sat</hi> them down at <placeName ref="pl0052">Durham</placeName>, in the year 1000 <lb/>“here it hath
                        ever since continued, there was a succession of 24 Bishops <lb/>“at
                            <placeName ref="pl2052">Lindisfarn</placeName>, now <placeName ref="pl2052">Holy Island</placeName>, before the founding of <placeName ref="pl0052">Durham</placeName> of whom <lb/>“<persName ref="pe1299">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Cuthbert</persName> was the sixth,
                            <persName ref="pe1300"><hi rend="underline">Aldwin</hi></persName> was
                        the <hi rend="underline">twenty</hi>
                        <hi rend="underline">fourth</hi> Bishop of <lb/>“<placeName ref="pl2052">Lindisfarn</placeName> and first of <placeName ref="pl0052"><hi rend="underline">Durham</hi></placeName> –––––</quote><note type="editorial">The manuscript Dawson alludes to may be Symeon of Durham's
                        history of the church at Durham: <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0152"><hi rend="italic">Libellus de exordio atque procursu istius hoc
                                    est Dunhelmensis ecclesie</hi></title></bibl>. However the text
                        of her account of the foundation of Durham closely matches that found in
                            <bibl type="editorial">Peter Heylyn, <title ref="bi0084"><hi rend="italic">A Help to English History</hi></title> (London:
                            1641)</bibl>, which went through several editions in the course of the
                        eighteenth century. See for example the edition of 1773: 'The Bishop's see,
                        now fixed in Durham, was first placed in Lindisfarne, a little island on the
                        sea-coast of Northumberland and there placed by the first bishops of this
                        Northern region, because of the privacy and solitude thereof, which made it
                        thought more fit and proper for devotion. But, both the bishop and the monks
                        being driven from thence by the merciless fury of the Danes (who raged here
                        extremely) about the year of Christ 800, they wandered up and down from
                        place to place for two hundred years, not finding any place where they might
                        repose themselves in safety, till in the end they sate them down in Durham,
                            <hi rend="italic">anno</hi> 990, or thereabouts, where it has ever since
                        continued', p.132</note></p>
                <p>The above manuscript appears to be a very great contradiction otherwise upon
                    consideration <persName ref="pe1300">Aldwin</persName> must have been a pretty
                    good age, when he <hi rend="underline">sat himself</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">down</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">at</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">Durham</hi>. —</p>
                <p>There is a place in this Cathedral — called the nine alters, where the Bishops
                    were formerly interred, they have lately dug up this place the <pb n="6"/>
                    Coffin of <persName ref="pe1301">Anthony Beck</persName> — Patriarch of
                        <placeName ref="pl2054">Jerusalem</placeName>, who died in the year 1283, we
                    were shown this coffin which is Iron and has had a wood one within it, it is all
                    shatter’d in pieces, (and though it was Sunday) a resistless impulse inclin’d me
                    to steal a morsel of it — I hope the Old Patriarch will give me <hi rend="underline">absolution</hi> as I did it from profound respect to <hi rend="underline">his</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">memory</hi>. — They also shew us a shoe and spur (at this
                    place) the former measures 14 inches, and ¾ in length, and is of propo<add place="above">r</add>tionable breadth, this my <persName ref="pe1290">Uncle</persName> measured himself otherwise we could not have believed it,
                    the spur is equally curious the woman gravely assured us, it was <persName ref="pe1299">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Cuthbert’s</persName>, — be that
                    as it may, we are not bound to credit her assertion. — most certainly it must
                    have <hi rend="underline">belong’d</hi> to a <hi rend="underline">Saint</hi>, as
                    it is widely different to those shoes that would fit the <hi rend="underline">degenerate</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">feet</hi> of the present age, I could not help making a
                    comparison between it, and the small toe’d slipper, of the modern <hi rend="underline">Beau</hi>; — we left <placeName ref="pl0052">Durham</placeName> about six and after a pleasant ride of 14 miles (in
                    which we had a fine view of <placeName ref="pl0450">Lumley Castle</placeName>
                    (The seat of the <persName ref="pe1302">Earl of Scarb<add place="above">o</add>rough</persName>) from <placeName ref="pl0055">Chester le
                        street</placeName>), — we reach’d <persName ref="pe1303">Lofthouse’s</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl2055">the Old White Hart</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl0057">Newcastle</placeName> about nine, where we met with good beds,
                    and excellent accomodations, as it was too late to see any thing of the Town
                    that night, we rose at six in the morning went to <add place="above">see</add>
                    the <placeName ref="pl2056">assembly rooms</placeName>, they are indeed very
                    light, and elegantly finished infinitely superior to those at <placeName ref="pl0763">York</placeName>, the dimensions of the large room are 94 feet
                    long by 34 broad, and 36 high, — from this we went to see the Glass manufactory,
                    it is curious but is a scene which rather disgusts than affords satisfaction. —
                    as the pallid looks of the workmen <pb n="7"/> plainly shew it must be a most
                    unhealthy business, after having seen these things which we were inform’d were
                    all at <placeName ref="pl0057">Newcastle</placeName> worth notice we return’d to
                    the inn, and breakfasted. — <placeName ref="pl0057">Newcastle</placeName> is a
                    large populous town, the streets in general narrow and confined, extremely
                    hilly, and disagreeable to travel through, — the south entrance into the town
                    must prejudice many against it, one is obliged to descend a prodigious steep
                    hill called <placeName ref="pl0056">Gateshead</placeName>, down which few have
                    courage to remain in their carriages, for our parts we did not hesitate a moment
                    but gladly alighted and proceeded slow, and cautiously, — from this hill one
                    might have a view of the town, were it not immers’d continually, in one black
                    cloud of smoke, which proceeds from the quantity of Glasshouses Potteries
                    &amp;c; When breakfast was over we set out for <placeName ref="pl0059">Morpeth</placeName>, and reach’d that place about 12, the inn there is kept
                    by <persName ref="pe1304">Nelson</persName> a Yorkshireman, from whom we met
                    with uncommon civility — This is a neat built place pleasantly situated but
                    nothing in it worth observation. We turned at <placeName ref="pe1304">Morpeth</placeName> from the great road in order to see <placeName ref="pl2057">Warkworth</placeName> a place celebrated in verse,<note type="editorial"><persName ref="pe1009">Thomas Percy's</persName> ballad,
                            <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0171"><hi rend="italic">The Hermit
                                    of Warkworth</hi></title></bibl> (London: 1771). The poem is
                        mentioned again below in relation to Warkworth Hermitage.</note> it was six
                    miles out of our way <add place="above">and</add> the road being a private one
                    is not very good, though the views from it are beautiful, which by keeping the
                    attention awake smooth the roughness of the way. — on the right of the road
                    about eight miles from <placeName ref="pl0059">Morpeth</placeName>, stands
                        <placeName ref="pl2058">Witherington Castle</placeName>, it attracted our
                    attention and being near the road my <persName ref="pe1290">Uncle</persName> and
                    I alighted to take a nearer view of it — we enquired of a Peasant that was by if
                    it was inhabited. (as it had a very antique appearance.) He reply’d it was, and
                    by a <persName ref="pe1305">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Loraine</persName>
                    and conducted us into the field where the Castle stood. there I sat down to take
                    a sketch of it, and my <persName ref="pe1290">Uncle</persName> stood by me. — we
                    had not remain’d long in this situation, when we observed a Gentleman of very
                    genteel appearance <pb n="8"/> approach. he accosted us very politely, and my
                        <persName ref="pe1290">Uncle</persName> apologized for our intrusion by
                    saying we were so much struck with the beauty of the situation that we had taken
                    the liberty to alight in order to make a short sketch of it, he reply’d there
                    was no occasion for any apology. he look’d upon it as a high compliment, by this
                    time I had finished — and he beg’d us to go up to the Castle (which was not
                    above 100 yards off) and dine with him, this kindness we were obliged to decline
                    as we had got a snack at <placeName ref="pl0059">Morpeth</placeName>, and our
                    time was precious it being now three o clock, — however he earnestly intreated
                    us to take a glass of wine, — we follow’d him — and he conducted us into an
                    elegant apartment where he introduced us to <persName ref="pe1306">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Lorain</persName>, an old Lady, who probably
                    might be her Mother, a young Lady of about twenty five, and two sweet little
                    Girls about five, or six. — they were at dinner and seconded <persName ref="pe1305">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Loraine</persName> in intreating
                    us to partake with them. — we still resisted their solicitations but drank their
                    healths in a glass of wine — we staid with them about a quarter of an hour and
                    left <placeName ref="pl2058">Witherington Castle</placeName> highly pleased with
                    the polite hospitality of its agreeable inhabitants. I cannot for<add place="above">e</add>go the pleasing subject without giving a short
                    description of these persons who had afforded us such entertainment, <persName ref="pe1306">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Loraine</persName> who seems
                    about 25 has a mild and placid countenance, expressive dark eyes, and a
                    beautiful complexion, her figure tho not tall is elegant and her dress and
                    manner easy, and genteel, <persName ref="pe1305">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Lorraine</persName> is about six 6 foot high extremely well made, has a
                    pleasing and sensible countenance. I was struck when in the Castle with a great
                    resemblance between this family and that of our <persName ref="pe1307">Eubanks</persName> at <placeName ref="pl2059">Bolton <hi rend="underline">Percy</hi></placeName>, the same kind of elegance and domestic
                    tranquillity seems to preside over both — The Castle stands upon, <pb n="9"/> a
                    fine eminence and commands a beautiful view of the sea, it belongs to <persName ref="pe1308">Sir George Warren</persName> to whom the hospitable inhabitant
                    is tenant. —</p>
                <p>We got to <placeName ref="pl2057">Warkworth</placeName> about five and after
                    committing our horses to an Ostler’s care, we walk’d to the <placeName ref="pl2060">Hermitage</placeName>, it is a most delightful spot on the
                    banks of the <placeName ref="pl0432">River Coquet</placeName>. the best
                    tradition that is to be found concerning this place is <persName ref="pe1009">Dr
                        Percy’s</persName> beautiful poem <sic>call’</sic>
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0171">The Hermit of
                        Warkworth</title></bibl>, it is hewn out of the solid rock, which must have
                    been an arduous task, as there are several different cells, and in one of them
                    the very image of which the Poet speaks, — the statue is much the <hi rend="underline">worse</hi> for <hi rend="underline">age</hi>, as there are
                    not now the least remains of beauty, — alas she has now no Hermit to count his
                    beads over her inanimate resemblance,<note type="editorial">In Percy's ballad
                        romance <hi rend="italic">The Hermit of Warkworth</hi> (London: 1771), the
                        eponymous hermit reveals himself to be Sir Bertram, a former knight and
                        retainer of the Percy family, earls of Northumberland. The hermit relates
                        that he has taken a voluntary penance having accidentally slain his bride to
                        be, Isabel, whose sculptured image he now attends in a cell above the river
                        Coquet.</note> — The walk to this place is charming, on one side are most
                    stupendous rocks overhung with trees, and wild shrubs, and on the other hand is
                    the river which one may just discern through the leaves of those trees which are
                    planted on its banks, — When we return’d from thence we walk’d up to <placeName ref="pl2057">the Castle</placeName> it is a fine old ruin situated on an
                    eminence and commands one of the most delightful prospects imaginable, on the
                    right at about the distance of three miles is <placeName ref="pl2061">Coquet
                        Island</placeName> — surrounded by the <placeName ref="pl1107">German
                        Ocean</placeName>, it belongs to the <persName ref="pe1309">Duke of
                        Northumberland</persName>, who has made several plantations upon it stock’d
                    it with Cattle and has built there by way of ornament something resembling the
                    Tower of a Church. nobody lives upon it as the sea at high water frequently
                    makes depradations. — On the left from the same eminence is a romantic view of
                    the <placeName ref="pl0432">Vale of Coquet</placeName> (in which is situated the
                        <placeName ref="pl2057">Village of Warkworth</placeName>) beautifully
                    interspersed with wood, and water, the <placeName ref="pl0432">river
                        Coquet</placeName> winding through it; — after having enjoy’d these charming
                    prospects we return’d to the inn it was the best in the Village; but a paltry
                    one notwithstanding, — after a little refreshment we set forward to <placeName ref="pl0062">Alnwick</placeName>. the road laid close to the Ocean <pb n="10"/> and the uncommon serenity of the evening conspired to make our ride
                    as agreeable as possible, we arrived at the <placeName ref="pl2062">White
                        Swan</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl0062">Alnwick</placeName> about nine,
                    and after supper retired to bed, much pleased with our days amusement. —</p>
                <p>In the morning my <persName ref="pe1290">Uncle</persName> call’d upon <persName ref="pe1310">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Grey</persName>, gave him
                        <persName ref="pe1295">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forster’s</persName>
                    letter and brought him to breakfast with us, when that was over he conducted us
                    to <placeName ref="pl1729">the Castle</placeName>, — we were first shewn the
                    stables which are within the great court, — there are stands for sixteen horses
                    and it is ornamented with a handsome cornish of plaister. — we then proceeded to
                        <placeName ref="pl1729">the Castle</placeName> it is not possible for me to
                    give an adequate idea of the Grandeur of its appearance, — the man inform’d us
                    the Gateway has been built 430 years, in part of which there is a dungeon which
                    was formerly a place of confinement for condemn’d criminals, on the floor above
                    the dungeon there are a large quantity of cannon balls (64 pounders). — We were
                    then shewn the inner rooms they are all equally superb and ornamented chiefly
                    with emblematical figures of war and <add place="above">on</add> the cornice the
                    arms of all the family and branches of the house of Northumberland, there is a
                    spacious library well furnish’d though it is the Chapel which is elegant beyond
                    description — the pilasters, and cornice being enriched with gold. on the walls
                    is the Genealogy of the family traced from the earliest periods down to the
                    present time, the end window is an exact imitation (tho in miniature) of the
                    East window of <placeName ref="pl0932">St. Peters</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl0763">York</placeName>. — it was done in <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> and the colours are remarkably fine. below this window
                    is a large marble tomb ornamented with elegant sculpture dedicated to the memory
                    of the <persName ref="pe0443">late Dutchess of Northumberland</persName>. — In
                    one of the rooms is a fine <rs ref="ar0243"> picture of that lady</rs> it is
                    admirably done she has a most majestic figure and a fine open countenance and
                    the drapery, which adds much to the <pb n="11"/> grandeur of the piece, is a
                    morone colour’d robe embroider’d with gold —</p>
                <p>When we return’d from the <placeName ref="pl1729">Castle</placeName>
                    <placeName ref="pe1310">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Grey</placeName>
                    accompanied us to <placeName ref="pl1730">the Duke’s mount</placeName> an
                    eminence about three miles west of <placeName ref="pl0062">Alnwick</placeName>.
                    the ride was extremely pleasant most of the way through a shrubbery and
                    plantation on the top of the emi<add place="above">n</add>ence is a beautiful
                    Obelisk of Gothic structure. there are stairs to the top of it. it is thirty
                    yards high and there are 131 steps to the second terrace, we ascended it and
                    from thence saw some very fine and extensive views, <add place="above">on</add>
                    the West there is a grand and rugged prospect of Hills and Mountains, the
                    highest of which was <placeName ref="pl0945"><hi rend="underline">Cheviot</hi></placeName>, — on the East a fine view of <placeName ref="pl1729">Alnwick Castle</placeName>, and in the valley a prospect of a
                    ruin, called <placeName ref="pl2063">Hull’s Tower</placeName> which stands on
                    the banks of the <placeName ref="pl2064">Alne</placeName>, the river that runs
                    through <placeName ref="pl0062">Alnwick</placeName>, the banks of which are
                    finely ornament’d with plantations — this view is terminated by the sea, —
                        <persName ref="pe0442">The late Duke</persName> has made great improvements
                    about this place and they all spoke of him with great respect. — From the mount
                    we return’d to the Inn took leave of <persName ref="pe1310">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Grey</persName> and left <placeName ref="pl0062">Alnwick</placeName> about twelve and being inclined to see
                        <placeName ref="pl0064">Bambrough Castle</placeName> we dined at <placeName ref="pl2065">North Charlton</placeName> —, six miles from <placeName ref="pl0062">Alnwick</placeName> — where we got a good lamb steak tho I dare
                    say the house is not much frequented, as there was neither Ostler, or Waiter,
                    and a <hi rend="underline">canny</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">old</hi> woman served in every capacity, — from this place
                    we turned to the right from the high road to get to <placeName ref="pl0065">Bambrough</placeName>, the road was bad and we did not reach it till five —
                    We gave our horses to the care of a boy and walk’d down to the sea <placeName ref="pl0064">the Castle</placeName> is situated upon a prodigious rock,
                    which at the time of high water is wash’d by the sea – This <placeName ref="pl0064">Castle</placeName> belongs to <persName ref="pe1311">Lord
                        Crue</persName> by whose family it had been endow’d. the institution is a
                    very humane one being founded for the relief of distress’d <hi rend="underline">Seamen</hi>. — We stay’d there about an hour and then set forward for
                        <placeName ref="pl0063">Belford</placeName>, the road part of the way <pb n="12"/> lays across the sands we were overtaken by a sharp shower, reached
                        <placeName ref="pl0063">Belford</placeName> about eight, where we met with
                    comfortable accomodations at <placeName ref="pl2066">the Blue Bell</placeName> —
                    and took up our residence till morning. –––––</p>
                <p>We rose at Six on Wednesday morning July the 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> and
                    reach’d Halls at <placeName ref="pl0067">Berwick</placeName> by ten, where we
                    order’d Breakfast and sent for <persName ref="pe1313">Robin Straughen</persName>
                    —, he appears to be about seventy, I no sooner told him I came from <persName ref="pe1312">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Brudenell</persName> and had
                    brought him a letter, than tears started into his eyes — “Oh God bless her how
                    does she do Ma’am” said the old man — he beg’d me to read her letter and at the
                    end of every sentence cried out, “Lord love her, — Lord lover her,” — I told him
                    he seem’d to have great respect for <persName ref="pe1312">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> B</persName>, — and assured him she had the
                    same for him, “respect Madam” (said he,) “I have known “her ever since she was
                    born, I lived with <persName ref="pe1314">Captain and M<hi rend="superscript">rs
                        </hi>Heburn</persName> above 13 years, and they used me more like a friend
                    than a servant. aye God knows, when the <persName ref="pe1314">Captain</persName> died, I lost a father as well as her — poor thing when
                    she could scarce walk it used <unclear reason="illegible">no end</unclear> to
                    nestle about me, and if it saw any body in distress, would have gone to my
                    Master to have beg’d a halfpenny for them”. ––––– he ceased from an inability to
                    articulate more. — never was any thing more affecting than the artless yet
                    expressive stories of this poor old Man, — and his <add place="above">countenance</add> while he was dwelling on this theme would have been a
                    subject for the pencil of a <persName ref="pe1108">Guido</persName>. <persName ref="pe1312">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Brudenell</persName> had
                    desired him to take a letter from her to <placeName ref="pl2067">Foulden</placeName>, which he did, along with a note from me to <persName ref="pe1315">Miss Wilkie</persName>, telling her we would call there in the
                    course of the day, we then set out for <persName ref="pe1316">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Greys</persName> in the parade. — we were
                    shewn in and immediately after came in <persName ref="pe1316">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Grey</persName> and a gentleman just arrived
                    from <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>, whose name was <pb n="13"/>
                    <persName ref="pe1317">Sanford</persName>. — we present’d <persName ref="pe1316">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Grey</persName> with <persName ref="pe1295">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsters</persName> letter by
                    way of introduction she is a most agreeable woman, and for her years (which must
                    be fifty) she is remarkably handsome, had a fine open countenance expressive of
                    Benevolence and goodwill. — She has met with no small number of calamities, —
                    lost the kindest and most affectionate of husbands when her children were all
                    young, — and her eldest daughter a most aimiable woman who married a <persName ref="pe1318">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hall</persName>, was suddenly
                    snatch’d from her, notwithstanding her feelings are strong — she supports these
                    severe strokes with becoming firmness, — she ask’d us to dine to which we
                    consented, soon after appear’d <persName ref="pe1316">Miss Grey</persName> she
                    had no sooner enter’d than she commanded our admiration, had no sooner spoke
                    than she won our esteem, — she walk’d out with us shew’d us the ramparts, and a
                    prodigious large Brewery, they have not yet begun to brew for exportation the
                    barley being so dear of late, the Copper is large enough to boil 76 casks, 36
                    gallons each, — from thence we return’d to dinner, during which time <persName ref="pe1313">Old Robin</persName> came with a polite note from <persName ref="pe1315">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Wilkie</persName>, telling us
                        <persName ref="pe1315">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName> and
                        <persName ref="pe1315">Miss Wilkie</persName> were gone to <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName> races, but she would be glad of our
                    companies to take a bed with her at <placeName ref="pl2067">Foulden
                        house</placeName>. — accordingly we were obliged to take leave of the two
                    agreeable Ladies in the parade. — and tho’ our acquaintance had been so short I
                    could not refrain from tears at parting. I never <add place="above">saw</add>
                    one so thoroughly form’d to please as <persName ref="pe1316">Miss
                        Grey</persName>, she seems about twenty two, her person tho’ not tall is
                    extremely elegant, her countenance beautiful and expressive, mild and gentle,
                    tho’ lively, and animated, she seems (to borrow the elegant expression of the
                    sentimental Journalist) she seems to be “All the heart wishes, or the eye looks
                    for in Woman.” —<note type="editorial"><bibl>Laurence Sterne, <title ref="bi0172"><hi rend="italic">A Sentimental Journey</hi></title>, 2
                            vols. (London: 1768), <biblScope unit="volume">ii</biblScope>,
                                <biblScope unit="page">pp.179-80</biblScope></bibl>. In the
                        posthumously published <hi rend="italic">Autobiography of Mrs. Fletcher</hi>
                        (Edinburgh: 1875), Eliza Fletcher (née Dawson) writes that her 1786 tour
                        journal was, in keeping with the tastes of the time, 'a sort of "sentimental
                        journey"', p.28.</note></p>
                <p>The Gentlemen were equally pleased, we called to thank <persName ref="pe1313">Robin</persName> for his trouble <pb n="14"/> and left <placeName ref="pl0067">Berwick</placeName> not without casting <del rend="overstrike">x x x x</del> many a look behind trying to trace the road to the parade, —
                    We reach’d <placeName ref="pl2067">Fouldon</placeName> about seven its a most
                    beautiful situation and an elegant and uniform building, we were graciously
                    received by <persName ref="pe1315">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                        Wilkie</persName>. she is a fine handsome looking Woman, has a regular set
                    of features is tall and rather fat, — tea was ready, after which she took us to
                    see the <placeName ref="pl2068">Village</placeName> which has been lately
                    rebuilt by <persName ref="pe1315">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Wilkie</persName>, she said she dare say we had heard much of Scotch dirt,
                    but for the credit of <placeName ref="pl2068">Foulden</placeName>, she would
                    shew us some Cottages that would incline us to think there are a few exceptions,
                    we accordingly went into two of them, and I never saw cleaner places in my life,
                    — we walk’d till supper after which we retired to rest. — in the morning a bad
                    prospect open’d to us, it rain’d hard, and the wind was extremely high,
                        <persName ref="pe1315">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Wilkie</persName>
                    intreated us much to stay the day with her, but <add place="above">we</add> were
                    obliged to decline her invitation. and about twelve o’clock Thursday July the
                        27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, we left <placeName ref="pl2067">Fouldon
                        House</placeName>, it was fair but the wind increas’d. the road lies across
                    a barren moor called <placeName ref="pl2069">Cowdingham moor</placeName> six
                    miles in length upon which neither tree or bush can flourish, it lies exceeding
                    high, and on the right about a quarter of a mile is the sea, — on this moor we
                    were in a dreadful situation, the wind was so very boisterous it was impossible
                    for the Mare to proceed, and very unsafe for us to stay in the carriage, as it
                    was very probable it might be blown down since there was a load of hay in that
                    situation, upon level-ground, we thought it therefore safer to alight and I took
                    fast hold of the chair behind. and by that means was dragg’d on, otherwise I
                    could not possibly have kept my feet, my <persName ref="pe1319">Cousin</persName> lead the horse <pb n="15"/> and in this trim we walk’d
                    for above three miles, — I had forgot to mention one circumstance which was
                    notwithstanding I held my hat on the wind tore it off and away it flew towards
                    the sea, — I bade farewell to it but my <persName ref="pe1319">Cousin</persName>
                    pursued and luckily overtook it. — we began to find ourselves exceedingly hungry
                    about 4 o’clock. so we sat down in a quarry hole, that was by the road side and
                    regaled ourselves with some peppercake, which our considerate old Friend at home
                    had provided us with, this refreshment enabled us to proceed stoutly. — about
                    half way between <placeName ref="pl2070">Press Inn</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl0070">Dunbar</placeName> there is a valley called <placeName ref="pl2071">Pease Valley</placeName>, over it they are building a Bridge
                    which is one hundred and thirty seven feet high, and consists of four arches.
                    this <add place="above">is</add> to render the road more commodius. as there is
                    no water in the Valley, — when we had pass’d this place we were a little
                    sheltered by some Hills on the left so we ventured to mount, — and got safe to
                        <placeName ref="pl0070">Dunbar</placeName> by six. it is a well built place
                    but the Inn is the worst looking house in it. here we order’d dinner and in the
                    meantime took a walk to see the Oyster shell, which we had heard so much of.
                    —</p>
                <p>It is the property of a <persName ref="pe1320">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Fall</persName>, the present Mayor of the place, we askd permission to see
                    it. but found it was not very usual for strangers. — a Lady who we supposed to
                    be <persName ref="pe1321">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> fall</persName> told
                    us we were very welcome, by she did not think it was so great a curiosity, it
                    was sent her from the <placeName ref="pl2072">East Indies</placeName> where she
                    believed they were plentiful. — she order’d a servant to carry us into the
                    garden where it was, it measures in length thirty three inches and is of
                    proportionable bre<add place="above">a</add>dth, and the lady inform’d us it
                    weighs one hundred and thirty seven pounds. This is but half the shell. it
                    resembles a muscle more than an Oyster, as it has been united to the other part,
                    by the side, and not the end, this was all at <placeName ref="pl0070">Dunbar</placeName> worth <pb n="16"/> observation. we then return’d to the
                    Inn and dined, and hearing it was twelve miles good road to <placeName ref="pl0948">Haddington</placeName> and our accomodations none the best at
                        <placeName ref="pl0070">Dunbar</placeName>. — we set forward for the first
                    mention’d place which we reached by nine, at <placeName ref="pl2073">the Blue
                        Bell</placeName> we found ourselves comfortably situated, which compensated
                    for the rude buffeting of the wind. —</p>
                <p>I could not help making comparisons between this day and the agreeable one we
                    spent before with <persName ref="pe1316">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi></persName> and <persName ref="pe1316">Miss Grey</persName>. it
                    furnish’d me with a fund of reflections, and serv’d to shew how whimsically life
                    is checquerd, — We staid at <placeName ref="pl0948">Haddington</placeName> all
                    night it is a small but well built town, and stands in a fine fertile valley —
                    We left this place <add place="above">on</add> Friday morning about 11 o clock
                    it rained all the way to <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName>, which
                    place we reach’d about two. we drove up to <placeName ref="pl2074">Walkers
                        hotel</placeName> by the recommendation of <persName ref="pe1315">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Wilkie</persName>, but he inform’d us his
                    house was entirely fill as were the other two Hotels but was so obliging as to
                    get us private lodgings next door at a <persName ref="pe1322">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Hutchinsons</persName>, and very comfortable
                    ones they were, — Our old Hostess was very civil and gravely assured me her beds
                    were free from vermin, — it rain’d so hard we could see very little of the town,
                    in entering it we met several elegant carriages coming from the races. — after
                    dinner we sent to <persName ref="pe1323">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Meliss</persName> and <persName ref="pe1315">Miss Wilkie</persName> the
                    latter who was in the same street came immediately was much surpriz’d to see us.
                    — <persName ref="pe1323">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Meliss</persName> was
                    not long after, and gave us a polite welcome to <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>, we had fix’d to go to the play that night which we
                    did, and were vastly entertain’d with <persName ref="pe1324">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Jordan</persName> — who play’d Miss Hayden in
                        <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0220">the trip to Scarb<add place="above">o</add>rough</title></bibl> the <placeName ref="pl2078">Theatre</placeName> was much crowded, and nothing could equal
                    the encomiums bestow’d on <persName ref="pe1324">Mrs Jordan</persName>, — The
                    Farce was <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0227">Comus</title></bibl> in
                    which <persName ref="pe1325">Mrs — <pb n="17"/> Kenedy</persName> sang (Sweet
                        Echo)<note type="editorial">A song appearing in John Milton's pastoral
                        masque, <hi rend="italic">Comus</hi> (first performed 1634),
                        ll.230-243.</note> — most divinely, ––––– <persName ref="pe1323">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Meliss</persName> return’d to Supper with us.
                    — and the next morning breakfasted and afterwards walk’d with us into the
                        <placeName ref="pl2075">New Town</placeName>, — nothing can equal the
                    elegance and regularity of the buildings, every dwelling is a sumptuous mansion.
                    — the plan of the town is one long and spacious street, called <placeName ref="pl0958">Georges Street</placeName> — and on each side of it, Two rows
                    one facing the <placeName ref="pl0083">Forth</placeName>, and the other the
                        <placeName ref="pl2076">Old Town</placeName>, from these rows are branching
                    streets into the middle on, — which form some elegant squares.— The three
                    principal streets extend from East to west and are intended to be each one mile
                    and a half in length.— after this we called upon <persName ref="pe1315">Miss
                        Wilkie</persName> to ask her to with us to <placeName ref="pl0077">Leith</placeName> races, to which we readily consented. it unfortunately
                    rain’d the whole time were there, — <placeName ref="pl0077">Leith</placeName> is
                    about two miles from <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName>, close by the
                    sea, the horses run upon the sands so they are guided by the tide. We went in a
                    hack Coach. there was the most elegant shew of carriages I ever beheld, a great
                    many Nabobs, the colour of whose horses it was hard to distinguish from the
                    superb richness of their harness. The <persName ref="pe1326">Lord Provost Sir —
                        Blair</persName> stands at the winning post, to decide the Race, and
                    Soldiers are placed along the cords to keep good order, the Race was over about
                    two, and we return’d and set <persName ref="pe1315">Miss Wilkie</persName> down
                    number 12 <placeName ref="pl0959">Princes Street</placeName>. — <persName ref="pe1315">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wilkie</persName> called before
                    dinner and ask’d us to go to see the new <placeName ref="pl2077">assembly
                        rooms</placeName>, when the Large room is intirely finish’d it will be
                    prodigiously elegant, — it is ninety six feet in length, and of proportionable
                    breadth and height, and is beautifully <sic>oramented</sic> with an elegant
                    cornice and very fine large Glass Chandeliers. — from thence we return’d to
                    dinner, <persName ref="pe1315">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wilkie</persName>
                    took his leave, and <persName ref="pe1323">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Meliss</persName> sat down with us — <pb n="18"/> during the time we had
                    been at the <placeName ref="pl2077">assembly rooms</placeName>, he had been
                    getting us tickets to see <persName ref="pe1324">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                        Jordan</persName> in <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0230">the Country
                            Girl</title></bibl>. and <persName ref="pe1325">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Kenedy</persName> in <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0236">the Poor Solider</title></bibl>, that evening, — as soon as dinner was
                    over, we took a walk into the <placeName ref="pl2076">Old Town</placeName>,
                    where they are making great improvements it is a dirty looking place, and the
                    houses extremely <add place="above">high</add> being most of them eight or ten
                    stories — and one we saw that was fourteen, the rooms are large, and one flat,
                    (as they call them) has every convenience for accomodating a moderate siz’d
                    family, — One pleasing Idea suggests itself while one is surveying the
                    stupendous height of those buildings, which is, the Goodness of Providence in so
                    seldom permitting fire to make depradations here, — alas what would become of
                    those placed in the upper stories, — what thousands of souls must inevitably
                    perish, without a possibility of receiving any Earthly assistance. ––––– Happily
                    they have no want of Earthly assistance. — Their protection is from above, –––––
                    The prison at <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName> has a mean
                    appearance, there is a part of the roof left flat, into which a door opens. from
                    a cell and upon this place the unhappy criminals are executed, — this prison is
                    in the most publick part of the Town. ––––– when we return’d <persName ref="pe1323">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Meliss</persName> took us to see
                    an Exhibition of paintings they were extremely fine, and a prodigious quantity
                    of them. There was <rs ref="ar0244">Robertson</rs>, <persName ref="pe0082">the
                        great Historian</persName>, a fine pleasant animated countenance, and <rs ref="ar0245">another</rs> of <persName ref="pe0085">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Webster</persName> who brought about the act wherein Clergymens
                    widows are well provided for, in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>,
                    the design is a room, in which he is sitting with the act of Parliament in his
                    hand, there is a picture in the back ground hung against the wall, which
                    represents a Widow weeping over the urn of her departed husband, and surroun<add place="above">d</add>ed by a young, and <pb n="19"/> numerous offspring, the
                    Countenances of the whole groupe are well express’d — from this place we went to
                    the <placeName ref="pl2078">Theatre</placeName> which <add place="above">was</add> infinitely more crowded than the night before, — and the Ladies
                    still finer dress’d Plumes nodding, and diamonds glittering <hi rend="underline">innumerable</hi>, I dont think Scotch Women remarkable for beauty in
                    general but this night there were many fine faces graced the boxes, one I
                    particularly remark’d for beauty of countenance, and elegance of figure, her
                    name Macdonald. — <persName ref="pe1324">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                        Jordan</persName> was great beyond description in <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0230">the Country Girl</title></bibl>, — and <persName ref="pe1325">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Kenedy</persName> pleased much
                    in the Songs (How sweet the love that meets return,) and Farewell to Locharber.
                    — in <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0236">the Poor Soldier</title></bibl>
                    she is far inferior to <persName ref="pe1324">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                        Jordan</persName>, — <persName ref="pe1323">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Meliss</persName> and <persName ref="pe1327">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        John Stewart</persName> return’d to sup with us, — and in the morning the
                    former and <persName ref="pe1315">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Wilkie</persName> came to breakfast, when that was over, we all went to
                        <placeName ref="pl1031">the Castle</placeName>. it stands upon an amazing
                    high rock, from which there is a fine extensive prospect, being Sunday we were
                    not allow’d to see the armoury or any thing in the Castle, for the Scotch are
                    strict observers of the Sabbath. the 36 regiment is at present garrison’d there,
                    — from thence we went to <placeName ref="pl0811">Coulton hill</placeName> upon
                    which is a burying place in which is <persName ref="pe1099">David
                        Humes</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl2079">monument</placeName>, it is a very humble affair, but
                    was built according to his request, this hill is on the East side the Town.
                    There is a fine prospect from it, but not so extensive as from the <placeName ref="pl1031">Castle Hill</placeName>, ––––– From this place we went to
                        <placeName ref="pl0724">Holyrood House</placeName> the ancient Palace of the
                    Scottish Kings, to recount the curiosities of this place would require a volume,
                    — therefore shall only mention a few particulars — we were first shewn a long
                    gallery full of fine ancient pictures, among which is an <rs ref="ar0080">original painting</rs> of the unfortunate <persName ref="pe0527">Mary</persName> I own I was a little disappointed in her, as all Historians
                    agree, she <pb n="20"/> was uncommonly beautiful, but I was inform’d there is
                    one in the possession of the Mariners company at <placeName ref="pl0077">Leith</placeName> which she herself gave them, — and that it <add place="above">is</add> beyond description beautiful, — this gallery is fifty
                    six yards long and <add place="above">the wall</add> intirely cover’d with
                    pictures, — of all those who signalized themselves in the service of their
                    Country, ––––– from this place we were taken into a kind of vault, where they
                    shew’d us the thigh bone of <persName ref="pe1328">James the Fifth</persName>
                    and a piece of his flesh, which actually resembles a dried herring, more than
                    any thing else, — They also shew’d us the same <hi rend="underline">joint</hi>
                    of the famous <persName ref="pe1329"><hi rend="underline">Lord</hi>
                        <hi rend="underline">Darnley</hi></persName>, it is a prodigious size —
                    There is no saying whether or <hi rend="underline">not</hi> they are the <hi rend="underline">bones</hi> of those <hi rend="underline">Great</hi> Men, —
                    but our conducteress seem’d to take such pains to assure us they were, that to
                    have disputed her would have been <hi rend="underline">cruel</hi>, — She then
                    went to a Coffin and took out of it the carcase of a woman, which she assured us
                    was the <hi rend="underline">Countess</hi> of <hi rend="underline">Roxburg</hi>,
                    who gave up the Ghost about five hundred years ago,<note type="editorial">There
                        is insufficient information to identify the individual to whom these remains
                        might have belonged.</note> she is six feet four inches high, and has been
                    so well preserved as to have here teeth and nails still entire, — the flesh is
                    dried so hard as to be imperishable. — the woman dangled her in her arms and
                    seem’d to pay no respect to persons. ––––– I was glad to hasten from so
                    disgusting a scene, and tho’ a dead Countess cuts a curious figure, — yet how
                    should we like <add place="above">to suppose,</add> some few years hence we
                    might be exposed as a subject of ridicule to others, — Several of the nobility
                    have apartments in <placeName ref="pl0724">Holyrood House</placeName> for their
                    winter residence, in one of <persName ref="pe1330">Lord Dunmores</persName>
                    rooms there is a remarkable <rs ref="ar0117">fine painting of Charles the first
                        and his Queen</rs> going out to ride. — it was done by <persName ref="pe0595">Vandyke</persName>,<note type="editorial">The painting in
                        question was made by <persName ref="pe0596">Daniel Mytens</persName>,
                            <persName ref="pe0595">Anthony van Dyck's</persName> predecessor as
                        court painter to <persName ref="pe0600">Charles I</persName>.</note> and is
                    esteem’d a capital performance. In the <persName ref="pe1331">Duke of
                        Hamiltons</persName>
                    <pb n="21"/> apartments there is a room in which <persName ref="pe0455">Rezzio</persName> was murdered and the blood mark is yet on the floor.
                    There is a bed and a chair work’d by <persName ref="pe0527">Queen
                        Mary</persName>. — and also the bed in which she used to sleep. Through this
                    room is a small closet, where she was sitting, when she heard the shrieks of
                        <persName ref="pe0455">Rezzio</persName>, — The Tap<add place="above">e</add>stry in these apartments is prodigiously fine, the battles of
                    Constantine the Great, which was brought by <persName ref="pe0527">Queen
                        Mary</persName> out of <placeName ref="pl0925">France</placeName> we
                    reckon’d extremely good,<note type="editorial">It is unclear which piece Dawson
                        is describing here. The tapestries displayed in Holyrood Palace are
                        predominantly seventeenth-century and thus could not have belonged to
                        Mary.</note> — There is in one of these rooms a full length <rs ref="ar0002">picture of Lord Darnley</rs>, he has been remarkably tall. ––––– From
                        <placeName ref="pl0724">Holyrood house</placeName> we return’d to our
                    lodgings <persName ref="pe1323">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Meliss</persName>
                    <persName ref="pe1327">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> John Stewart</persName>
                    and we, sat down to dinner, <persName ref="pe1315">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wilkie</persName> being ingaged to <persName ref="pe1332">Lord
                        Grey</persName>. — however he was kind enough to bring his daughter in the
                    afternoon to take leave of us, — <persName ref="pe1315">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wilkie</persName> is a very agreeable man having been much in
                    the army, he has quite the Military air, ––––– We left <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName> on Sunday, July the 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                    and after a pleasant — ride of about nine miles, arrived at <placeName ref="pl0082">Queens ferry</placeName> by seven. — where we ordered tea, and
                    afterwards <persName ref="pe1323">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Meliss</persName> sent for a gentleman to sup whose name was <persName ref="pe1333">Taylor</persName>, — he told him our intention of seeing
                        <placeName ref="pl0242">Hopeton House</placeName> early in the morning, that
                    we might get over <placeName ref="pl0083">the Firth</placeName> at the time of
                    low water. — <persName ref="pe1333">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Taylor</persName> said he would accompany <add place="above">us</add> and
                    beg’d we would breakfast with him in the morning. ––––– accordingly we did rise
                    early and the gentlemen thought it would be better to send the carriage and
                    horses over first. — and we took a chaise to go to <placeName ref="pl0242">Hopeton House</placeName>, — it is pleasantly situated about two miles up
                    the <placeName ref="pl0083">Firth of Forth</placeName> of which it commands a
                    fine prospect. — It makes a most princely appearance, is a prodigious mass of
                    building, in the form of a crescent. The rooms are not large but are ornamented
                    with an admirable collection of paintings ––––– <pb n="22"/> In the first room
                    one enters, there is a <rs ref="ar0247">full length picture</rs> of <persName ref="pe1335">Lord Hope</persName> elder Brother to <persName ref="pe1097">the present Earl</persName>, who died before <persName ref="pe1334">his
                        father</persName>, he is just come from shooting and is leaning his arm on
                    the stump of an old tree with his gun in his hand, — it was taken when he was
                    going off in a consumption, and is beautifully expressive of a languid and ill
                    state of health, — it’s thought to be an excellent painting. and was done by
                        <persName ref="pe1336">Dance</persName>. — To give a minute detail of all
                    those pictures, is not in my power therefore I shall but mention those which
                    particularly pleas’d me, — There is a <rs ref="ar0248">painting of S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Frances</rs> in the attitude of prayer. and
                    never was fervent devotion more strongly delineated in any countenance whatever,
                    — it is by Connoisseurs reckon’d one of the most admirable performances, and was
                    done by <persName ref="pe1108">Guido Rheni</persName>. — there is also another
                    done by the same great artist. It is <rs ref="ar0249">St. Andrew the
                        Apostle</rs> haul’d to the cross, submission and patient suffering of spirit
                    are strongly expressed in the face of <persName ref="pe1337">Andrew</persName>,
                    as is relentless cruelty in the vissage of those that conduct him. — there is
                    another of <rs ref="ar0250">the asscension of Our Saviour</rs> — . such a
                    glorious benignity is express’d in the countenance of Our Lord, as exceeds all
                    power of description — . I cannot recollect the painters name, but he certainly
                    has great merit ––––– Tho the painting that pleas’d us most, was <rs ref="ar0251">the death of Lucretia</rs> it is in that part when <persName ref="pe1338">Brutus</persName> snatchs up the dagger (with which she has
                    just executed her bloody purpose), and makes that elegant harangue which is
                    justly deem’d an extraordinary piece of Oratory, — She is dying and supported by
                    her husband whose — excess of grief the painter has been unable to describe, so
                    has cover’d his face with his mantle, — in her countenance death is <pb n="23"/>
                    visibly painted without its agonies, she looks as if she was well pleas’d with
                    the glorious choice she had made, which was preferring Death to loss of Honour,
                    — In the faces of the bystanders there is a sort of admiration — mixt with an
                    excess of grief. — the blood is streaming from her side and stands in drops upon
                    the daggers point. — the figures are all as large as life: — and the whole has
                    an effect so astonishing that the different passions so forceably expressed in
                    the piece, vibrate by turns through the heart of the spectator. — it was done by
                        <persName ref="pe1343"><unclear reason="illegible">Gavin</unclear>
                        Hamilton</persName>. — these are all that we particularly remark’d. — we
                    return’d charm’d with our excurtion, and breakfasted with <persName ref="pe1333">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                        Taylor</persName>. — about twelve <persName ref="pe1323">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Meliss</persName> lit a fire upon the shore
                    that being the signal for boats to come over, since they are all kept <add place="above">on</add> the North side. The Ferry, it was not long in coming
                    and we and several other passengers got into it — I always expected to be sick
                    in this expedition — but however I was happily disappointed, the <placeName ref="pl0083">Firth</placeName> was very smooth it is in that part two miles
                    across, and we were but sixteen minutes in performing it. — Nothing could equal
                    the kind concerns of <persName ref="pe1323">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Meliss</persName> with regard to us they demand our sincere
                    acknowledgements, and shall ever be rememberd with gratitude. — we got into the
                        <unclear reason="illegible">Chair</unclear> on the other side and arrived at
                        <placeName ref="pl0085">Kinross</placeName>, the county town of the shire
                    about three. — about a mile to the East of this place, is a small Loch, called
                        <placeName ref="pl0086">Loch Leven</placeName>, there is an Island about the
                    middle of it on which there is the ruin of a <placeName ref="pl0087">Castle</placeName>. — Where we were inform’d <persName ref="pe0527">Queen
                        Mary</persName> was once confined. — the road to this place is rough and
                    hilly. fifteen miles from the ferry. — here we dined and from thence proceed’d
                    to <placeName ref="pl2081">Rosemount</placeName>. — Tho the whole of the journey
                    had been most delightful, yet the pleasure I felt in seeing my friend <persName ref="pe1346">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Meliss</persName> after an
                    absence of above a year occasion’d me the most heartfelt <pb n="24"/>
                    satisfaction I could possibly experience. our pleasure was mutual and I will not
                    attempt to describe the delight we felt at the recollection of those days, when
                    our esteem and unalterable Friendship first took root, and there was not a scene
                    that had pass’d at that happy time but was fresh in our rememberance. —
                        <persName ref="pe1346">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Meliss’s</persName>
                    situation in life is as happy as her deserts are great. — She is blest with a
                    husband who knows the true value of the treasure he possesses, in him every
                    virtue is united, he is lively and animated has a great deal of humanity and
                    true feeling, without the least pretension to it. — as an affectation of fine
                    feelings, is of all affectations the most disgusting. ––––– his manner is easy
                    and genteel and his first study seems to oblige, and make every one about him
                    happy, — <persName ref="pe1346">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                        Meliss</persName> is no less amiable. her friendships, and her attachment to
                    her husband and little infant, are strong, she has a warm and disinterested
                    heart very susceptible of the sorrows of others, — She is form’d for domestic
                    happiness, has not taste for fashionable Levities, but enjoys herself most in a
                    small circle of dear friends, of whom her husband makes the chief, — she is
                    rather more reserved than <persName ref="pe1323">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Meliss</persName> which proceeds from an extreme diffidence, which she is
                    not able to conquer, her understanding is excellent, and as well as her husband
                    she has a great taste for Literature. — This without prejudice is the Character
                    of the worthy inhabitants of <placeName ref="pl2081">Rosemount</placeName>. —
                    for whom I have the most lively friendship. — the situation of this place is
                    extremely beautiful. it is situated on a rising ground about a quarter of a mile
                    from <placeName ref="pl0094">Perth</placeName>, of which Town and excellent
                        <placeName ref="pl0309">bridge</placeName> it commands a good prospect. — on
                    the other hand is a fine view up the Valley in which one sees the windings of
                    the <placeName ref="pl0096">Tay</placeName>. this prospect is terminated <pb n="25"/> by the <placeName ref="pl1166">Grampian Hills</placeName>, ( — <hi rend="underline">where</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">Norval</hi> fed his flock) — .<note type="editorial">A
                        reference to the central character in John Home's play <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0237"><hi rend="italic">Douglas: A
                                    Tragedy</hi></title></bibl> (first performed in 1756), who is
                        introduced as a shepherd boy in the Grampians.</note> — The first week we
                    spent intirely at home, tho we had often company. We generally breakfast’d
                    between nine and ten, then walk’d out, dress’d for dinner read or conversed till
                    three, at which hour we dined, at five if Company was expect’d adjourn’d into
                    the drawing room, drank tea at six, music or conversation till ten, at <add place="above">which</add> time we sup’d, and after it for an hour or two
                    either Scotch reels, or singing. — The people here are extremely sociable and
                    friendly they frequently stay till Twelve, or one o clock in the morning. —
                    There is much more deference paid to the <hi rend="underline">fair</hi> sex here
                    than in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> by the Lords of the
                    creation, the reason is obvious, so much greater attention is paid to the
                    Education of the women that it renders the knowledge of the Two sexes upon a
                    greater equality, — There attention and hospitality to strangers is particularly
                    worthy of remark. — They seem conscious what an uncandid Idea the English have
                    of them and appear to have a great desire to change it. — In short tho the
                    Scotch may be far behind us in Agriculture commerce and all the fine arts, — yet
                    in Mental qualifications they seem infinitely to surpass us. — Where are the
                    stricter observers of the Sabbath. — Where are thefts murders, and suicides
                    seldomer commit’d, — Where are there soldiers or Seamen that in Time of danger,
                    can brave hardships like a Caledonian. ––––– Where is there an Historian like
                        <persName ref="pe0082">Robertson</persName>, a Preacher like <persName ref="pe1102">Blair</persName>, or a Muse like <persName ref="pe1347">Beattie’s</persName>, — I perhaps may be prejudiced in favour of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> as I know nothing so likely to endear a
                    place to us, as containing those we love, — On Sunday August the sixt we went to
                    hear a sermon it was in the Churchyard which as well as the Church was as
                    crowded as could possibly be. — the Clergyman stands in a kind of small wooden
                    house, it is large enough to hold three or four people — and as the day was cold
                        <persName ref="pe1346">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Meliss</persName> and
                    I were usher’d into it. — Notwithstanding <del rend="overstrike">
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/>
                    </del> the solemnity of the <pb n="26"/> occasion I could scarce refrain from
                    laughing at being box’d up with the <hi rend="underline">parson</hi>, Clark, and
                    another man, in a place we had hardly <add place="above">room</add> to stand in.
                    The Clergymans name was <persName ref="pe1348">Chapman</persName>, he is
                    esteem’d here an excellent Orator — tho I cant say his pronounciation pleased me
                    much. he seem’d affecting to speak good English, without having the power to do
                    it — The Presbiterians Pray, and preach extempore. he made a very good prayer.
                    which was longer than most of our Clergymens sermons, — after this he gave out
                    his text which was — (set your affections on things above)<note type="editorial">Colossians 3:2</note> — he preach’d fifty minutes during which time he <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/> fully on the subject. — The
                    people all stand or sit on the cold ground. with their hats or bonnets on. that
                    is the men after the women, at least the lower class never wear any, but have
                    plaids or long blue cloaks which reach to their feet, and have large hoods which
                    upon occasion they put up. — at the end of the prayer and sermon they all pull
                    off their bonnets and bow to the Preacher, this I imajined was by way of thanks
                    — but <persName ref="pe1323">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Meliss</persName>
                    inform’d me it was by way of Obeidiance to the Supreme Being, ––––– This
                    happen’d to be the Fast week at <placeName ref="pl0094">Perth</placeName>
                    <add place="above">It</add> is only once a year when they on the Sunday receive
                    sacrament. — they being on the Thursday to pray and preach, and continue till
                    Sunday in the above manner. and as soon as the Clergyman has done, another
                    ascends the wooden house. — so there the congregation sit or stand. going out
                    perhaps once a day for a little refreshment — On the Sunday when sacrament is
                    received in the Church the congregation all sit round a long table which is
                    placed in the middle aile, and the Clergyman stands on a chair exorting them. to
                    consider <del rend="overstrike">
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/>
                    </del> the consequences of this sacred <pb n="27"/> institution during this
                    exortation, the Elders of the Church who are chosen by the parish as learn’d and
                    judicious men, go round the table and gather tokens which are given by the
                    Clergy of the several parishes to signify all such as are worthy to recive the
                    sacrament, and if they have no token they are rejected as being unfit for it, —
                    They are going to have the Sacrament more frequently to prevent this preaching
                    out of doors, as having it only once a year occasions such crowds to assemble as
                    to make the Churches unable to contain them, — it is said they like it to rain
                    when they are out, and suffer themselves to be wet to the skin, rather than move
                    from the place. — they like it, because they think it gives them an air of
                    greater devotion, — on Monday evening we had a very agreeable party most of
                    whom, on my <persName ref="pe1290">Uncles</persName> account were musical, after
                    the concert Reels were danced, in which <persName ref="pe1349">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Rose</persName> an Old Lady of seventy six —
                    join’d. — and after supper sung us many sprightly airs, — On Tuesday we all
                    except <persName ref="pe1346">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Meliss</persName>
                    (who could not leave her little boy) went to dine at <persName ref="pe1351">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Macalpins</persName> at <placeName ref="pl2083">Cromley ha</placeName>, — six miles from <placeName ref="pl0094">Perth</placeName>, — the road was bad but the prospects from it
                    delightfully pleasant, on the left of the road at the distance of half a mile is
                    a fine view of the ruins of <placeName ref="pl0307">Huntingtour
                        Castle</placeName>, —,</p>
                <p><quote>“In which place <lb/>“<persName ref="pe0533">James the sixth of
                            Scotland</persName> was held prisoner. he was invited there to hunt
                        <lb/>“which was his favorite diversion. but a secret conspiracy was forming
                        against <lb/>“him, All the nobles of <del rend="overstrike">
                            <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/>
                        </del> the realm were assembled, and <persName ref="pe0533">James</persName>
                        <lb/>“conscious he was wrong, in bestowing too much power on his favorites
                            <persName ref="pe1352">Lennox</persName>, <lb/>“and <persName ref="pe1353">Arran</persName>, felt great uneasiness, and when he was
                        about to depart, the Nobles <lb/>“enter’d his bed room in a body, and
                        present’d a memorial against the illegal <lb/>“and oppressive actions of his
                        two favorites, whom they represented as most <lb/>“dangerous enemies to the
                        religion and liberties of the Nation. — <lb/>“<persName ref="pe0533">James</persName> expostulated, threaten’d, and complain’d, but finding
                        these without <lb/><pb n="28"/> effect, burst into tears. The conspirators
                        without regarding either his tears <lb/>or indignation dismiss’d such of his
                        followers as they suspected and allow’d <lb/>none but their own party to
                        have access to him. — and though they <lb/>treated him with great respect,
                        gaurded his person with the greatest <lb/>care, this enterprize is usually
                        call’d by our historians the <lb/>Raid of <placeName ref="pl0307">Ruthven</placeName>, –––––</quote><note type="authorial">NB for the
                        above account see <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0241">Robertsons
                                History of Scotland</title> vol the second, and page the 90</bibl>,
                        ––––– </note></p>
                <p>— We reach’d <placeName ref="pl2083">Cromley</placeName> about two, were
                    introduced to <persName ref="pl2083">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> and Miss
                        Macalpin</persName> after the first salutations were past, which in
                        <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> is always a shake by the hand,
                    — I sat for a Quarter of an hour without speaking a painful <hi rend="underline">situation</hi> for a <hi rend="underline">female</hi>, — at last I was
                    determin’d to try some conversation with <persName ref="pl2083">Miss
                        Macalpin</persName>, not <hi rend="underline">being</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">able</hi> to <hi rend="underline">endure</hi> it <hi rend="underline">any</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">longer</hi>. — but first I will give you a little
                    description of that Lady, not with an intention to excite ridicule, but merely
                    to show what an unpromising subject I had to work upon. — Nature has not been
                    very lavish of her beauties either to her person or face, which is remarkably
                    long, large, light eyes steadfastly fixt, — a long sharp nose, and a mouth none
                    of the smallest, and throughout the whole of her face there is such an unmeaning
                    and forbiding gravity, as I never saw in any countenance before. — I spent a
                    second silent quarter of an hour in studying what topic to enter upon — at last
                    I said — “This <hi rend="underline">is</hi> a <hi rend="underline">charming</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">situation</hi> — Ma’am, — “yes Ma’am — “Don’t you like the
                    country better than the Town in summer — “I really don’t know Ma’am — silence
                    succeed’d — “I am told you have not been here long Ma’am — “No not long Ma’am
                    dinner was announced and down stairs I went with a joyful <pb n="29"/> heart not
                    more because I was hungry but because it relieved me from the most
                    unentertaining discourse I ever enter’d upon. — I remark’d this Lady as being
                    the only one <add place="above">we saw</add> in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> that want’d vivacity — or was at a loss for
                    conversation, — after dinner we went to see the Printing Works <persName ref="pe1351">Mr Macalpin</persName> has great merit, for in a year and a
                    half, he has beautified a place which was before perfectly a wilderness, it is
                    now extremely romantic. — its a narrow Valley through which runs the <placeName ref="pl0306">river Almond</placeName> on one side of it are stupendous rocks
                    cover’d with fine fir trees, and on — the other side <persName ref="pe1351">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Macalpin</persName> has erected a prodigious
                    printing Mill with various houses and sheds for the convenience of the business
                    he has also cut a canal which turns the mill and in which they dip the linnen
                    after every colour is put on.<note type="editorial">The printing works described
                        by Dawson were later mentioned in <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0169"><hi rend="italic">The Statistical Account of
                                Scotland</hi></title>, 21 vols. (Edinburgh: 1791-1799), <biblScope unit="volume">xv</biblScope>, <biblScope unit="page">p.530</biblScope></bibl>: 'Mr William M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Alpine, from the neighbourhood of Glasgow, a clergyman's son, who
                        had been bred a callico printer, came to view this country, and having
                        beheld with astonishment the great quantity of fresh water, made choice of
                        this spot for erecting a cotton mill and print-field.'</note> — it is
                    astonishing how quick they print pocket handkerchiefs these they do with a
                    copper plate, and other things with wooden printers. — There were in one room
                    about a hundred girls putting in the colours with hair pencils (for they only
                    trace the outlines with the wooden instrument) — I told them I thought their
                    occupation a very pleasant one, and assured them the women in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> had <hi rend="underline">much</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">harder</hi> work. — they seem’d much pleas’d at my taking
                    notice of them — . — but made no answer except a general smile, — we return’d to
                    the house drank tea and set off for <placeName ref="pl2081">Rosemount</placeName> ––––– The Day following we went to breakfast with a
                        <persName ref="pe1354">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sandemane</persName>
                    at <placeName ref="pl0097">Luncarty</placeName> three miles full north of
                        <persName ref="pl0094">Perth</persName>. — <persName ref="pe1354">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sandemane</persName> is about 64 has great
                    Grandchildren six years old and is the most allert and lively man I ever saw,
                    though a great oddity he is a good deal respected in the Neighbourhood as being
                    the head of that society called Sandemonians, it was an <persName ref="pe1355">Uncle</persName> of his that was the first founder of it, and this man is
                    now the chief. — His only topic is matrimony, and so great a friend he is to it,
                    that he actually <unclear reason="illegible">almost</unclear> hawks his Children
                    about and generally gets his daughters married by they are fifteen and his sons
                    eighteen. — after breakfast he carried us to see <pb n="30"/> his <placeName ref="pl2084">works</placeName> which are for whitening all sorts of linnen.
                    This is reckon’d the greatest Bleachfield in <placeName ref="pl0777">Briton</placeName>, he helps many weavers employ’d in <placeName ref="pl0094">Perth</placeName> and the colour of his cloth is prefer’d to
                    Irish, — He accompanied us to <placeName ref="pl2085">Stanley</placeName> to
                    dine at <persName ref="pe1356">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Keys</persName>. —
                    This is a beautiful place and stands on the banks of the <placeName ref="pl0096">Tay</placeName> there is a prodigious cotton Mill erect’d at this place
                    which when it is intirely finish’d will employ five hundred people. There are
                    eight proprietors one of which is <persName ref="pe1356">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Key</persName> a very agreeable man who resides on the spot. —
                    they are building a large village for the convenience of the work people and
                    amongst the rest of the improvements a large Sunday School is erecting, which is
                    the first in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>.<note type="editorial">The Sunday School movement in Scotland originated in the 1780s as a
                        response to the increasing number of children who worked full-time in
                        factories and mills such as that at Stanley, and thus had no access to
                        education during the week. It was not uncommon for progressively-minded mill
                        owners (such as David Dale at New Lanark) to provide schools in this way.
                        See R. D. Anderson, <hi rend="italic">Education and the Scottish People
                            1750-1918</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1995), p.13.</note> I
                    was truely sorry to find they were not more general, as the minds of the lower
                    class are totally ignorant and consequently superstitious, and therefore have
                    much want of the benefits attending that excellent institution. — This School is
                    to be support’d by the eight proprietors of the Mill who intend giving an a<add place="above">n</add>nual salery to some Clergyman of good character, who is
                    out of preferment to preach to them every Sunday, teach them to read and
                    instruct them in their duty, — There is no place where there is more occasion
                    for a School of that sort than <placeName ref="pl2085">Stanley</placeName>. —
                    for it is astonishing what a quantity of Children are employ’d in the Cotton
                    Mill. — I could not help expressing the joy I felt in recollecting the
                    advantages this little group would reap from this human institution, and so
                    great an impression it made upon me, that I invoked the Muses aid to give it
                    utterance, this very trifling production so unworthy of the subject which
                    excited it, I am prevailed upon to transcribe and it is as follows. –––––</p>

                <p><pb n="31"/>Verses on <placeName ref="pl2085">Stanley Vale</placeName>
                    <l>Genius of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>, wake the sacred
                        nine</l>
                    <l>Thou Wilt not ask their tuneful aid in vain.</l>
                    <l>Eager they’l listen to a voice like thine,</l>
                    <l>And gladly pour, the sweet, melodious strain.</l>
                    <l>To <placeName ref="pl2085">Stanley Village</placeName>, strike the sounding
                        lyre,</l>
                    <l>That <placeName ref="pl0705">Caledonia</placeName> may catch thy lays,</l>
                    <l>May feel the ardour of poetic fire,</l>
                    <l>Attentive hear, and echo back its praise.</l>
                    <l>Sweet <placeName ref="pl2085">Stanley</placeName>, seated on the banks of the
                            <placeName ref="pl0096">Tay</placeName></l>
                    <l>Whose beauteous Stream, winds copiously along</l>
                    <l>And murmuring oft its circling <add place="above">eddies</add> play </l>
                    <l>Responsive to the pipe, or Milkmaids song. —</l>
                    <l>Along its sides, are ranged the stately pine.</l>
                    <l>Whose verdant foliage, braves the tempest drear,</l>
                    <l>Whose sturdy trunks to neither side incline,</l>
                    <l>But tall and straight their haughty honors rear.</l>
                    <l>Here Industry that ever prosperous fair —</l>
                    <l>Rears her bright standard, spreading peace around,</l>
                    <l>Dispersing penury, and vain dispair,</l>
                    <l>And the shrill cry of want, — heart piercing sound.</l>
                    <l>The Cotton here from <placeName ref="pl1024">India’s</placeName> coast we
                        see,</l>
                    <l>Safe wafted by a kind propitious gale.</l>
                    <l>Behold the produce of that useful tree,</l>
                    <l>Spread competence, and wealth through <placeName ref="pl2085">Stanley
                            Vale</placeName>. —</l>
                    <pb n="32"/>
                    <l>Here we behold employ’d the livelong day</l>
                    <l>A youthful tribe, — who erst knew nought but want,</l>
                    <l>Who spent their hours in idling time away —</l>
                    <l>Without instruction, — of provision scant;</l>
                    <l>And now alas, it grieves my heart to say,</l>
                    <l>Without instruction, they e’en now remain,</l>
                    <l>And spend the Holy Lords, appoint’d day —</l>
                    <l>In wanton resting, and open shame.</l>
                    <l>No longer famish’d cries the ears assail,</l>
                    <l>No longer rest these images of woe,</l>
                    <l>Fell Sloth is banish’d from the Peaceful Vale,</l>
                    <l>Sloth first great cause from whence all evils flow —</l>
                    <l>This praise industry merits, — ha! behold,</l>
                    <l>What form angellic swims before my eyes,</l>
                    <l>A snowy robe, her graceful limbs infold,</l>
                    <l>Sure tis some heavenly regent of the skies.</l>
                    <l>Her mein, her looks, bespeak her heavenly birth,</l>
                    <l>In her right hand, a milk white dove she bears —</l>
                    <l>Emblem of peace, and ever conscious worth,</l>
                    <l>Soother of grief, and quieter of cares. —</l>
                    <l>Her cloudless brow, unconscious of a frown,</l>
                    <l>Her eye beam’d energy and artless truth,</l>
                    <l>Around her form were thousand Graces thrown</l>
                    <l>And her cheek ting’d with the soft blush of youth,</l>
                    <l>She spoke, and speaking charm’d the listening ear,</l>
                    <l>Sweet vibrated the sound through <placeName ref="pl2085">Stanley
                            Vale</placeName>,</l>
                    <l>The <placeName ref="pl0096">Tay</placeName> stopt short, as if intent to hear
                        –</l>
                    <l>When thus the voice soft float’d on the gale —</l>
                    <pb n="33"/>
                    <l>Ye sons of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>, — by supreme
                        command,</l>
                    <l>Know that in me, t’is piety ye view —</l>
                    <l>Lo, I am sent by an Almighty hand,</l>
                    <l>To you, ye highly blest, and favour’d few —,</l>
                    <l>What tho’ Industry here her standards bring,</l>
                    <l>Tho’ Plenty, ever teems her golden horn,</l>
                    <l>Yet if you know not whence these bounties spring,</l>
                    <l>Still must the heart feel wretched, and forlorn —</l>
                    <l>Know that from Heaven, each precious blessing flows,</l>
                    <l>From Heaven, all pure and perfect gifts descend,</l>
                    <l>There will the wearied pilgrim find repose —</l>
                    <l>There will the wretched, find one Faithful Friend,</l>
                    <l>Then teach betimes the unexperienced youth,</l>
                    <l>The Power Supreme, to worship and adore. —</l>
                    <l>To keep his <add place="above">holy</add> word, — to x x x x cherish
                        truth.</l>
                    <l>Thus said, she vanish’d quick, — nor utter’d more. —</l>
                    <l>She said, and none her precepts dare dispise. —</l>
                    <l>Quick throbs the impulse of each generous heart,</l>
                    <l>For see, the humble Village school arise,</l>
                    <l>And each commercial Brother bears a part,</l>
                    <l>A good and virtuous Pastor, next they seek:</l>
                    <l>To rule the youthful tribe with peaceful rod,</l>
                    <l>And the revolving Sabbath of each week —</l>
                    <l>Teach their young Minds the surest way to God.</l>
                    <l>Blest Village, happiest far on <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotia’s</placeName>
                        plains,</l>
                    <l>Blest Institution, form’d by judgement cool,</l>
                    <l>Where pure Religion source of comfort reigns —</l>
                    <l>Religion founder of The Sunday School. </l>
                </p>
                <p><pb n="34"/>The day at <placeName ref="pl2085">Stanley</placeName> was much more
                    agreeably spent than that at <placeName ref="pl2083">Cromley</placeName>, as
                        <persName ref="pe1356">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Key</persName> has two
                    sisters both of whom are chatty and good humour’d. it was rather <add place="above">late</add> before we got to <placeName ref="pl2081">Rosemount</placeName> where we found our friend <persName ref="pe1346">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Meliss</persName> anxiously waiting our
                    return. — The rest of the week was past at home where we had frequently very
                    agreeable parties, and spent a very jovial evening on Saturday August the
                    twelfth with the two <persName ref="pe1357">Miss Andersons</persName> — . The
                    Tuesday following we went to breakfast at <persName ref="pe1358">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wright’s</persName> of <placeName ref="pl2086"><hi rend="underline">Lawtown</hi></placeName>, nine miles from
                        <placeName ref="pl0094">Perth</placeName>. <persName ref="pe1346">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Meliss</persName> and her little boy
                    accompanied us in this excurtion, which made it particularly agreeable — We
                    reached <placeName ref="pl2086">Lawtown</placeName> about eleven, — <persName ref="pe1358">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Wright</persName> we had seen before at <placeName ref="pl2081">Rosemount</placeName>. They seem each upwards of forty <persName ref="pe1358">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> W</persName> is a very sensible
                        <unclear reason="illegible">jocase</unclear> man, and <persName ref="pe1358">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> W</persName> is reckon’d remarkably
                    clever is Cousin to the great Scotch Poet <persName ref="pe1347">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Beattie</persName> and has a great taste for
                    Literature. We were introduced to <persName ref="pe1359">Miss
                        Brandling</persName> Governess to the two <persName ref="pe1358">Miss
                        Wrights</persName>, who had her education at <persName ref="pe1360">Miss
                        Procters</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0768">Doncaster</placeName>. This Lady seems about three and
                    twenty has a countenance extremely dejected, and looks as in a bad state of
                    health. — The pleasure she took in conversing about <placeName ref="pl0768">Doncaster</placeName> was evident, since it enliven’d a face in which
                        <unclear reason="illegible">fervors</unclear> seem’d deeply implanted. — My
                        <persName ref="pe1290">Uncle</persName> said he was once at <persName ref="pe1360">Miss Proctures</persName> when there was a young Lady whose
                    name he had forgot; that she was preparing for a voyage into <placeName ref="pl0697">America</placeName> where she had a sister well settld under
                    whose protection she was going to put herself. I have heard add’d he that she
                    was disappointed by the sudden death of her sister, but you doubtless may know
                    something more <unclear reason="illegible">about it,</unclear>
                    <pb n="35"/> he had no sooner said this than <persName ref="pe1359">Miss
                        Brandling</persName> left the room in great disorder. <persName ref="pe1358">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Wright</persName> (whose attention to
                    this young Lady deserves the highest encomiums) instantly followed her, — and in
                    a short time came back making an apology from <persName ref="pe1359">Miss
                        Brandling</persName> for her strange and sudden departure, “but that he had
                        “<hi rend="underline">touch’d</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">upon</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">the</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">string</hi> on <hi rend="underline">which</hi> hung all her
                        <hi rend="underline">sorrows</hi>”<note type="editorial">Sterne, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0172"><hi rend="italic">Sentimental
                                    Journey</hi></title></bibl>, ii, p.177.</note> — for she herself
                    was the unfortunate girl to whom he alluded. — The death of that sister (add’d
                        <persName ref="pe1358">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Wright</persName>)
                    blast’d all the promising expectations of <persName ref="pe1359">Miss
                            Brandl<unclear reason="illegible">ing</unclear></persName> — without
                    friends — without fortune — a dependant station was the highest she could aspire
                    to. — to a girl possess’d of such a fund of <hi rend="underline">Sensibility</hi> a stroke so unexpected must have been doubly felt, and a
                    deep dejection of spirit which naturally impairs her health has been the result
                    of this disappointment, — I have a sincere affection for her continued she, as
                    well as <persName ref="pe1358">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wright</persName>
                    and we think it our duty by showing her all the tenderness in our power to
                    endeavour to alleviate her sorrows. — My <persName ref="pe1290">Uncle</persName>
                    was much hurt at being the smallest instrument in bringing back so painful a
                    remembrance — <persName ref="pe1359">Miss Brandling</persName> enter’d — and we
                    again commenced a conversation about <placeName ref="pl0768">Doncaster</placeName> and its inhabitants which seem’d the only topic
                    interesting to <persName ref="pe1359">Miss B—</persName> and the rest of the day
                    was spent very x x x agreeably —. <placeName ref="pl2086">Lawtown</placeName> is
                    about two miles from <placeName ref="pl0098">Dunsinane Hill</placeName> where
                        <persName ref="pe0553">Macbeths</persName> Castle stood. — I had express’d a
                    desire to see that place but the day after turn’d out so ill I gave up all
                    thoughts of it, however it clear’d up and after tea <persName ref="pe1358">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Wright</persName> said she was determin’d I
                    should not be disappointed and if nobody would attend us she and I would go
                    together. however <persName ref="pe1346">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                        Meliss</persName> and we got into the Chaise <persName ref="pe1358">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wright</persName> a <persName ref="pe1361">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Berriman</persName> and my <persName ref="pe1290">Uncle</persName> on horsebacks — <pb n="36"/> The road to it
                    was terrible, not being much frequented as few people have an inclination to
                    climb the stupendous steep. — we found it impossible to ride up it; so each of
                    us secured the arm of a Beau, and with much fatigue difficulty, and length of
                    time, reach’d the summit, the evening was too far advanced for us to discern
                    objects at any great distance, otherwise we should have seen one of the finest
                    and most extensive prospects <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>
                    affords, — there are not the smallest remains left of the Castle above ground.
                    but the <persName ref="pe1362">Lord Privy Seal</persName> and several more
                    Antiquarians have dug <add place="above">of late</add> and found several
                    vestiges that lead them to conclude the <persName ref="pe1363">Thane of
                        Fife</persName> by whom it was destroy’d, had levell’d it by fire, as they
                    have discover’d a quantity of burnt corn, and stones which have the appearance
                    of cinders, — there is a high bank raised round it which has been by way of
                        defence.<note type="editorial">Dunsinane lay on the estate of James
                        Stuart-Mackenzie of Belmont, keeper of the privy seal of Scotland. Thomas
                        Pennant writes in his description of Dunsinane: 'At present there are not
                        any remains of this celebrated fortress: its place is now a verdant area, of
                        an oval form, fifty-four yards by thirty, and surrounded by two-deep
                        ditches. On the north is a hollow road, cut through the rock, leading up to
                        the entry, which lies on the north east, facing a deep narrow chasm, between
                        this and the next hill. The hill has been dug into; but nothing was
                        discovered, excepting some very black corn, which probably had undergone the
                        operation of <hi rend="italic">Graddan</hi>, or burning', <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0010"><hi rend="italic">Tour in Scotland
                                    and Voyage to the Hebrides 1772 Part II</hi></title>, (London:
                            1776), <biblScope unit="page">p.179</biblScope></bibl>. The mineralogist
                        John Williams mentions Dunsinane in his treatise on vitrified forts, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0235"><hi rend="italic">An account of
                                    some remarkable ancient ruins, lately discovered in the
                                    Highlands</hi></title> (Edinburgh: 1777), <biblScope unit="page">pp.51-55</biblScope></bibl>.</note> — <placeName ref="pl2087">Ber<hi rend="underline">n</hi>am Hill</placeName> is about twelve miles
                    off. there is now no wood upon it — having been (if we may credit <persName ref="pe0494">Shakespeare</persName>) all cut down by <persName ref="pe1363">Macduff’s</persName> forces,<note type="editorial">A reference to the
                        events of Shakespeare's <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0570"><hi rend="italic">Tragedy of Macbeth</hi></title></bibl>,
                        V.iv-vi.</note> — after staying there about a quarter of an hour, we
                    descended the Hill, got into the carriage, and got safe to <placeName ref="pl2086">Lawtown</placeName>, this place takes its name from a
                        <placeName ref="pl2088">hill</placeName> which is close by <persName ref="pe1358">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wright’s</persName> house. on
                    this <persName ref="pe0553">Macbeth</persName> used every week to dispense the
                    laws to a crowded assembly. — henceforth the Village just by is called
                        <placeName ref="pl2086">Lawtown</placeName>,<note type="editorial">Pennant
                        notes in this area 'several tumuli composed of earth and stones of a
                        pyramidical form, called, here Lawes. One of a considerable size, near a
                        gentleman's seat, called Law-town, is supposed to have been that from which
                        Macbeth administered justice to his people', <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0010"><hi rend="italic">Tour in Scotland 1772 Part
                                II</hi></title> (1776) pp.179-180</bibl>. See also <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0169"><hi rend="italic">The Statistical
                                    Account of Scotland</hi></title> 21 vols (Edinburgh: 1791-1799),
                            xiii, p.537n</bibl>.</note> — we related our excurtion to <persName ref="pe1359">Miss Brandling</persName>
                    <persName ref="pe1323">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Meliss</persName> and my
                        <persName ref="pe1319">Cousin</persName>, and spent a very jovial evening, —
                    In the morning when breakfast was over we took leave of the worthy and agreeable
                    family at <placeName ref="pl2086">Lawtown</placeName>. — The parting on the side
                    of <persName ref="pe1359">Miss Brandling</persName> was truely melancholy. The
                    delight she had felt in talking of a place where she had cherish’d so many
                    flattering expectations, — a place in which she had <add place="above">known</add> nothing but pleasure, — <pb n="37"/> was superior to any
                    injoyment she had experienced since she has left it, she seem’d to have
                    conceived an attachment for us, and wept as if she had been parting with the
                    nearest relatives. — I never felt greater compassion for any one, and for some
                    time <persName ref="pe1359">Miss Brandlings</persName> misfortunes gain’d such
                    an ascendancy over my heart as to make me insensible of injoyment. <persName ref="pe1346">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Meliss</persName> who is ever
                    desirous of promoting pleasure earnestly intreated her to come to <placeName ref="pl2081">Rosemount</placeName> while we staid, and <persName ref="pe1358">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Wright</persName> kindly
                    seconded the motion, but she refused saying a second parting would but renew her
                    uneasiness. — <persName ref="pe1323">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Meliss</persName> my <persName ref="pe1290">Uncle</persName>
                    <persName ref="pe1319">Cousin</persName> and myself set off for <placeName ref="pl0316">Dundee</placeName>, and <persName ref="pe1346">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> M.</persName> with her child and Maid for
                        <placeName ref="pl2081">Rosemount</placeName> — The road from <placeName ref="pl2086">Lawton</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0316">Dundee</placeName> is most delightfully picturesque and romantic, between
                    two enormous hills where we seem’d hem’d in on every side, a little further the
                    hills divide, and form the sweetest little Valley imajinable, through which runs
                    a burn that often meets with rocks and other obstructions and dashing over them
                    forms the most delightful cascades — in this Valley are several little huts
                    scatter’d about at some distance from each other. at the North side of them they
                    plant firs to shelter them from the Northern blast, and in the South they have
                    little gardens stock’d with Cabbages Pottatoes, and other vegetables for winter
                    use, — they are ten or twelve miles from any Town and I really think it is not
                    possible for nature to have lavish’d more beauties, than in the compass of this
                    little Arcadian Valley. ––––– We reach’d <placeName ref="pl0316">Dundee</placeName> about one, it is a pretty good Town, pleasantly situated
                    near the <placeName ref="pl2091">Firth of Tay</placeName>. There is a large
                    Manufactory of coarse Cloth at this place, there is nothing much worth
                    observation at <placeName ref="pl0316">Dundee</placeName>
                    <unclear reason="illegible">&amp;</unclear> I called upon <persName ref="pe1367">Miss Read</persName> for whom I had x x x x x a large packet from
                        <placeName ref="pl0763">York</placeName> — That Lady was well and express’d
                    a great <pb n="38"/> regard for <placeName ref="pl0763">York</placeName> and its
                    inhabitants, from whom she said she had receiv’d many civilities, I parted with
                    her about five, and arrived at <placeName ref="pl2081">Rosemount</placeName> by
                    eight. — On Thursday we spent a very agreeable evening at old <persName ref="pe1349">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Roses</persName> there was a
                    large party, and amongst the rest, a <persName ref="pe1368">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Stewart</persName> — a very stately Beau, who
                    after supper when merriment prevail’d sat without deigning to smile, and look’d
                    as if he thought mirth extremely vulgar, — The day following there was a very
                    agreeable Concert and Ball at Cambells large room. — <persName ref="pe1349">Old
                            M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Rose</persName> danced from eight o
                    clock till three in the morning. — The day after we went to <placeName ref="pl0092">Duplin</placeName>, the seat of <persName ref="pe0583">Lord
                        Kinnoul</persName>, it is about 4 miles from <placeName ref="pl0094">Perth</placeName>, the pleasure grounds are very extensive and laid out
                    with great taste — . Nature indeed has done much for it, — furnished them with
                    rocks and natural cascades Gifts infinitely superior to <add place="above">all</add> the skill of labour’d art, — The house is not large, and nothing
                    in it but family pictures, which are very unentertaining, <persName ref="pe0583">Lord Kinnoul</persName> was twice Ambassador — by which means he has had
                    two services of plate which together with a large quantity belonging to the
                    family cuts a conspicuous figure. — from this place we went to <placeName ref="pl2092">Stillend</placeName> to dine at <persName ref="pe1370">Captain
                        Stewarts</persName> — <persName ref="pe1370">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                        Stewart</persName> appears to be about forty, is still a handsome looking
                    woman and has a large family. — <persName ref="pe1370">The Captain</persName>
                    exactly answers the Character of the <hi rend="underline">British</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">Tar</hi>, — is honest, open hearted and courageous — it was
                    rather late before we reach’d <placeName ref="pl2081">Rosemount</placeName> The
                    two days following were taken up with the unpleasant occupations of taking
                    leave, and packing up, — And on Tuesday August the twenty second about ten o
                    clock, we left <placeName ref="pl2081">Rosemount</placeName>
                    <persName ref="pe1346">
                        <hi rend="superscript">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                        Meliss</hi></persName> myself the child and maid in a chaise and <persName ref="pe1323">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Meliss</persName> with my
                        <persName ref="pe1290">Uncle</persName> in the Chair. — <placeName ref="pl0099">Dunkeld</placeName> is about fifteen miles from <pb n="39"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0094">Perth</placeName>, the road rather rough and hilly, but
                    the views from it uncommonly pleasant. — we reached it about one — and went
                    before dinner to see <placeName ref="pl2093">Ossians Hall</placeName> — which,
                    is about a mile from the inn. — The road to it is by the side of the river
                        Rumble,<note type="editorial">A reference to <placeName ref="pl2094">Rumbling Bridge</placeName> over the <placeName ref="pl2095">River
                            Braan</placeName></note> — which falls into the <placeName ref="pl2095">Tay</placeName> a little below — The name of this river takes its rise from
                    the various obstructions that impedes its course, over these obstructions it
                    rushs with redoubled violence and forms cascades which cause a never ceasing <hi rend="underline">Rumble</hi>. — <placeName ref="pl2093">Ossians
                        Hall</placeName> on the outside appears a half circular building when you
                    enter it it is perfectly round and opposite the door is a fine <rs ref="ar0252">painting of Ossian, the poet and some of the Celestial <hi rend="underline">nine</hi></rs>, — while our attention was busily occupied in observing
                    this picture — it suddenly vanish’d (by the help of a pulley) — and behind it we
                    perceived a most elegant apartment, — the surprise this occasion’d us was great.
                    — what with the noise of the pictures removal and the sight of this unexpected
                    room — on entering it the pleasure and surprise is infinitely increas’d by a
                    most beautiful and romantic cascade which is just below the window, the rocks
                    are very high and rugged and the water dashes over them with astonishing
                    violence. — On the Ceiling of the apartment are several mirrors, and to look up
                    and see the reflection of the water foaming above, has the finest effect
                    imaginable. —</p>
                <p>Many think a hermitage in this situation would have been more in character than
                    this elegant little Temple, the sides of which are ornamented with paintings on
                    the plaister all well executed, and the cornish gold, — A little below the
                    cascade is a bridge built of rude stone, and just by it a cave hewn out of the
                    solid rock. This cave is a great contrast to the superb richness of <placeName ref="pl2093">Ossians Hall</placeName> — it is ornament’d with shellwork,
                    Scotch pebbles &amp;.c — <pb n="40"/> This part of the pleasure Grounds of the
                        <persName ref="pe0548">Duke of Athol</persName>, which is on the south side
                    of the ferry, was intirely the taste of <persName ref="pe1372">Lady Charlotte
                        Murrey</persName>, sister to the Duke — to whom when it was compleated she
                    made a present of it. — From thence, we return’d to dinner after which we
                    cross’d the ferry. The House and principal part of the pleasure grounds lay on
                    the north side of it. but as the day was far advanced, we had not time to see
                    them — and now the most painful task was come. the parting with our dear and
                    worthy friends <persName ref="pe1323">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName>
                    &amp; <persName ref="pe1346">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Meliss</persName>,
                    ––––– Over this scene, then let me draw a veil ––––– Nor dwell upon a theme the
                    sadness of which could by be alleviated by the kind promise (If Heaven
                    permitted) of a visit from them next summer, — I will not attempt a description
                    of our feelings at this moment — but borrow the elegant lines of a deservedly
                    celebrated Poetess. –––––</p>
                <p><quote>
                        <l>For every Good and Gracious Soul</l>
                        <l>Where gentle feelings dwell,</l>
                        <l>Will better far conceive the whole</l>
                        <l>Than any Muse can tell, —<note type="editorial">Hannah More, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0242">‘Sir Eldred of the Bower’,
                                        ii, ll.148-48, <hi rend="italic">Sir Eldred of the Bower and
                                            the Bleeding Rock: Two Legendary Tales</hi> (London:
                                        1776)</title></bibl>. More's poem is set on the banks of the
                                Tay.</note></l>
                    </quote></p>
                <p>We left them at <placeName ref="pl0099">Dunkeld</placeName>, and made the best of
                    our way to <placeName ref="pl0110">Blair</placeName> which place we reach’d by
                    nine. — it is twenty miles and the road <hi rend="underline">remarkably</hi>
                    good and the prospects uncommonly beautiful, and diversified with wood, rocks,
                    and water. — <placeName ref="pl0110">Blair</placeName> is another seat of the
                        <persName ref="pe0548">Duke of Athol</persName>. the situation is not equal
                    to that at <placeName ref="pl0099">Dunkeld</placeName>. but the pleasure grounds
                    more extensive. and. well laid out. some fine natural cascades
                        <sic>ornaments</sic> it very much The outside appearance of the house is not
                    very striking and it <pb n="41"/> is a faithful index of the inside, as the
                    furniture is very plain and there are no paintings. — The family had just
                    breakfasted and had regaled themselves <hi rend="underline">with</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">herrings</hi> as we saw several plates full of well pick’d
                    bones. — I suppose this is their Graces usual breakfast — They live very retired
                    and attend much to the education of their children, and have neither been at
                        <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> or <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName> these three years. — sometimes they reside at
                        <placeName ref="pl1127">Dunkeld</placeName>, but oftener at <placeName ref="pl0110">Blair</placeName>, —</p>
                <p>— We left this place at twelve, and went eight miles back on the <placeName ref="pl0099">Dunkeld</placeName> road to get to the ferry of <placeName ref="pl0281">Logyret</placeName>. which we cross’d — about five miles from
                        <placeName ref="pl0110">Blair</placeName> is the pass of <placeName ref="pl0112">Gillicranké</placeName> — a streight road between two
                    stupendous rocks, where the <persName ref="pe0556">Duke of Cumberland</persName>
                    met and fought the rebels in 1745,<note type="editorial">A concatenation of the
                        events of the Jaocbite rising of 1745 with the 1689 battle of Killiecrankie,
                        which was fought between the Jacobite forces of John Graham of Claverhouse,
                        viscount Dundee, and the supporters of William of Orange, led by General
                        Hugh Mackay.</note> — We dined at <placeName ref="pl2102">Weimss</placeName>, a wretch’d village and our accomodations were nearly
                    correspondent with the look of the habitations. — From this place we pursued our
                    rout to <placeName ref="pl0101">Kinmore</placeName> the seat of the <persName ref="pe1375">Earl of Bredalbane</persName>. — this place we reach’d in the
                    evening and early next morning were conducted by the Park keeper through his
                    Lordships <hi rend="underline">Policy</hi> — .<note type="editorial">An echo of
                        Thomas Pennant's description of the earl of Breadalbane's grounds at
                        Taymouth: 'His Lordship's policy surrounds the house'. Pennant notes: 'This
                        word here signifies improvements, or demesne: when used by a merchant, or
                        tradesman, signifies their warehouses, shops and the like.' The wording is
                        identical in Pennant, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0001"><hi rend="italic">Tour in Scotland 1769</hi></title></bibl>
                        (Chester: 1771), p.77(n), and <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0010"><hi rend="italic">Tour in Scotland and Voyage to the Hebrides 1772
                                    Part II</hi></title></bibl> (London: 1776), p.34(n).</note> we
                    follow’d him along a broad grass walk the trees forming an Alcove, this walk is
                    two miles and a half in length but we went only one. — when turning on the right
                    we cross’d a neat <placeName ref="pl2103">Chinese bridge</placeName> which is
                    over the <placeName ref="pl0096">river Tay</placeName>. this road lead us to the
                    park where the house stands and in which there is a great quantity of fallow
                    deer. — this place we cross’d in order to ascend a mount on which is built an
                    elegant fortress at the top of it is a flag which is hoisted on any particular
                    occasion — and on the ramparts are placed eighteen small cannons. — From this
                    eminence there is a most delightful prospect of <placeName ref="pl0104">Loch
                        Tay</placeName>, which is about a mile distant. also of the Church and
                    Newbuilt <placeName ref="pl0103">Village of Kinmore</placeName> — <pb n="42"/>
                    which stands close by the Loch. — we descended this hill and went to see the
                    house the middle part of it has a very antique appearance but the two wings have
                    been built by the <persName ref="pe0036">late Earl</persName>, and look very
                    modern. we did but see the dining and drawing rooms both of which are good. the
                    former is ornament’d with family pictures by <persName ref="pe0595">Vandyke</persName> and other eminent artists.<note type="editorial">In his
                        description of Taymouth Pennant mentions two portraits by van Dyck, of the
                        brothers <rs ref="ar0255">Henry Rich, First Earl of Holland</rs> and <rs ref="ar0256">Robert Rich, Second Earl of Warwick</rs>, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0010"><hi rend="italic">Tour in Scotland
                                    and Voyage to the Hebrides 1772 Part II</hi></title></bibl>
                        (London: 1776), pp.31-33.</note> — the latter has some fine Historical
                    paintings chiefly from scripture —, one remarkably fine of the <rs ref="ar0257">meeting of <hi rend="underline">Jacob</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Easau</hi></rs>, another of <rs ref="ar0258">St Frances</rs> and
                    several others. — after walking above four miles we return’d to <placeName ref="pl2104">the inn</placeName>, which as well as the rest of the Village
                    is intirely new. — <placeName ref="pl0101">Kinmore</placeName> is by many <hi rend="underline">travellers</hi> reckon’d the most beautiful place in
                        <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> the situation is indeed
                    remarkably good. — but what to me gives it the highest preferance. — is the
                    neatness of the Village above mention’d<note type="editorial">Unusually, Dawson
                        appears to use the name 'Kinmore' to refer to both the village and parish of
                            <placeName ref="pl0103">Kenmore</placeName>, and to <placeName ref="pl0101">Taymouth Castle</placeName>.</note> — For after having
                    admired the beauties of <placeName ref="pl1127">Dunkeld</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl0110">Blair</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl0092">Duplin</placeName>
                    &amp;c where every effort of luxurious art is practised to assist the works of
                    Nature, — after having gazed upon the dazzling luster of a splendid sideboard —
                    your pity, your resentment is awakened when you behold these places surrounded
                    by miserable hovels unfit for human creatures to reside in. — mere sheds through
                    which the sharp Northern wind finds a thousand crevices to enter. –––––</p>
                <p>How is one disgusted at the thought, that what is <add place="above">in</add> one
                    week expended in unnecessary trifles, would give comfort to the hearts of so
                    many poor famish’d shivering sufferers. — To me a neat and comfortable Village
                    would add much more <add place="above">to</add> the beauty of any pleasure
                    grounds, than a set of the most sumptuous temples dedicated to any of the
                    Heathen Deities. — this may x x x be said to be an unfashionable and romantic
                    preferance —, but let it be what <pb n="43"/> it may I am determined to indulge
                    it. — The <persName ref="pe1375">present Earl</persName> is very young and but
                    lately return’d from his travels, — but seems to be much liked and is said to
                    have an amiable disposition, his policy is very extensive as is also his
                    property, for he can travel one hundred miles streight forward in his own estate
                    and yet I fancy has not more than twelve thousand a <hi rend="underline">year</hi> — . we were inform’d <placeName ref="pl1122">the
                        hermitage</placeName> was well worth seeing which was about four miles out
                    of our direct road. to this place we went and devoutly do I wish I had a pen
                    sufficiently descriptive to give an adequate Idea of the unequal’d beauties of
                    this little Elysium. However I will aim to give a faint imperfect sketch of it.
                    ––––– Art has little hand in it and Nature reigns predominant. — It is a steep
                    glen in the midst of which are high and rugged rocks, over them rush large
                    sheets of waters, which form the most beautiful cascades imaginable. — the sides
                    of these rocks are cover’d with trees shrubs and wild flowers. ––––– One is lead
                    by a winding path to a door which conveyed us through a dark subteranuous
                    passage. — hewn out of an astonishing rock. — at the end of this passage is
                    another door, which when open’d discovers a hermitage, which one enters. it is
                    built of clay and moss and in the inside ornament’d with shellwork and plaister
                    in imitation of fruit — which is supposed to be the Hermits food. — there is a
                    humble couch of goats skin for him to repose on, and above it an old library of
                    ancient manuscripts which apparently might have been <hi rend="underline">saved</hi> in <hi rend="underline">Noah’s Ark</hi> — this <placeName ref="pl1122">Hermitage</placeName> is built in the form of a Sexagan stands
                    on a high rock — and exactly opposite the window at the distance of about 60
                    yards is a Cataract which is said to be the finest in <placeName ref="pl0777">Briton</placeName>.<note type="editorial">The <placeName ref="pl2105">Falls
                            of Acharn</placeName>.</note> it falls eighty yards perpendicular is an
                    amazing sheet <add place="above">of water</add> — and loses itself in murmurs
                    among the rocky bed below — <pb n="44"/> I sincerely wish every one who has a
                    true taste for the beauties of nature to visit the <placeName ref="pl1122">Hermitage</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl0107">Taymouth</placeName>. —
                    after seeing it how dull and insipid is the stiff cut avenue and gravel walk. —
                    We found we should be obliged to go back to <placeName ref="pl0103">Kinmore</placeName> in order to get the right road to <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName> which we did and travel’d fifteen miles
                    close by the side of <placeName ref="pl0104">Loch Tay</placeName>, — it is a
                    fine peice of water in some parts a mile and a half across, its computed to be
                    from fifty to one hundred fathom deep. — and what is very remarkable was never
                    known to freeze tho’ it can have no communication with the sea. — we arrived at
                        <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName> about three o clock. <placeName ref="pl2106">the Inn</placeName> there is kept by a Yorkshireman and Wife
                    who formerly lived at — <placeName ref="pl2041">Wetherby</placeName>. My
                        <persName ref="pe1290">Uncle</persName> knew them and it is natural to
                    suppose the pleasure they would feel at the unexpect’d sight of their Country
                    people The situation of <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName> tho’ an odd
                    house is extremely pleasant being between the two rivers<note type="editorial">The <placeName ref="pl0995">Dochart</placeName> and the <placeName ref="pl1003">Lochay</placeName>.</note> that feed <placeName ref="pl0104">Loch Tay</placeName>, — We left this place about five and made
                    the best of our way to <placeName ref="pl0212">Tynedrum</placeName>. it was
                    twenty miles to that place and I dare venture to say worse road was never
                    travell’d, — We were in constant fear of an overturn. durst not venture out of a
                    foots pace and were frequently obliged to alight, and walk ––––– by this means
                    it grew dark long before we reach’d <placeName ref="pl0212">Tynedrum</placeName>. — we kept enquiring how far to that place and which was
                    the road. but could gain little information as most of our informers spoke
                    nothing but Erse. — <pb n="45"/> however we journied on terribly fatigued
                    without knowing when we should have rest, at length we perceived a light and
                    never were poor benighted travellers more rejoiced. we made up to it and found
                    it to be <placeName ref="pl2107">the Inn</placeName>. — I got out of the Chair
                    and was running in when I was met in a long dark passage by a prodigious fat
                    gigantic woman, with a candle in her hand and with a hoarse voice scarcely
                    intelligable inform’d me she could <add place="above">not</add> possibly make
                    room for us, — you positively must spare us a corner said I we will put up with
                    any accomodations but for Gods sake admit us into the house for we are almost
                    starved and tired to death, —</p>
                <p>— well replied she then follow me, — I did so, up a pair of dark stone stairs at
                    the top of which she open’d a door, pop’d in her head and mutter’d something I
                    could not understand, upon which a large party of drunken Highlanders stagger’d
                    out of it, we enter’d. it was a very small apartment in one corner stood a bed a
                    table just by it, it smelt much of Wiskie which nectar I suppose the above
                    mention’d Gods had been quaffing. — This room said she is bespoke by a Gentleman
                    in the house — but perhaps he may give it up to you. — I will ask him — as for
                    the Gentlemen I don’t <add place="above">know</add> what to do with them, we
                    must make them a place somewhere — . I then desired her to show them up — and
                    make us a good fire — then gave her a brace of Moorgame, which had been politely
                    sent us at <placeName ref="pl0103">Kinmore</placeName> by two Gentlemen who were
                    shooting those — and beg’d her to roast them for supper — , soon after <persName ref="pe1376">Captain Cambell</persName> sent his <choice>
                        <abbr>Comp<hi rend="superscript">ts</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>Compliments</expan>
                    </choice>. and desired me to make use of his room. — which offer I readily
                    accepted and return’d my thanks. — We spent our evening very merrily in <hi rend="underline">praising</hi> the gallantry of the Caledonian <hi rend="underline">Beaux.</hi> — about twelve we parted and lucky for us we
                    were so tired as not to regard our uncomfortable lodgings — <pb n="46"/> we left
                    this place early the next morning, and found the road to <placeName ref="pl0214">Dalmally</placeName> pretty good at that place we breakfasted, I had forgot
                    to mention a fine Loch, which we pass’d before we reach’d <placeName ref="pl0214">Dalmally</placeName> it is called <placeName ref="pl0269">Loch
                        Awe</placeName>, — it is of a very irregular form and has several Islands
                    upon it, which are well planted and many of them ornamented with old ruins. — We
                    left <placeName ref="pl0214">Dalmally</placeName> about one and persued our rout
                    to <placeName ref="pl1072">Inverary</placeName>, the road between these two
                    stages is very good but rather hilly, the last four miles which is through the
                        <persName ref="pe0086">Duke of Argyle’s</persName> policy, is very rich and
                    beautiful and well contrasted with the former part of the roads which is
                    incompass’d with high rocks and stupendous hills cover’d with nothing but black
                    Ling and Broom. — We reached <placeName ref="pl1072">Inverary</placeName> about
                    four, order’d dinner after what which we took a long walk, up to the summit of
                    an amazing steep, called <placeName ref="pl0218"><hi rend="underline">Dunikaith</hi> Hill</placeName>, where an Observatory is built — At the
                    top of this hill one looks almost perpendicularly down upon the <placeName ref="pl0217">Castle of Inverary</placeName>, the residence of the <persName ref="pe0086">Duke of Argyle</persName>, which cuts a grand and ancient
                    appearance. It is a large building nearly square flat roof’d and a large Tower
                    in the middle, a considerable height above the rest of the building. — The
                    situation is delightfully pleasant in a fine lawn and commands a most beautiful
                    prospect of <placeName ref="pl1070">Loch Fyne</placeName>, which having a
                    communication with the sea ––––– is salt water. — When we descended this hill
                    went to <add place="above">see</add> the <placeName ref="pl0217">Castle</placeName> the appartments are spacious and lofty and are most
                    elegantly finish’d, there are some good family pictures but few from history. —
                        <persName ref="pe1377">Lady Augusta Campbell</persName> the Dukes eldest
                    Daughter, is very handsome and <add place="above">has</add> a great taste for
                    music, painting, and all the fine arts — <persName ref="pe1379">The
                        Dutchess</persName> we saw but at a distance with <persName ref="pe1380">Lady Darby</persName>
                    <pb n="47"/>
                    <persName ref="pe1381">Madame Halliarde</persName>, a French woman of quality
                    and several others whose names I have forgot, after having seen all the
                    apartments below we were taken up stairs to a square gallery form which one
                    looks down into the saloon it is support’d by large pillars — from this gallery
                    one ascends still higher till one gets to the lead terrace which surrounds the
                    foot of the middle tower from whence we had a fine prospect of <placeName ref="pl1070">the Loch</placeName>, tho not an extensive one as it is
                    encompass’d with high rocks, we descended and return’d to the Inn, well pleased
                    with the days diversion, —</p>
                <p>We left <placeName ref="pl1072">Inverary</placeName> about nine the next morning
                    and travell’d by the side of <placeName ref="pl1070">Loch Fyne</placeName>, for
                    about ten miles, — before a very serious calamity befel us, which was one of the
                    main hind springs broke, we were sadly distress’d by this accident being fifty
                    miles from <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName>, which was the nearest
                    place we could get it mended at, — it rain’d ter<add place="above">r</add>ibly
                    and we <add place="above">were</add> obliged to go slow and cautiously. My
                        <persName ref="pe1290">Uncle</persName> and <persName ref="pe1319">cousin</persName> thought it would be best to tye the spring with a piece
                    of card — we stopt opposite a wretched looking hovel in order to do it and ask’d
                    for some water to steep it in. — which was brought us by a little girl, the
                    picture of miserable poverty she ran back again, and fetch’d me some berries in
                    a little tub, — Her name she said was <persName ref="pe1382">Taby M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>Darty</persName>, she spoke good English and
                    seem’d to be about nine years old. — the habitation she came out off was built
                    of clay and laths, and was badly thatch’d with broom, holes were left in the
                    side to admit light, through these holes issued all the smoke — so they serve
                    both for windows, and chimneys. — My <persName ref="pe1290">Uncle</persName>
                    advised me to dispose of the Goosberries, by throwing them away as the hands
                    they came from where none of the cleanest. — this advice was needless as I
                    scarce durst touch them with my fingers for fear of the disorder for which the
                    lower class in this country, are pretty famous —<note type="editorial">Eighteenth-century travellers to Scotland were wary of a skin disease known
                        as the Sibbens, also rendered 'sivvens' or 'civvens', particularly
                        associated with the poor of the Highlands. It was described by Pennant in an
                        appendix to his <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0010"><hi rend="italic">Tour in Scotland 1772 Part II</hi> (1776)</title></bibl>: 'A
                        Loathsome and very infectious disease of the venereal kind, called the <hi rend="italic">Sivvens</hi>, has long afflicted the inhabitants of the
                        Highlands, and from thence some parts of the Lowlands in <hi rend="italic">Scotland</hi>, even as far as the border of <hi rend="italic">England</hi>. Tradition says that it was introduced by the soldiers of
                            <hi rend="italic">Cromwell</hi> garrisoned in the Highlands',
                        p.447</note>
                    <pb n="48"/> about five miles from this place we reach’d a prodigious Hill on
                    which is a stone with this inscription <placeName ref="pl0220">(<hi rend="underline">Rest and be thankful</hi>)</placeName> from this Hill
                    (which is very steep) the road is lead as gradually as possible it is two long
                    miles to the bottom of this x x x Valley<note type="editorial"><placeName ref="pl1068">Glen Croe</placeName>.</note> we walk’d all this way, as in
                    the state our carriage was in, we judg’d it dangerous to remain in it. — it
                    luckily clear’d up, and we had no unpleasant walk, our prospect was amazing
                    rugged and romantic rocks on each side at least a quarter of a mile
                    perpendicular, down their sides rush torrents which dash’d from one rock to
                    another with amazing violence these were greatly augmented with the prodigious
                    quantity of rain which had fallen in the night. — no other prospect than this
                    afford’d itself for several miles —</p>
                <p>I could not help thinking how many there are in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> who would travel this stage and many others in
                        <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> full of anger and vexation, and
                    when they got seated by their own fire sides would most bitterly abuse the
                    barren and unfruitful soil of this Kingdom — How impotent and <add place="above">irreligious</add> is such conduct: to find fault with Nature is surely to
                    arraign the Wisdom of God; is this then a proper return to him who cloaths our
                    feilds with verdure. — and gives us every luxury we enjoy. — Is it a proper
                    return to blaspheme his works. because they do not smile with riches like our
                    own? ––––– These scenes methinks should have a tendancy quite different They
                    should impress us with a lively gratitude for the inestimable blessings so
                    lavishly bestow’d <hi rend="underline">upon us</hi>. — and by seeing how much
                    they overballance those in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>, create
                    in us an ardent desire of deserving them. for as we have much more give, — so
                    have we much more reason to be thankful.<note type="editorial">Like those of
                        many of her contemporaries, Dawson's response to the Highland landscape
                        touches on a long-lived debate on the divine purpose of wilderness, often
                        associated with Bishop Thomas Burnett, whose <hi rend="italic">Sacred Theory
                            of the Earth</hi> (1684) argued that mountains were the debris of the
                        biblical flood and thus an instructive reminder that the imperfections of
                        worldly creation were the product of human sin. See Marjorie Hope Nicolson,
                            <hi rend="italic">Mountain Gloom and Mountain Glory: The Development of
                            the Aesthetics of the Infinite</hi> (Ithica: Cornell University Press,
                        1959) and Peter Womack, <hi rend="italic">Improvement and Romance:
                            Constructing the Myth of the Highlands</hi> (Houndmills: Macmillan,
                        1988).</note>
                    <pb n="49"/> a little onward another prospect open’d to us. which was <placeName ref="pl0221">Loch Long</placeName>. it is a fine sheet of water, of an
                    irregular form but not very broad. — we cross’d a bridge which is over the river
                    that feeds it,<note type="editorial"><placeName ref="pl2108">Loin
                            Water</placeName></note> which joins the <placeName ref="pl0833">Firth
                        of Clyde</placeName> by which means it is salt water, — about four miles
                    farther is <placeName ref="pl0222">Tarbet Inn</placeName>, which we reach’d by
                    four o clock. the look of this house did not promise us much comfort, however we
                    order’d dinner and Good stomach (according to the old proverb) being the best
                    sauce. — we found no fault with our provisions, which (by the by) were not
                    capital, This Inn stands close by <placeName ref="pl0223">Loch
                        Lomond</placeName> a Lake which all agree is not <add place="above">to</add>
                    be equal’d by any in <placeName ref="pl0777">Briton</placeName>. — and exactly
                    opposite on the other side the Loch is that most astonishing and stupendous hill
                    called <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben Lomond</placeName>. of which every traveller
                    that visits this part of the <placeName ref="pl0711">Highlands</placeName> takes
                    particular notice, and many mount <hi rend="underline">his</hi> summit. which
                    commands a very extensive prospect, but that entirely depends upon the day for I
                    was inform’d by a gentleman who had been there that when the atmosphere was
                    clear one may easily discover the <placeName ref="pl0889">Irish
                        Coast</placeName>. — whereas the day we were at <placeName ref="pl0222">Tarbet</placeName> the clouds hung so low we could not discern the top of
                        <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben</placeName>. — it is three miles from the base
                    to the summit and one mile perpendicular — The road in many parts is totally
                    impassible on foot, so those who have curiosity to ascend this steep are obliged
                    to hire little Shelties or Galloways which are kept here for that purpose, and
                    are well acquainted with the way ––––– But there were some lines on a pane of
                    Glass in the Inn which I really think worth transcribing. tho’ few scratchs on
                    tavern windows deserve a look. — however should any of my friends visit
                        <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben Lomond</placeName>, they may be mindful of the
                    advice given by — <persName ref="pe0459"><unclear reason="illegible">S</unclear>
                        Russel.</persName><note type="editorial">Dawson attributes the below poem to
                        'S. Russel', however others name the author as one Thomas Russel.</note> —
                        <pb n="50"/></p>
                <p><bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0536">Verses on Ben Lomond written on a
                            Window</title></bibl> —</p>
                <p><quote><l>Strangers, if this pane of glass perchance,</l>
                        <l>Thy roving eyes should cast a casual glance;</l>
                        <l>If taste for grandeur ,and the dread sublime,</l>
                        <l>Prompt thee, <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben Lomonds</placeName> fearful
                            height to climb;</l>
                        <l>Here stop attentive, nor with scorn refuse,</l>
                        <l>The humble rhimings of a tavern Muse: —</l>
                        <l>For thee the Muse, this rude instruction plan’d,</l>
                        <l>Prompt’d for thee, her poets humble hand.</l>
                        <l>— Trust not at first a quick adventurous pace,</l>
                        <l>Six miles its top points gradual form the base. —</l>
                        <l>Up the high rise, with panting haste I past,</l>
                        <l>And gain’d the long laborious steep at last.</l>
                        <l>More provident thou, — when once you pass the deep,</l>
                        <l>With cautious steps, and slow, ascend the steep. —</l>
                        <l>Oh, stop awhile oft taste the cordial drop,</l>
                        <l>And rest, oh rest, long, long upon the top,</l>
                        <l>There hail the breezes, nor with toilsome haste,</l>
                        <l>Down the rough slope thy useful vigour waste:</l>
                        <l>So shall thy wondering sight at once survey,</l>
                        <l>Woods, lakes, and mountains, vallies rocks, and sea. —</l>
                        <l>Huge hills, that heaped in crowded order stand,</l>
                        <l>Stretch’d o’er the Western, and the Northern land,</l>
                        <l>Enormous groupes; while <placeName ref="pl0609"><hi rend="underline">Ben</hi></placeName> who often shrouds,</l>
                        <l>His lofty summit in a veil of clouds,</l>
                        <l>High o’er the rest, exulting in his state,</l>
                        <l>In proud pre-eminence sublimely Great: —</l>
                        <pb n="51"/>
                        <l>One side all awful to the astonish’d eye —</l>
                        <l>Presents a rise three hundred fathoms high:</l>
                        <l>Which swells tremendous on th’ astonish’d sense,</l>
                        <l>With all the pomp of dread magnificence,</l>
                        <l>All this and more thou shalt with wonder see,</l>
                        <l>And own a faithful Monitor in me. <persName ref="pe0459"><unclear reason="illegible">S</unclear> Russel</persName>
                        –––––</l></quote></p>
                <p>I think <persName ref="pe0459">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Russel</persName>
                    gives very wholsome advice, we left this place about five the afternoon was
                    pleasant and <add place="above">the</add> road to <placeName ref="pl0224">Luss</placeName> all the way by the side of <placeName ref="pl0223">Loch
                        Lomond</placeName>. this Loch is twenty four miles long, and in many parts
                    six and seven broad, it has twenty eight Islands upon it, none of which are very
                    small, and all ornamented with wood which adds much to this enchanting prospect.
                    we reach’d <placeName ref="pl0224">Luss</placeName> by eight, at which place our
                    accomodations were very comfortable — after eating a hearty supper we retired to
                    bed, and left <placeName ref="pl0224">Luss</placeName> at eight on Sunday
                    morning August the 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. it rain’d heavily therefore
                    we could not enjoy the pleasant prospects between <placeName ref="pl0224">Luss</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl0226">Dumbarton</placeName> as the
                    road was still by the Loch. — we reach’d the last mention’d place about eleven,
                    where we order’d breakfast — There is the remains of a <placeName ref="pl1104">Castle at Dumbarton</placeName> which most travellers passing through go to
                    see, but it rain’d so hard the whole time we were there — we were obliged to be
                    content without seeing it. — This place though the county Town, is but small and
                    trifling we left <add place="above">it</add> about two, and had a very pleasant
                    ride to <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> — the Country here wears a
                    different aspect to that we had pass’d through a day or two before, — here the
                    surrounding lands are well cultivated, and many Gentlemens seats are scatter’d
                    about. — <pb n="52"/> These are the summer residences of some of the best
                    families in <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> their situations are
                    well chosen most of them commanding either a view of <placeName ref="pl0223">Loch Lomond</placeName> or of the <placeName ref="pl0600">Clyde</placeName>
                    — which is the river that comes to <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName>
                    and is one of the three that is navigable, it is rather remarkable so many
                    rivers as are in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> there are but
                    three, the <placeName ref="pl0600">Clyde</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName>, the <placeName ref="pl1116">Forth</placeName> to
                        <placeName ref="pl0235">Stirling</placeName>, and the <placeName ref="pl0096">Tay</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0094">Perth</placeName>. —
                    about two miles before we reach’d <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> is
                    an <placeName ref="pl1064">Obelisk</placeName> near the road side but tho’ it
                    did not appear ancient, the inscription was effaced; however we enquired and
                    found it was erected to the memory of <persName ref="pe0536">Smollet</persName>
                    the historian, and were also shewn <placeName ref="pl2109">the house he was born
                        in</placeName>, which was just by and cuts a mean appearance. —</p>
                <p> — We arrived at <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> about five o’clock,
                    and were recommended to <placeName ref="pl2110">the Saracens Head
                        Gallowgate</placeName>, which was quite the South end of the Town, we were
                    all much struck with the beauty and regularity of the buildings, and the
                    spacious and well paved streets. — after tea we sent <persName ref="pe1384">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wauds</persName> letter to <persName ref="pe1383">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Williamson</persName> one of the
                    Professors inclos’d in a note from my <persName ref="pe1290">Uncle</persName>
                    desiring to know what time we should wait on the Dr, to see <placeName ref="pl1061">the College</placeName>, he sent his <choice>
                        <abbr>Comp<hi rend="superscript">ts</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>Compliments</expan>
                    </choice> and would wait on us that evening, accordingly he came about eight
                    o’clock supp’d with us and staid till twelve; he is a very agreeable man full of
                    entertainment and instruction, is very lively and seems to be about sixty five.
                    — My <persName ref="pe1290">Uncle</persName> was much pleased with him and we
                    agreed we had seldom spent pleasanter hours, for tho’ a great Phylosopher, he is
                    perfectly easy, and quite the gentleman, is much caress’d by the <persName ref="pe0548">Dukes of Athol</persName>, <persName ref="pe0086">Argyle</persName>, and <persName ref="pe1331">Hamilton</persName>, as a man
                    of great understanding, and sound judgement, he was perfectly <pb n="53"/>
                    acquainted with the late <persName ref="pe0073">Doctor Johnson</persName>, who
                    he acknowledges to have had a great genius, but agrees with every body else in
                    saying he had the most unpleasant manner and disposition in the world. — he
                    added, one part of <persName ref="pe0073">Johnsons</persName> character
                    surprized him much as he had always thought it incompatible with sound
                    judgement, which was his amazing bigotism, he said he once ask’d him the
                    Principle of the established Church of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>, and when he told him it differ’d <hi rend="underline">only</hi> in form to that of the English, he exclaim’d enough, enough, your
                    fate is inevitable, as is all those who in the smallest degree deviate from the
                    only true religion. I need not tell you what will be your portion, ––––– He told
                    us a circumstance of <persName ref="pe0073">the D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName> breakfasting with one of the Professors, and according to
                    the custom of this country preserved sweetmeats were produced, the <persName ref="pe0073">Doctor</persName> who was very near sighted ask’d what they
                    were, and being inform’d Marmalade to spread upon his bread, and butter, he put
                    his hand into the glass and brought it out <add place="above">full</add> of
                    sweetmeats, spread it with his fingers upon the bread, and noding significantly
                    said (<hi rend="underline">this will do</hi>)<note type="editorial">In his <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0214"><hi rend="italic">Journal of a Tour
                                    to the Hebrides with Samuel Johnson</hi></title></bibl> (London:
                        1785), James Boswell writes that while at Glasgow on Friday 29 October 1773,
                        'The professors of the university having been informed of our arrival, Dr.
                        Stevenson, Dr. Reid, and Mr. Anderson, breakfasted with us', p.462.</note> —
                    This <persName ref="pe1383">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Williamson</persName>
                    alledged he saw, and told us many more stories similar to these about <persName ref="pe0073">Johnson</persName> — he ask’d us to breakfast with him the next
                    morning which we did, and were by him introduced to <persName ref="pe1385">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Williamson</persName>, She does not seem
                    above thirty, great inequality in age is in general disgusting, but when one
                    recollects how agreeable <persName ref="pe0073">the Doctor</persName> is, one
                    ceases to wonder at it. — They both accompanied us to see <placeName ref="pl1061">the College</placeName> — we were first shewn the apparatus for
                    Electricity; Astronomy; the art of preserving in specific several valuable
                    Fosils a magnet the power of which is equal <pb n="54"/> to 151 lb — these
                    apparatus’s are carried into the lecturers hall, and explain’d by the professors
                    of the several class’s to the students; — From thence we were taken into a place
                    in which are aranged several peices of roman architecture which have been found
                    by digging the canal near this place, there are many Altars, the inscriptions
                    still very legible one of <add place="above">the</add> most superb has been <rs ref="ar0260">dedicated to Jupiter Olympus</rs>, there is a place at the top
                    on which the libation has been put, also several pieces of Roman wall, pavements
                    &amp;c. which have the appearance of great antiquity, — from this place we went
                    to the library which is large and well furnish’d, and has a gallery intirely
                    round it. They have a book which was sent by the <persName ref="pe1387">King of
                        Naples</persName> to this college, which is full of extraordinary fine
                    copper plates which were copied from the admirable collection of paintings found
                    in the <placeName ref="pl2113">Herculanium</placeName>,<note type="editorial">Possibly Baiardi's <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0245"><hi rend="italic">Le pitture antiche d'Ercolano e contorni incise
                                    con qualche spiegazione</hi></title></bibl> (Naples: 1755).
                        Dawson may be confusing the royal sponsorship and dedication of the work
                        with its provenance.</note> they are not historical, nor very interesting,
                    but the plates uncommonly fine. —</p>
                <p>— Another much more entertaining <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0256">book</title></bibl> was made a present of to this college by <persName ref="pe1386">Sir William Hamilton</persName>, it is full of drawings taken
                    by himself in <placeName ref="pl2111">Sicily</placeName>, cheifly views of
                        <placeName ref="pl1874">Etna</placeName>, and <placeName ref="pl2112">Vesuvius</placeName>, most incomparably finish’d by that gentleman the
                    burning Lava streaming down the sides is well express’d and fills one with
                    horror and consternation, there is an explanation to every drawing, the
                    colouring is delicate and the subjects noble and striking: from this place we
                    went to the large Hall where on any particular occasion such as chusing
                    Professors &amp;c. all the College assembles and entertainments are given. — In
                    this place are some <pb n="55"/> paintings, the best of which is (according to
                    my humble opinion) <rs ref="ar0261">the Athenian School</rs>, <persName ref="pe1387">Plato</persName>, and <persName ref="pe1388">Aristotle</persName>, are nearly in the center, the former in the attitude
                    of speaking, the figures and countenances are good and expressive. — <persName ref="pe1389">Pythogarus</persName> is writing. — <persName ref="pe1390">Diogenes</persName> in a posture of study — and the rest teaching their
                    different sciences. the countenances of the young students indicate extreme
                    attention. — after seeing this place <persName ref="pe1383">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Williamson</persName> very politely conducted
                    us into a small apartment at the end of it, where we sat down, and regaled
                    ourselves with cake, wine, and almonds and raisins. — We then went to the
                        <placeName ref="pl1059">High Church or Cathe<del rend="overstrike"><gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" quantity="1"/></del>deral</placeName> which is the only one remaining in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>, and is indeed very ancient. the structure
                    is Gothic, but there are no monuments worth observation — fronting the reading
                    desk is an elegant pew in which <persName ref="pe1391">Oliver
                        Cromwell</persName> once sat to hear Divine service. What is very remarkable
                    the place under the Church which was intended for Vaults is converted into a
                    place of worship where there is divine service every Sunday, it must be supposed
                    it is dimly lighted and has a very dismal appearance. it is surely calculated to
                    inforce gloomy ideas of religion, — there still remain several burial places,
                    and if the deceased happen to die young the friends have a horrid custom of
                    painting the walls ajoining the tomb black, with white spots, and observe the
                    same only reverse it when they depart this life pretty far advanced in years. —
                    these we were inform’d were to represent tears. — but — really every tear
                    resembles both in size and shape a good large <hi rend="underline">Gargonel
                        Pear</hi>. and had it not been for <pb n="56"/>
                    <persName ref="pe1383">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Williamson</persName> who
                    is a man of exquisite information we could not possibly have found out there
                    meaning. — From <placeName ref="pl1059">the Cathedral</placeName> we went to the
                        <placeName ref="pl1057">Tontine Inn</placeName>, in which is the assembly
                    room, it is neat, but small, there are also several other comodius apartments
                    and below them a spacious and elegant Coffee room, — at the entrance of this
                    room is a lofty dome supported by pillars, at the top of this <hi rend="underline">Dome</hi> is a Skylight, the other end of the room is made
                    circular by a large bow window, — and there two lights seem fully sufficient. —
                    from thence we went to the <placeName ref="pl2114">new Church</placeName> it is
                    neatly fitted up, and lofted on three sides the pews about are all mahogany, and
                    those below a good imitation of it the aisles are all carpeted, and except the
                        <persName ref="pe1309">Duke of Northumberlands</persName> chaple at
                        <placeName ref="pl1729">Alnwick Castle</placeName>, it is the most elegant
                    place of worship we had seen — From thence we return’d to the Inn and dined,
                    after which the <persName ref="pe1383">Doctor</persName> conducted us to
                        <placeName ref="pl1099">the Green</placeName>, round which there is a gravel
                    walk by the side of the <placeName ref="pl0600">river Clyde</placeName>, which
                    is extremely pleasant, — we then went back to tea and retir’d to bed pretty well
                    fatigued, — rose early in the morning and after breakfast set out for <placeName ref="pl0605">Paisley</placeName> which is seven miles west of <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName>, — This is a large well built town and
                    famous for the gauze manufactory which is brought to great perfection. — they
                    also manufactor muslon and ribbands, and no town is in a more flourishing state
                    — I Copied an account which was taken in the year 1781 of the population of this
                    place it was as follows: <pb n="57"/><list>
                        <item>Number of Families in <placeName ref="pl0605">Paisley</placeName>
                            ————————— 3723 —</item>
                        <item>Persons five to each Family —————————— 18615 —</item>
                        <item>There were Weavers Looms —————————— 3800 —</item>
                        <item>— And thread Mills ——————————————— 132—</item>
                        <item>Fronting Houses ——————————————— 1441 —</item>
                        <item>Houses Built in — 1777 ————————————— 83 — </item>
                        <item>---------------- in — 1778 ————————————— 45 — </item>
                        <item>---------------- in — 1779 ————————————— 43 — </item>
                        <item>---------------- in — 1780 ————————————— 64 — </item>
                        <item>---------------- in — 1781 ————————————— 103 —</item>
                    </list><note type="editorial">The source of this account has not been
                        identified.</note></p>
                <p>They are now much employ’d in building and consequently the population much
                    increas’d since this account was taken <placeName ref="pl0605">Paisley</placeName> is reckoned the fourth town in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> 1777 — <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName>, and <placeName ref="pl0128">Aberdeen</placeName> only excelling it. — we spent the day there very
                    agreeably in seeing the curious process of weaving gauze &amp;c, — and return’d
                    in the evening by <placeName ref="pl0606">Renfrew</placeName> which is the
                    County Town of the Shire; is but a very trifling place — <persName ref="pe1383">Doctor Williamson</persName> came and spent the evening with us, and after
                    a short time took his leave. — We left <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> the morning after about eight o’clock, <persName ref="pe1383">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Williamson</persName> informed
                    us of <placeName ref="pl0599">Bothwell Castle</placeName> which was the ancient
                    seat of the Douglas Family but is now in ruins, it is not far from the road
                    side, at the distance of about nine miles from <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName>, — the situation of it is beautiful on the banks of the
                        <placeName ref="pl0600">river Clyde</placeName>, when intire, it seems to
                    have been <add place="above">a</add> prodigeous mass of building, and has the
                    appearance of amazing strength, it is built on a rock and has been strongly
                    fortified by a surrounding rampart; <pb n="58"/> near this ruin is a neat
                        <placeName ref="pl2115">modern built house</placeName> in which <persName ref="pe0506">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Douglas</persName> resides, from
                    this house the pleasure grounds extend to the <placeName ref="pl0599">old
                        Castle</placeName> and down to the <placeName ref="pl0600">Clyde</placeName>, they are laid out with exquisite taste, and for the size of
                    it, this was one of the prettiest places we saw. — This is part of the estate,
                    the property of which was so long contested by the Families of Douglas, and
                    Hamilton and decided in favour of the former (who now enjoys it) by the house of
                    Lords, in the year 1767,<note type="editorial">The so-called 'Douglas Cause' of
                        the 1760s was one of the most famous litigations of the day. The case saw
                        the Paris-born <persName ref="pe0506">Archibald James Edward
                            Douglas</persName> attempt to prove his identity as the nephew of
                        Archibald Douglas, duke of Douglas, and thus heir to the Douglas estates
                        which had passed to the duke of Hamilton in the apparent absence of a
                        Douglas claimant. Douglas was finally recognised as heir by the House of
                        Lords in 1767, after a lengthy legal battle with the Hamiltons.</note> —
                        <persName ref="pe1383">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Williamson</persName>
                    who is a man of universal knowledge was well acquainted with all the parties, —
                    with the <persName ref="pe1392">Dutchess of Douglas</persName> he was
                    particularly intimate, and also with the <persName ref="pe1393">late Duke of
                        Queensberry</persName> who was very strenuous for the Douglas side, tho’ a
                    relation of the Hamilton’s. — he told us of a conversation he had with that
                    nobleman (after the matter was decided), who told him he was fully convinced of
                        <persName ref="pe0506">Douglas</persName> being the rightful heir, not
                    (added he) “from all <lb/>“the publick proofs that have been <add place="above">given</add> for there perjury may <lb/>“have been pra<add place="above">c</add>tised, but in my youth, I had a strong <lb/>“attachment to <persName ref="pe1392">Lady Jane Douglas</persName>, and would most — <lb/>“willingly
                    have married her. — I know her to have been a <lb/>“woman of exemplary honour,
                    and integrity, she declared <lb/>“on her death bed she was the mother of those
                    young men, <lb/>“this to me is the strongest of all proofs. for <persName ref="pe1392">Lady Jane <lb/>“Douglas</persName> would never have launch’d
                    into Eternity with a <lb/>“Falshood in her mouth. — This Nobleman also told
                        <persName ref="pe1383">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Williamson</persName>
                    a circumstance greatly to the credit of the <persName ref="pe1331">present Duke
                        of Hamilton</persName>, which was soon after the <pb n="59"/> cause was
                    decided, <persName ref="pe0506">young Douglas</persName> was with the <persName ref="pe1393">Duke of Queensberry</persName> at <placeName ref="pl1105">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> James</placeName> where they were met by the
                        <persName ref="pe1331">Duke of Hamilton</persName>, who went up to <persName ref="pe0506">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Douglas</persName>, took him by
                    the hand and said, — “ <persName ref="pe0506">Douglas</persName> its long since
                    we met, but now I’m happy to call <lb/>“you Cousin”. — This circumstance
                    reflects great honour on the <persName ref="pe1331">Duke of Hamilton</persName>,
                    who must be possess’d of a soul above disappointment, and revenge, and must give
                    every one a high opinion of the rectitude of his hear, and benevolence of his
                    disposition, — <persName ref="pe1383">The D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName> gave us an odd account of the <persName ref="pe1395">Dutchess of Douglas</persName>. — She was a woman of astonishing strong
                    parts, — had a high Idea of honour, — and bore an unblemish’d character — but
                    had none of those gentle, and insinuating graces, those mild and placid virtues,
                    which ought to be the characteristic of the sex, — She was strong in her
                    resentments, and had it not been for her unshaken fortitude, and enterprizing
                    spirit, <persName ref="pe0506">Douglas</persName> would never have possess’d the
                    estate. — She lived to see him united to the <persName ref="pe1394">Duke of
                        Montrose’s daughter</persName> they were some years without having any
                    family which gave the <persName ref="pe1395">Dutchess</persName> great
                    uneasiness, as she fear’d in spite of all her exertions, the Hamiltons would
                    prove victorious, however in time she was made happy by seeing an heir to the
                    Family of Douglas. —</p>
                <p>— From <placeName ref="pl0599">Bothwell Castle</placeName> we made the best of
                    our way to — <placeName ref="pl0597">Hamilton</placeName>, which place we
                    reach’d by ten o’clock, there we breakfasted, it is a small neat built town. —
                    we express’d a desire to see the <placeName ref="pl0231">Dukes
                    house</placeName>, upon which the waiter inform’d us, it was necessary to ask
                    the <persName ref="pe1396">Dutchess’s</persName> permission. My <persName ref="pe1290">Uncle</persName>
                    <pb n="60"/> accordingly sat down and wrote to her Grace for that purpose. and
                    soon after her assent came. — we proceeded to the house and the porter refused
                    us admittance till we assured him we had leave, a servant conducted us into the
                    gallery where all the most valuable pictures are put, it is an elegant
                    apartment, on entering it we perceived a Gentleman sat writing, he immediately
                    rose and approached us, — by this time our attentions were engaged with a
                    beautiful painting which hung at the bottom of the room, — This the gentleman
                    informed us was the parting of — <rs ref="ar0262">Hector and Andromache</rs>, it
                    was done by <persName ref="pe1343"><unclear reason="illegible">Gavin</unclear>
                        Hamilton</persName> and was a passage chosen by <persName ref="pe1331">the
                        Duke</persName>. — When <persName ref="pe1397">Hector</persName> is casting
                    his last glance on his wife and infant the former is leaning in an elegant
                    attitude on his shoulder, while the Nurse is upon her knees at his feet holding
                    the Child: — In the back ground stands a magnificent <unclear reason="illegible">Carr</unclear>, in which are two white coursers, around stand the Matrons
                    with their infants in their arms, and with some grey headed old Men raise their
                    hands and eyes to Heaven, imploring the protection of the Gods for the great
                    chief of <placeName ref="pl2116">Troy</placeName>, in whose countenance and
                    figure, are blended glory, pity, anguish, and affection; — The manly figures of
                    two young Warriors leaning on their spears is highly beautiful, their rough
                    visages seem to have lost all the fierc<add place="above">e</add>ness of war and
                    their bosoms to: melt with compassion at the sad scene before them. The figures
                    are all as large as life <pb n="61"/> and exquisitely expressive, — we were much
                    pleased with it, as also with a <rs ref="ar0077">portrait of the Old Earl of
                        Denbigh</rs>, and a negro boy, the former with a gun in his hand, this was
                    done by <persName ref="pe0595">Vandyke</persName> — over the fireplace is that
                    inestimable and much esteem’d <rs ref="ar0076">picture of Daniel in the <hi rend="underline">Lyons</hi>
                        <hi rend="underline">den</hi></rs>. I am utterly unable to give the least
                    conception of this incomparable peformance, — but cannot pass over it without
                    making a faint attempt, — <persName ref="pe1398">Daniel</persName> is
                    represented sitting amidst a group of Lyons with his hands and eyes uplifted in
                    a posture of most ernest prayer, — in his countenance horror is strongly
                    delineated but it is softened by resignation, and a humble hope in the goodness
                    of the Supreme Being, — The animals are incomparably done, one fast asleep with
                    his head upon the foot of <persName ref="pe1398">Daniel</persName> another close
                    by him howling for hunger; and several more in different attitudes all looking
                    horridly savage and ter<add place="above">r</add>ific, yet none seeming to have
                    any intention to molest the Holy Prophet. at the bottom of the picture are
                    several bones and a scull — the gentleman who still attended us desired us to
                    observe how well they <hi rend="underline">were picked</hi>, — and told us this
                    inimitable peice was done by <persName ref="pe1110">Reubans</persName>, — at the
                    bottom of the room is a <rs ref="ar0263"> painting of a treaty of peace</rs>
                    made in <persName ref="pe1091">Queen Elizabeths</persName> time, between the
                    English and Spanish this is held in great veneration as the gentleman informed
                    us which amongst them was the Famous <persName ref="pe1399">Cecil</persName>,
                    they seem all in deep debate. but his countenance was particularly cunning and
                    crafty, ––––– On each side of this are scripture pieces one <rs ref="ar0264">Our
                        Saviour <pb n="62"/> being taken from the cross</rs>, and the other <rs ref="ar0265">his interment</rs>, the countenances here are finely expressed,
                    and they were done by that inimitable artist <persName ref="pe1400">Raphael</persName>, these were the only historical paintings in the gallery
                    the rest were all portraits well finished by <persName ref="pe0595">Vandyke</persName> — As much as we were pleased with the admirable
                    collection of paintings we were not less so with our informer, — he seemed about
                    fifty, a good size inclining to corpulency and a countenance penetrating and
                    expressive, his manner uncommonly graceful, and elegant, accompanied with a
                    frankness the most pleasing, — to have left his occupation and give himself so
                    much trouble merely for the entertainment of perfect strangers was doubtless a
                    great instance of affability, — out of the gallery we went into the billiard
                    room, — facing the door is the <rs ref="ar0266">portrait of three gentlemen in a
                        group</rs>, one of which Our guide informed us was the present <persName ref="pe1331">Duke of Hamilton</persName>, and that (said he) pointing to a
                    figure on his Graces right hand) was taken for me, and that on the left for a
                    son of mine, it was done by <persName ref="pe1343">Hamilton</persName> at
                        <placeName ref="pl1623">Rome</placeName>, we happened to be standing one
                    evening in that very place when he approached us and said he had been trying to
                    group us, and would take us in the attitudes we were then in, The place in which
                    we stood was formerly the <placeName ref="pl2117">Grand Forum</placeName> at
                        <placeName ref="pl1623">Rome</placeName>, but is now converted into a low
                    market, and we were returning from contemplating the ruins of that ancient <add place="above">City</add> which you see <pb n="63"/> there (added he) in the
                    back ground — He had no sooner <hi rend="underline">said that was</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">taken for me</hi> — than it instantly struck me it might
                    probably be that charming and most entertaining author <persName ref="pe0958">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Moor</persName>, well known to have been
                    the <persName ref="pe1331">Duke of Hamiltons</persName> Tutor and companion of
                    his travels, the same, the same Idea struck my <persName ref="pe1290">Uncle</persName> and I took the first opportunity of asking the servant who
                    attended us, and he informed me it was him. —</p>
                <p>I was scarce able to contain the delight I felt in being with a man whose works I
                    had so much admired, I communicated it to my <persName ref="pe1290">Uncle</persName>, who I wished to partake of my pleasure, to have a proper
                    idea of this man, it is only necessary to read his works, as they are an exact
                    type of himself Easy entertaining, interesting, and eligant, — but I must
                    withold my rapsody, and go on with an account of the paintings, — In the
                    billiard room there is an excellent <rs ref="ar0267">head of Rezzio</rs><note type="editorial">Pennant notes that along with another portrait this was
                        'mistakenly called David Rizzo's, but I could not learn that there was any
                        portrait of that unfortunate man.' <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0008"><hi rend="italic">Tour in Scotland and Voyage to the
                                    Hebrides 1772</hi></title></bibl> (Chester: 1774), p.143. The
                        work has since been identified as seventeenth century and thus not a
                        portrait of <persName ref="pe0455">Riccio</persName> (d.1566). </note> the
                    unfortunate favorite, of a more <persName ref="pe0527">unfortunate
                        Queen</persName>, — a violin in his hand, his eyes lively and peircing and
                    his countenance keen, and expressive, — In this room are some portraits and
                    excellent Landscapes — and a small painting which, I think was done by <persName ref="pe1108">Guido</persName> — It was <rs ref="ar0268">Our Saviour taken
                        from the cross</rs>, and two angels standing over him, the Vissage of one of
                    those Beings is perfectly divine, it exceeds any thing earthy, and is totally
                    undescribable. — through this we were shewn a bed room and dressing room which
                    are ornamented chiefly with landscapes, from thence we returned again through
                    the gallery and went through another range of rooms, in one of which, was a fine
                    old <rs ref="ar0269">head of S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Catherine</rs>
                    <pb n="64"/> Bless me said <persName ref="pe0958">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Moore</persName>, I’ve seen many a <persName ref="pe1401">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Catherine</persName>, but they were all smart
                    young Ladies, this seems very ancient — Here is also a <rs ref="ar0270">portrait
                        of Knox the Great Reformer</rs> and the <rs ref="ar0271">Holy family in a
                        group</rs>, which I think was done by <persName ref="pe1108">Guido</persName>, an artist famous for expression of countenance, — There
                    were many others the subjects of which I have forgot I was so attentive to our
                    charming conductor, — he told us the <persName ref="pe1331">Duke</persName> was
                    in <placeName ref="pl0889">Ireland</placeName> and <add place="above">the</add>
                    <persName ref="pe1396">Dutchess</persName> not being well he came down about a
                    fortnight ago to keep her company in the <persName ref="pe1331">Dukes</persName>
                    absence, — Ay! thought I, I envy her, her companion, more than any thing she
                    possess,</p>
                <p>— He staid sometime, conversing about our journey and all the beauties of
                        <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>, wished us much to see the
                        <persName ref="pe1331">Dukes</persName> pleasure grounds,<note type="editorial">The duke of Hamilton's deer park and ostentatious lodge at
                            <placeName ref="pl0232">Chatelherault</placeName> were frequently
                        remarked upon by visitors: see Pennant, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0001"><hi rend="italic">Tour in Scotland
                            1769</hi></title></bibl> (Chester: 1771), pp.206-07 and <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0008"><hi rend="italic">Tour in Scotland
                                    and Voyage to the Hebrides 1772</hi></title></bibl> (Chester:
                        1774), p.143.</note> and after sometime took his leave —, we returned to the
                    Inn and soon after set forward on our journey. — it rained and blew excessive
                    hard, and our situation was te<add place="above">r</add>ible the road laying
                    across a bleak heath without a single tree to shelter us, and we really thought
                    it dangerous to remain in the carriage, — One circumstance made it particularly
                    similar to the Tempest on <placeName ref="pl2069">Cowdingham Moor</placeName>
                    July the 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, the day before, had been past with
                        <persName ref="pe1316">Miss Grey</persName>, and now we had just left
                        <persName ref="pe0958">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Moor</persName>, and
                    to have our pleasentest hours twice succeeded by tempests was very remarkable —
                    However at five we arrived at <placeName ref="pl0587">Douglas Mill</placeName>,
                    where we met with comfortable accommodations, and took up our residence for the
                    night — which was a very tempestuous one <pb n="65"/> we rose early in the
                    morning but if offered us no better a prospect that the preceeding day, being
                    still extremely windy and likely for rain, and as we were preparing to set off
                    (being obliged to encounter it) — the Landlord came with the <choice>
                        <abbr>Comp<hi rend="superscript">ts</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>Compliments</expan>
                    </choice> of two Gentlemen who were going to the next stage, and offered me a
                    place in their post Chaise, to this proposition we readily assented, and I got
                    into the carriage with the two <hi rend="underline">Beaux</hi>. Conversation
                    soon turned to literary subjects, in which they both, especially the younger
                    seemed well versed, repeated many striking passages from <persName ref="pe0494">Shakespeare</persName> as well as from other Great authors, spoke french
                    fluently, and seemed to have a knowledge of the dead languages, it rained te<add place="above">r</add>ribly the whole way to <placeName ref="pl2120">Elvenfoot</placeName> which is fifteen miles from <placeName ref="pl0587">Douglas Mill</placeName>, here we breakfasted and parted with our agreeable
                    fellow travellers whose names we did not learn, — from thence we persued our
                    rout to <placeName ref="pl0247">Moffat</placeName> which place we reached by two
                    it is a neat small market town, and excellent accommodations at the Inn we
                    dined, and left it about four, we had a pleasant ride of sixteen miles, fine
                    road to <placeName ref="pl0248">Lockerby</placeName> through the <placeName ref="pl2121">Vale of Annan</placeName> we arrived at the last mentioned
                    place by seven were we staid all night. — On Friday morning September the first
                    — we rose at 9 breakfasted and left <placeName ref="pl0248">Lockerby</placeName>
                    about eleven, the road was very good and about a quarter of a mile on the right
                    hand of it at the distance of sixteen miles from <placeName ref="pl0248">Lockerby</placeName>, stands that celebrated Village called <placeName ref="pl0558">Gretna Green</placeName>. — we understood it was in the direct
                    road to <placeName ref="pl0253">Carlisle</placeName> and intended dining at it,
                    but passed it half a mile — however when we found out our mistake we returned,
                    not willing to pass so near a spot so famous, without seeing it — accordingly
                        <unclear reason="illegible">
                        <gap unit="letters" quantity="2"/>
                    </unclear>
                    <pb n="66"/> we asked for the best Inn, and were shewn a small thatched Cottage
                    built of mud, at the end of which hung out the Kings arms, here we alighted and
                    were shewn into a neat little apartment where we ordered diner, — I asked where
                    people were married the girl looked significantly at me and pointed to a little
                    thatched alehouse of still meaner appearance than that we were in. “Do you want
                    to go there Ma’am said she because if you do, we must send for the Minister, he
                    lives about a quarter of a mile off, — I assured her I had no desire to see that
                    Gentleman, but expressed my surprize why they were not married in the Kirk, as
                    there is a very neat one in the Village — She said She knew no reason, but
                        <persName ref="pe1402">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Paisley</persName>
                    (the Minister) did not chuse it. — I asked her if we could see the room in which
                    the ceremony is performed, and she immediately desired us to follow her, we did
                    so, and were conducted to the little alehouse above mentioned, and turning to
                    the right she opened the door of <hi rend="underline">Hymens</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">Temple</hi>, which we entered — it is a room of about four
                    yards in bre<add place="above">a</add>dth and five in length, very low, a coarse
                    flag floor, and white walls, the furniture consisted of three white wood chairs,
                    an old oak table, a corner cupboard, and two press <hi rend="underline">beds</hi>. — The people told us a week never passed without a wedding and
                    some times two of a day, — and the ceremony is two hours in performing</p>
                <p>— We left <placeName ref="pl0558">Gretna Green</placeName> about four and it
                    rained very fast most of the way to <placeName ref="pl0253">Carlisle</placeName>, in this stage we bade farewell to <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> which is divided from <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> by a small river which we crossed at <placeName ref="pl0251">Longtown</placeName>, ten miles from <placeName ref="pl0253">Carlisle</placeName> — which place we reached about seven and took up our
                    residence at the <placeName ref="pl2122">Kings arms</placeName>, where we met
                    with excellent beds and good accommodations, we rose about eight o’clock and
                    after breakfast went to see the printing works <pb n="67"/> which are very
                    extensive at <placeName ref="pl0253">Carlisle</placeName> but as I before took
                    notice of them at <placeName ref="pl2083">Cromley</placeName>, these being
                    exactly the same, I shall pass over them in silence — From thence we went to the
                        <placeName ref="pl2123">Cathedral</placeName>, it appears to <add place="above">be</add> an old strong building but there are no monuments
                    worth looking at and it happening to be Service time we could not be admitted
                        <add place="above">but</add> into the prayerhouse, — From this place we went
                    to the <placeName ref="pl2124">Castle</placeName> where — the fortieth regiment
                        <add place="above">of foot</add> were garrisoned, they happened to be
                    exercising and <add place="above">we were</add> much pleased with the harmony of
                    their music, — we had leave from the Officers to ascend the ramparts where
                    several large cannon are placed, from thence we had a charming and extensive
                    prospect and took a farewell glance of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>; a place we had every reason to like, not only from
                    its beauties which are very numerous, but from the extreme kindness and
                    hospitality we met with from its inhabitants, — We were informed there was
                    nothing within the <placeName ref="pl2124">Castle</placeName> worth observation
                    and therefore did not enter it. but were told by the people of <placeName ref="pl2122">the Inn</placeName> there was a clock which was very curious.
                    accordingly we went and found it so. — It shewed us the Revolution of the
                    heavens, and motion of the globe, and upon the whole was a capital peice of
                    mechanism, — We were also informed there was a <persName ref="pe1404">blind
                        Man</persName> just by who had an organ and played upon it himself, and that
                    he had been born blind, — this intelligence it was difficult to credit, however
                    we were determined to be satisfied and followed our conducter down a straight
                    lane, then ascended a pair of high stone stairs, at the top of which at the
                    right hand he opened a door, and telling our errand a woman desired us to enter,
                    which we did, and this astonishing man approached us he seemed about sixty and
                    rose from a table where he <pb n="68"/> three women and two men were at dinner —
                    it was a mean apartment, — in one corner stood a bed — a fire where dinner had
                    been cooked close by it, — and at the bottom of the room was the organ the Old
                    man drew near us and taking from the wall a small frame in which was <hi rend="underline">Joseph</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">Lenton</hi> wove on a piece of Cloth — you will doubtless
                    think it remarkable said he, when I tell you this was my weaving, it is true, I
                    was not born blind as some say, by lost my sight of the small pox when I was
                    between three and four years old, you will ask how I knew the form of letters,
                    why my mother with her finger end used to trace them on my hand and by this
                    means I know the exact shape of every letter, — I have also made this organ both
                    the bellows keys and wood part of it, and I play upon it — and blow the bellows
                    with my foot, — He immediately began played Martino’s minuet the Birks of
                    Invermay — and many sprightly airs. –––––</p>
                <p>— Now said he I will give you one of my own composition it is an imitation of a
                    Voluntary when the Judges come into the Church — he did play it — and most
                    delightful it was — he touch’d the instrument with great taste and expression. —
                    When he had done pray said my <persName ref="pe1290">Uncle</persName> what first
                    gave you an idea of making an organ. — he began a long na<add place="above">r</add>rative which was exactly as below, or as near as I can remember.
                    —</p>
                <p>You must know Sir when I was about twelve years old I went to the <placeName ref="pl2123">Cathedral</placeName> were I was so struck with the music of
                    the organ that it quite overpower’d me — I fainted away and was carried out —
                    when I came to myself I enquired very earnestly <pb n="69"/> what the organ was
                    like — My friends who were poor illiterate people could inform me very little
                    about it. they said there was a bellows and some pipes and that they played on
                    keys. — I could then have played a little on the bagpipe I made a bellows and
                    got some childrens trumpets, and blew into the bellows this I found would not
                    answer, as I could not get it to make different sounds. — I was much distressed
                    that this attempt failed, and my friends afraid such application and study would
                    impair my understanding — insisted upon me giving up the scheme, this (added the
                        <persName ref="pe1404">Old man</persName>) duly obliged me to promise, but
                    strong inclination forbade me to perform — there was a small dark place at the
                    top of the house there I got my work tools unknown to every body. I was then
                    about seventeen and had made some bagpipes and other little things, but <add place="above">my</add> mind was still set upon an organ, — and I was
                    determined to make a second attempt, I had made some enquiries about it, — and
                    set to work to make the air Chest, bellows, –— pipes, — and keys, — which I
                    compleated, the only thing that now remained was to pitch it, — sometimes I
                    thought to go to the Organist and ask a little of his assistance — then again I
                    considered perhaps he will think it impertinent in a poor blind boy. — as I was
                    one day busied with these reflections, I went to the <placeName ref="pl2123">Cathedral</placeName> which I then constantly attended, I had one of my
                    pipes in my pocket and was ringing the bells after service was over, — when one
                    of the Vergers told the Sexton he had left the organ pew door open,— he replied
                    it was no matter nobody would go there — Now though I is the luck<add place="above">e</add>y moment if I have courage to embrace it, — Immediately
                    went and hid myself, and sometime after they went out and locked the door. — I
                    then groped my way up to the organ loft and after filling the organ chest with
                    air, took my pipe out of my pocket, and counted the notes 1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10
                    from the top, till it exactly came to the sounds of my pipe from thence I knew
                    where to place this pipe and makes as many above and below as I liked.<pb n="70"/> — I
                    stayed in the Church all night practising in the above manner — I knew nothing
                    then of the name of notes — my ear was my only instructor — in the morning
                    various were the conjectures made upon finding me in the church, — some said he
                    smiling thought it was the Old Organist risen again. — I told them what I had
                    been about as I was no longer desirous of keeping it a secret. — it soon reached
                    the ears of the Bishop and Dean, who sent for me and ordered I should have free
                    access to the organ, whenever I wished it, from this indulgence I soon
                    compleated my instrument and got <add place="above">to</add> know the names of
                    notes. This is not the Organ you now see, it was sent into the <placeName ref="pl0707">Isle of Man</placeName>. this I have made since. I will play
                    you another song added he and immediately began of singing and playing. (Says
                        <persName ref="pe1387"><hi rend="underline">Plato</hi></persName> why <hi rend="underline">should</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">man be</hi> Vain — when he had finished, this said he is my
                    favorite song. for a great deal of morality is united to fine music, it shows
                    most plainly the vanity of this world, — Our venerable friend delivered this
                    narration with an ease, and frankness that astonished and delighted us, — and
                    one could not help regarding him as one whom Providence had bountifully
                    compensated for the loss of eyesight — Nothing could be more affecting than to
                    hear him sing that song. — it brought along with it a crowd of reflections. —
                    Who indeed has occasion to be vain when they can see here an instance of a man
                    destitute of every comfort that can arise from competence &amp; dependant solely
                    on the bounty of others, yet see that man by the peculiar grace of Providence
                    endowed with a disposition of mind and soundness of understanding not often to
                    be equalled. — <persName ref="pe1290">My Uncle</persName> asked him if he knew
                        <persName ref="pe1405">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Stanley</persName> the
                        <add place="above">late</add> organist of <placeName ref="pl2002">the
                        Temple</placeName>
                    <pb n="71"/> who was very great tho like him deprived of eyesight. — He said he
                    went up to <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> soon after he had made the
                    organ and was introduced to <persName ref="pe1405">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Stanley</persName> who he had the honour of playing too, that he
                    was at his house and he was very kind to him. — He is dead lately said <persName ref="pe1290">my Uncle</persName> — so I hear said the old Man and am sorry
                    for it, ay Sir I labour under great disadvantages, if in the earlier part of my
                    life I had, had a good education I might have done better. — I told him the
                    merit was considerably greater on that account — because had that been the case
                    much more would be expected and now <add place="above">we</add> were all
                    astonishment. — The old man (smiled and) said, you are very good Ma’am, and very
                    true, <persName ref="pe1290">My Uncle</persName> then gave him a small trifle,
                    for which he was very thankful but we assured him the obligation was greatly on
                    our sides — we then returned to the inn. dined and set off for <placeName ref="pl0254">Penrith</placeName>. which is eighteen miles from <placeName ref="pl0253">Carlisle</placeName> and the road not very good. but the
                    prospects <add place="above">finely</add> diversified, on one side a black heath
                    and on the other a woody, cultivated, Valley, — Our old Friend whom we had just
                    left furnished us with conversation, till about seven o’clock we reached
                        <placeName ref="pl0254">Penrith</placeName>, — Our hostess informed us her
                    house was so full of company she feared we should not like our accommodations,
                    which she assured us were the best that were unoccupied, for there was <persName ref="pe1406">Lord Lonsdale</persName> and all the Gentlemen of distinction
                    in the County assembled above stairs, and had been signing a congratulatory
                    address to <persName ref="pe0465">his Majesty</persName> (which she added with a
                    smile) was just <hi rend="underline">then quite the </hi><hi rend="underline">fashion</hi> — she spoke this with a tone of voice and sweetness of
                    countenance that we could have put up with any inconvenience rather than have
                    distressed her. We ordered tea and before it was <pb n="72"/> over a great mob
                    assembled before the window where they lit a prodigious bonfire and fired guns
                    and crackers inumerable. <persName ref="pe1406">Lord Lonsdale</persName> and
                        <add place="above">the</add> gentlemen ordered the populace thirteen barrels
                    of ale, and the whole night, was one continued scene of drunkenness, riot, and
                    confusion. — We breakfasted at <placeName ref="pl0254">Penrith</placeName> in
                    the morning and about ten o’clock set off for <placeName ref="pl2125">Appleby</placeName>. the road on this stage is good, and the prospects
                    delightful, it is fourteen miles and we arrived at <persName ref="pe1407">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wilkinsons</persName> about twelve, and were
                    happy to find <persName ref="pe1407">Miss W—</persName> well. she is a girl I
                    esteem exceedingly from the goodness of her heart and sweetness of <add place="above">her</add> disposition — <placeName ref="pl2125">Appleby</placeName> is <sic>a most charmingly situated</sic> it is but
                    small tho’ the County town of <placeName ref="pl2126">Westmorland</placeName>,
                    the country about it is very rich and cultivated, and the prospects are
                    terminated with Hills resembling those in the <placeName ref="pl0711">Highlands</placeName>. — at this place there is a <placeName ref="pl2127">Castle</placeName> which belongs to the <persName ref="pe1408">earl of
                        Thanet</persName>, it is finely situated upon a rising ground and overlooks
                    the Town; the eminence on which it stands, is finely or<add place="above">na</add>mented with trees, and the <placeName ref="pl2128">river
                        Eden</placeName> runs just below. It is inhabited by his Lordships Steward
                    and family, the rooms are large wainscoted and boarded with oak, — there are
                    some paintings but all wretchedly bad. the only entertainment in the <placeName ref="pl2127">Castle</placeName>, is the figure of a man armed <hi rend="underline">cap</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">à pee</hi>, it is kept very clean and is iron inlaid with
                    gold. — near the <placeName ref="pl2127">Castle</placeName> there is an old
                    square building very high with a turret on each corner, it has the appearance of
                    great strength. no tradition is to be found concerning it but from the iron bars
                    which remain it is supposed to have been a place of confinement. — We staid at
                        <placeName ref="pl2125">Appleby</placeName> till <pb n="73"/> Wednesday
                    morning when we left them notwithstanding their pressing invitations for a
                    longer visit, we returned to <placeName ref="pl0254">Penrith</placeName> and
                    about four miles from the last mentioned place on the high road stands a
                        <placeName ref="pl2129">pillar</placeName> on which is a dial, it was
                    erected 130 years ago by <persName ref="pe1409">Lady Ann Pembroke</persName>,
                    she parted with her daughter (who was going to live in <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>) upon this spot, and she ordered a donation of four
                    pounds to be given a<add place="above">n</add>nually to the poor of the
                        <placeName ref="pl2134">parish of Broom</placeName> (where it stands —)<note type="editorial">The pillar bears the following inscription, probably the
                        source of the slightly distorted account given by Dawson: THIS PILLAR WAS
                        ERECTED ANNO 1656 BY YE HON'BLE ANNE COUNTESS DOWAGER OF PEMBROKE AND
                        DAUGHTER AND SOLE HEIRE OF YE RT HONO'BLE GEORGE EARL OF CUMBERLAND AND FOR
                        A MEMORIAL OF HER LAST PARTING IN THIS PLACE WITH HER GOOD AND PIOUS MOTHER
                        YE RT HONO'BLE MARGARET COUNTESS DOWAGER OF CUMBERLAND YE 3RD OF APRIL 1616.
                        IN MEMORY WHEREOF SHE ALSO LEFT AN ANNUITY OF FOUR POUNDS TO BE DISTRIBUTED
                        TO YE POOR WITHIN THIS PARISH OF BROUGHAM EVERY 2ND DAY OF APRIL FOR EVER
                        UPON YE STONE TABLE HERE HARD BY</note> every second day of April, the same
                    Charitable Lady also endowed an Hospital at <placeName ref="pl2125">Appleby</placeName> and left land sufficient to allow twelve poor Widows
                    two <sic>comfortables</sic>
                    <add place="above">apartments</add> each and ten pounds <hi rend="underline">per</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">anum</hi> — there is an elegant monument erected to her
                    memory in <placeName ref="pl2130">Appleby Church</placeName> — we dined at
                        <placeName ref="pl0254">Penrith</placeName> and left it about three, the
                    road to <placeName ref="pl0522">Keswick</placeName> is beautifully picturesque
                    and about a mile from that place one of the most beautiful landscapes that can
                    be conceived presents itself, it is a most fertile Valley through which runs the
                        <placeName ref="pl2131">river Derwent</placeName>, also <placeName ref="pl0522">Keswick</placeName>, and a part of the lake which is esteemed
                    the finest in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> — this Valley is
                    encompassed by an astonishing Hill called <placeName ref="pl1097">Skiddaw</placeName> and other Mountains of stupendous height — We arrived
                    at <placeName ref="pl0522">Keswick</placeName> by seven at which place we met
                    with comfortable accomodations — When we arose, we wer te<add place="above">r</add>ribly disappointed by a dreadful rainy morning, as we intended had
                    it been fine to have gone upon the lake, and ascend’d the summit of <placeName ref="pl1097">Skiddaw</placeName> — these hopes however were frusterated —
                    after breakfast we walked to see a <placeName ref="pl2132">Museum</placeName>
                    which is kept by a man of this place — here we spent three very entertaining
                    hours — The keeper of this <placeName ref="pl2132">Museum</placeName>
                    <pb n="74"/> was formerly a Captain in the East India Service and is now Admiral
                    at <persName ref="pe1411">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Pocklingtons</persName>
                    <hi rend="underline">regattas</hi>. which happen a<add place="above">n</add>nually and generally in August, — he has really collected a number of
                    curious things a minute description of them is utterly impossible but I will
                    endeavour to recollect those that most pleased Among his Fosils (which are very
                    numerous) there is an Egyptian aget, which is about the size of a crown piece,
                    it is finely polished and nature has depicted on one side the semblance of a
                    monsterous cavern, — and on the other a rugged bridge and water beneath it.
                    there is another no less worthy observation and it was found in the neighbouring
                    mountains it is a stone of blue colour, in which are thinly scattered several —
                    garnets of rich hue, and different dimensions, — and upon examining those he
                    took from the stone <persName ref="pe1410">Crosthayte</persName> perceived some
                    had twelve and others twenty four <unclear reason="illegible">sides</unclear> as
                    exact as the most skillful artist could have formed them. — he has got six
                    musical stones, which he found in the <placeName ref="pl2131">river
                        Derwent</placeName>, they are of flat oblong form, and so well in tune with
                    each other by nature, that by striking them with mallets he can perform any
                    piece of music that does not require a greater extent of notes. — this harmony
                    is totally new and very pleasing. — There is also a remarkable branch of oak in
                    this form <note type="editorial">At this point in the document there is a small
                        sketch of a forked branch roughly Y shaped, but with the forks of the Y
                        bridged by another transverse length of wood.</note> also the <hi rend="underline">wen</hi> of an oak, in which there is the resemblance of a
                    distorted countenance, the features are human, and in the mouth which is much
                    extended, there is a face exactly like that of a monkey. — This was discovered
                    by accident when the bark was stript off, and may deservedly be reckon’d a <pb n="75"/> very great curiosity — there are many different kinds of wood,
                    Coins, dried plants, birds, and beasts, all well preserved, in short it is out
                    of my power to enumerate all the sports of nature that amuses us in this
                    collection. <persName ref="pe1410">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Crosthayte</persName> has also some knowledge of Astronomy on the walls are
                        <add place="above">represented</add> the Sun and planes in their
                    correspondent — distances and magnitudes — after dwelling long upon these and
                    many more things worthy our attention — we returned to <placeName ref="pl2133">the Inn</placeName>, and took an early dinner (after which) as the day had
                    cleared up, we embarked on board the <hi rend="underline">royal</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">oak</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">yatch</hi> for an excurtion up <placeName ref="pl0525">the
                        lake</placeName>. — this boat is a very neat and large enough to accommodate
                    fifty people — it is kept by our Landlord for the use of his company, and takes
                    its name from his sign –––––</p>
                <p>— The afternoon was uncommonly pleasant and the excurtion delightful beyond
                    conception, the first object that presented itself was <placeName ref="pl2135">Pocklington Island</placeName> it is charmingly situated near the bottom of
                    the lake and commands a fine prospect up it. — This Island is by much the
                    largest being about six acres nearly circular and rising gradually from all
                    sides, at the middle of it is an excellent Mansion belonging to <persName ref="pe1411">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Pocklington</persName> in which
                    he resides most of the summer — he has likewise ornamented this little <hi rend="underline">Elysium</hi> with wood and some buildings, on one side of
                    it there is an excellent imitation of a small Church, which adds greatly to the
                    beauty of the landscape, — between the porters lodge and the lake, on a rampart,
                    are planted a garrison of small cannons (six pounders) which are employed in
                    defence of the Island when attacked by the gun boats at the time of the <hi rend="underline">Regatta</hi> — There are several other Islands finely
                    planted with wood <pb n="76"/> one of which (before the rebellion 1715) belonged
                    to <persName ref="pe1412">Lord Derwent-water</persName> who had a house upon it.
                    — and he being ingaged in the part of the rebels, that, as well as other lands,
                    in the neighbourhood were forfeited, and are now appropriated for the benefit of
                        <placeName ref="pl2136">Greenwhich Hospital</placeName>, the house is
                    intirely demolished — from thence we persued our course to the top of the lake,
                    which is three miles and a half from the place we entered the boat. — we landed
                    here and were conducted to a beautifull <placeName ref="pl2137"><hi rend="underline">waterfall</hi></placeName> which far exceeded any we
                    had seen except that at <placeName ref="pl0101">Kinmore</placeName>,<note type="editorial">The <placeName ref="pl1122">Falls of Acharn</placeName>,
                        which Dawson had seen from Lord Breadalbane's Hermitage near
                        Taymouth.</note> we were informed it fell one hundred yards but not
                    perpendicular, it rushes over a very rugged bed, and forces itself down between
                    two stupendous rocks, which tho they have a very barren appearance, are finely
                    ornamented with <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/> shrubs,
                    trees, and flowers, the rock on the right side of the <hi rend="underline">Cateract</hi> is called <placeName ref="pl2138">Shepherds Hill</placeName>,
                    and that on the left (which is considerably higher), is named <placeName ref="pl2139">Gowdring Crag</placeName>. — after having gazed long upon this
                    inchanting scene, we returned to the boat, and crossed the south end of the
                    Lake. From whence we had a grand and sublime view of <placeName ref="pl1764"><hi rend="underline">Borrowdale</hi></placeName>, and tho’ it is usually
                    known by that name, (— which implys a Valley) There seems not more than merely
                    sufficient room for the <placeName ref="pl2131">river Derwent</placeName> to
                    force itself a passage. — which river together with the waterfall supply this
                    Lake. — The evening grew more pleasant and scarce a breeze ruffled the smooth
                    surface of the Lake, The Sun was just declining below the Western hills and his
                    departing beams glimmering on the water occasioned a beautiful reflection of the
                    adjacent rocks and Wood <pb n="77"/> never was there more inchanting scene. I
                    shall not attempt a description of it, but refer all those who have not been
                    there to that lively and <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0287">just account
                            given of it by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Brown</title></bibl>, in a
                        <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0288">micellany compiled by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Scot of Edinburgh</title></bibl>, we were
                    about three hours in making this delightful excurtion, and returned to the inn
                    charmed with our days amusement — Friday September the twenty eight a dreadful
                    rainy morning, we were again disappointed, as we intended mounting <placeName ref="pl1097">Skiddaw</placeName>, — however we were obliged to be content
                    without it, and left <placeName ref="pl0522">Keswick</placeName>, soon after
                    breakfast, intending to reach <placeName ref="pl0259">Kendall</placeName> that
                    evening, but got no farther than <placeName ref="pl0518">Ambleside</placeName>
                    on account of the tempestuous — weather. had it been more favourable we should
                    have had a most delightful ride, the road good and uncommonly pleasant laying
                    through a beautiful, cultivated valley, encompassed with rocks equal (if not
                    superior) in height and grandeur, to any we saw in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>, in — this valley are three fine lakes, the first
                    called <placeName ref="pl0523">Thornmere</placeName>, the next <placeName ref="pl0521">Grasmere</placeName>, and the one next <placeName ref="pl0518">Ambleside</placeName> (which belongs to <persName ref="pe1413">Sir Michael
                        Fleming</persName> who has a seat by it) is called <placeName ref="pl0519">Rydale</placeName>, — We left <placeName ref="pl0518">Ambleside</placeName>
                    the next morning and <add place="above">got</add> to breakfast at <placeName ref="pl0259">Kendall</placeName> by ten, it rained as usual most of the way
                    which was a disappointment to us, as a great part of the road lies by the side
                    of <placeName ref="pl0516">Windimere Lake</placeName>, this is a beautiful piece
                    of water, thirteen miles in length, of an irregular form and from half a mile,
                    to two in breadth, — and tho’ much larger than <placeName ref="pl0525">Keswick
                        Lake</placeName>, the latter by most people is prefered on account of the
                    sublimity and grandeur of the adjacent rocks, whereas the lands adjoining
                        <placeName ref="pl0516">Windimere</placeName>, are all in high cultivation.
                    — We staid to dine at <placeName ref="pl0259">Kendall</placeName> it seems a
                    good <pb n="78"/> town and is pleasantly situated. in a fine fertile Valley, we
                    left it about three, and after a pleasant ride reached <placeName ref="pl2140">Kirby Lonsdale</placeName> by six, and took up our residence at <placeName ref="pl2141">the Royal Oak</placeName> till — morning. This is a small
                    pleasant town situated on the banks of <placeName ref="pl2142">the
                        Lune</placeName>. — On Sunday morning we persued our way to <placeName ref="pl2143">Lerawnest</placeName> which is a quarter of a mile to the right
                    of the road about four miles from <placeName ref="pl2144"><hi rend="underline">Settle</hi></placeName>. — <persName ref="pe1414">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Waddington</persName> and his family were much
                    surprized at the sight of such unexpected visitors, and treated us with the most
                    friendly hospitality. we left them on Monday afternoon in spite of all their
                        intre<add place="above">a</add>ties to the contrary. — We reached <placeName ref="pl0477">Skipton</placeName> that evening, there is at this place
                    another Castle belonging to <persName ref="pe1408">Lord Thanet</persName>, which
                    a good deal resembles that at <placeName ref="pl2127">Appleby</placeName>, — We
                    left this place early in the morning and breakfasted at <placeName ref="pl2145">Ilkley</placeName>. where I was happy in seeing <persName ref="pe1384">Miss
                        Waud</persName> and <persName ref="pe1415">Miss Brown</persName>, — from
                    thence we went to <placeName ref="pl2146">Otley</placeName> dined with <persName ref="pe1416">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Flesher</persName>. who kindly
                    entertained us at her house till Friday, till which time we were storm–staid by
                    a flood occasioned by the quantity of rain which had fallen just before.
                    Notwithstanding the <hi rend="underline">sublime</hi> and diversified prospects
                    we had enjoyed, we were not blind to the justly celebrated beauties of
                        <placeName ref="pl2147"><hi rend="underline">Wharfdale</hi></placeName>.
                    which appeared like an extensive <hi rend="underline">policy</hi> through which
                    the river (in its course resembling <placeName ref="pl0096">the Tay</placeName>)
                    unwinds itself. — We passed through <placeName ref="pl2148">Harwood</placeName>
                    but having <unclear reason="illegible">no</unclear> house did not stop.
                        <placeName ref="pl2149">Thorparch</placeName> appeared more beautiful
                        <unclear reason="illegible">even</unclear> than <hi rend="underline">usual</hi> . — and by six we reached <placeName ref="pl2039">Oxton</placeName>. — I shall not <unclear reason="illegible">write</unclear> the <hi rend="underline">meeting</hi> was a happy one —
                    that surely is <hi rend="underline">unnecessary</hi> — Thus closes the Journal —
                    and if to any of my friends <unclear reason="illegible">too</unclear>
                    <pb n="79"/> it gives the smallest entertainment. I shall esteem myself
                    particularly happy. I trust it will never be perused but by the candid eye of
                    friendship which is ever ready to excuse every error, when it is not the error
                    of the heart. —</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>