<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0055">
    <teiHeader type="s">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Notebook belonging to Sir John MacGregor Murray — description of his
                    tour of Highlands and Islands
                    <date>1800</date></title>
                <author><persName ref="pe1815">Sir John MacGregor Murray</persName></author>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Edited with an Introduction by Alex Deans</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
                <date when="1800"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Stirling</settlement>
                        <repository>Stirling Council Archives</repository>
                        <idno>PD60</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab>
                            <locus>Bundle 301</locus>
                        </ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <additional>
                        <p>Notebook bound into a marbled cover; text begins on f.2r.</p>
                    </additional>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p/>
            </abstract>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gd">Gaelic</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>

                <p><pb n="f.2r"/>
                10 July 1800 left <placeName ref="pl0076">Edin<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></placeName> on a Journey to the <placeName ref="pl0708">Hebrides</placeName> — attended the funeral of the late <persName ref="pe1507">Colonel James Eidingtoun</persName> of <placeName ref="pl2320">Gargunnock</placeName> between noon &amp; 1 <hi rend="superscript">o</hi>Clock — He had been a man of an amiable &amp; respectable character — the
                    intimate friend and companion of <persName ref="pe1508">Colonel Alex<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Gregor
                        Murray</persName> of the Royal Clan Alpin regiment in the early part of
                    their Lives. <persName ref="pe1507">Col Eidingtoun</persName> had served in —
                        <gap reason="authorial" unit="lines" quantity="3"/></p>
                <p>proceded, after din<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> at <placeName ref="pl0235">Stirling</placeName>, to <placeName ref="pl2321">Lanrick</placeName>.</p>
                <p>16 — left <placeName ref="pl2321">Lanrick</placeName> about noon — passed
                        <placeName ref="pl2322">Cambusmore</placeName> on the left the Seat of
                        <persName ref="pe1509">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Buchanan</persName> of
                        <placeName ref="pl2323">Strathtyre</placeName> who has had the merit of
                    making <pb n="f.2v"/>great improvements and of creating a handsome annual
                    Revenue from Lands that had been barren &amp; uncultivated till he commenced his
                    agricultural operations to which he has devoted the greater part of an useful
                    Life since his return from the <placeName ref="pl0704">West Indies</placeName>
                    where he resided a short time in his youth.</p>
                <p>Our road was through <placeName ref="pl2324">Callander of Mentieth</placeName> a
                    Village beautifully situated — near which at a bank called <placeName ref="pl2325">Roman Camp</placeName> but which the Romans never formed, &amp;
                    probably never visited, resides the Hospitable <persName ref="pe1510">Captain
                            <unclear reason="illegible">Fairfal</unclear></persName> a Gentleman of
                    great urbanity of manners who made his fortune as the able Commander of an East
                    Indiaman —</p>
                <p>Visited the Minister <persName ref="pe1511">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Robertson</persName> but missed him — <persName ref="pe1512">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Buchanan of the <unclear reason="illegible">Mains</unclear></persName> an old Gentleman of <hi rend="underline">78</hi>
                    <pb n="f.3r"/>passed on an Island or small peninsula on the left — the
                        <placeName ref="pl2326">Burying place of the Buchanans of
                        Arnprior</placeName> a respectable Family whose last male representative was
                    forfeited for joining <persName ref="pe0559">Prince Charles Edward</persName> in
                    1745 —</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl2327">Leny</placeName> — The Seat of this respectable Family
                    (now the property of <persName ref="pe1513">Captain Hamilton Buchanan</persName>
                    descended by a female) is well situated facing the South on the right about a
                    mile west of <placeName ref="pl2324">Callander</placeName></p>
                <p>Through the <placeName ref="pl2328">pass of Leny</placeName>, by a romantic Road,
                    we went to <placeName ref="pl2323">Strathtyre</placeName> leaving on the right
                    two farm Houses well built the property of the antient &amp; respectable Family
                    of Stirling of Kier</p>
                <p>In <placeName ref="pl2323">Strathtyre</placeName> on the South side of the River
                    there was a Tent for the accommodation of a Party of Ladies &amp; Gentlemen whom
                    we had the pleasure of admiring in the sportive <pb n="f.3v"/>dance upon the
                    Green — The attractive power of the fair drew us across the River to join the
                    cheerful groupe whom we found to consist of the proprietor <persName ref="pe1518">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Buchanan</persName> &amp; his
                        <add place="above">oldest</add> Son, with Several of his Daughters<note type="editorial">See Eliza Fletcher’s account in J.G. Fyfe, <hi rend="italic">Scottish Diaries and Memoirs, 1746-1843</hi> (Stirling: E.
                        Mackay, 1927-1942), 2 vols, ii, pp. 320-321. (AMC).</note> — <persName ref="pe0960">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bruce of . . . .</persName>; his
                    Lady <persName ref="pe0963">a Daughter of Lord Rollos</persName> — a B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> of hers and <persName ref="pe1510">Cap<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Fairfal</persName> — after paying our respects
                    to this Joyous party we proceeded to <del rend="overstrike">
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="5"/>
                    </del>
                    <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName> — <persName ref="pe1519">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Nab</persName>
                    of <placeName ref="pl2329">Bovain</placeName> with whom we intended to have
                    spent the night hav<hi rend="superscript">g</hi>
                    <unclear reason="illegible">intimated</unclear> that his House was painting
                    &amp; unfit for the reception of his Friends —*</p>
                <p>17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> July early in the morn<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> visited the <placeName ref="pl0999">Ruins of the House of
                        Finlarig</placeName> — over an aperture whether a door or window could not
                    be distinguished was the Royal Arms without the Supporters — the date 1609 — the
                    Letters F R<note type="editorial">In the manuscript a small drawing of a shield
                        appears between the two letters.</note> above and the Letters A R lower on
                    the sides of the shield — The situation is beautifully picturesque commands an
                    extensive View — Near the old House is the <placeName ref="pl2241">Burying place
                        of the Family of Breadalbane</placeName> — in a Vault <choice>
                        <abbr>w<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi>in</abbr>
                        <expan>within</expan>
                    </choice> a modern room w<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> a <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/> Roof — near this above the
                    present Inn is the part of the <placeName ref="pl1003">River of
                        Lochay</placeName> in which <persName ref="pe1539">Gregor mhac Dhonachy
                        Ladasach</persName> is s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to have been murdered
                    as ment<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> by <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0199">Douglas</title></bibl> — the Person who opened <pb n="f.4r"/>the Mausoleum had another edition of this story — that the Lairds of
                        <placeName ref="pl0105">Glenlyon</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl1002">Lawers</placeName> had at the instigation of <persName ref="pe1540">Duncan
                        Dubh</persName> enticed <persName ref="pe1539">Gregor</persName> by some
                    fraud to an <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" atLeast="2" atMost="4"/>
                    interview in which they <unclear reason="illegible">shewed</unclear> a design to
                    murder him — that he took one of their necks in each hand &amp; was going to
                    drown them in the <placeName ref="pl1003">Lochay</placeName> when some person
                    (an old woman) came behind him &amp; murdered him — and that his Head was cut
                    off on a hillock where the Gallows usually stood. — The same man informed one of
                    my attendants that 18 of <persName ref="pe1540">Duncan Dubhs</persName>
                    Grandsons were buried there in one day, in rows of Sixes — they had been killed
                    in a Battle w<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> the MacGregors — at a La Coinna<note type="editorial">Possibly latha na coinneamh (day of the meeting.
                        (AMC).</note> — or day of meeting <choice>
                        <abbr>appt<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>appointed</expan>
                    </choice> for action —</p>
                <p>* In passing from <placeName ref="pl0299">Lochearn</placeName> through <placeName ref="pl2349">Glenogle</placeName> we observed on the left hand the Rocks
                        w<hi rend="superscript">h</hi> burst down from the mountain &amp; left the
                    sides covered with huge masses of the Rock — called <hi rend="underline">Scàinach</hi><note type="editorial">Sgàinneadh (cracking). (AMC).</note> in
                    the Galic — we were assured with great seriousness that whenever <add place="above">the death or change of</add> the proprietor of the Estate of
                        <placeName ref="pl2350">Edinample</placeName> was always foretold by the
                    fall of great fractions of the mountain and that the Relater himself had seen
                    five proprietors <del rend="overstrike">who do <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/></del> we were also informed that one
                    proprietor had spent the Estate in Whisky without ever calling for more than a
                    Gill — and that therefore the Gill is called an <placeName ref="pl2350">Edinample</placeName> in that part of the country.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.4v"/>
                At <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName> we were informed that <persName ref="pe1540">Duncan Dubh</persName> was “a great <hi rend="underline">Witch</hi>” — that he had left a <add place="above">Leabher Derg</add> red
                    Book at <placeName ref="pl0101">Taymouth</placeName> which no person ever
                    ventured to open since his death — that the <persName ref="pe0023">Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Stuart</persName> of <placeName ref="pl0224">Luss</placeName> had offered to
                    go to open it — but that his <persName ref="pe0449">Father</persName>, the late
                    minister at <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName>, had prevented him from
                    adventuring it. —</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl2351">Ardeoinaig</placeName> — There were two Brothers —
                    Campbells the Senior of whom was proprietor of this Farm — <persName ref="pe1540">Duncan</persName> instigated the younger to murder his B<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi>to become Lord himself —
                    the younger objected that he w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be hanged — but
                        <persName ref="pe1540">Duncan</persName> promised protection and an
                    adjoining Farm of his own as Bonus for executing the <unclear reason="illegible">task</unclear> — The murder was committed — &amp; on the report of it to
                        <persName ref="pe1540">Duncan</persName> by the perpetrator he made him fly
                    the Country &amp; seized the property —</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe1544">Callain Naine</persName> — was a Son of <persName ref="pe1540">Duncan Dubhs</persName> — he took a crech<note type="editorial">Creach (a cattle raid). (AMC)</note> — plundered from the <placeName ref="pl2353">Braes of Doun</placeName> across the Hills to <placeName ref="pl2354">Dundurn</placeName> — His Piper played a Tune Tecil an Cro
                        Dhonachy<note type="editorial">Possibly 'Togail chrodh Dhonnchaidh': the
                        lifting of Donnchadh or Duncan’s cattle.</note> — which was understood by a
                    McGregor of that Name in <placeName ref="pl2354">Dundurn</placeName> — he let
                    fly an arrow at <persName ref="pe1544">Callain Naine</persName> &amp; struck off
                    the Gold Button <pb n="f.5r"/>from his Bonnet — <persName ref="pe1544">Callain</persName> left the Spoil — and went to <placeName ref="pl2355">Bochaistal</placeName> where he repeated the same depridation — he was
                    followed to <placeName ref="pl2357">Larig Earn</placeName> above the <placeName ref="pl2358">Kirktown of Balquhidder</placeName> by the Buchanans from whom
                    he had taken the Crech — one of them missed him w<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                    an arrow which he took up &amp; in Derision descried it might be carried to the
                    old women at <placeName ref="pl2100">Kilmahog</placeName> (a small collection of
                    Cot Houses near <placeName ref="pl2324">Callander</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl2355">Bochastle</placeName>) — another drew his Bow &amp; struck
                        <persName ref="pe1544">Callain</persName> between the Eyes descring him to
                    carry that — &amp; he expired —</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName> — Upon enquiring the etimology of this
                    word I was told it was so called because it was <add place="above"><hi rend="underline">Keeil Eein</hi></add> the Burial place of <persName ref="pe0540">Fion Mac Dhuil</persName> — and that there was an old man
                        <persName ref="pe1678">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Indoire</persName> at
                        <placeName ref="pl2360">Suiche</placeName> who could repeat much of the
                    Poems of <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian</persName> — and who had an extraordinary
                    Relick of <persName ref="pe0543">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Filan</persName>
                    — The man was not at home: but we saw the Relick — which it appears has been in
                    the keeping of these people at least 313 years.<note type="editorial">Under a
                        royal grant made by James III in 1487, the Dewars of Glendochart were the
                        heredity keepers of the crozier of <persName ref="pe0543">Fáelán
                            Amlabar</persName> (St Fillan) — which was reputed to have healing
                        powers — and the Coigreach, a decorative reliquary that incased it. In 1785,
                        William Thomson, a student at Oxford, wrote to the earl of Buchan, informing
                        him that in 1782 he had seen the 'Quigrich', in the possession of one Malice
                        Doire (Dewar), a day labourer from Killin, and inclosing a drawing. Thomson
                        notes that Dewar's son, then nineteen, appeared to be mortally ill. In 1819,
                        Archibald Dewar, then the heriditary keeper, emigrated to Ontario, taking
                        both the crozier and Coigreach with him, although they were later returned
                        to Scotland. <hi rend="italic">Archaelogia Scotia: or Transactions of the
                            Society of Antiquaries of Scotland</hi>, vol. iii, pp.289-91. See also
                        Anon., <ref target="0051.xml">'A Tour in Scotland 1794'</ref>.</note> It
                    appears to be the head of Pastoral Staff — has a representation of the <del rend="overstrike">
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" atLeast="3" atMost="5"/>
                    </del> crucifiction on one end — my <unclear reason="illegible">dear
                        Son</unclear> attempted a Sketch of it — &amp; if the time had allowed w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> have succeeded <unclear reason="illegible">pretty</unclear> well.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.5v"/>
                <placeName ref="pl2359">Innishewen</placeName><hi rend="superscript">x</hi> —
                    called on the venerable <persName ref="pe1545">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                            M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Nab</persName> — a Hero of the days of old
                    — His Daughter a fine little Girl — Found the old Gentleman witnessing Sheep
                    Shearing — in a <hi rend="underline">Fang</hi> the place enclosed in which the
                    sheep are collected — to have the wool <unclear reason="illegible">taken</unclear> off — a Roman Catholic Family. My B<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                    <persName ref="pe1508">Col Alex’<hi rend="superscript">s</hi></persName>
                    Godfather — which I did not know — or recollect —</p>
                <p><del>
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" quantity="several"/>
                    </del><add place="above"><placeName ref="pl2361"><hi rend="underline">Achlone</hi></placeName></add> — Called on <persName ref="pe1546">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Campbell Lochdochart</persName> a
                    Gentleman who has encreased the fortune of his Family by the improvement of his
                    Estate — the most useful of all services rendered to a Country.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl2362">Port an Eilan</placeName> — Called on <persName ref="pe1547">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Campbell</persName> the Tacksman
                    at this place who conducted us in his Boat to the old building on the Island <choice>
                        <abbr>f<hi rend="superscript">m</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>from</expan>
                    </choice> which the Farm has its name — s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to have
                    been <unclear reason="illegible">Erected</unclear> by <persName ref="pe1540">Duncan Dubh</persName> — <persName ref="pe1540">Sir Duncan
                        Campbell</persName> — Its Insular situation made it strong in feudal times —
                    the MacGregors are reported to have retaken it (for the Isle is reputed to have
                    been theirs) by the stratagem — of setting <unclear reason="illegible">rucks</unclear> of Hay on the Ice &amp; pushing these before them till they
                    got close to the Rocks when they took the place by assault —</p>
                <p><pb n="f.6r"/>
                <placeName ref="pl2363"><hi rend="underline">Inverarderan</hi></placeName>
                    Inspected the Plantations and the House — both much in want of more attention
                    than has been shewn to them. <unclear reason="illegible">mean</unclear> to write
                    to <persName ref="pe1548">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Gregor</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe1549">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> MacEwen</persName> respecting them.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl2364"><hi rend="underline">Achriaoch</hi></placeName> — called
                    on <persName ref="pe1550">Cap<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Ronald
                        Campbell</persName> who had been my School fellow at <placeName ref="pl2324">Callander</placeName> — but he was f<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">m</hi></hi> home — <persName ref="pe1551">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Campbell</persName> &amp; his daughter <choice>
                        <abbr>rec<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>received</expan>
                    </choice> us with politeness &amp; attention —</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl2365">Chapel of St Filan</placeName> — crossed from <placeName ref="pl2364">Achriaoch</placeName> to visit the ruins of the seat of this
                    celebrated Saint — there are scarcely any vistiges of it remaining — but
                    superstion is still alive here — we saw <unclear reason="illegible">there
                        those</unclear> stones in the midst of weeds &amp; <unclear reason="illegible" unit="words">bell</unclear> within the ruins where
                    demented persons had been lately led under the persuasion of their Friends &amp;
                    of the lower order of people in General that they w<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> be cured of their insanity — which it is firmly believed often
                    happens through the influence of the Saint —</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl0990">Linn Eulain — St Filans pool — or Linn</placeName> — a
                    deep pool in the River to the westward of the Church about a mile — to this Pool
                    in which the Holy Saint used to bath such people resort for Health through the
                    efficacy of the holiness of the water not <unclear reason="illegible">believing</unclear> that the torrents that <pb n="f.6v"/>have passed
                    through it for several hundred years has washed away the sanctity of the Bath of
                    the S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> — to this Pool the Inhabitants also bring
                    their sick diseased Cattle, for cure by immersion in the water, or by being
                    sprinkled with it — mak<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> Offerings of rags or adding
                    stones to the Cairns on the top of the Rock under which the Linn is situated</p>
                <p>17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                    <placeName ref="pl0212">Tigh an Drum</placeName> — Slept here — the Honb<hi rend="superscript">l</hi>
                    <persName ref="pe1552">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Murray</persName> &amp; a
                    young Lady travelling to <placeName ref="pl0652">Staffa</placeName> also here
                    this night —</p>
                <p>Had a strong desire to go to <placeName ref="pl2366">Achmore</placeName>, the
                    residence of <persName ref="pe1553">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> John
                        Campbell</persName>, of <placeName ref="pl2367">Ach</placeName>, who had
                    been a school companion, and whom I have not seen since that time — but I was
                    prevented by the apprehension of incommod<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> the
                    Family as I heard there were some visitors already there —</p>
                <p>18 Proceed<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> through <placeName ref="pl2368">Glen
                        Lochay</placeName> passed close to <placeName ref="pl0212">Tigh an
                        Drum</placeName> the deserted <add place="above">lead</add> mine on the left
                    — fancied the <del>country</del>
                    <add place="above">mountains &amp; the Glen</add> remarkably Verdant — all under
                    Sheep — very few Inhabitants — the view on coming in sight of <placeName ref="pl2369">Strath-urchay</placeName> very grand &amp; beautiful —
                        <placeName ref="pl0213">Glenurchay</placeName> is situated on the right hand
                    in going out at <placeName ref="pl2368">Glen Lochay</placeName> &amp; lies north
                    &amp; South with an inclination to the east at the northern part of what we
                    could see — On the left near the School House passed a Farm called <placeName ref="pl2370"><hi rend="underline">Brackly</hi></placeName> which I observed
                    was very shaded with rocks towards the South West — and to this circumstance I
                    ascribed the Name <placeName ref="pl2370">Breachd-Sliamh</placeName> — this was
                    the residence &amp; gave designation to the antient Family <pb n="f.7r"/>of
                    MacGregor of <placeName ref="pl2370">Brachily</placeName> —</p>
                <p>At <placeName ref="pl0214">Dalmaly</placeName> visited the Church yard in which
                    there is a great number of Tombstones apparently of very great antiquity — Many
                    of them exhibit sculpture of no despicable execution — Several tiers or layers,
                    of stones said to have belonged, in the <del>
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/>
                    </del><add place="above">language of</add>
                    <persName ref="pe1554">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Peter M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Lennan schoolmaster</persName>, who &amp; the
                        <persName ref="pe1555">Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Intyre Jun<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName> shewed the church yard, to “<hi rend="underline">a warlike people called M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Gregors</hi>” — (he knew not whom he was addressing) <add place="above"><hi rend="underline">some</hi> of</add> these Tombstones have
                    a variety of flowers &amp; ornaments cut upon them — at the edges — in the
                    Center <add place="above">of each</add> a Warriour with a Spear — or <del>
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" atLeast="1" atMost="3"/>
                    </del> possibly pastoral staff — two animals which I concieve to be Greyhounds
                    facing each other with their Tails cocked up — on one there <add place="above"><gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/> of the <persName ref="pe1556">MacGregor</persName></add> were the figures of two Horsemen
                    mounted — the Sculpture very good — this is at the east end of the Church — at
                    the West end I discovered by clearing away a little of the Earth &amp; grass
                    that had overgrown it, a <hi rend="underline">Tree</hi> at the South west corner
                    on <add place="above">the</add> left hand close to the head of the Stones — very
                    distinctly cut, standing erect — four of these stones we were informed had
                        <unclear reason="illegible">framed</unclear>
                    <persName ref="pe1556"><hi rend="underline">MacGregors</hi></persName> Coffin:
                    but had been detached &amp; laid over four Graves where they now appear by some
                    unknown person — One of them had a remarkably well executed Garter of flowers
                    extending the ½ breath of the face of the stone — The Stone with the tree had a
                    Bow &amp; arrow <add place="above">nicely</add> cut upon it near the foot. Of
                    one of the Stones appertaining to a MacGregor Grave we were informed that a
                    person of some other clan had inscribed a <choice>
                        <abbr>diff<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>different</expan>
                    </choice> name and we saw that several lines the last word whereof “spouse” had
                    been cut away by order of a M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Gregor who w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> not admit of the Theft of the Gravestone <pb n="f.7v"/>of a Namesake — the word “spouse” had not been so compleatly
                    obliterated so as not to be perceptable — the <add place="above">figures
                        denoting the</add> year, in which this was done were left unaltered “<hi rend="underline">1798</hi>” at the foot of the Stone — <del>
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="several"/>
                    </del> We were informed that that Country <add place="above">particularly</add>
                    on the path of the <placeName ref="pl0988">Urchay</placeName> had of old
                    belonged to the MacGregors — they had been stripped of it very long ago — and
                        <unclear reason="illegible">then</unclear> their Tombstones were attempted
                    to be robbed — We were shewn the Gallows hill used by <persName ref="pe1556">the
                            <hi rend="underline">MacGregor</hi></persName> on a hill on the North of
                    the <placeName ref="pl0988">Urchay</placeName> near the present manse where his
                    Courts <del>
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" quantity="several"/>
                    </del>
                    <add place="above"><unclear reason="illegible">were in</unclear></add> use to
                    administer Justice — One of the Places where a residence is s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to have been is called <placeName ref="pl2371">Stron Mialachan</placeName> — the point of the Greyhound — this is a little
                    distance from the manse on the North of the <placeName ref="pl0988">Urchay</placeName> facing to the South —</p>
                <p>Visited <placeName ref="pl0215">Castle <hi rend="underline">Keulchuirn</hi></placeName> — the Inscription above the main doorway I <hi rend="superscript">E</hi> B 1695<note type="editorial">In the manuscript a
                        shield is depicted in the middle of the four-digit date.</note> M<hi rend="superscript">C</hi>C. The Antient part of this Building was a square
                    Tower front<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> the North — the west side &amp; south
                    were added in 1715 as we were informed by <persName ref="pe1557">Angus M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald</persName> who attended us by the
                        <persName ref="pe1681">Earl of that day</persName> to form Barracks for
                        <persName ref="pe1558">James the 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>s</persName>(the pretender to the British Crown) Troops in case of need
                    — the <persName ref="pe1681">Earl</persName> having been inclined to favour the
                    cause of the Stuart Family — This <add place="above">part of the</add> Building
                    had never been furnished — the whole was dismantled &amp; the Timber Slate
                    &amp;c sold by auction between 25 &amp; 30 years ago —</p>
                <p>Over the Church door was a stone s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to have been
                    taken from the Castle with the inscription <unclear reason="illegible">Siv</unclear>
                    <del>
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/>
                    </del> 1440 C.C. <pb n="f.8r"/>and over the door of the manse, I<hi rend="superscript">E</hi>M M<hi rend="superscript">C</hi>C without any Arms
                    or Date — s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> also to have been taken from the Castle
                    —</p>
                <p>In <placeName ref="pl1005">Glenlochay</placeName> met the <persName ref="pe0158">Rev<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Intyre</persName> &amp; <unclear reason="illegible">one</unclear> of his Daughters going to <placeName ref="pl0224">Luss</placeName> the minister of which is his Son In Law<note type="editorial"><persName ref="pe0023">John Stuart</persName>, who had
                        accompanied Thomas Pennant on his voyage and tour of 1772, and was married
                        to MacIntyre's daughter, Susan.</note> — I ment<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>
                    to him <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0436">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                            Laings attack</title></bibl> on the late <persName ref="pe0558">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Pherson</persName>, whom <persName ref="pe1563">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Laing</persName> charges with having forged
                    the Poems published under the Name of <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian</persName> —
                    the D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> — he asserts a falsehood — I was in
                        <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> a considerable time ago and had a
                    conversation with <persName ref="pe0558">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Pherson</persName> relative to that work — I
                    had supposed that <del>tho</del> he had used considerable liberty in connecting
                    parts &amp; supplying deficits of words which might have been lost in the course
                    of time or varied in the recitations. He said that he had done much less <add place="above">in</add> that way than I (the D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>)
                    could conceive — that he would shew me a greater collection of Galic Poetry than
                    I could believe had existed — desired me to go to him any day for ten days to
                    see that Collection and to see what he had done — but some circumstances
                    intervened to prevent my going — this was my fault not his — <persName ref="pe0558">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> MacPherson</persName> was as
                    unequal to such a Task as I am — <placeName ref="pl2375">Badenoch</placeName> is
                    not a Country in which good Galic is spoken — there were men in this Country
                        <persName ref="pe1564">Nicol M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Nicol</persName>
                    <add place="above">in <placeName ref="pl2376">arimian</placeName></add> &amp;
                        <persName ref="pe1565">Donald More Ludir Macilenlan</persName> who could
                    have repeated many of the poems of <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian</persName> —
                        <persName ref="pe0558">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Pherson</persName> was at the manse of
                        <placeName ref="pl0213">Glenurchay</placeName> in the time of my predecessor
                        M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                    <persName ref="pe1566">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Vean</persName> — and I
                    believe <persName ref="pe1567">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Jo
                        Hume</persName> was with him when in the course of making his collection.
                    —</p>
                <p>At the Manse resumed the subject with <persName ref="pe1555">Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> MacIntyre
                            Jun<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName> — &amp; the schoolmaster
                        <persName ref="pe1554">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Peter <pb n="f.8v"/>MacLelan</persName> — they treated the doubts of authenticity with the
                    greatest contempt — <persName ref="pe1554">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Lelan</persName> himself repeats parts of the
                    Poems — which are generally received in his country as pure &amp; Genuine —</p>
                <p>18 reached <placeName ref="pl1072">Inveraray</placeName> the seat of the
                        <persName ref="pe0086">Duke of argyle</persName> — the only Inn at the place
                    under repair — could only get one Room for my son &amp; myself — disturbed by an
                    extraordinary noise after going to bed — which I ascertained in the morning was
                    made by a Calender for Linnen — most improperly situated above a Bed room —</p>
                <p>19 <persName ref="pe0517">Col Graham</persName>, the Dukes Chamberlain to whom
                        <persName ref="pe1568">Lord Bannatyne</persName> had written called upon me
                    and I understood the Duke w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> like well enough to see
                    Company — went about 1<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>Clock to pay my respects —
                    and promised to dine with him — at <add place="above">½ after</add> four found
                    his Grace returned from his airing — <persName ref="pe1569">Sir W<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">m</hi></hi> Hart</persName> w<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> him — <persName ref="pe1377">Lady Augusta
                        Clavery</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe1570">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Campbell Carrick</persName> — the Duke very attentive — asked
                    which of my Names I put first — said “— you are a Brother Chieftan of mine — I <choice>
                        <abbr>ans<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>answered</expan>
                    </choice> — a very inconsiderable one my Lord — Duke — Nay — you make a good
                    figure now that you are <del>all collected</del>
                    <add place="above">united</add> and not of diff<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>
                    Names — did any of them take the Name of Campbell? I ans<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/>
                    <pb n="f.9r"/>had that I had seen an original Bond of Kinsmanship between one of
                    the <placeName ref="pl2377"><unclear reason="illegible">Auchinbreck</unclear></placeName> Family &amp; some MacGregors —</p>
                <p>The Duke was remarkably pointed in his attentions and I left him with an
                    increased veneration &amp; respect for his Character — and without feeling
                    towards him the slightest sense of resentment on acc<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> of the innumerable cruelties which some of his Predecessors had
                    committed <choice>
                        <abbr>ag<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>against</expan>
                    </choice> mine and the Clan in general — for which it w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be most unjust &amp; illiberal to attach any blame to any of the
                    present Generations on either side. — The Castle a chaste build<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> suited to the Scenery which is grand &amp;
                    magnificently beautiful</p>
                <p>20 Proceeded by <placeName ref="pl0270">Portsonachan</placeName> to breakfast —
                    walked out to the House of <persName ref="pe1571">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Campbell of Sonachan</persName> — whose B<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi>
                    <persName ref="pe1571">John</persName> had been a class fellow of mine —
                        <persName ref="pe1571">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Campbell</persName>
                    was not at home — From thence crossed the ferry passed the Church of <placeName ref="pl1248">Lochchrianan</placeName> where there was a very good appearance
                    of people assembled — through a romantic tract of <persName ref="pe1440">Lochnells</persName> woods of great extent passed in to <placeName ref="pl1074">Tigh an Uilt</placeName> (the House at the Rivulet) near a
                    Church where there was likewise an assemblage of very decent people <pb n="f.9v"/>and amongst them some M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Gregors — the Innkeeper is
                    of that name — These men expressed satisfaction at seeing me &amp; my Son — In
                    the Church yard there a Tombstone of great antiquity with some <add place="above">rude</add> sculpture — of which <persName ref="pe1598">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Leyden</persName> Tutor to two young
                    Hamburgers who are making an excursion as far as <placeName ref="pl0652">Staffa</placeName> attempted to take a Sketch — These Boys &amp; their
                    Tutor walked from <placeName ref="pl1072">Inveraray</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0270">Portsonachan</placeName>
                    <add place="above">not being able to procure horses</add> — on the West side of
                    the ferry I took the youngest into my Carriage — the other got a Horse at
                        <placeName ref="pl1248">Kilchrainan</placeName> — and I procured one from
                        <persName ref="pe1599">Dougal MacGregor</persName> at <placeName ref="pl1074">Tigh an Uilt</placeName> for the Tutor —</p>
                <p>Reached <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName> in the Ev<hi rend="superscript">g.</hi> &amp; met <persName ref="pe1684">Col M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald Lyndal</persName> there — <persName ref="pe1685">MacDougal
                        younger of MacDougal</persName> came to <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName> on hearing of my being there and my Son &amp; I went to
                        <placeName ref="pl0722">Dunolly</placeName> with him <del>
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" quantity="1"/>
                    </del>. Here we saw <persName ref="pe1685">old MacDougal</persName> in his 88<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> year — a venerable figure of fine appearance —
                    confined to his Room — but his Intellect &amp; his voice as whole as ever. He
                    was angry at my hav<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> gone to <placeName ref="pl0217">Inveraray</placeName> — considering that one of the last Lairds of
                    Macgregor had been treacherously murdered there by an <persName ref="pe1817">Earl of Argyle</persName> — &amp; considering the attrocities committed by
                    the Family of Argyle <choice>
                        <abbr>ag<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>against</expan>
                    </choice> the MacGregors — I <add place="above"><unclear reason="illegible">felt</unclear> my</add> excuse <del unit="words" quantity="several"/>
                    in this, — that it was impossible with any degree of Justice to harbour ill will <choice>
                        <abbr>ag<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>against</expan>
                    </choice> the present Generation, for the acts of their predecessors. <pb n="f.10r"/>The old Gentleman ment<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> the
                    particulars of the above murder briefly in these words — a <persName ref="pe1600">Sir Duncan Campbell</persName> of <placeName ref="pl2377">Auchinbreck</placeName> was extremely intimate <del>and <gap unit="letters" atLeast="2" atMost="3"/></del>with the <persName ref="pe1818">Laird of
                        MacGregor</persName> — the <persName ref="pe1817">Earl of Argyle</persName>
                    wished to see <persName ref="pe1818">MacGregor</persName> &amp; imployed
                        <persName ref="pe1600">Sir Duncan</persName> to induce him to visit him at
                        <placeName ref="pl0217">Inveraray</placeName> on the most solemn assurances
                    of good treatment &amp; safety — They came to <placeName ref="pl0217">Inveraray</placeName> and after they had been a day or two there <persName ref="pe1600">Sir Dun<hi rend="superscript">.s</hi></persName> Servant having
                    come to attend his master one morn<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> on opening the
                    window of the Room he started back in great agitation — <persName ref="pe1600">Sir Dun.</persName> demanded the reason and was informed that <persName ref="pe1818">MacGregor</persName> was murdered &amp; hung upon a Tree in
                    front of the Window — <persName ref="pe1600">Sir Duncan</persName> who, as <add place="above">was much</add> his Family in general, was a man of honour <del unit="words" quantity="1"/> was extremely enraged &amp; afflicted by this
                    murder which he feared would stain his own Honour — &amp; sought to revenge it —
                        <persName ref="pe1819">Campbell of Aberuchill</persName> was then the
                    adviser &amp; manager of the Earl — <persName ref="pe1600">Sir Dun.</persName>
                    endeavoured to get them together — but they went of without his <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/> to <placeName ref="pl0076">Ed<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></placeName> — Wither <persName ref="pe1600">Sir Duncan</persName> followed - &amp; having found them in a
                    House in the <placeName ref="pl2277">Cowgate</placeName> rushed into the Room
                    with <pb n="f.10v"/>a pistol in one hand and a sword in the other — reproached
                        <persName ref="pe1817">argyle</persName> in the most severe manner for his
                    barbarous treachery and believing he had been prompted to the diabolical act by
                        <persName ref="pe1819">Aberuchill</persName> told the Earl that if he did
                    not immediately put that fellow to death he <persName ref="pe1600">Sir
                        Duncan</persName> would instantly blow out his the Earls brains — The Earl
                    then very cooly thrust his sword or dirk into <persName ref="pe1819">Aberuchills</persName> belly &amp; killed him on the spot. — <del unit="letters" quantity="3"/> And that was all the ammends <persName ref="pe1600">Sir Duncan</persName> got for the murder of <persName ref="pe1818">MacGregor</persName> — no enquiry was made how <persName ref="pe1819">aberuchil</persName> had died.” —</p>
                <p>I recollect this old Gentleman’s having told me the same melancholy story in the
                    very same words about 32 years ago — He says he had often heard his Father tell
                    it. See * *<note type="authorial">** <persName ref="pe1685">MacDougal</persName>
                        says the only Freehold the <persName ref="pe1375">Earl of
                            Breadalbane</persName> has in <placeName ref="pl0818">argyleshire</placeName> is the Lands which MacGregor had on the
                            <placeName ref="pl0988">Urquhay</placeName>
                        <placeName ref="pl2369">Strathurquhay</placeName> &amp; the Glen of that
                        Name —</note></p>
                <p>This Family were forfeited in the days of <persName ref="pe0544">Robert the
                        Bruce</persName>
                    <choice>
                        <abbr>ag<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>against</expan>
                    </choice> whom they fought with the Cummings &amp;c at the Battle of <placeName ref="pl0273">Dalriogh</placeName> where he was defeated — the Macdougals had
                    nearly taken him prisoner — hav<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> caught his Mantle
                    which with a large Silver Brach (or Buchile) was in possession of the Family of
                    MacDougal <del unit="words" quantity="1"/> the home of the present old mans
                    Grandfather when the Family seat was burnt down &amp; these articles lost with
                    the effects that <pb n="f.11r"/>were in the House<note type="editorial">A
                        similar anecdote concerning a broach taken from Robert the Bruce at Dalrigh
                        and handed down by the Dunollie family until its destruction by fire is
                        given in Thomas Pennant, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0010">A tour
                                in Scotland 1772, part II</title></bibl> (1776), p.14.</note> — This
                    Family suffered much in consequence of the attempt of the Stuarts in 1715 — in
                    1737 the present Laird <choice>
                        <abbr>obt<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>obtained</expan>
                    </choice> some grant of the forfeiture through the Argyle of that day for 60,000
                    marks, — he had no more than £10 p<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> an. <unclear reason="illegible">clear</unclear> for ten years after he married — he paid
                    all off and added between 4 &amp; 5000 £s worth of Lands to the remnant of the
                    Estate to which he succeeded - &amp; will leave his property without a shill<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> of incumberance —</p>
                <p>23<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> July 1800<note type="editorial">The date is
                        clearly given in the manuscript as 23 July 1800 although this does not fit
                        with the dating of subsequent entries.</note> this morn<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> the Lady of <persName ref="pe1821">M<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> Duncan
                        MacDougal</persName> second son of this Family had a Son. <del unit="words" quantity="1"/> Her husband is at present abroad in <placeName ref="pl0889">Ireland</placeName> in <persName ref="pe1375">Lord Breadalbans</persName>
                    Fencible Reg<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> —</p>
                <p>— The old Laird paid us the Compliment of saying that if agreable his little
                    newborn Grandson w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be named <hi rend="underline">Gregor</hi> in compliment to me and of course I made my acknowledgements
                    for the <unclear reason="illegible">intended</unclear> honour</p>
                <p>21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> July on the excursion to <persName ref="pl0691">Eisdale</persName> the Cairn of Stones known by the Inhabitants past all
                    memory under the name <placeName ref="pl2406">Carn Alpin</placeName> was pointed
                    out at the west <add place="above">or south</add> end of <placeName ref="pl0268">Loch Feuchan</placeName> — The tradition is that this Cairn was made to
                    perpetuate the <del>memory of</del> remembrance of the embarking for <placeName ref="pl0651">Icolumkill</placeName> of the first of the Alpinian Kings who
                    was sent to be interred there —</p>
                <p><pb n="f.11v"/>
                22 July. With <del>young</del>
                    <persName ref="pe1820">MacDougal</persName> younger — visited the <placeName ref="pl0685">Castle of Dunstaffnage</placeName> the Seat of the Early
                    Scottish Kings — The outer walls are entire as far up as the Curtain — It is
                    built upon a Rock which bears <unclear reason="illegible">indeed</unclear> marks
                    of fusion — the Castle was a square with a Bastion at each angle — In the center
                    is s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to have been a large House of which <persName ref="pe1820">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Dougal Jun<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi></persName> recollects vestages — <unclear reason="illegible">M<gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" quantity="1"/> N<gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" quantity="1"/>b<gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" atLeast="2"/></unclear> who met us at this place said
                    that the tradition was that this Castle was erected before that of
                        <unclear>GR</unclear> that <placeName ref="pe1601">King Fergus</placeName>
                    built it — another said the tradition was that it had been built 500 years
                    before the Christian era — “Coig ceud bliana mass danic Críoste er tallamb”<note type="editorial">Còig cheud bliadhna mas tàinig Crìosd air talamh.
                        (AMC).</note> — It is evidently extremely antient — near it are the remains
                    of a very old Chapel in which it is said some of the first Kings of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> were buried — the style of building is
                    very old — Gothic — at the east end there is a modern <choice>
                        <abbr>add<hi rend="superscript">n</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>addition</expan>
                    </choice> in which the <hi rend="underline">MacInnishes</hi> (the descendants of
                        <persName ref="pe1822">Angus</persName>) the patronimic of the Campbells of
                        <placeName ref="pl0685">Dunstaffnage</placeName> were buried.</p>
                <p>The Castle is considered a Royal <pb n="f.12r"/>House — <persName ref="pe1820">MacDougal</persName> Doubts whether ever the Dunstaffnage Family got
                    possession of the Castle as a property — The <persName ref="pe0086">D. of
                        argyle</persName> is hereditary Keeper.</p>

                <p><placeName ref="pl2407">Glenshira</placeName> which makes a beautiful part of the
                    Pleasure Ground of the <persName ref="pe0086">D: of argyle</persName> is said to
                    have belonged to the MacGregors —</p>
                <p>23 proceded from <persName ref="pe1685">MacDougals</persName> up the <placeName ref="pl2195">Sounds of Mull</placeName> — &amp; <placeName ref="pl0683">Morvern</placeName> — on the <add place="above">right hand or north
                        side</add> passed <placeName ref="pl2205"><hi rend="underline">an
                            Charrig</hi></placeName> a flat Rock of some extent upon which one of
                    the MacLeans of <placeName ref="pl0684">Duart</placeName> put his Lady, the
                    daughter of the argyle of the day, in order that she might be drowned: but she
                    was saved by the accident of <add place="above">the Crew of</add> some Vessel
                        <del unit="words" atLeast="2" atMost="4"/> tak<hi rend="superscript">g</hi>
                    her up — <persName ref="pe1823">MacLean</persName> is s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to have gone to Visit <persName ref="pe1824">Argyle</persName> to
                    report the death of his wife — who was the first he saw at the head of her
                    Brothers Table — <persName ref="pe1824">Argyle</persName>
                    <add place="above">in dismissing him</add> told him he <add place="above">himself</add> would not punish him but to beware of his Brother — and it is
                        s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> the B<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> did
                    actually run him thro’ the Body on the Street at <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName> —</p>
                <p>On the left passed <placeName ref="pl0684">Castle Duart</placeName> the Chief
                    Seat of the MacLean family in a commanding situation from which they had very
                    extensive views in all directions —</p>
                <p><pb n="f.12v"/>
                The Castle walls appear to be pretty entire and it is occupied by some persons
                    amongst whom is one <add place="above">Soldiery</add> Invalids —</p>
                <p>The day being hazy the mist on the mountains of <placeName ref="pl0729">Mull</placeName> displayed scenes of great variety and undescribable
                    Sublimity — Some times the tops of the mountains were obscured by a dense
                        <unclear reason="illegible">opake</unclear> mist &amp; their bases clear. —
                    In some places the drapery resembled the finest muslin moving in various
                    fantastic festoons over the Sides and tops of the Hills — <persName ref="pe0557">Ossians</persName> columns of Mist were exhibited in a thousand <choice>
                        <abbr>diff<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>different</expan>
                    </choice> Shapes and it is impossible for any person to have any competent Idea
                    of the justness of his Imagery without visiting the Regions that suggested them:
                    and they are so grand &amp; magnificent that it is impossible that any Poet but
                        <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian</persName> could have found expression to have
                    described them.</p>
                <p>Passed <placeName ref="pl1091">Scallastale</placeName> a beautifully <add place="above">situated</add> Farm in <placeName ref="pl0729">Mull</placeName> — and arrived at</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl2196">Ard Torr Innish</placeName> — <persName ref="pe1602">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>Gregor of
                        Durrin</persName> resides here — his Family consists of his wife 5 Sons
                    &amp; 4 Daughters besides a Son abroad in the army — a very fine flock of
                    Children the Young Ladies <pb n="f.13r"/>very genteel in their appearance &amp;
                    the Boys Very promising. The eldest Son is a Stout man — <persName ref="pe1603">John</persName> —</p>
                <p>Here was one of the principal Seats of the MacDonalds Kings of the Isles — my
                    Maternal Ancestors — the Castle is on a promontory projecting into the Sound of
                        <placeName ref="pl0683">Morvern</placeName> and <add place="above">lies on
                        the North Side of it</add> front<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> the South —
                    The Situation commands an extensive view east &amp; west to <placeName ref="pl0684">Duart</placeName> &amp; beyond the <placeName ref="pl0682">Castle of Aros</placeName> which <add place="above">last</add> also
                    belonged to MacDonald — To this place, <placeName ref="pl2196">Ard
                        torr-innish</placeName> it is s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> an Embassador
                    from one of the Edwards of <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> to the
                    King of the Isles<note type="editorial">The so called treaty of Westminster
                        Ardtorinish in 1462. See J. and R.W. Munro, eds., <hi rend="italic">The Acts
                            of the Lords of the Isles, 1336-1493</hi> (Edinburgh: Scottish History
                        Society, 1986), pp.110-116. (AMC)</note> — The Castle has been a place of
                    strength — the walls be<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> about 10 Feet thick — the
                    Center which is the most entire was an oblong square — on the north &amp; south
                    there are vestiges of circular walls — as outwards — that surrounded the Body of
                    the place — the foundation of the Court Room is still visible a Room between 60
                    &amp; 70 Feet long with smaller Rooms on each side at the South end — there are
                    the vestiges of many buildings and of the Garden around the Castle — <add place="inline">some persons who s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> they were
                        skilled in architecture supposed this Build<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> to
                        have been of the 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Century.</add></p>
                <p>It is said that there was an aqueduct from a Rivulet <add place="above">named
                            <placeName ref="pl2408">ault more</placeName> in contradistinction to
                        many smaller</add> — that precipitates over the Hill called <placeName ref="pl2409"><hi rend="underline">GlaishVein</hi></placeName> on the north
                    in a circular direction to the west &amp; then South to the Castle about a mile
                    — Some of the flowers that had been in the Garden grew since <persName ref="pe1602">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gregorson</persName> came to
                    reside here — &amp; there is still some Tansey in it —</p>
                <p>— On the top <add place="above">or edge</add> of <placeName ref="pl2409">Glaishvein</placeName>
                    <add place="above">at the distance of a mile &amp; half</add> there is a flat
                    spot called <unclear reason="illegible"><placeName ref="pl2410">Lùid na
                            Cùirt</placeName></unclear> — where <persName ref="pe1825">MacDonald</persName> is s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to have held
                    Criminal Courts — and just below is a perpendicular precipice over which felons
                    capitally convicted are s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to have <add place="above">sometimes</add> been pricipitated, <pb n="f.13v"/>after the
                    manner of the Romans — this precipice is named <placeName ref="pl2411"><unclear reason="illegible"><hi rend="underline">Garih</hi></unclear> na
                        Cuirt</placeName> — from its <add place="above">b<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> so</add> extremely perpendicular as to represent a Wall —</p>
                <p>Near this spot, further to the East is a Cave called <placeName ref="pl2412"><add place="above">Uamb</add> Breedan</placeName>
                    <del>Cave</del> — the <placeName ref="pl2412">Cave of S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Bride</placeName> in which that recluse, from whom the M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Brides took their Name, is s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to have resided — people of that Name still resort to see the Cave —
                    which has for about a century past <choice>
                        <abbr>obt<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>obtained</expan>
                    </choice> the Name of <placeName ref="pl2412">Dugal Buies Cave</placeName> from
                    a freebooter of the Name of <persName ref="pe1826">MacLachlan</persName> who
                    occupied it for a considerable time —</p>
                <p>A low point of land near that Cave is called <placeName ref="pl2413">Rûh an
                        Riderih</placeName> from the circumstance it is supposed of the Knights of
                        <placeName ref="pl0684">Duart</placeName> land<hi rend="superscript">g</hi>
                    there occasionally on their Visits to <placeName ref="pl0683">Morvern</placeName> — &amp; by the point <add place="above">on a small Rock
                        or Island</add> one of the ships that composed the Spanish Armada was lost —
                    the commander of which was interred near the Point.</p>
                <p>The M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Leans are said to have got this part of
                        <placeName ref="pl0683">Morvern</placeName> by Marriage from the Lords of
                    the Isles — and the Campbells wrested it from the M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Leans by means which <pb n="f.14r"/>are reputed to have been the most
                    fraudulent.</p>
                <p>The Key of the <placeName ref="pl0683">Castle of ard torr innish</placeName>
                    <add place="above">or of the Prison</add> was found about 5 or 6 &amp; twenty
                    years ago in digging rubbish of one of the out Houses on the east side of the
                    Castle by some of <persName ref="pe1602">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Gregorsons</persName> workmen — He says it was 16 or 18 Inches long and as
                    thick as his wrist — <persName ref="pe1602">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                        Gregorson</persName> and some others of the Family saw it — But the workman
                    in the absence of <persName ref="pe1602">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Gregorson</persName> on a fish<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> party went <add place="above">clandestinly the same night</add> to the Smithdy and used the
                    Key for mend<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> the points of his <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" quantity="4"/>
                    <unclear reason="illegible">axes</unclear> &amp; other Tools which of course
                    displeased <persName ref="pe1602">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Gregorson</persName> very much and the <persName ref="pe0086">Duke of
                        argyle</persName> is s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to have been exceedingly
                    vexed at this circumstance.</p>
                <p>24 July <persName ref="pe1602">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Gregorson</persName> sent a Boat with a <choice>
                        <abbr>L<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>Letter</expan>
                    </choice> — for the <persName ref="pe1604">Rev<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi>
                            M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Nicol</persName> Minister of <placeName ref="pl0688">Lismore</placeName> whom I was very desirous to see &amp; converse with
                    regarding the Poems of <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian</persName> with which he
                    was acquainted long before any of them were translated — He was unluckily from
                    home at <placeName ref="pl2414">Port Appin</placeName> on official duty &amp;
                    could not come — <persName ref="pe1602">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Gregorson</persName> sent me his answer to the note that was sent to him — *
                    see near the end of this Book — <note type="authorial"><p>*See <placeName ref="pl2196">Ardtorrinish</placeName> at this mark — 24 July 1800
                                f<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">m</hi></hi>
                            <persName ref="pe1603">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gregor
                                Junior</persName> &amp; the rest of the Family</p>
                        <p>The <persName ref="pe0559">Prince Charles Edward</persName> landed at
                                <placeName ref="pl2492">Borradale</placeName> on <placeName ref="pl2493">Loch nan Uamh</placeName> pronounced Uavh near the
                            Summer quarter or Shealing of <persName ref="pe1827"><add place="above">Angus mac Ian mhic Ruary</add>
                                <del><unclear reason="illegible">Dougal</unclear></del>
                                MacDonald</persName> of <placeName ref="pl2622">Duchamus</placeName>
                            of Brother to <persName ref="pe1828">Borradale</persName> — He sat upon
                            a creel (a wicker basket used for the carriage of peats &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>) and cut of a chest — both were regarded
                            by <persName ref="pe1827">Duchamus</persName> as sacred <add place="above">&amp; made use of the Chest all his life as his only
                                table at home</add> — Both Brothers attended the Prince throughout
                                <add place="above">the greatest part of</add> his distresses 'till
                            he <unclear reason="illegible">embarked</unclear> again for <placeName ref="pl0925">France</placeName> at the same spot where he had landed
                            — <persName ref="pe1830">Katharine MacGregor</persName> Aunt to
                                <persName ref="pe1829">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                                MacGregor</persName> of <placeName ref="pl2623">Durrin</placeName>
                            now resides at <placeName ref="pl2196">ardtorinish</placeName> was the
                            wife of <persName ref="pe1827">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald</persName> of <placeName ref="pl2622">Duchamus</placeName>. The present <persName ref="pe1624">Barra</persName> got a memorandum from <persName ref="pe1827">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald <add place="above">Duchamus</add></persName> cald
                            a narrative of the Princes escapes &amp; adventures<note type="editorial">Possibly a version of <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0167">A Plain, Authentic and Faithful Narrative of
                                        the Passages of the Young Chevalier</title></bibl> (London:
                                1750).</note> which he gave to <persName ref="pe1567">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> John Hume</persName></p>
                        <p><persName ref="pe1831">Capt <del unit="letters" atLeast="5" atMost="7"/>(Ferguson <del unit="letters" atLeast="20" atMost="23"/>)</persName> made <persName ref="pe1832">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald</persName> a
                            prisoner &amp; kept her three days onborad ship <add place="above">and
                                then put her upon an insulated Rock</add> — he made some of his Crew
                            take her Gold rings <del>off</del><add place="above">from</add> her
                            fingers which were swelled by the violence of attempting to get them off
                            that they could only get them sawing which they did.</p></note></p>
                <p>25 Left <placeName ref="pl2196">Ardtorrinnish</placeName> — carried on board a
                    man of the Name of <persName ref="pe1686">Cameron</persName> who was reported to
                    know some of the History of the Fingalians: but tho’ there were some gleamings
                    of it to be discovered in two tales or three he told it was evident that he knew
                    little of the genuine productions of <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian</persName> —
                    he named several of the Chiefs &amp; of the Ladies properly <pb n="f.14v"/>the
                    stories he had were manifestly Irish legends perfectly distinct from the
                    Highland traditions relative to the Ffions —</p>
                <p>On my objecting to the possibility of the Lochlanites of whom he spoke as coming
                    to <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> &amp; of <persName ref="pe0540">Fingals</persName> going to <placeName ref="pl2428">Lochlan</placeName> for
                    ‘want of Vessels fit for the purpose <add place="above">hav<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> had only wicker Boats covered w<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Hides</add> he said that they had vessels
                    constructed of Oak called <hi rend="underline">Luinis fad</hi><note type="editorial">Luingis fada. (AMC).</note> Long shipping with many oars in
                    a side he in particular <choice>
                        <abbr>ment<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>mentioned</expan>
                    </choice> 16 oar Boats which he said would carry a considerable number of men
                    —</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl2429"><hi rend="underline">Finari</hi></placeName> — dined at
                    the <persName ref="pe0899">Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Leods</persName> — this place is said to have
                    been a summer quarter or hunt<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> resort of <persName ref="pe0540">Fingals</persName> — There is a Rock covered with soil <add place="above">form<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> a circular mound</add> about
                    30 paces in diameter called <placeName ref="pl2430"><hi rend="underline">Dun
                            Fin</hi></placeName> — <persName ref="pe0540">Fingals</persName> mound —
                    there is a distinct vestige of the foundation of a wall which went round the
                    verge of this Rock. — the present ministers predecessor took down the remains of
                    a wall 3 f. high to build other Houses w<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> it — The
                    prospect from this mound is extremely extensive and romantic — <placeName ref="pl0722">Dunolly</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl0684">Duart</placeName>,
                        <placeName ref="pl0682">Aros</placeName> &amp; &amp; may be seen from it —
                    and close to it in the west is a deep Glen <add place="above">fringed with
                        wood</add> — through which a torrent runs constantly — rendering the scene
                    extremely worth of being called <placeName ref="pl2431">Shalla Mah</placeName>
                    <pb n="f.15r"/>or the <hi rend="underline">pleasant View</hi>
                    <unclear reason="illegible">A</unclear>
                    <placeName ref="pl2431">Selma</placeName> of <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian</persName> of which it is <persName ref="pe0899">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Leods</persName>
                    opinion <persName ref="pe0540">Fingal</persName> had many — He of course treats
                    with derision the doubts of the authenticity of <persName ref="pe0557">Ossians</persName> Poems. —</p>
                <p>Proceded to <placeName ref="pl2432">Drimnin</placeName> where I was astonished to
                    find a group of elegant young Ladies.</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe1610"><hi rend="underline">Isobel Chaum</hi> —
                        Cameron</persName> — this woman died four or five years ago aged 126 or 127.
                    She remembered the Massacre of <placeName ref="pl2433">Glenco</placeName>
                    perfectly — had two Sons fit to bear arms in 1715, and lived in the woods with
                    them to prevent their being compelled to served that year in the army. She
                    walked about the Country ‘till within a few months of her decease. resided
                    chiefly in the Parish of <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" quantity="1"/> in
                        <placeName ref="pl0683">Morvern</placeName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0818">argyleshire</placeName>
                    <add place="above">passed <placeName ref="pl0682">Aros</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl0729">Mull</placeName> an old Castle belong<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to the M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donalds Afterwards to the
                            M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Leans &amp; now to the <persName ref="pe0086">D. of Argyle</persName> — his Factor <persName ref="pe1611">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Maxwell</persName> resides <unclear reason="illegible">there</unclear> in a modern House —</add></p>
                <p>26 Visited <placeName ref="pl0681">Tobermory</placeName> — <add place="above">Passed <placeName ref="pl2434">Caistal nan Coin</placeName> — s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to have also belonged to the <choice>
                            <abbr>M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>D<hi rend="superscript">ds</hi></abbr>
                            <expan>M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donalds</expan>
                        </choice> on the <placeName ref="pl0683">morvern</placeName> side — where
                        they used to keep their Dogs —</add> saw the <choice>
                        <abbr>Co<hi rend="superscript">y</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>Company</expan>
                    </choice> of Volunteers there inspected by Major B<gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" quantity="several"/> of the 73 who recollected me in
                        <placeName ref="pl1024">India</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Conversed with several of the settlers in the Village of <placeName ref="pl0681">Tobermory</placeName> estab<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> by the Society for
                    British Fisheries.</p>
                <p>They stated that Leases for 99 y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> of the site of
                    their Houses &amp; Gardens <add place="above">&amp; of 30 years for their crofts
                        of 5 acres to each person</add> had been promised but not yet given to them
                        <pb n="f.15v"/>that according to the Regulations for establishing the
                    Settlement each Settler was to have one Cows grass but that the number of 16
                        <add place="above">who</add> had built Houses on the faith of that promise
                    have not been allowed any Grass for Cows which they regarded as a very severe
                    hardship <add place="inline">as they cannot get any for the Tenants in the
                        Country</add></p>
                <p>Those who have Grass pay 5/ for a Cows Grass — 2/6 for Peat moss Licence and 1<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> or 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> p<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> foot for the ground
                    occupied by their Houses &amp; Gardens in the 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>
                    &amp; 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> choice of situations — 6<hi rend="superscript">s</hi> p<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> foot in the front
                    row in which slated Houses only are allowed to be erected — argyles Street — the
                    next is Braidalbane Street — a House 30 Feet long by 14 Broad <add place="above">&amp; 7½ high</add> thatched cost £30 — uncertain whether the interior of
                    the walls were limed or only the two outer faces pinned w<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> it —</p>
                <p>In the Evening four of the Settlers came to <placeName ref="pl2432">Drimnen</placeName> to call upon me and to represent the grievances under
                    which they allege they are respect<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> not only their
                    Cows Grass but the crofts of 5 acres each — They shewed me a <choice>
                        <abbr>L<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>Letter</expan>
                    </choice> — which had been written to them by the <choice>
                        <abbr>Sec<hi rend="superscript">y</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>Secretary</expan>
                    </choice> of the Society in answer to a complaint on this Subject. of which a
                    copy had been sent to <persName ref="pe1611">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Maxwell</persName> the Societies agent &amp; Factor to the <persName ref="pe0086">Duke</persName> from whom I saw a <choice>
                        <abbr>L<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>Letter</expan>
                    </choice> adress<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to these men, on the subject of
                    their Complaint — imputing that they had not been candid in their Statements —
                    that the extra ground was intermediatly occupied by other Settlers between Terms
                    — that he could not assize their lots like a Surveyor sh<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> measure them off &amp; that he had applied to one — that the
                    Society meant to direct the attention of the Settlers to commerce &amp; not to
                    Farming — upon the whole substance of this <choice>
                        <abbr>L<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>Letter</expan>
                    </choice> it occurred to me that the men had ground of complaint ag<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> the Society or their agent. as they have not yet <choice>
                        <abbr>rec<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>received</expan>
                    </choice> their lots tho’ the Surveyor has been there — These men alleged that
                    they had offered to accept of their lots of 5 acres without insisting for the
                    present for the Cows grass but that they had been refused unless they w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> sign declarations that they either had no right or
                    that they relinquished their right to Cows grass which they <pb n="f.16r"/>declined to do. I was sorry these men had not <choice>
                        <abbr>ment<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>mentioned</expan>
                    </choice> these particulars to me when I was on the spot at <placeName ref="pl0681">Tobermory</placeName> as I could have conversed with <persName ref="pe0086">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Maxwell</persName> regard<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> them</p>
                <p>observed that the want of a proper Road <add place="above">from the Shore up to
                        the Hills</add> must greatly impede the operations of the Settlers — and it
                    appears to me that the first improvement that ought to be attempted is the
                    throwing a small arch over a rill of water at the north end of the terrace to
                    make the access to the Town tollerably easy — a road up to the Village slanting
                    south first &amp; then northwards so as to give access to wheel carriages — 3 a
                    pier for the accommodation of Vessels in time of bad weather and for
                    facilitating shipping &amp; unshipping of articles — 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> the removal by force of powder of some rocks that are dry at low
                    water in the narrow passage between the <placeName ref="pl2435">Isle of <hi rend="underline">Calimb</hi></placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl2436">Drumfin</placeName> which w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> give the advantage
                    of access to the Port to the Eastward or towards the <placeName ref="pl2195">Sound of Mull</placeName>.</p>
                <p>The Villagers informed me that the <placeName ref="pl2435">Island of
                        Calish</placeName> belongs to the Dukes of Argyle which from its position in
                    the mouth of the Harbour it is highly necessary sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>
                    be acquired by the Society — it is s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to be under
                    lease to the <persName ref="pe1612">Chamberlain of Tiree</persName> — for about
                    £10 — the Settlers said they w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> pay them that rent
                    rather than not have it.</p>
                <p>Respect<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> the grass for their cows I observed to him
                    that the Innkeeper could not accommodate the public without the means of
                    providing travellers with provisions which rendered a suitable extent of ground
                    indispensable for him — they admitted this but said that he had more than w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> answer that purpose —</p>
                <p>27<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> In the morn<hi rend="superscript">g</hi>
                    <choice>
                        <abbr>rec<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>received</expan>
                    </choice> a Memorand<hi rend="superscript">m.</hi> from these Settlers in a
                    Letter which they sent by the master of the Cutter — Left <placeName ref="pl2432">Drimnen</placeName> where I was delighted with the contentment
                    of <persName ref="pe1613">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Lean</persName> &amp; the elegance of the young
                    Ladies and reached <placeName ref="pl0896">Coll</placeName> in the Ev<hi rend="superscript">g</hi></p>
                <p><add place="inspace">On mentioning to <persName ref="pe1613">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Lean</persName> that there was a <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0436">Book</title></bibl> published just before I left
                            <persName ref="pl0076">Ed<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName> to
                        prove <persName ref="pe0557">Ossians</persName> poems to have been a forgery
                        of <persName ref="pe0558">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Phersons</persName>
                        she mildly ans<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> — “But that will not be listened
                        to —”</add>*<note type="authorial">*<persName ref="pe1614">Malcom
                            Fletcher</persName> in <placeName ref="pl2437">Glenforsa</placeName> in
                            <placeName ref="pl0729">Mull</placeName> died about 10 years ago ab<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Eighty years old — <persName ref="pe1613">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> MacLean</persName> used to be delighted
                        to hear him repeat the Poems of <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian</persName> —
                        he could read Galic only</note></p>
                <p><pb n="f.16v"/>
                28 July — <placeName ref="pl0896">Coll</placeName>. We intended to have proceeded
                    to <placeName ref="pl0652">Staffa</placeName> direct but were obliged to make
                    for <placeName ref="pl0896">Coll</placeName> to prevent our retrograding by the
                    force of the Tide — anchored in <placeName ref="pl2440"><hi rend="underline">Loch Uirn</hi></placeName> which from its ruggedness merits the Name of
                    the infernal Loch — we were rowed in the yact to the <placeName ref="pl2438">House of Coll</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl2439">Loch <add place="above">a</add> Chaistle</placeName>, from an old Square tower
                        stand<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> there — built at too remote a period for
                    their History — The Family mansion is comfortable and it is occupied by an
                    amicable group of Ladies — and an intelligent spirited Landlord — Who has made
                    an excellent Garden with a Hot House producing some good fruit.<note type="editorial">The Macleans of Coll had other well-heeled travellers at
                        this time. These included Edward Clarke, sometime professor of mineralogy
                        and Sarah Murray of Kensington (1802). See Nicolas Maclean-Bristol, <hi rend="italic">Clan to Regiment</hi> (Barnsley: Pen &amp; Sword Military,
                        2007), pp.297-306. (AMC).</note></p>
                <p>His side table was ornamented with a Bust of <persName ref="pe0484">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Fox</persName> — <del unit="words" quantity="1"/></p>
                <p>28 — We proceeded to <placeName ref="pl0652">Staffa</placeName> and had the good
                    fortune of a remarkably fine day for the purpose — the magnificence of this
                    specimen of Natural Architecture<note type="editorial">The architectural
                        comparison is a common trope in travellers' descriptions of Staffa,
                        originating with Joseph Banks's account of the island and its caves,
                        published in Pennant, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0008">A tour in
                                Scotland 1772</title></bibl> (1774), pp.299-309.</note> can
                        <del>only</del>
                    <add place="above">not</add> be described by the most able delineator — It is an
                    instance of its <unclear reason="illegible">kind</unclear> of the sublimity of
                    the works of Nature over that of Art and a proof how vain it is in man to aim at
                    equalling the creative powers of the Almighty Architect — It is evidently
                    volcanic — and is a grand proof of the power of that Being who produced such
                    symmetry from confusion — <placeName ref="pl1082">Fingals Cave</placeName> is
                    inimitably grand the roof composed of innumerable <add place="above">five
                        sided</add> prisms of various dimensions — The <pb n="f.17r"/>Pillars of
                    various sizes &amp; in various directions represent on a colossal scale the
                    cristilization of <del unit="words" quantity="1"/> a mountain of Saltpetre —</p>
                <p>In <del unit="words" quantity="1"/> the Cave of <del>called</del> the <placeName ref="pl1089">Cormorants'</placeName>
                    <del unit="words" atLeast="1" atMost="3"/> the young Gent<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>
                    <persName ref="pe1833">Coll Son</persName> — <unclear reason="illegible">M<add place="above">r</add></unclear> Lachlan <persName ref="pe1618">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Lean</persName> &amp; my own Son with several
                    of the Boats crew attempted to beat down with stones from the crevices young
                        <del unit="words" quantity="1"/> Cormorants — and I could not help
                    reflecting at <unclear reason="illegible">this</unclear> instant how vicious
                    &amp; cruel the nature of Man is and how ungovernable without the strongest
                    possible Bridle of Control! — and how despicable it was in so many beings
                    counting themselves rational to assault the lives of these unoffend<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> &amp; unresisting Birds — It was with difficulty I
                    could get them off — &amp; I was glad they had not succeeded in killing any of
                    the Birds.</p>
                <p>There are three Deer on this Island which has a good sward —</p>
                <p>We sail the Boat to take up <persName ref="pe0053">MacQuary of Ulva</persName>
                    the representative of the Antient Branch of the Alpinian Race who took that Name
                    — who hav<hi rend="superscript">g</hi>
                    <del unit="words" quantity="1"/> involved the Family Estate lost it — <del unit="words" quantity="2"/> he now resides in a very small Isle, near
                        <placeName ref="pl0652">Staffa</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl1078">Ulva</placeName> called <placeName ref="pl2441">ICollonsay</placeName>
                    which the part paid Creditors are in the act of wrest<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> from the old man in the 83<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> year of his
                    age — He went with us to I<unclear reason="unclear">c</unclear> Colum Kill this
                        Ev<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> — <add place="inspace">upon ment<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> to him that there was a <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0436">Book</title></bibl> recently published which
                        was intended to prove that <persName ref="pe0557">Ossians</persName> Poems
                        were a forgery by <persName ref="pe0558">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Pherson</persName> he said if there was such a Book it shd be
                        burnt by the <unclear reason="illegible">Common</unclear> Hangman.</add></p>
                <p>29<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi>— Visited <placeName ref="pl2442">Port an Churrich</placeName> where <persName ref="pe0066">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Colum</persName> is s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to have landed f<hi rend="superscript">m.</hi>
                    <placeName ref="pl0889">Ireland</placeName> in a Vessel of about 60 foot long
                    the dimensions of which are s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to be represented <pb n="f.17v"/>by some vestiges of a Building of the exact size that was erected
                    to perpetuate the event — this small Bay is situat<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>
                    at the Southern extremity of the Island —</p>
                <p>We Visited the <placeName ref="pl0975">Nunnery</placeName> — Tombs &amp;
                        <placeName ref="pl0978">Cathedral</placeName> after our return — the Marble
                    altar of which there was a part in the Chapel when I was here about 32 years ago
                    is taken away — the Tombs of the Kings are covered with earth &amp; weeds so as
                    to be totally undistinguishable and upon the whole this celebrated nursery of
                    Religion and the repository of all that was Great &amp; Royal in the Land is now
                    in the most miserable state to which neglect and pollution can bring it —
                    affords an awful example of the insignificance of human grandeur — and at the
                    same time a lamentable instance of the degeneracy of the age in which such
                    shameful prostitution of things sacred &amp; great is tollerated. It w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> have become the Royal Family to have taken care
                    that the apses of their predecessors were undisturbed and, for the sake of
                    influencing the living, it would have been wise to have preserved the reverence
                    &amp; respect for the <unclear reason="illegible">ashes</unclear> of Kings of
                    other times instead of having their Tombs even more neglected than those of the
                    Beggars of the Country — who have some relatives on the spot that pay some
                    attention to their <del unit="words" quantity="1"/> places of rest.</p>
                <p>Returned to <placeName ref="pl0896">Coll</placeName> that Ev<hi rend="superscript">g</hi></p>
                <p>30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Left <placeName ref="pl0896">Col</placeName> for
                        <placeName ref="pl2444">Barra</placeName> — about noon — were all night at
                    Sea — had reached <placeName ref="pl2444">Barra</placeName> on the 31 before
                    dinner after passing an uncomfortable night at Sea &amp; being very sea
                    sick.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.18r"/>
                <placeName ref="pl2444">Barra</placeName> — 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>
                        Aug<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">t</hi></hi> Wrote to
                        <persName ref="pe1620">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald of Valay</persName>
                    <persName ref="pe1619">Lord MacDonald</persName>s Chamberlain in <placeName ref="pl0853">North Uist</placeName> intend<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> my
                    arrival here on my way to visit <persName ref="pe1619">Lord M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donalds</persName> Estate, as one of his
                    Commissioners &amp; desiring <persName ref="pe1620">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald</persName> to meet me at
                        <placeName ref="pl2445">Benbecula</placeName> on the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> instant.</p>
                <p>Wrote a note to <persName ref="pe1622">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                        Gillespie</persName> the Architect employed by <persName ref="pe1619">Lord
                            M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donalds</persName> Commissioners to carry
                    on public Buildings &amp;c in <placeName ref="pl0715">Skye</placeName> to meet
                    me at <placeName ref="pl2446">Lochmaddy</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl0853">North Uist</placeName> w<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>out delay — I wish to
                    have him with me when examin<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> the intended Site of a
                    Village at <placeName ref="pl2446">Lochmaddy</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Wrote a note to my Cousin <persName ref="pe1623">Miss Peggy M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald Clanranald</persName> who resides in
                        <placeName ref="pl0854">South Uist</placeName>, notifying her I w<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> call soon.</p>
                <p><add place="margin"><hi rend="underline">Kelp</hi></add>
                    <persName ref="pe1624">Barra</persName> informs me in answer to questions
                    relative to Kelp — that his has sold at a higher price than that of any other
                    proprietor unless Perhaps the Kelp of <persName ref="pl1078">Ulva</persName>
                    sold about the same price — <hi rend="superscript">G</hi>13 p<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ton — That he ascribes the <choice>
                        <abbr>diff<hi rend="superscript">ce</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>difference</expan>
                    </choice> of quality much to the circumstance of his making but a small quantity
                    compared to <persName ref="pe1619">Lord M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald</persName> &amp; being able to attend to it himself. Next he
                    puts as much in a Kiln as makes about 1½ Ton of Kelp — great care sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be taken to preserve it in as great pieces as
                    possible — he recommends for that reason that no Vessel above 80 Tons burden be
                    employed as the breaking on throwing it into the holds of deep vessels is very
                    injurious to the sales — that he finds small cargoes have always sold better
                    than large because there may be more competitors — &amp; on acc<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> of the breakup being less — Insurance 1½<unclear>£
                            p<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></unclear> from 10/ to 21/ p<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ton — the Earlier the manufacture is begun the
                    better — &amp; also the sooner dispatched — Early in <pb n="f.18v"/>May is the
                    best time to begin &amp; the Vessels sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be engaged
                    in due season to carry it away soon after it is made — Rain injures the Weed —
                    as well as the Kelp — manufacture costs on an average something between.
                        2<unclear reason="illegible">G<hi rend="superscript">s</hi></unclear> &amp;
                        2<unclear reason="illegible">G<hi rend="superscript">s</hi></unclear>½ p<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ton. — he pays 7£ p<hi rend="superscript">
                        ton</hi> for making some in very difficult situations where none at all c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be made but for such encouragement — Sand very
                    injurious to Kelp — He sometimes throws very bad Kelp into the Sea — the
                    Labourers losing their <unclear reason="illegible">fare</unclear> — but oftener
                    returns it <unclear reason="illegible">on their hands</unclear> &amp; they
                        <unclear reason="illegible">fuze</unclear> it over again &amp; clean it
                    —</p>
                <p>The present <placeName ref="pl2447">House of Barra</placeName> is modern &amp;
                    was built by the Laird who now occupys it — the Family resided till this house
                    was built in the <placeName ref="pl2448">old Castle of <unclear reason="illegible">Kiesh</unclear></placeName> on an insulated Rock —
                    era of build<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> not known — The present Laird saw a
                    Genealogical <unclear reason="illegible">Tree</unclear> of the Family about 35
                    years ago which carried the descent back to <persName ref="pe1625">Noah</persName> — It was borrowed by the present <persName ref="pe1615">Clanronalds</persName> Grand father &amp; has never been recovered — it was
                    partly in Galic and partly in English — <placeName ref="pl2449">The Estate of
                            <unclear reason="illegible">Boisdale</unclear></placeName> in <placeName ref="pl0854">South Uist</placeName> belonged to the Family of Barray — a
                    Brother of one of the Lairds murdered the Crew of a Vessel which had been ship
                    wrecked — Gov<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> desired Barray to apprehend him which
                    not chusing to do himself he employed the <unclear reason="illegible">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald of the time</unclear> to seize him On
                    promise of the Lands in question for Seven years: but at the expiration of that
                    period the Lands <pb n="f.19r"/> were withheld by force — are included still in
                        <persName ref="pe1624">Barrays</persName> Charters — but prescription has
                    run in favour of the MacDonalds by possession — M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Niel Brother was apprehended &amp; the tradition is that he was put into
                    a Barrel &amp; thrown over the Rocks of the <placeName ref="pl1031">Castle of
                            Ed<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></placeName> where there is Rock still
                    called M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Niels.</p>
                <p><add place="margin">Barra &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Lean</add>
                    <persName ref="pe1626">Cap<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Scott</persName> hanged
                    a man of the name of M<hi rend="superscript">Lean</hi> considered one of the
                    handsomest men in the <placeName ref="pl0711">Highlands</placeName> at
                        <placeName ref="pl2444">Barra</placeName> without any form of trial — made
                    him stand on a creel &amp; be tied to the roof of the House &amp; the Creel to
                    be then pushed away from under his feet — this was done in the presence of the
                    mother of the person murdered — The man was found dress<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> in the Highland Garb — &amp; had been at the Battle of <placeName ref="pl0155">Culloden</placeName> —</p>
                <p><add place="margin"><persName ref="pe1624">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Niel</persName></add> The same <persName ref="pl0155">Scott</persName> whipped <unclear reason="illegible"><persName ref="pe1834">Lochiels</persName></unclear> Gardner to death in order to oblige him
                    to confess where he &amp; anoth<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> man had hidden the
                    plate.</p>
                <p>This <persName ref="pl0155">Scott</persName> hanged three men on the same
                    occassion without any form of trial <add place="above">because they w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> not give inform<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>
                            ab<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> the <persName ref="pe0559">Prince</persName>
                        <unclear reason="illegible">that they had seen</unclear></add> — He put
                    powder between the toes &amp; fingers of one <persName ref="pe1835">Mac<unclear reason="illegible">Eachan</unclear></persName> for three successive days
                    &amp; blew it up in order to compell him to betray the <persName ref="pe0559">Prince</persName>. He burnt the habitations of the Tenantry in <placeName ref="pl2243"><unclear reason="illegible">Lochaber</unclear></placeName> and
                    particularly <add place="above">did not spare those</add> of the poor.</p>
                <p><add place="margin"><placeName ref="pl2444">Barray</placeName></add>
                    <persName ref="pe1836">Sir Alex<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        MacDonald</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe1838">MacLeod</persName> sent
                        <persName ref="pe1837">MacDonald of Boisdale</persName> Father of the
                        <persName ref="pe1642">Boisdale</persName>
                    <unclear reason="illegible">now</unclear> a Corps to the <persName ref="pe0559">Prince</persName> on his arrival at <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" quantity="1"/> to notify to him that as he had come without the Army which
                    he had promised to bring it w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be impossible to
                    succeed <pb n="f.19v"/>in the attempt to recover the Crown; advised him by all
                    means to return to <placeName ref="pl0925">France</placeName>, and acquainted
                    him <add place="above">that as he had come without Forces</add> they could not
                    engage to join him in such a desperate and hopeless undertaking — The <persName ref="pe0559">Prince</persName> upon hearing this intelligence sailed to
                        <placeName ref="pl2450">Arasaig</placeName>. This is a strong exculpatory
                    circumstance in favour of the above four Gentlemen —</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl2444">Barray</placeName>
                    <lb/>3 Aug<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>
                    <lb/>1800} From <placeName ref="pl2447">Barray House</placeName> is seen an old
                    Building, on a Rock in the Sea connected with a small Island <add place="below">from some weaver supposed to have been interred there</add> called
                        <placeName ref="pl2451">Caistal a mhrebitar</placeName> — supposed to have
                    been some fish <unclear reason="illegible">out-station</unclear> — near this the
                        <persName ref="pe0559">Prince</persName> anchored: and the first British
                    land he set his foot on was the neighbouring <placeName ref="pl2452">Isle of
                        Eiriskay</placeName> belonging to <persName ref="pe1837">Boisdale</persName>
                    <unclear reason="illegible">close</unclear> to the s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Rock on which the Castle is — He slept on a Bed of the tops of
                    Heather at <placeName ref="pl2453">Otirmore</placeName> - the Tenant
                        understand<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> he was a great man but not know<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> whom, made a fire of the heather binding that kept
                    the thatch on his House — and when he shewed the Bed which he had prepared said
                    that is a Bed a Prince might sleep on — not suspect<hi rend="superscript">g</hi>
                    the Prince was the person addressed. It was at this place <persName ref="pe1837">Boisdale</persName>
                    <pb n="f.20r"/> waited on the <persName ref="pe0559">Prince</persName> with the
                    message from <persName ref="pe1836">Sir Alex M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald</persName> and <persName ref="pe1838">MacLeod</persName>.
                        <persName ref="pe1837">Boisdale</persName> never took any part in in 1745
                    —</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe1627">Lady Grange</persName> who was confined in <placeName ref="pl0737">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Kilda</placeName> about the 1745
                    — died at <placeName ref="pl2454">Trumpan</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl0715">Skye</placeName>.</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe1628">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> John M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Lean</persName>
                    <del>of</del>
                    <add place="above">in</add>
                    <placeName ref="pl0950">Troternish</placeName> who was factor for the Family of
                        M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald had the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0647">Aphorisms of Hippocrates</title></bibl> in Galic — into
                    which they had been translated by the <persName ref="pe1691">Ollamh
                        Iilich</persName>, predecessor of the Beatons of <placeName ref="pl0950">Sky</placeName>, who was Physician to <persName ref="pe1839">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald<del rend="overstrike">d</del> of the
                        Isles</persName> — <persName ref="pe1618">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Lachlan M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Lean</persName> at <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" quantity="1"/> is the son of the s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    <persName ref="pe1628">John</persName>.</p>
                <p>4 Aug<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> 1800 — Visited two circles of stones which the
                        <persName ref="pe1689">Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>MacQueen</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe1624">Barray</persName> consider druidical but which are called by
                    the <unclear reason="illegible">Sielgan</unclear> Natives <placeName ref="pl2458"><hi rend="underline">Sornoch Coir</hi> Ein</placeName> — or the
                    supporters of <persName ref="pe0540">Fingals</persName> Caldron — Of one of the
                    Circles only one Stone remains in its place — several others appeared evidently
                    to have been very recently thrown down — the second we visited is intire and the
                    diameter of the Circle is about 12 or 14 foot — There was the appearance of some
                    Building close to them — the stones resembling either the foundation of some
                    ancient building or Stones placed at the head of Graves — <pb n="f.20v"/>Indeed
                    the stones of the circle are so little above ground that they may possibly have
                    been the foundation or part of the Wall of some very ancient Building — of so
                    remote a period that all tradition is lost and the fabulous Idea of them hav<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> here a fire place adopted — the two Circles are
                    within two Gun shots of each other &amp; absurdity of hav<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> Cauldrons large enough to set on such large circles &amp; of having
                    two of them so close together does not strike the Natives.</p>
                <p>The <placeName ref="pe0540">Island of Barra</placeName> &amp; the smaller Islands
                    connected with it contain about 2000 Souls — the people are, without any
                    exception but <persName ref="pe1624">Barray</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe1840">Vatersays</persName> Families, of the Roman Catholic
                    persuasion; &amp; in the deepest ignorance. There was an Effigy of S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Barr in existence during the incumbency of the
                        <persName ref="pe1630">Rev<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> John M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Pherson</persName> who was some time Minister of the Gospel here — It
                    is reputed that he was a man of much humour — that a Country fellow <add place="above">hav<hi rend="superscript">g</hi></add> applied to him for
                    Tobacco the the D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> refused to give him any — but in
                    a jocular manner said if he would castrate S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Barr
                    he would give him a pound of Tobacco — the fellow came several times to ask
                    Tobacco &amp; not finding that he could get any at last brought to the D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> that part of the Statue which he had jocosely
                    demanded and rec<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> his Tobacco — The Saint has since
                    vanished entirely some hav<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> taken one part &amp;
                    some others as precious relicks. He is s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to be in
                    some old Calenders tho' not the Roman one —</p>
                <p>The inhabitants of this Island were Protestants after the reformation — but as
                    there was no clergyman at <pb n="f.21r"/>that time nearer than <placeName ref="pl0954">Harris</placeName> this people were left without spiritual
                    Pastors and upon the establishment of Episcopacy in <placeName ref="pl0889">Ireland</placeName> after the Restoration a number of Priests flocked to
                    the <placeName ref="pl0708">Western Isles</placeName> &amp; owing to the
                    scarcity of Clergymen of the Established Kirk found it the easier to convert the
                    Inhabitants to the Church of <placeName ref="pl1623">Rome</placeName> and this
                    has been so <unclear reason="illegible">efficiently</unclear> done in this
                    Island that there are not 40 Protestants in it and those consist of the two
                    Families <choice>
                        <abbr>ment<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>mentioned</expan>
                    </choice> with Servants brought from other parts who are only temporary
                    residents — the whole as <persName ref="pe1631">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                            M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Queen</persName> the Minister says not
                        exceed<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> 40 — as above ment<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>.</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe1632">Bishop Chisolm</persName> is reputed to be a Bigot in the
                    extreme — and to have made an Instrument of a Priest, <persName ref="pe1841">Allan MacDonald</persName>, son of <persName ref="pe1827"><unclear reason="illegible">Duchamus</unclear></persName>, to pervert the minds
                    of the Inhabitants of this Island who made such demands and shewed such
                    democratic dispositions lately that <persName ref="pe1624">Barray</persName> was
                        oblig<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to banish some of them from the Island by
                    dispossessing about a dozen of the most turbulent <del unit="words" quantity="1"/> &amp; this Priest has also been removed from the Island — &amp; another put
                    in his place of whom better conduct is expected.</p>
                <p>In <placeName ref="pl2444">Barray</placeName> — In the South end of <placeName ref="pl0854">South Uist</placeName> — the <placeName ref="pl0653">Island of
                        Cannay</placeName> — In <placeName ref="pl2459">Orasay</placeName> —
                        <placeName ref="pl2460">Moidart</placeName>
                    <placeName ref="pl2461">Knoidart</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl2243">Lochaber</placeName> there are <sic>from 12 to 12</sic> Roman catholics.
                    —</p>
                <p>This day after our ride <persName ref="pe1624">Barray</persName> informed me that
                    his Gardner who is a Papist but his wife a Protestant was to have his Child
                    christened by the Presbyterian Minister as the Priests had put off the
                    christening about two years on acc<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> of the Father
                        hav<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> married a Heretic, &amp; the <unclear reason="illegible">Parents</unclear> not <pb n="f.21v"/>choosing to leave
                    their Child any longer unchristened — and that the Father wished me to allow my
                    name to be given to the Child — In complement to <persName ref="pe1624">Barray</persName> I of course agreed — The Laird &amp; Lady their Son &amp;
                    Daughter with the <unclear reason="illegible">McNiels Tutor</unclear> &amp; my
                    Son proceeded to the Gardners House with the Parson — When the Name to be given
                    the Child the Father ans<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>
                    <q>Sir John Murray MacGregor</q> — which forced us all to <del unit="words" quantity="1"/>
                    <add place="above">smile.</add> — The Boy was named <q>John MacGregor</q> — his
                    Surname is MacSween —</p>
                <p>In the after noon <persName ref="pe1842">Niel M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Niel</persName>
                    <unclear reason="illegible">residenter at</unclear>
                    <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" quantity="1"/> who was supposed to know
                    some of the Poems of <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian</persName> attended — He is
                    79 years old — was a Soldier with <persName ref="pe1624">Barrays</persName>
                    Father in the war of 1756 — is a brisk old man having before <unclear reason="illegible">dining</unclear> walked 7 miles over bad ground (for
                    there is no Road on the Island) excep<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> a very rough
                    &amp; extremely bad Bridle path — to come to us — and he took leave in the Ev<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> return home but it is supposed he w<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> have remained in some of the Houses at the
                    Village of <placeName ref="pl2462">KilBarr</placeName>. —</p>
                <p>This man repeated an edition of the death of Oscar — which he informed us he had
                    learnt before he went first abroad, when he knew many more of the Poems of
                        <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian</persName> than he now recollects. — Some of
                    the lines are verbatim as in <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0507">Smiths
                            collection</title></bibl> — but the General purport agreed with that
                    part of <persName ref="pe0558">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Phersons</persName>
                    <add place="above">translation of</add>
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0513">Temora</title></bibl> in which
                        <persName ref="pe1638">Oscars</persName> death is ment<hi rend="superscript">d</hi><note type="editorial">The death of Ossian's son, Oscar, is narrated
                        in James Macpherson, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0513">Temora: An
                                Ancient Epic Poem in Eight Books</title></bibl> (London: 1763). In
                        James Smith's versions of the death of Oscar, he is given the name Artho;
                        see <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0648">The Death of Artho and the
                                Death of Fraoch</title></bibl> (Glasgow: 1769) and <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0507">Galic Antiquities: Consisting of a
                                History of the Druids, Particularly of Those of Caledonia; a
                                Dissertation on the Authenticity of the Poems of Ossian; and a
                                Collection of Ancient Poems, Translated from the Galic of Ullin,
                                Ossian, Orran, Etc.</title></bibl> (Edinburgh: 1780).</note> — upon
                    being told that such translations had been made — He <unclear reason="illegible">discovered</unclear> that the had never heard of that circumstance nor even
                    of the name of <persName ref="pe0558">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ja<hi rend="superscript">s MacPherson</hi></persName> tho he had known <pb n="f.22r"/><persName ref="pe1630">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> John
                        MacPherson</persName>
                    <del unit="words" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> when Minister here — "and an
                    excellent man he was. — he had a Son <persName ref="pe1634">John</persName> a
                    Great man" — Being told that there were doubts of the authenticity of <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian</persName> &amp; that the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0569">Poems</title></bibl> were said to have been forged by
                        <persName ref="pe0558">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ja<hi rend="superscript">s</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Pherson</persName> he said — hut hut, ha nel fockel feerin an shin —
                    Shame Shame there is not a word of truth in that — <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian</persName> Mai Ein, the last of the Fions, was the Poet who made
                    them — He ment<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> the names of many of the Warriours
                    of that day — the wife of <persName ref="pe0540">Fingal</persName> was daughter
                    of <persName ref="pe1635">Cormac, Rè Erin</persName> — many old men in the days
                    of my youth could repeat <add place="above">great part of</add> them —
                    particularly <persName ref="pe1844">MacRuory Mhore <add place="above">Morriston</add></persName> who was then very old <del unit="words" quantity="2"/> His Son w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> have been now 70 years
                    if he had lived. — <persName ref="pe1842">Niel</persName> says he heard that
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" quantity="2"/>un (ale) was made of
                    the Tops of the Heather — &amp; that the Ancient Highlanders buried vessels with
                    whey to ferment it into an <add place="below">intoxicat<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> spirit.</add></p>
                <p><persName ref="pe1845">Rory MacNiel of Barray Esq<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName> the <persName ref="pe1689">Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Edmund MacQueen</persName>
                    Minister of the Parish — <persName ref="pe1846">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Taylor</persName> Tutor to <persName ref="pe1624">Barray's</persName> Son —
                        <persName ref="pe1815">Sir John MacGregor Murray</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe1847">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> John Evan John</persName> were
                    present during the time <persName ref="pe1842">Niel Niel</persName> was
                    repeating the Stories &amp; the verses he knew of <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian</persName> — &amp; <persName ref="pe1848">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Niel</persName> also for a
                    considerable part of the time. <persName ref="pe1847">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Evan</persName> was the only person present who could not
                    understand the Galic —</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe1842">Niel MacNiel</persName> mentioned that the M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Niels of whome he gave a long Genealogical <unclear reason="illegible">acc<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></unclear> came from
                        <placeName ref="pl1202">Spain</placeName> — the M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donalds also &amp; Camerons — the Campbells are from <persName ref="pe1636"><unclear reason="illegible">Dermid o'Dhuin</unclear></persName>
                    — that the <unclear reason="illegible">Ailpeinich</unclear> were the first of
                    the Clans — &amp; that they were <pb n="f.22v"/> from <persName ref="pl2428"><unclear reason="illegible">Lochlan</unclear></persName> — from which
                    country he derived the origin of Several other Clans. — The most extraordinary
                    Genealogical anecdote he ment<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> was that <persName ref="pe1637">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Patrick</persName> was married
                    to a daughter of <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian</persName> &amp; that his
                    patronimic was <persName ref="pe1637">Paric mhac Alpin mich Riagh
                        Lochlan</persName>.</p>
                <p>In inumerating the Forces that were in <placeName ref="pl0889">Ireland</placeName> when <persName ref="pe1638">Oscar</persName> was killed
                    he expressly mentioned a Body of 1500 from <placeName ref="pl0705">Albin</placeName>
                    <unclear reason="illegible">pior</unclear> — that <persName ref="pe1638">oscar</persName> killed the 8 nearest relatives of <persName ref="pe1639">Cairbar Riogh</persName> — besides that 120 other relations of that Kings
                    were slain in the action. He mentioned that the Fingalian Family had many places
                    of residence in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> — that <persName ref="pe1640">Cuchullin</persName> rested at <placeName ref="pl2465">Dunskiach</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl0715">Sky</placeName>.</p>
                <p>He &amp; <persName ref="pe1624">Barray</persName> mentioned that a man in Armour,
                    on Horseback, was found, not many years ago, interred in the Isle of <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" quantity="1"/> belonging to <persName ref="pe1624">Barray</persName>: and many articles of Horn <del unit="words" atLeast="1" atMost="3"/>
                    <add place="above">furniture</add>
                </p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl2466">Barray Head</placeName> is the westermost point of
                        <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>. —</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl2444"><hi rend="underline">Barr. <unclear reason="illegible">Iil</unclear></hi></placeName>
                    <lb/>5<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> Aug<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>} Went to the <placeName ref="pl2467">Isle Meal
                        donich</placeName> Which is <persName ref="pe1624">Barrays</persName> Deer
                    Forest to shoot Deer — the Island is high and I had an extensive view of the
                    neighbouring Isles inclosed under the Gen<hi rend="superscript">l</hi> name and
                    forms the property of <persName ref="pe1624">Barray</persName> — each of which
                    has however a distinct name — there are many of them — &amp; of the whole 5
                    Inhabited.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.23r"/>
                Met <persName ref="pe1840">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Neil
                        Vatersay</persName> who is married to a Sister of <persName ref="pe1624">Barrays</persName> &amp; resides on the <persName ref="pl2468">Isle of
                        Vatersay</persName> within 3 miles of <placeName ref="pl2467">Meal
                        donich</placeName> — He &amp; I killed each a Deer. — <del unit="words" quantity="1"/></p>
                <p><persName ref="pe1689">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> MacQueen</persName>
                    mentions <persName ref="pe1849">Ruory Mac Cuian</persName> in <placeName ref="pl2469">Tighary</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl0853">North
                        Uist</placeName> — and <persName ref="pe1850">Donald M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald</persName> in <placeName ref="pl2470">Fromiscary</placeName> — as persons likely to be able to repeat some parts
                    of <persName ref="pe0557">Ossians</persName> Poems.</p>
                <p>6 Aug<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>
                    <placeName ref="pl2444">Barray</placeName> — remained with the Hospitable &amp;
                    kind Friends <persName ref="pe1624">Barra</persName> &amp; his Lady — took down
                    through the medium of the <persName ref="pe1689">Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> MacQueen</persName>
                    <persName ref="pe1842">Niel MacNiels</persName> edition of <persName ref="pe0557">Oscars</persName> death — clearly distinguishing <persName ref="pe0557">Oscar</persName> to have <add place="above">been a</add>
                    Caledonian — though the edition is not pure — yet there is enough of the
                    original design of the poem to satisfy any unbiased person who knows any thing
                    of Galic of the Authenticity of that historical fact as related in the reading,
                    which <persName ref="pe0558">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Pherson</persName> had collected</p>
                <p><pb n="f.23v"/>
                6<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> Aug<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> — <placeName ref="pl2444">Barra</placeName>, after
                    taking leave of <persName ref="pe1848">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi> Neil</persName> &amp; the Children, conveyed
                    us to <placeName ref="pl2471">Kilbride</placeName> — the seat of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    <del unit="words" quantity="1"/>
                    <persName ref="pe1641">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald</persName> of
                        <placeName ref="pl2449">Boisdale</placeName> — for whose funeral <add place="above">to take place to day</add> I waited at <placeName ref="pl2444">Barray</placeName> since last Friday — Here I met <persName ref="pe1642">Col M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald now Boisdale</persName> his B<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi>
                    <persName ref="pe1643">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ronald M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald</persName> advocate <persName ref="pe1620">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> MacDonald</persName> of
                        <placeName ref="pl2472">Valey</placeName> &amp; a number of other Gentlemen
                    who came to attend on this mournful occasion — also <persName ref="pe1852">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Kenzie</persName> Daughter of the late <persName ref="pe1853">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        <unclear reason="unclear">Peter</unclear> MacLean</persName> of <placeName ref="pe1842">Glasgow</placeName> &amp; afterwards of <placeName ref="pl0729">Mull</placeName> with whom I was acquainted before I went to <placeName ref="pl1024">India</placeName> in 1769/70 — also my Cousin <persName ref="pe1623">Miss Peggy MacDonald</persName> Daughter of <persName ref="pe1615">Clanronald</persName> grand aunt of the present Mins<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> —</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl2444">Barray</placeName> — 6 Aug<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> —
                    Infusion of Shalavag or Sorrel with the Bark of the Bramble said to make a light
                    Blue dye — a woman of this Country habited in cloth so dyed —</p>
                <p>Bramble Bark &amp; copperas make Brown — now used on the Main Land.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.24r"/>
                <persName ref="pe1840">Vatersay</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe1624">Barray</persName> informed me that the Skeleton of a Horseman &amp; Horse
                    were found in <placeName ref="pl2468">Vatersay</placeName> about 15-or 16 years
                    ago — That 2 dozen of <hi rend="underline">square</hi> Brass Buttons were found
                    near or with the man the Buttons had red paint or enamel across at right angles
                    — These were sent to <persName ref="pe1641">Boisdale</persName> — The Horseman
                    is supposed to have been an Islander. According to tradition a quarrel arose
                    between a Shipmaster of the name of <persName ref="pe1856">John Allan</persName>
                    &amp; a Brother of the Laird of <placeName ref="pl2444">Barra</placeName> in
                    consequence of their dogs having fought — The owner of the vanquished dog <add place="above">which was killed</add> put his dirk into the dog that killed
                    it —&amp; the Masters came to blows in which the Lairds Brother put the Stranger
                    to death — he was an Irishman — a Brother who was of the party made his escape
                    to the Vessel &amp; came afterwards with an armed party to revenge the murder of
                    his Brother — the Islanders met them and a bloody battle was fought — the result
                    of which is s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to have been that not one of the
                    Irish escaped — The greatest slaughter appears from the number of Graves to have
                    been close to the shore when the Irish were retreating — This action is supposed
                    to have been subsequent to christianity because many <add place="above">glass</add> Beads of diff<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> colours were found
                    where the Horsemans skeleton was discovered by the drifting of the Sand Banks —
                        <add place="above">near another human Skeleton</add> A spear <add place="above">was found — It appears</add> to have been broken in the groin
                    of the man And a small piece of the <add place="above"><unclear reason="illegible">Iron</unclear> point</add> was in the Bone — The
                    staff was near but decayed — the crown of the Helmet was on the Head of the
                    Skeleton — and part of the Armour that fitted the <del unit="words" atLeast="3" atMost="5"/>
                    <add place="above">Haunch still remained — the</add> Helmet &amp; armour was of
                    Brass. — A Silver pin of about Six Inches long with a ring through one end —
                    such as were used to fix the plaids &amp; mantles of old was also found — Dealg
                        Feuntrain<note type="editorial">The second word here had not been
                        identified. One would expect dealg gualainn. Dealg means pin, gualainn means
                        shoulder. (AMC).</note> — But — no armour <add place="above">was</add> found
                    on the Horseman</p>
                <p>A considerable number of Coins were found in the year 1799 at <placeName ref="pl2468">Vatersay</placeName>
                    <add place="above">most of them</add> in a Cows Horn — <persName ref="pe1624">Barray</persName>
                    <pb n="f.24v"/>was given one Six of them — <persName ref="pe1840">Vatersay</persName> saw the Skeletons &amp; other articles above ment<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> — &amp; sent the Coins to <persName ref="pe1624">Barra</persName> when found —</p>
                <p>The Castle in which the Barra Family resided is supposed to have been erected by
                        <persName ref="pe1859">Rory Breachd</persName> in the time of <persName ref="pe1863">James the 4<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi></persName></p>
                <p><persName ref="pe1858">Rory <unclear reason="illegible">Tartar</unclear></persName> (turbulent or noisy) was coeval with <persName ref="pe0533">Ja<hi rend="superscript">s</hi> the 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></persName> it is believed — He committed hostility on some <add place="above">English</add> Vessels; <unclear reason="illegible">of</unclear>
                    <persName ref="pe1091">Queen Elizabeth</persName> in the neighbouring Seas &amp;
                    the Queen remonstrated to the Scotch King in such manner that through the agency
                    of <persName ref="pe1860">Seaforth</persName>
                    <persName ref="pe1858">Barra</persName> was apprehended &amp; carried to
                        <placeName ref="pl0076">Ed<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi></placeName> where it is reputed he was questioned by the
                    King. <del unit="words" atLeast="16" atMost="18"/> for showing hostility to
                        <persName ref="pe1091">Q.E.</persName> to which <persName ref="pe1858">Barray</persName> ans<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> is not that the woman
                    who struck off your mothers Head? — I conceived I was in the discharge of my
                    duty. He escaped with his Life but the Superiority of his Estate is s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to have been granted to <persName ref="pe1860">Seaforth</persName> — the M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald Family now
                    have it. —<note>This is slightly inaccurate. Roderick Mackenzie of Coigeach
                        acquired this superiority in around 1609. He passed it to his son and heir
                        John Mackenzie of Tarbet. They leased this or farmed it out to the
                        MacDonalds of Sleat, the Mackenzies retaining this superiority until at
                        least the nineteenth century. (AMC).</note></p>
                <p><pb n="f.25r"/>
                <placeName ref="pl2471">Kilbride or Boisdale</placeName> 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Aug<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> 1800 — This day the funeral of
                        <persName ref="pe1641">MacDonald of Boisdale Esq<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName> for which I have waited a week, took place — There
                    were between 12 &amp; thirteen hundred persons present including four Companies
                    of Volunteers — The procession by accident I suppose was in the form of a cross
                    — three Companies of Volunteers in front — The great Body of Tenantry or Country
                    people — the Corpse attended by the considerable numbers of Gentlemen Clergy
                    &amp; principal Tacksmen of the neighbouring Islands of <placeName ref="pl2444">Barra</placeName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0853">North Uist</placeName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0653">Canna</placeName> &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>
                        &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>
                    <add place="above">on foot</add> — then <choice>
                        <abbr>foll<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>followed</expan>
                    </choice> a company of Volunteers <persName ref="pe1641">Boisdales</persName>
                    Carriage, Gent<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> on Horse back Servants &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi> and on each side of the Corpse a Body of women
                    projecting to right &amp; left which gave the figure of the cross — at different
                    parts Bodies of Women were found loudly lamenting the deceast — &amp; singing
                    his praises — and it was impossible for any person of feeling, conversant in
                    Galic, not to be deeply affected by their afflictions — at short Intervals there
                    were parties of Volunteers who relieved each other at the palls — which the
                    Gentlemen carried to some distance from the House — &amp; afterwards resumed
                    near the Burying Chapel — Both before the departure from the House &amp; after
                    the internment the people sat down in lines &amp; were served with Bread &amp;
                    Cheese &amp; Whisky — and the Gent<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> under cover —
                    The man who chiefly acted as Gravedigger <persName ref="pe1285">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Lellan</persName> was extremely affected and
                    shed tears most abundantly <add place="above">during</add> the whole time of the
                    interment. He was the only Gravedigger I ever saw so affected — such is the <hi rend="underline">savageness</hi> that is peculiar to the Highlanders — whom
                        <persName ref="pe1563">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Laing</persName>
                    treats as if they had never emerged from Barbarism — <persName ref="pe1285">MacLellan</persName> has feelings that such men know not — after the
                    Interment the Gent<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> repaired to <placeName ref="pl2471">Boisdale House</placeName> to dinner &amp; the Glass was
                    circulated till near Midnight — This is a part of the High<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Custom of the propriety of which I am doubtful — It <pb n="f.25v"/>has certainly for the time the effect of <del rend="overstrike">
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" atLeast="10" atMost="15"/>
                    </del>
                    <add place="above">counteracting</add>
                    <del rend="overstrike">the</del> sorrow — but it is a query whether that is or
                    is not a desirable object — Whether it is not best to allow the soul to be
                    melted — the mind of man to be humbled by leaving him to reflections of a
                    serious &amp; awful cast — or to seek to drive them suddenly away in this manner
                    —</p>
                <p>At Dinner the <persName ref="pe1861">Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Munro</persName> Minister of <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" quantity="1"/> told me that <persName ref="pe1650">Sir James Foulis</persName> had applied to him in a very
                    earnest manner for some part of the Poem of <hi rend="underline">Oithona</hi><note type="editorial">See Macpherson, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0569">Fingal, an ancient epic poem, in six books:
                                together with several other poems, composed by Ossian the son of
                                Fingal</title></bibl>, pp.241-248.</note> of which he supplied him
                    with an edition — that <persName ref="pe1650">Sir James</persName> express<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> obligations but not the least hint of scepticism
                    respecting the authenticity of <persName ref="pe0557">Ossians</persName> poems
                    on the contrary that he appeared to be fully satisfied of their originality — on
                    my ment<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> the recent attack<note type="editorial">A
                        further reference to <persName ref="pe1563">Laing</persName>, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0436">The History of
                            Scotland</title></bibl> (London: 1800).</note> on <persName ref="pe0558">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Pherson</persName> as the forger of the
                    Poems published by him as translations of <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian</persName>
                    <persName ref="pe1861">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Munro</persName> exclaimed
                        <del unit="words" quantity="1"/>
                    <add place="above">chan nel</add> shin <add place="above">ach</add> smerr na
                    breigah — agus bu dāna amfer a rin i san aige <add place="below">ha bhāish
                        —.</add><note type="editorial">Chan eil sin ach smior na brèige agus bu dàna
                        am fear a rinn i: is ann aige a bha fios. (That is nothing but lies to the
                        marrow – how bold the man who composed this – he well knew it).
                        (AMC).</note></p>
                <p>The <persName ref="pe1689">Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" quantity="1"/> Mac Queen</persName>
                    Minister of <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" quantity="1"/> who sat between
                    us coincided with <persName ref="pe1861">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Munros</persName> last observation — Said he had seen in the possession of
                        <persName ref="pe1628">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        <unclear reason="illegible">Jo</unclear> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Lean</persName> in <placeName ref="pl0950">Troternish</placeName>
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0647">the aphorisms of Hippocrates in
                            Galic</title></bibl> transcribed by the <persName ref="pe1690">Ollah
                        Iilich</persName> — Physician to <persName ref="pe1862">Macdonald (of
                        Kintyre)</persName> in the last page of which was written Mīleh Biannachd er
                        <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" quantity="1"/> MacChonicher<note type="editorial">Mìle beannachd air MacConchair (a thousand blessings on mac
                        Conchair). (AMC).</note>
                    <pb n="f.26r"/>bag dhosa an clar so gu scribhat" which Shows that he only copied
                    it — The <persName ref="pe1690">Olla Iilich</persName> is supposed to have lived
                    about 200 years ago — but how long before that <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0647">Aphorisms</title></bibl> had been renderd into Galic must
                    be uncertain — <persName ref="pe1689">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        MacQueen</persName> said that he informed <persName ref="pe1650">Sir James
                        Foulis</persName> of the existence of this Book — and that he imagines
                        <persName ref="pe1650">Sir James</persName> got it f<hi rend="superscript">m.</hi>
                    <persName ref="pe1628">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Lean</persName> as that Gentleman some time afterwards told
                        <persName ref="pe1689">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Queen</persName> that he had Sent the Book to <placeName ref="pl0076">Edin<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></placeName> —</p>
                <p>I have not yet met with any individual <add place="above">x Highlander. Man or
                        woman</add> of The many with whom I have conversed who doubts the
                    authenticity of <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0626">the Poems of
                            Ossian</title></bibl> or who does not consider the scepticism on this
                    head as very absurd.</p>
                <p>The <persName ref="pe1631">Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Allan M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Queen</persName>
                    <add place="above">&amp; several other Gentl<hi rend="superscript">n</hi></add>
                    informed me — that <persName ref="pe0558">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Jas
                            M<hi rend="superscript">Pherson</hi></persName> in the course of his
                    circuit in search of <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0626">the Poems of
                            Ossian</title></bibl> came to <placeName ref="pl2446">Loch
                        maddy</placeName> and travelled from thence across the <add place="above">Moorland part of the</add> Country in order to reach <placeName ref="pl2445">Benbecula</placeName> where <persName ref="pe1864">Macodrum</persName> a celebrated Bard then resided and happening to go into
                    a Shealing to ask for a drink questioned the Landlord if he knew <persName ref="pe1864">Macodrum</persName> to which he ans<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> that he was intimately acquainted with him. — Where is he? — at hand
                    — <del unit="words" atLeast="2" atMost="3"/> — "bhel dad agid fein a Dhuina
                    Choir <lb/>"er na feintibh — Cha nel, <del unit="words" quantity="1"/>
                    <pb n="f.26v"/>agus cha bear leom gun bhitre chuinse <del>j</del>un a chaile na
                    coirichin nach bhurrin ni feitin bhuohe. bhel dad agid ir na feintibh means —
                    "do the Fions owe you any thing" — whereas <persName ref="pe0558">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Pherson</persName> if he had been a better Gallician would have put
                    the question <del unit="words" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> whether the man knew any
                    part of the History of the Fions <del><unclear reason="illegible">or</unclear></del>
                    <add place="above">related in</add> the Poems of <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian</persName> — <persName ref="pe1864">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Odrum</persName> being a <del unit="words" quantity="1"/>
                    <add place="above">man of humour</add> — played upon <persName ref="pe0558">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Phersons</persName> bad Galic; <del rend="overstrike">and</del> answered that the Fions owed him nothing and
                    that he was not sorry for it, as the obligations hav<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> been lost he could not recover any thing — This offended <persName ref="pe0558">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Pherson</persName> so much that
                    he did not converse more with <persName ref="pe1864">Macodrum</persName> — which
                    he afterwards said he regretted and was owing to his not knowing the man he had
                    been conversing with was <persName ref="pe1864">Macodrum</persName> himself —
                        <persName ref="pe0558">MacPherson</persName> is said to have mentioned this
                    Anecdote to <persName ref="pe1867">Sir James Macdonald</persName> at <placeName ref="pl0076">Edin<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></placeName> — This is an
                    important fact and it is generally known in this Country — <placeName ref="pl2473">the Long Island</placeName>, because it establishes that
                        <persName ref="pe0558">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Pherson</persName> was
                    but an indifferent Galic Scholar &amp; spoke it imperfectly when he began to
                    Collect the Poems of <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian</persName>. <persName ref="pe0558">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Pherson</persName> did not go to <placeName ref="pl0854">South
                        Uist</placeName> nor to any of the Islands to the South of <placeName ref="pl0853">North Uist</placeName> — <pb n="f.27r"/><persName ref="pe1631">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Allan MacQueen</persName> heard the
                    preceding circumstance related by <persName ref="pe1864">Macodrum</persName>
                    himself who express<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> his concern that he did not
                    know <persName ref="pe0558">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Phersons</persName> object — and said that if
                    he had not left him suddenly he meant to have notified his name to that
                    Gentleman.</p>
                <p>8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Aug<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> left <placeName ref="pl2471">Boisdale</placeName> and rode about 30 miles along the Western
                    Shore of <placeName ref="pl0854">South Uist</placeName> the greater part of the
                    ride along <del unit="letters" quantity="1"/> extensive sandy desert occasioned
                    by the drifting of the Sands called Shiaban which destroys great tracts of Land
                    — the Estate of <persName ref="pe1641">Boisdale</persName> marches at a short
                    distance from <placeName ref="pl2471">Kilbride</placeName> with that of
                        <persName ref="pe1615">Clanronald</persName> to whom the greatest part of
                        <placeName ref="pl0854">South Uist</placeName> belongs in property — In the
                    course of our Journey we called at the House of <persName ref="pe1674">Captain
                        Macdonald</persName> of <placeName ref="pl2475">Miltoun</placeName> one of
                    the Tacksmen on the Clanronald Estate — At <persName ref="pe1673">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> MacDonald</persName> of <placeName ref="pl2484">Borrishnish</placeName>
                    <unclear reason="illegible">uachdrich</unclear> aged 73, who as well as
                        <persName ref="pe1674">Milton</persName> was of our party from <placeName ref="pl2471">Boisdale</placeName>, — This <persName ref="pe1673">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl2484">Borrinish</placeName> is the Heriditary Baillie or
                    Chamberlain of the Family of Clan ronald and possesses a small Estate which
                    derived to him from his ancestors as such. It is said he makes about 40 Tons of
                    Kelp annualy on his property which may be estimated at £200 exclusive of his
                    Land Rent. — We afterwards called on the <persName ref="pe1861">Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Munro</persName> Minister of <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" quantity="1"/>
                    <add place="below">His wife was a Grand daughter of Ronald <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" quantity="14"/> the natural brother of
                        my Grand fathers.</add>
                    <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" quantity="1"/> who promised to look out for
                    the Letters he had received from <persName ref="pe1650">Sir James
                        Foulis</persName> relative to Oithona as ment<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>
                    to me at <placeName ref="pl2471">Boisdale</placeName> —</p>
                <p>About 12 miles from <placeName ref="pl2471">Kilbride</placeName>, <persName ref="pe1642">Boisdales</persName> seat, we passed on the right the ruins of
                    a Seat of the Clanronald Family which is s<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to have
                    been <pb n="f.27v"/> built in the year 1700 — and the Gentlemen of the Country
                    all agree that this situation <placeName ref="pl2476">Armadale</placeName> is
                    the best for the Family Residence. — <del unit="letters" atLeast="4" atMost="5"/>
                    <persName ref="pe1623">Miss Peggy</persName> resides here —</p>
                <p>In the Evening we reached <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" quantity="1"/>
                    <persName ref="pe1868">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Nicolsons</persName> a
                    Tacksman of <persName ref="pe1615">Clanronalds</persName> who has lately
                    purchased some part of the Estate of MacLeod in <placeName ref="pl0715">Skye</placeName> — He was from home but we were hospitably entertained by
                        <persName ref="pe1855">Miss Martin</persName> and two Daughters of <persName ref="pe1868">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName> Nicolsons — our party
                    thus far consisted of <list>
                        <item><persName ref="pe1624">MacNiel of Barray</persName> — who took the
                            trouble to accompany me thus far</item>
                        <item><persName ref="pe1869">Cap<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> James
                                Macdonald</persName> a brother of the <persName ref="pe1641">Boisdale</persName> recently deceased — who also came <lb/>in
                            complement to <unclear reason="illegible">M</unclear>
                            <lb/>— <persName ref="pe1870">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald Griminish</persName> — <persName ref="pe1871">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>Donald
                                Balranald</persName></item>
                        <item><persName ref="pe1872">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>MacDonald</persName></item>
                        <item>The <persName ref="pe1631">Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Allan M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Queen</persName></item>
                        <item><persName ref="pe1873">the Rev<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Nicolson</persName> Missionary
                            Minister</item>
                    </list> Besides <persName ref="pe1674">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald Milton</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe1874">Borrinish</persName> there were two Romish Priests a <persName ref="pe1875">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Each<add place="below">an</add></persName> &amp; a <persName ref="pe1876">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald</persName> of the party <del unit="words" quantity="1"/> in
                    the morning &amp; <persName ref="pe1875">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        MacEachan</persName> was so obliging as to guide us through the strand
                    between <placeName ref="pl0854">South Uist</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl2445">Benbecula</placeName> the Island on which <persName ref="pe1877">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Nicolson</persName> resides. He
                    also got an old man named <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" atLeast="1"/> and
                    sent directions to the Son of <persName ref="pe1882">the Bard Mac
                        bhurish</persName> to attend at <persName ref="pe1877">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Nicolsons</persName> — in order that we might
                    converse with them on the subject of the Poems of <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian</persName>.</p>
                <p>––––– <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" quantity="1"/> came and entertained us
                    with three or four pieces of Ancient Poetry <unclear reason="illegible">One</unclear> of which had not been heard <add place="above">before</add>
                    by any of the Gentlemen present — M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" quantity="4"/>
                    <pb n="f.28r"/>
                    <persName ref="pe1877">Nicolson</persName> has promised to take down two of
                    these poems for me —</p>
                <p>9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                    <persName ref="pe1880">Lauchlan M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>bhurish</persName>
                    the son of the <persName ref="pe1882">Bard of that name</persName> waited on us
                    this morning and appears to be but a <del unit="words" quantity="1"/>
                    <add place="above"><del><unclear reason="illegible">poor</unclear></del>
                        inadequate</add> representative of his ancestors — being totally illiterate
                    — He complained that the Farm which his Family had <unclear reason="illegible">enjoyed</unclear> from Clanronald for ages had been wrested from his Father
                    unjustly and ascribed to that circumstance his Fathers hav<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> relinquished all attention to the profession of his Ancestors who
                    had been Bards for many Generations — There were none he said who enquired for
                    Poetic or Historick productions nor who encouraged any person to devote
                    attention to them and of course they had gone into disuse — he illustrated this
                    by saying he w<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> not put a hand to the Kelp if he
                    was not paid for it — He had a perfect recollection of his Father having had
                    various manuscripts and Galic Letter used in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl0889">Ireland</placeName>
                    <add place="above">particularly the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0646">Lheabher Dearg or red Book</title></bibl></add><note type="editorial">The so-called 'Red Book' of Clanranald, a Gaelic manuscript
                        dating to the seventeenth century, was obtained by James Macpherson while
                        searching for sources of Ossianic poetry in 1760. It is now in the
                        collections of the National Museums of Scotland.</note> and a declaration
                    respecting his recollection of them was taken down by the <persName ref="pe1631">Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Allan
                        MacQueen</persName> Minister of <placeName ref="pl0853">North
                        Uist</placeName> which was repeatedly read as it was taken down and it was
                    afterwards read <add place="above">by him</add> to him in presence of several
                    Gentlemen when he was desired to correct any expression he might think required
                    it — but he repeatedly <add place="below">said</add> that there was not any room
                    for alteration that the whole was correct &amp; he <add place="below">put his
                        mark to it</add>
                    <persName ref="pe1631">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Queen</persName> is to make a fair copy to be signed by <persName ref="pe1624">Barray</persName> as a Justice of Peace —<note type="editorial">The witnessed declaration of Lachlan MacMhuirich is given in Gaelic and
                        English in Henry Mackenzie, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0662">Report of the Committee of the Highland Society of Scotland,
                                Appointed to Inquire into the Nature and Authenticity of the Poems
                                of Ossian</title></bibl> (Edinburgh: 1805), pp.275-79.</note>
                    <persName ref="pe1882">Macbhurish</persName> being informed that doubts were
                    entertained of the authenticity of <persName ref="pe0557">Ossians</persName>
                    <pb n="f.28v"/>Poems which were said to have been composed by <persName ref="pe0558">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> James M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Pherson</persName>, exclaimed that these Poems were known for
                    ages before he was born — and treated the doubts with derision —</p>
                <p>This man <del unit="words" atLeast="1" atMost="3"/> said he had intended to have
                    applied to Bardichd if his Father had not when he was young been discouraged by
                    the deprivation of the hereditary <unclear reason="illegible">servant</unclear>
                    — that he did not receive any education — and knew scarcely any poems whatever —
                    he however repeated the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0660">Brosnichih
                            cabh macconil</title></bibl> — the war Spear of the MacDonalds which is
                    a poem of great merit. This man and most whom I conversed with on <placeName ref="pl2444">Barray</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl0854">South
                        Uist</placeName> made <placeName ref="pl0889">Ireland</placeName> the
                    Country of the Fions — except<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> one Man who made
                        <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> their Country — <persName ref="pe1624">Barray</persName> suggested that these Ideas had probably been
                    circulated by the Legion of Priests who came over to those Southern Isles fr<hi rend="superscript">m —</hi>
                    <placeName ref="pl0889">Ireland</placeName> after the restoration as before
                        ment<hi rend="superscript">d —</hi> — Their Skealichds<note type="editorial">Sgeulachdan (tales). (AMC).</note>
                    <add place="above">or Tales</add> are fabulous &amp; extravagant and totally
                    different from the Poems they themselves repeat — &amp; this renders <persName ref="pe1624">Barray</persName> Idea, which occured to myself also, the more
                    probable —</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe1880">Macbhurich</persName> told me that his Father held it as
                    his belief that the Fions were coeval with <persName ref="pe0236">Jesus
                        Christ</persName> — bha m'Air de anibh amach gun rubh Chrïst ir tallabh an
                    am na feinlibh" —</p>
                <p><pb n="f.29r"/>
                In one of the Poems rehearsed by <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/>
                    <persName ref="pe1637">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Patrick</persName> was
                    styled <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" quantity="1"/>ic Alpin —
                    corresponding to the relation of <persName ref="pe1842">Niel M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Niel</persName> in <placeName ref="pl2444">Barray</placeName> —</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe1852">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Kenzie</persName> shewed me at <placeName ref="pl2471">Boisdale</placeName> an old Book which She said was about 100 years old in
                    the nature as it appeared to me of a sort of common place Book in which the
                    owners occasionally inserted whatever stikes their fancy — Some of it was in the
                    Galic character and some in the Roman. — It contained a variety of <add place="above">Galic</add> poems — and amongst others parts of the Poems of
                        <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian</persName> — particularly the advice of
                        <persName ref="pe0540">Fingal</persName> to his Grandson <persName ref="pe1638">Oscar</persName>, of which &amp; some other Extracts from <add place="above"><unclear reason="illegible">that</unclear> Book</add> She had
                    begun to prepare a copy for me — but though it was not finished <persName ref="pe1624">Barray</persName> took from her the paragraph end<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> the above advice which is expressive of the
                    noblest Sentiments that could enrich and exalt the human Mind &amp; I find to be
                        <del unit="words" quantity="1"/>
                    <add place="below">closely</add> translated by <persName ref="pe0558">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Pherson</persName><note type="editorial">See
                        Macpherson, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0569">Fingal</title></bibl>, Book III.</note> — This single circumstance is
                    enough to establish the authenticity of the Poems <del><unclear reason="illegible">because it expresses</unclear></del> If the sublimity
                    of the mind of <del><unclear reason="illegible"><persName ref="pe0557">Ossian</persName> and of his Father</unclear></del>
                    <persName ref="pe0540">Fingal</persName> be estab<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>
                    in this important instance it will carry a conviction of the characters
                    represented by <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian</persName> hav<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> been those of real Life — at whatever era these
                    Heroes lived. — <unclear reason="unclear">Mhic in bhish jica</unclear> —</p>
                <p><pb n="f.29v"/>
                9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> — proceeded towards <placeName ref="pl0853">North
                        Uist</placeName> — passed <placeName ref="pl2632">Balnan calich (Nun
                        Town)</placeName> the present Seat of the Family of Clanronald consisting of
                    modern Houses of indifferent appearance — The <unclear reason="illegible">Factor</unclear> resides here and has the Surround<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> Lands in Farm — his crop of Barley very extensive and of excellent
                    appearance — Indeed it is surprising how good the crops in these sandy districts
                    are — both of Barley &amp; Potatoes — as also of Rye <persName ref="pe1884">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Brown</persName> was just recovering from a
                    putrid fever which prevented our going in — Here my Friend <persName ref="pe1624">Barra</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe1869">Cap<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> James MacDonald</persName> B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> to <persName ref="pe1641">Boisdale</persName> who
                    escorted me thus far took leave — and I continued my Journey attend<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> by <persName ref="pe1871">Balranald</persName>
                        &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c—</hi> near <placeName ref="pl2632">Nun
                        Town</placeName> we passed <add place="above">the ruin of</add> an old
                    Castle in an Island — further to the Eastward <placeName ref="pl2633">Balbhanich
                        (Monk town)</placeName> — The burying ground of the Family of Clanronald is
                    close to the present House — a very <del rend="overstrike">
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/>
                    </del>
                    <unclear reason="illegible">small</unclear> building without a Roof —</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe1873">The Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Alex<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Nicolson</persName> pointed out an old burying ground which had been brought
                    to view recently by the Shieban or Sand drifts hav<hi rend="superscript">g</hi>
                    carried off a mound of Sand that had covered it time out of mind — small square
                    stone inclosures of the nature of Graves but of less dimensions were discovered
                    in it — There were also traces of Houses in several parts of this days ride laid
                    open by the Shieban — The opinion in this Country is that <pb n="f.30r"/> a
                    Country had extended from these Islands to a great extent westward.<note type="editorial">There is a township on a low lying island (still occupied)
                        at the western extremity of north Uist called Baile Shear (the eastern
                        township). The presumption is that there was a western township that
                        disappeared due to erosion. (AMC).</note></p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl2445">Benbecula</placeName> — this is the Island in which
                        <persName ref="pe0558">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> James M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Pherson</persName> met <persName ref="pe1864">Macodrum</persName> the Bard when the anecdote before ment<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> occurred — This was the seat of the second B<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> of Clanronald who succeeded to the Estate about
                    the 1740 — <placeName ref="pl2635">Bhein bheul</placeName> is the name of a
                    Mountain on this Island from which it is suppos<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> the
                    Word <placeName ref="pe0558">Benbecula</placeName> had its rise —</p>
                <p>The strands that intervene between <placeName ref="pe0558">Benbecula</placeName>
                    on the East separate it <del rend="overstrike">at high water</del>
                    <add place="above">when the Tide is in</add> from <placeName ref="pl0853">North
                        Uist</placeName> — We passed them at ebb — these are of great extent and
                    imbricated with various Small Isles evidently the remains of Lands which existed
                    before the Sea made its way through them to east &amp; west — The first part of
                        <persName ref="pe1619">Lord M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donalds</persName>
                    Estate we reached in <placeName ref="pl0853">North Uist</placeName> is annexed
                        <add place="above">in lease</add> to <placeName ref="pl2485">the Isle of
                        Barneray</placeName> at the other extremity of <placeName ref="pl0853">North
                        Uist</placeName> —</p>
                <p>Saw many Kelpers <del rend="overstrike">
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/>
                    </del> burning the ware in troughs of loose Stone about 6 feet by 2.— <del unit="letters" atLeast="2" atMost="3"/>
                    <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" quantity="1"/>
                    <persName ref="pe1871">Balranald</persName> informed me that the Kelp <add place="above">making</add> Season expires on the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> of Aug<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> old Style — ' ' about the 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> new — that the ware that is thrown ashore after
                    that season is used for manure — thinks Sandrift <pb n="f.30v"/>might be greatly
                    checked by laying on such ware after levelling the <add place="above">sand</add>
                    Banks — We saw in <placeName ref="pl0854">South Uist</placeName> great sheets of
                    Sands from which the high Banks had been blown away beginning to recover verdure
                    chiefly bent — &amp; a sort of Creeper which last I was told if not cut up by
                    the Cattle would soon bind the Sand — <persName ref="pe1871">Balranald</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe1631">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Allan M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Queen</persName> agreed in
                    thinking that Bent often occasions the formation of new sand banks by the
                    interruption it gives to the Sheaban &amp; collecting little banks which soon
                    gather more sand &amp; become great Banks — <persName ref="pe1871">Balranald</persName> stated that he is of opinion sandrift w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be more checked if the Tenantry were encouraged to
                    labour the Sand &amp; Level the Banks — but that poor men could not afford to
                    risk the labour &amp; their Seed and Manure in the event of an unsuccessful
                    attempt which might happen occasionally.</p>
                <gap reason="authorial" unit="lines" quantity="several"/>
                <p><pb n="f.31r"/>
                Genealogy of the Family of MacDonald of the Isles taken down at <placeName ref="pl2638">Balronald</placeName>
                    <add place="above">in <placeName ref="pl0853">North Uist</placeName></add> the
                        10<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> of Aug<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> 1800
                    from the diction of <persName ref="pe1675">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Hūstain M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald</persName> Tacksman of
                        <placeName ref="pl2639">Kilphedre</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl0854">South Uist</placeName> — <del rend="overstrike">
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" atLeast="2" atMost="4"/>
                    </del>
                    <list>
                        <item>1 Alister mhac Alister</item>
                        <item>2 <gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="7"/> bhic
                            Alister</item>
                        <item>3 <gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="7"/> bhic
                            Shemis</item>
                        <item>4 <gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="7"/> mhic Dhail
                                <del rend="overstrike"><unclear reason="illegible">bhriochd</unclear></del> Bhriochd</item>
                        <item>5 <gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="7"/> bhic
                            Shemis</item>
                        <item>6 <gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="7"/> mhic Dhoil
                            Ghuirm oig</item>
                        <item>7 <gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="7"/> mhic
                            Gillespie</item>
                        <item>8 <gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="7"/> bhic Dhoil
                            Ghuirm Shasnich</item>
                        <item>9 <gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="7"/> mhic Dhoil
                            Ghuirm</item>
                        <item>10 <gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="7"/> bhic Dhoil
                            Gruomich</item>
                        <item>11 <gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="7"/> bhi Dhoil
                                G<unclear reason="illegible">h</unclear>allich</item>
                        <item>12 <gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="7"/> Mhi
                                Alistair<hi rend="superscript">x</hi><note type="authorial"><hi rend="superscript">x The first who got the Estate of <placeName ref="pl0667">Duntuilm</placeName></hi></note> — of
                                <placeName ref="pl0655">Slate</placeName></item>
                        <item><gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="7"/> Mhic Alister
                                <note type="authorial">his eldest Son John lost the Earldom of Ross
                                had no Male issue. </note></item>
                        <item><gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="7"/> bhic<hi rend="superscript">xx</hi><note type="authorial"><hi rend="superscript">xx</hi> first Earl of Ross — who fought the
                                Battle of <placeName ref="pl2486">Harlaw</placeName> S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> James's day 1411 this not from Harlaw
                                16 March <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" atLeast="4" atMost="6"/> taken from <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0397">the Peerage</title></bibl> what is here
                                enclosed</note> Dhoil — Brother of Rhoial the first of the family of
                            Clanronald</item>
                        <item><gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="7"/> Mhic Eoin</item>
                        <item><gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="7"/> Mhic Innish
                            oig</item>
                        <item><gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="7"/> Mhic Innish
                            Mhore</item>
                        <item><gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="7"/> Mhic
                            Alister</item>
                        <pb n="f.31v"/>
                        <item><gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="7"/> Mhic shean Innis
                                <del rend="overstrike">
                                <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" atLeast="6" atMost="9"/>
                            </del>
                            <add place="above">hanic</add> Tenglich Mhic Iean <del rend="overstrike">
                                <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" atLeast="8" atMost="10"/>
                            </del>
                            <add place="above">in</add> ardnamurchan agus Glencoah bho Iean mhic
                            Shean Innis — </item>
                        <item><gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="7"/> Mhic Dhoil </item>
                        <item><gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="7"/> Mhic Ra<gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" quantity="1"/>il</item>
                        <item><gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="7"/> Mhic
                            Shoirlih</item>
                        <item><gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="7"/> Mhi
                            Gillibrideh</item>
                        <item><gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="7"/> Mhic
                                Gillo<unclear reason="illegible">enan</unclear></item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>*<note type="authorial">The Estate remained with the principal Family<add place="below">recently.</add> — they Signed Clan Rhonil like
                        MacRonald.</note>Shelistan — which he says sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>
                    be Gillespie in Galic — was a natural son of Alister mhic Dhoil — he was Brother
                    of Alistair of Slate and of John who lost the Earldom of Ross — cha ro ê <add place="above">(John)</add> strïcha ro Ri er bih — ach cur suos ri Riogh nan
                    Sassnich — agus nuor chunic a Bhrair Alistair Shid ghabh e fein coirichen bon
                    Riogh. — bha aid graid gumn bi Riogh Hessen a mhil gnoich Eoin.<note type="editorial">Cha robh e [John] striochdadh ro Rìgh air bi ach cuir suas
                        ri Rìgh nan Sasannach. Agus nuaira chunnaic (?) a bhràthair, Alasdair, siud
                        ghabh e fhèin còraichean bhon rìgh. Bha iad gradha gum by rìgh esan a mhill
                        gnothaich Eoin. (He [John] bowed to no king but put up with the English
                        king. But when his brother, Alasdair saw that he himself assumed the right
                        of kingship. They said that he was the king that spoiled things for John).
                        (AMC).</note></p>
                <p>One of the Family of Glengary was married to a Daughter of Shelistan and asserted
                    that, in her right, they had a <del unit="words" quantity="1"/>
                    <add place="above">claim</add> to the Earldom of Ross alleging that Shellistan
                        Sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> succeed his B<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                    John — Whereas Shellistan was a natural son &amp; the</p>
                <p><pb n="f.32r"/>
                Genealogy of the Family of Clanronald taken down 10<hi rend="superscript">th—</hi> Aug<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> 1800 from the diction of the said
                        <persName ref="pe1675">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        <unclear reason="illegible">Hustain</unclear> MacDonald</persName>
                    <list>
                        <item><del rend="overstrike">
                                <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" atLeast="4" atMost="6"/>
                            </del> Rhaoil</item>
                        <item>Mhac Ian</item>
                        <item>Mhic Rhaoil</item>
                        <item>bhic</item>
                        <item>Mhic Dhoil</item>
                        <item>Mhic Rhaoil oig</item>
                        <item>Mhic Rhaoil mhore</item>
                        <item>Mhic Allain</item>
                        <item>Mhi Ian Mhadairtich</item>
                        <item>Mhic Alister</item>
                        <item>Mhic Allain</item>
                        <item>Mhic Ruory</item>
                        <item><add place="margin">mhac bhic Alister <lb/>patronimic of the
                                <lb/>Glengary Family</add>Mhic Allain — His Brother Dhoil the
                            <lb/>first of Ten<unclear reason="illegible">list</unclear> mhac <add place="above">bhic</add> alaster <lb/>or Glengary who got that
                            Estate <lb/>second Son of Rhaoil M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Eoin</item>
                        <item>Mhic Rhaoil</item>
                        <item>Mhic Eoin — Father also of <lb/>Dhoil who carried <lb/>on the Line of
                            the <lb/>Principal Family</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>The Estate of Clanronald was given to Rhail as or second Brother the Principal
                        <pb n="f.32v"/>Family then residing in the Southern Isles of <placeName ref="pl0717">Isla</placeName> &amp;<hi rend="superscript">ca.</hi></p>
                <p>Donald Roy mhac Rhaoil bhic Sir Shemis told the said <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> that he was informed by William Mhac
                    Sir Formaid (M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Leod that hav<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> observed an inscription on a Stone at <placeName ref="pl2487">R<del rend="overstrike"><gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/>i</del><unclear reason="illegible">o</unclear>dil</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl0954">Harr<unclear reason="illegible">ie</unclear>s</placeName> bearing the name of Ruory
                    mhore MacLeod (Father of Sir Normand) and <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> MacRanald his Wife — asked W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> the reason — he ans<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>
                    <add place="above">by asking if they did not know</add> that the Lady was his
                    Grandmother — they replied that they did not know the<del rend="overstrike">y</del> reason of <hi rend="underline">MacRonald</hi> being on the
                    Inscription — W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> ans<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> do
                    you not know that Teulich Mhac bhic Alister<note type="editorial">Teaghlach mac
                        mhic Alasdair (the family of mac mhic Alasdair). (AMC).</note> is from that
                    of Clanronald (mhac bhic Allain) — they replied that they knew this but did not
                    know that they called them selves — or signed — MacRanald — W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> ans<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> that they wrote
                    MacRonald at the time of the decease of that Lady but <pb n="f.33r"/>had lately
                    discontinued it — W<hi rend="superscript">m.</hi> added that he did not consider
                    the disuse of M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Ronald judicious or wise — and asked
                    the reason for that opinion — said that if they had continued to call themselves
                        M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Ranald they would have been the Chieftains of
                    their own Name or Branch whereas they w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> cease to
                    have that <del rend="overstrike"><unclear reason="illegible">marked</unclear></del> distinction <del rend="overstrike">by</del>
                    <add place="above">and</add>
                    <del rend="overstrike"><unclear reason="illegible">the adoption of Mac Donald or
                            MacD</unclear><gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" atLeast="4" atMost="6"/></del> — to thereafter only <del rend="overstrike"><unclear reason="illegible">as for</unclear>
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" quantity="11"/></del> one of the Name
                    nac roh ard uishl ach fer don Chinneah<note type="editorial">nach robh na àrd
                        uaisle ach fear don chinneadh (that wasn’t a high noble but [simply] one of
                        the clan [Macdonald]). (AMC).</note> —</p>
                <p>11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> — Visited the farms southward between <placeName ref="pl2638">Balronald</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl1632">Carinish</placeName> — see separate notes.</p>
                <p>Aug<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> 13 left <persName ref="pe1871">Balronalds</persName> &amp; went two miles to the northward to <persName ref="pe1631">the Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> allan M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Queens</persName> at
                        <placeName ref="pl2469">Tighary</placeName> — called on his Sister <persName ref="pe1886">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Lean</persName> of <placeName ref="pl2640"><unclear reason="illegible">Heiskier</unclear></placeName> at <placeName ref="pl2641">Peinmore</placeName> in our way to his House — saw her Daughter
                    &amp; youngest Son — descended f<hi rend="superscript">m—</hi>
                    <unclear reason="illegible">Roinal</unclear> Mhache Sir Shemus<note type="editorial">Raghnall mac mhic Sheumais. (AMC).</note></p>
                <p><persName ref="pe1631">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Queen</persName> is B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> of <persName ref="pe1689">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ed. M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Queen</persName> Min<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> of <placeName ref="pl2444">Barra</placeName> who has <add place="above"><unclear reason="illegible">am<hi rend="superscript">g</hi>
                        others</unclear></add> followed me to this place in order to take down Galic
                    Poems &amp;<hi rend="superscript">ca</hi></p>
                <p><pb n="f.33v"/>
                In the Church yard of <placeName ref="pl2642">Kill mhoirah (Kilmuir)</placeName>
                    in <placeName ref="pl0853">North Uist</placeName> is the Tomb Stone of <persName ref="pe1889">Ronald MacDonald</persName> who was a natural Son of <persName ref="pe1867">Sir James M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald</persName> of
                        <placeName ref="pl0655">Slate</placeName>, my Great Grandfather, &amp; this
                    Ronald was of course my Grand uncle — B<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> to
                        <persName ref="pe1890">John of <unclear reason="illegible">Balcory</unclear></persName> my Grandfather — I do not recollect to have
                    every heard before of this Ronald — He is said to have been long abroad — in the
                    Dutch Service — at <placeName ref="pl2488">Battavia</placeName> &amp; <del rend="overstrike">
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" atLeast="9" atMost="12"/>
                    </del> in <placeName ref="pl1473">Turkey</placeName> after he settled at home he
                    was stiled of <unclear reason="illegible">Ballisheare</unclear> — he had made
                        <del rend="overstrike">a</del> considerable fortunes several times — whilst
                    abroad — but either lost or spent them — He married four times — his 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Wife was <persName ref="pe1891">Barbara M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Pherson</persName> Grand Aunt of <persName ref="pe1634">Sir John M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Pherson</persName> by
                    whom he had 5 Sons<hi rend="superscript">#</hi><note type="authorial"># Hugh —
                        Donald Roy. Donald Gorm who was in the Prussian Service &amp; noticed by
                        Marshal Keith. uncertain whether he left any Family. Gillespie
                        Ronald.</note> &amp; 3 daughters — <list>
                        <item>2. Wife a Daughter of Barra</item>
                        <item>3. Wife a Daughter of Ronald Mhic Allain<note type="editorial">Raghnall mac mhic Ailein. (AMC).</note> MacDonald of the Clanronald
                            Family —</item>
                        <item>4. a Daughter of Angus Mhache Roanil<note type="editorial">Aonghas Mac
                                Raghnaill. (AMC).</note> a Gentleman of <placeName ref="pl0655">Slate</placeName> by whom he had one son John whom I remember — he
                            could not sleep alone in a room — heard noises of hammering — &amp;
                            often told me he would be drowned — which actually happened several
                            years afterwards — when I was in <placeName ref="pl1024">India</placeName> — </item>
                    </list> of Ronalds Sons I did not get any account. <pb n="f.34r"/>His Daughters
                    were married — <list>
                        <item>1 to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Arch<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>
                                M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Lean of Heiskir of whom M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Lean (M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Queens
                            Sisters) Children are descended</item>
                        <item>1 to Donald Campbell of Scalpay in Harries</item>
                        <item>1 to Alex<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> MacDonald Heisker first and
                                2<hi rend="superscript">dly</hi> to Lachlan MacDonald of Dreemisdale
                            in Southuist.</item>
                    </list> Ronald died on the 13 august 1742 — (before I was born) — aged 87. — His
                    first wife was buried twenty two years before him in the same Tomb — 16 Nov 1720
                    —</p>
                <p>12<hi rend="superscript">th—</hi> remained at <placeName ref="pl2638">Balranald</placeName> till late in the afternoon — &amp; then <del rend="overstrike">
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/>
                    </del> Went to <placeName ref="pl2469">Tighare</placeName>
                    <persName ref="pe1631">the Rev<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Allan MacQueens</persName> — to dinner &amp;
                    stay the night employed in endeavouring to collect some of <persName ref="pe0557">Ossians</persName> poems — and in seeing <persName ref="pe1675">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        <unclear reason="illegible">Hustain</unclear> MacDonald</persName> of
                        <placeName ref="pl2471">Kilbride in South Uist</placeName> dictate his
                    declaration relative to <persName ref="pe0557">Ossians</persName> Poems taken
                    down in Galic —<note type="editorial">Hugh Macdonald's testimony is reproduced
                        in Gaelic and English in Mackenzie's <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0662">Report</title></bibl> pp.38-51. </note></p>
                <p>13 left <placeName ref="pl2469">Tighare</placeName> late in the afternoon —
                    called at <placeName ref="pl2645">Hosta</placeName> on <persName ref="pe1886">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Lean</persName> Sister of <persName ref="pe1631"><add place="above">the Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></add> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Queen</persName> saw in <placeName ref="pl2646">Lochscorpaig</placeName>, a pendicle of the farm of <placeName ref="pl2647">Greeminish</placeName>, the remains of a Dun in which there had
                    been a building — Here <persName ref="pe1897">Raonil mhache Dhonil
                        Herrich</persName> was strangled — through the <pb n="f.34v"/>influence of
                    some of his Relations — His son fled to <placeName ref="pl0889">Ireland</placeName> or was sent thither when young — When arrived at
                    Manhood he returned to revenge his Fathers Murder — The man who strangled him
                    was named Paul — &amp; had the Nick name of Paul na feiligh — from the Leathern
                    thing with which he put Raonil to death — the Son walked so like his Father that
                    Paul knew he must be the Son — &amp; made off to take sanctuary at <placeName ref="pl2642">Kill Mhoira</placeName> — but <persName ref="pe1897">Raonil</persName> Son shot him in the Heel with an arm which brought him
                    down &amp; he was then put to death — the spot is still called <placeName ref="pl2648">Lead Phail</placeName> — the breadth of Paul. —</p>
                <gap reason="authorial" unit="lines" quantity="several"/>
                <p><pb n="f.35r"/>
                Names of Sons of the Family of MacDonald — taken down from M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    <persName ref="pe1675"><unclear reason="illegible">Hustain</unclear> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald</persName> 13 Aug<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> 1800 <list>
                        <item>Ian : no sons.</item>
                        <item>Hūstain 12 — Donal Gallich — born in Gallen} had children</item>
                        <item>Donil Herrick —</item>
                        <item>Gillespie — s b'donnah a} no children</item>
                        <item>Aonnis —</item>
                        <item>Doil <unclear reason="illegible">Gallash</unclear>
                            <lb/>11. Dòil Gruomach</item>
                        <item>Alister.</item>
                        <item>Doil Gruomich <lb/>10. Doil Gorm killed at Ellan Donnan in Seaforths
                                Lands<note type="editorial">Dòmhnall Gorm MacDonald of Sleat killed
                                with an arrow through the thigh which burst an artery while
                                besieging Eilean Donan castle, c.1540. He was carried away but must
                                have bled to death. (AMC).</note></item>
                        <item>Shemis — <lb/>Gillespie} had children <lb/>Killed in Slate <del>by
                                Clan <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/></del></item>
                        <item>Ian — killed when young in Slate by clan ronal — Hustain son of
                            Gillespie</item>
                        <item>Alister — ŭochdir — <add place="above">a murderer</add> from uochdir
                            Sleat</item>
                        <item><unclear reason="illegible">Ranal — Calbhaich</unclear></item>
                        <item>9. Doil Gorm no children</item>
                        <item>9. Doil Gorm <unclear reason="illegible">Salnach —</unclear>
                            <del>had no children</del> the worst that ever held the Estate</item>
                        <item><del>Gillespie — had children &amp; carried on the present
                            line</del></item>
                        <item>Doil Gorm more — no children</item>
                        <item>8 — Gillespie — carries on the present line</item>
                        <item>7 <del>D</del>
                            <lb/>Doil Gorm oig<note type="editorial">Dòmhnall Gorm Òg, chief of the
                                MacDonalds of Sleat, died c.1643. Elegies to him were composed by
                                Iain Lom, Murchadh MacKenzie and Cathal MacMhuirich.
                            (AMC).</note></item>
                        <item>Alister More — a madman</item>
                        <item>Alister oig</item>
                        <item>6 — Sir Shemis</item>
                        <item>Doil Gorm Sleitach had Children</item>
                        <item>Gillespie. — had a son <add place="above">Eion</add> — killed in
                            atholl mar<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>
                            <lb/>Grandfather of <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/>
                            a Daughter of Barra</item>
                        <item>Alister Ruogh — hanged himself at <unclear reason="illegible">Kirk</unclear><gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" quantity="4"/>
                            <lb/>married to MacKays daughter — had a son Hustain a <unclear reason="illegible">Cap</unclear> in Holland no son — a daughter
                            married to Torlusk in Mull</item>
                        <item>Aonise died young</item>
                        <pb n="f.35v"/>
                        <item>by a daughter of the Tutor of <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/> predecessor of the Earl of Cromarty.<note type="editorial">Ruairidh MacCoinneach (Roderick Mackenzie) of
                                Còigeach, Tutor of Kintail (d.1626). Father of Sir John Mackenzie of
                                Tarbat and grandfather of George Mackenzie of Tarbat, first earl
                                Cromartie. (AMC).</note></item>
                        <item>5 Donil —</item>
                        <item>Huistean</item>
                        <item>Somerled — Somhairle</item>
                        <item>Shemis oig</item>
                        <item>Aonis — no children</item>
                        <item>Ruory —one natural son — who had no issue</item>
                        <item>2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> marriage <lb/><hi rend="underline">Ian</hi>.</item>
                        <item>Raonil. <del unit="words" quantity="1"/></item>
                        <item>Eoin Eirinach no issue</item>
                        <item>Aonis — had a son who went to America} natural Sons</item>
                        <item>4 — Donil — Obhar — Shir Donal Beg — <lb/>no children — had one who
                            lived not a year after him</item>
                        <item>Shemis —</item>
                        <item>William —</item>
                        <item>3 Alister</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p><persName ref="pe1867">Sir James</persName> gave his Son <persName ref="pe1890">John</persName> of the 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Marriage — that part
                    of <placeName ref="pl0950">Troternish</placeName> extending from <placeName ref="pl2649">the River of Glenteltin</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl2650">the River of Patrie</placeName> as a patrimony — besides the Lands of
                        <placeName ref="pl2651">Boalcnie</placeName>
                    <add place="below">Bailcnie <hi rend="underline">Bailecoumhni</hi></add>
                    purchased for him — <hi rend="underline">all</hi> this from <persName ref="pe1898"><unclear reason="illegible">Hustan</unclear> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald</persName></p>
                <p><pb n="f.36r"/>
                13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                    <persName ref="pe1675"><unclear>Kil<del rend="overstrike">
                                <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" quantity="1"/>
                            </del></unclear>phedere</persName> in <placeName ref="pl0854">South
                        Uist</placeName> who remembers his Father having often talked of the gross
                    injustice done to the Children of <persName ref="pe1899">Ian mhic S'hir
                        Shemis</persName> — ie to my Grandfathers Children —</p>
                <p>13 Aug<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> left <placeName ref="pl2469">Tighair</placeName> and proceeded to <placeName ref="pl2472">Valay</placeName></p>
                <p>14 remained at <placeName ref="pl2472">Valay</placeName></p>
                <p>15 — proceeded to <placeName ref="pl2652">Borera</placeName> — attended by
                        <persName ref="pe1620">Valay</persName> — <persName ref="pe1644">Boreray</persName> — <persName ref="pe1870">Greeminish</persName> —
                        <persName ref="pe1896">the Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> James MacQueen</persName> — <persName ref="pe1902">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gillespie</persName> — at
                        <placeName ref="pl2485">Berneray</placeName> found his Lady the youngest
                    daughter of <persName ref="pe1900">Berneray</persName> — a Sister of <persName ref="pe1900">Bernerays</persName> married to <persName ref="pe1901">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Neil</persName>
                    younger of <placeName ref="pl0737">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>
                        Kilda</placeName> — who was also there.</p>
                <p>remained at <placeName ref="pl2652">Boreray</placeName></p>
                <p>17 proceeded to <placeName ref="pl2485">Berneray</placeName>
                    <add place="above">left <persName ref="pe1689">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                            Edmund M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Queen</persName> &amp; <placeName ref="pe1870">Greemishnish</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl2652">Boreray</placeName></add> where I found the old Gentleman of 85 looking
                    well — but his Eyesight &amp; knees weak — <add place="above">but his spirits
                        good &amp; mind <unclear reason="illegible">intire</unclear></add> On a
                    marble Tabulet above the door of a small old House <del rend="overstrike">was</del> is the foll<hi rend="superscript">g</hi> inscription <lb/>Hic
                    natus est <lb/>illustrius ille <lb/><persName ref="pe1903">Normannus
                        MacLeod</persName>
                    <lb/>Armiger Auribis</p>
                <p><pb n="f.36v"/>
                This Gentleman &amp; a Brother of his <persName ref="pe1904">Ruarie</persName>
                    were knighted on the field of the Battle of <placeName ref="pl0806">Worcester</placeName> — <persName ref="pe1903">Sir Norman</persName> was
                        <persName ref="pe1905">Lady Murrays</persName> Great Grandfather.</p>
                <p>18 proceeded through the district of <placeName ref="pl2489"><unclear reason="illegible">Sannd</unclear></placeName> to <placeName ref="pl2446">Lochmaddy</placeName> accompanied by <persName ref="pe1644">Boreray</persName> — <persName ref="pe1620">Valay</persName>
                    <persName ref="pe1901">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Neil</persName> — &amp;
                    part of the way by <persName ref="pe1631">the Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>
                            M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Allan MacQueen</persName> who followed me
                    from <placeName ref="pl2469">Tighair</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl2485">Berneray</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Passed <hi rend="underline"><placeName ref="pl2489">Clachan</placeName></hi>
                    where <persName ref="pl2485">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Queen</persName> informed me there is the
                    remains of a druidical circle as the name implys — <persName ref="pl2485">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Queen</persName>
                    officiates at this place once in three weeks on the open field — he applied, for
                    a House for divine Service, to me as one of <persName ref="pe1619">Lord M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donalds</persName> Commissioners — The request
                    is reasonable — <add place="below">passed <hi rend="underline"><placeName ref="pl2653">Balmhic <unclear reason="illegible">Conmar</unclear></placeName></hi></add></p>
                <p>19 Inspected the intended site of <placeName ref="pl2446">the Village of
                        Lochmaddy</placeName> and some of the ground in the vicinity — determined to
                    recommend an alteration of the plan that had been proposed for reasons to be
                    detailed elsewhere</p>
                <p>20 Left <placeName ref="pl2446">Lochmaddy</placeName> &amp; arrived at <placeName ref="pl0665">Dunvegan</placeName></p>
                <p>21 Discharged the <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName> Cutter and gave
                        <persName ref="pe1906">John <pb n="f.37r"/>Livingston</persName> £12 — of
                    which by his own advice each of the five men composing his Crew was invited to
                    get a Guinea leaving £5.15 — for himself which he s<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> was too much — his men expressed their thankfulness —</p>
                <p>21 proceeded to <placeName ref="pl2490">Greeshinish</placeName>
                    <persName ref="pe1907">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> John M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald of Castletowns</persName> — Sheriff
                    substitute of this district of <placeName ref="pl2230">Invernesshire</placeName>
                    <add place="above">my selection &amp; old acquaintance</add> — married to a very
                    old acquaintance of mine <persName ref="pe1908">Miss Peggy M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Leod</persName> of <placeName ref="pl2654">Bearnsdale</placeName> whom I recollect to have known at <placeName ref="pl2324">Callander</placeName></p>
                <p>About half way from <placeName ref="pl0665">Dunvegan</placeName> met <persName ref="pe1909">L<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Col M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald of Lyndale</persName> who came to meet me — The Sheriff
                    &amp; he sent Horses for our riding &amp; for our Baggage which met us — but we
                    had procured Horses that enabled us to move from <placeName ref="pl0665">Dunvegan</placeName> — where I unexpectedly found a relation <persName ref="pe1910">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Lean</persName> married to the Tacksman — Grand Daughter of one of my
                    mothers Sisters — found also here <persName ref="pe1911">Cap<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Cyprus M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Leod</persName> — <add place="above">a natural</add> Uncle of the
                    present <persName ref="pe0446">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Leod</persName>,
                    married to a <unclear reason="illegible">Cousin Germain</unclear> of <persName ref="pe1912">Col Jo. M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donalds</persName>.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl0665">Dunvegan</placeName> is grandly situated —
                <pb n="f.37v"/>
                <pb n="f.38r"/>
                <pb n="f.38v"/>
                <pb n="f.39r"/>
                <pb n="f.39v"/>
                <pb n="f.40r"/>
                <pb n="f.40v"/>
                <pb n="f.41r"/>
                <pb n="f.41v"/>
                <pb n="f.42r"/>
                <pb n="f.42v"/>
                <pb n="f.43r"/>
                <pb n="f.43v"/></p>
                <p><pb n="f.44r"/>
                <list>
                        <item><unclear reason="illegible">Poccint</unclear> — <lb/><unclear reason="illegible">Ah Heo</unclear> Hemlock</item>
                        <item><unclear reason="illegible">Brighan</unclear> — mas corn <lb/>wild
                            skerrit</item>
                        <item>cromac</item>
                        <item>caornan —</item>
                        <item>Peasir na luch — vetches<note type="editorial">Peasair nan luch
                                (tufted vetch). (AMC).</note></item>
                        <item><unclear reason="illegible">Cuach Phadric</unclear> — a drawing
                            medicine</item>
                        <item><unclear reason="illegible">Slan</unclear> Lus — a healing
                            quality</item>
                        <item>Goche <unclear reason="illegible">Rude</unclear> — a sort of
                            Thistle</item>
                        <item>Blonigen — wild spinnage</item>
                        <item>Bui<gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" atLeast="2" atMost="3"/>ag —
                            the stem of the Sorrel</item>
                        <item>meach<unclear reason="illegible">e</unclear>an the leaf of the
                                <unclear reason="illegible">Bur</unclear> or <unclear reason="illegible">Cliathan</unclear></item>
                        <item>Sceallan — wild mustard —</item>
                    </list>
                    <pb n="f.44v"/>
                    <table>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <list>
                                    <item>Fūïr — wild Cellery</item>
                                    <item><unclear reason="illegible">C</unclear>notill — rock moss
                                        — a bad red dye</item>
                                    <item>Alder Bark — a black dye</item>
                                    <item>Fearn — Do</item>
                                    <item>Ruitt — wild Gall — yellow</item>
                                    <item>Heath tops Green — yellow</item>
                                    <item>Gŭírnig — small Barnicles that attach to wood or any hard
                                        substance producing insects said to destroy wood &amp; to
                                        take wing.</item>
                                    <item>Guirnan — Blue — </item>
                                    <item>Rûib red</item>
                                    <item>Tree rannach a sort of Fearn</item>
                                    <item>Buolan — ragwort — a yellow dye</item>
                                    <item>Shemrag a <unclear reason="illegible">mhanik</unclear> the
                                        milky Shemrag — white Clover</item>
                                    <item>Shemrag a Eich — the Horse Shemrag — Red Clover —</item>
                                    <item>Shalavag — Sorrel —</item>
                                </list>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <list>
                                    <item><unclear reason="illegible">Cliathan</unclear>
                                        <lb/>Cluoran —} burr.</item>
                                    <item><unclear reason="illegible">Geigan</unclear>
                                        Thistle</item>
                                    <item>Cuisag Stem of the Docken</item>
                                    <item>Coppag the blade or Leaves of Do</item>
                                    <item>Smear Bramble berry</item>
                                    <item>Smearah plural of D<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="superscript">o</hi></hi></item>
                                    <item><unclear reason="illegible">Shallisbher
                                        Siggin</unclear></item>
                                    <item>Meelaûhag — wild poppy</item>
                                    <item><unclear reason="illegible">Glunich</unclear></item>
                                    <item>Luochir ghoir dwarf rashes</item>
                                    <item><unclear reason="illegible">Buiag</unclear> — the
                                        yellowest part of Sea ware that makes the best kelp —</item>
                                    <item>Femin Sea ware —</item>
                                    <item>mhuirskein — Razor fish.</item>
                                </list>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table></p>
                <p><add place="inspace">Gaelic Description of the best Bow.</add></p>
                <p><add place="overleaf">Bogha Iubhar Esragain <lb/>Itè Firean Locha Freig <lb/>Ceir
                        Buidhe Bhaile nan Gobhan <lb/>'S Cean o'n Cheard MacPheidēran</add></p>
                <p><pb n="f.45r"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>