<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0056">
    <teiHeader type="s">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Anonymous, Journal of a Voyage to the Western islands of Scotland — from July 7. to Aug.
                    7. 1810
                    <date>1810</date></title>
                <author/>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Edited with an Introduction by Alex Deans</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
                <date when="1810"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
                        <idno>MS.10257</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p/>
            </abstract>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>T.W.<note type="editorial">The NLS catalogue notes suggest that T.W. is one T.
                        Winfield, the author of the manuscript.</note></p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">1810</hi>
                </p>
                <p><pb/>
                <fw>i</fw>
                T. Winfield</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">1810 —</hi>
                </p>
                <p><pb/>
                <fw>ii</fw>
                Journal <lb/>of a <lb/>Voyage to the Western <lb/>islands of Scotland — <lb/>from
                    July 7. to Aug. 7.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">1810.</hi>
                </p>
                <p><pb n="1"/></p>
                <p>July. 7<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> 1810 —</p>
                <p>We this day agreed with Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi>
                    <persName ref="pe0218">M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>Iver</persName>, <persName ref="pe2087">M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>Viccar</persName>, and <persName ref="pe2088">M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>Corquodale</persName> of
                        <placeName ref="pl0723">Liverpool</placeName>, to hire a sloop of theirs in
                    the <placeName ref="pl0603">Greenock</placeName> Trade — for the purpose of
                    taking a voyage amongst the <placeName ref="pl0708">Western Islands</placeName>
                    of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>, touching at any place we might
                    think proper —<hi rend="superscript">x</hi><note type="authorial"><hi rend="superscript">x</hi> Had we not done this, we sh<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> have incurred considerable expence from the
                        additional premium required on insurance — chiefly on account of the number
                        of Privateers, Danish &amp; other, which frequent the N. Seas.</note> but
                    stipulating that the <placeName ref="pl2902">Butt of Lewis</placeName> should be
                    the most Northerly point of our Cruise — Every thing being in readiness, we
                    shipped our sea store — and went on board the vessel at three o-Clock — and
                    immediately got under weigh the breeze was very light — but <pb n="2"/> the Ebb
                    Tide soon carried us far beyond the <hi rend="superscript">x</hi><placeName ref="pl2904">Black Rock</placeName><note type="authorial"> a low Rock
                        running out into the Sea at the N. Western Point of <placeName ref="pl2905">Wirral</placeName>, wh<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi> together with the
                        sand banks that stretch out from nearly the same place render the entrance
                        into <placeName ref="pl2906">Liverpool River</placeName>, narrow &amp;
                        difficult.</note> — The sight of the welsh coast, with the <placeName ref="pl1958">Great ormshead</placeName> &amp;c induced us to endeavour to
                    get into <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName> — but the tide failing us
                    when we came to <placeName ref="pl1959">Puffin Island</placeName>, &amp; the
                    wind not quite fair we took the small <add place="above">boat</add> a shore to
                        <placeName ref="pl1487">W Penmon Point</placeName> — &amp; from thence
                    walked up to <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName> about 5 miles distant
                    — <hi rend="superscript">x</hi><note type="authorial"><hi rend="superscript">x</hi> The Captain in the mean time brought our vessel up to the Point
                        above the Town —</note> The same afternoon we left it by return of the Ebb
                    Tide — &amp; passing between <placeName ref="pl1488">Priestholme
                        Island</placeName> &amp; the <placeName ref="pl1487">Penmon P<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi></placeName> steered for the <placeName ref="pl0707">Isle of Man</placeName> — at two oClock a.m. the morning
                    following — we came to in the bay of <placeName ref="pl1590">Douglas</placeName>
                    — near to the Light House — The architecture of this aspires at more ornament
                    than buildings of this sort in general boast of being <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/> having pilasters around it, with pannels between
                    them <pb n="3"/> &amp; a deep frieze &amp; cornice above them — it is almost
                    handsome, but the upper part looks heavy &amp; ill suited to the lower — it
                    stands at the end of a very substantial &amp; beautiful Quay — or rather pier —
                    built with an exceedingly hard stone of a reddish colour — which is brought from
                    the <placeName ref="pl0719">isle of <hi rend="underline">Arran</hi></placeName>
                    on the left, immediately opposite to the light House — is seated a large white
                    House belonging to <persName ref="pe2090">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                        Wallesly</persName> the situation of it, would be particularly fine — if
                    there were any trees near it, but at present it seems naked &amp; exposed —
                    about a mile to the N.E. of the Town stands a new built house of the <persName ref="pe0548">Duke of Athol’s</persName> — it is on the flat sandy beach,
                    quite low with lofty hills rising immediately at the back of it — but yet from
                    its size, it is conspicuous, &amp; certainly looks fine — it consists <add place="above">chiefly</add> of a large square with square Towers at the <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/> angles —</p>
                <p><pb n="4"/>
                In the harbour of <placeName ref="pl1590">Douglas</placeName> we saw a number of
                    vessels some of them particularly an american just come in, of a large size,
                    which gave it a very commercial appearance — but the Quay is the only
                    respectable part of the Town — the streets are narrow &amp; dirty — In the
                    evening we went to the Theatre Royal, to see the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0697">Merchant of Venice</title></bibl>, &amp; a Harlequin
                    Pantomime — bespoken by <persName ref="pe2091">Sir J<hi rend="superscript">n.</hi> Piers</persName> — The Theatre is <add place="above">a</add>
                    very small room — but the performances were by no means bad — We here had an
                    opportunity of seeing pretty closely several noted characters, who honour the
                    island with their presence for their own private convenience — what is singular
                    They wear a costume peculiar to themselves, wh<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>
                    makes them look ridiculous — it consists of long blue Trowsers, which reach up
                    to the chest almost — having a buff waistcoat underneath <add place="above">over</add> above which the red braces are seen — for the short child’s
                    jacket which they wear studded with little bell buttons, is constantly thrown
                    open — with this they wear a <pb n="5"/> black, or coloured silk handkerchief
                    high up to their chins — whiskers, if not mustachios also, enormous, and
                    occasionally large rings thro their ears — Were not the character of these men
                    known, their dress &amp; manners are such as to <add place="above">excite
                        disgust</add>
                    <gap reason="authorial" unit="lines" quantity="14"/><note type="editorial">There
                        is a significant deletion here of approximately 14 lines. The deleted
                        passage appears to be an invective against the Manx natives.</note></p>
                <p> We left the <placeName ref="pl0707">Isle of Man</placeName> the day following
                    about 4 oClock P.M. &amp; coasted slowly round to <placeName ref="pl2907"><unclear reason="illegible">Mauglan</unclear> head</placeName>, &amp;
                    the <placeName ref="pl1585">Point of Air</placeName> — from hence we saw
                        <placeName ref="pl2908">Jurby Head</placeName> &amp; as we sailed onward,
                    could descry the whole coast towards <placeName ref="pl2909">Peel</placeName> —
                    &amp; even beyond it — towards the <placeName ref="pl2910">Calf of
                        Man</placeName> — the Land is for the <add place="below">most part</add>
                    <pb n="6"/> Mountainous (but <add place="above">tho’</add> not very high) —
                    where it is otherwise it appears very rich &amp; fertile — but every where
                    appears <add place="above">there is</add> a great scarcity of trees, without
                    which a country can never boast great pretensions to beauty — we soon got sight
                    of the <placeName ref="pl2911">Mull of Galloway</placeName> — but on nearing it,
                    the wind failed — <hi rend="superscript">x</hi><note type="authorial"><hi rend="superscript">x</hi> off</note> The Tide carried us some distance
                    back — but in the afternoon we again had it in our favour — and early on the
                    morning following we were opposite to <placeName ref="pl2912">Port
                        Patrick</placeName> — at this Time it was perfectly calm — &amp; a thick fog
                    came on — about mid day it cleared up — &amp; we saw the <placeName ref="pl0632">Craig of Ailsa</placeName> at a distance — rising from the sea in the form
                    of a cone — very high &amp; abrupt — it <add place="above">is</add> an
                    exceedingly fine object — &amp; well worthy of a visit — before we landed on it
                    — we fired a swivel — but the number of birds disturbed by it, was not <pb n="7"/> so great as we had been led to expect — there were however immense numbers of
                    them to be seen — we found the Tacksman on shore with about half a dozen men,
                    whom he employs to destroy the birds, which is done for the sake of the feathers
                    — for which the proprietor of the rock, L<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi>
                        Elphinstoune<note type="editorial">The proprietor of Ailsa Craig was
                            <persName ref="pe2092">Archibald Kennedy</persName>, twelfth earl of
                        Cassillis and first baron of Ailsa.</note> receives a rent of about <hi rend="underline">£30</hi>, as we were told — no guns are allowed to be fired
                    on the island. &amp; the only method Employed for destroying the birds is by
                    robbing their nests — this is done by men who having fastened a rope to the
                    summit of a rock lower themselves down, until they meet with a nest in which the
                    birds are concealed — many of which are knocked down by a <add place="above">long</add> stick, which the man always carries with him for the purpose —
                    we walked up with some difficulty to the castle, a small square tower at about
                    one third of the <pb n="8"/> way to the Top — the ascent is narrow &amp; very
                    steep — but it is the only part that is accessible — for the rock is almost
                    perpendicular on everyside — our sail from hence to <placeName ref="pl0603">Greenock</placeName> up the <placeName ref="pl0833">Frith of the
                        Clyde</placeName> was very pleasant — the banks being very beautiful on each
                    side — the long coast of <placeName ref="pl2586">Ayr</placeName> extending on
                    the Eastern Side — with <placeName ref="pl0719">Arran</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl0714">Bute</placeName> &amp;c opposite &amp; the 2 islands of
                        <placeName ref="pl2556">Cumray</placeName> between them — We did not reach
                        <placeName ref="pl0603">Greenock</placeName> until the following morning
                    about four oClock — the Town is not large but part of it is tolerably handsome —
                    The new <hi rend="superscript">x</hi><note type="authorial"><hi rend="superscript">x</hi> Protestant. the living is worth about £600 –
                        &amp; is one of the best in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> —
                    </note>Church, &amp; the Tontine are the best public <sic>building</sic> —
                    indeed they are the only ones worth notice excepting a castellated Gaol, now
                    building at the back of the church. — The Presbyterian Kirk is seen as you enter
                    the Town from the Westward — it is large &amp; rather ancient — The Trade of
                        <placeName ref="pl0603">Greenock</placeName><pb n="9"/> is considerable —
                    together with <placeName ref="pl0602">Port Glasgow</placeName> it has the whole
                    trade of <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> — but yet we found great
                    difficulty at the Bank in getting change for our English notes — of which they
                    always have suspicion — &amp; will scarcely ever take them — we were under the
                    necessity of indorsing the notes with our name, &amp; particulars of Residence.
                    — The situation of <placeName ref="pl0603">Greenock</placeName> is quite
                    beautiful — the Sea has the appearance of a large Lake encircled with mountains,
                    in general well cultivated &amp; fertile — with the rugged mountains of
                        <placeName ref="pl2916">Cowal</placeName> rising beyond the <persName ref="pe1433">Duke of Argyles</persName> woods at one extremity, while the
                    celebrated rock of <placeName ref="pl0226">Dunbarton</placeName> rises at the
                    opposite end — <placeName ref="pl0602">Port Glasgow</placeName> is also seen on
                    the shore, about four of 5 miles higher up than <placeName ref="pl0603">Greenock</placeName> — &amp; looks very beautiful — Leaving <placeName ref="pl0603">Greenock</placeName>
                    <pb n="10"/> we again sailed along the <placeName ref="pl0833">Frith of
                        Clyde</placeName> — &amp; saw the <persName ref="pe0278">Marquis of
                        Bute’s</persName> house <placeName ref="pl0616">Mount Stuart</placeName>, in
                    a delightful situation on <placeName ref="pl0714">Bute Island</placeName> not
                    far from <placeName ref="pl0619">Rothsay</placeName> — the house does not appear
                    very large or <unclear reason="illegible">grand</unclear> — with the woods
                    around it the land which appears uncommonly fertile under it beautiful — The
                    whole island is said to be very rich &amp; good — &amp; in general not very
                    mountainous — <placeName ref="pl0719">Arran</placeName> also is said to contain
                    Excellent land — but it has more mountains of which <placeName ref="pl0626">Goatfield</placeName> is particularly high — &amp; from its form &amp;
                    situation near the Sea, uncommonly fine — at the foot of it stands <placeName ref="pl0625">Brodick Castle</placeName>, belonging to the <persName ref="pe0250">Duke of Hamilton</persName>, as descendant from <placeName ref="pl0232">Chatelherault</placeName> — in fact the whole island, excepting
                    only one or two small farms, is the property of the Duke — we landed at
                        <placeName ref="pl0629">Brodick</placeName>
                    <pb n="11"/> &amp; walked up to the castle, which commands a very noble view of
                    the sea, with fine mountainous country around it — we were desirous of seeing
                    the interior of the Castle — but on sending to the Tacksman who lives <add place="above">in</add> it, to request leave — we were told that the
                        <persName ref="pe2152"><hi rend="underline">Laird Lamont</hi></persName> was
                    at dinner, &amp; could not see us — we therefore took our leave — &amp; found a
                    reception at the inn below — where we also met with some Excellent Whiskey — at
                        3<hi rend="superscript">L.</hi> the bottle — We now soon came under
                        <placeName ref="pl0631">Lamlash island</placeName>, which rises very nobly
                    from the sea, &amp; is in height &amp; form peculiarly fine it stands in front
                    of the entrance into a bay &amp; harbour of the same name — in which is good and
                    safe anchorage —</p>
                <p><pb n="12"/>
                on the following morning we found ourselves not far from the <placeName ref="pl2915">Mull of Cantire</placeName> — but the weather being calm —
                    &amp; the Tide against us — we endeavoured in vain to get round <placeName ref="pl2629">Fair Head</placeName> on the coast of <placeName ref="pl0889">Ireland</placeName> — and therefore we took the small boat, &amp; went on
                    shore in <placeName ref="pl3004">Cushendon bay</placeName> — about a mile to the
                    South of <placeName ref="pl3003">Torr’s point</placeName> — The coast is every
                    where on this part steep, rugged &amp; dangerous — We were told by the
                    inhabitants many of whom crowded to us on our landings — that the distance from
                        <placeName ref="pl2913">Bally castle</placeName> was exactly seven miles —
                    that for the first two miles we had to ascend the hills, but that afterwards, we
                    should find an excellent level road — We were four hours in walking to
                        <placeName ref="pl2913">Ballycastle</placeName> — &amp; the distance could
                        <pb n="13"/> not be less that 13 or 14 miles <note type="authorial">The
                        Country is on all sides dreary &amp; mountainous —</note> About half a mile
                    before you come to the <hi rend="underline">Town</hi> of <placeName ref="pl2913">Bally castle</placeName> we passed the remains of an abbey which seems to
                    have been extensive it is now much used as a place of burial — &amp; the smell
                    of it we found quite offensive, as the night-fell — the Town is about a quarter
                    of a mile distant from the sea, &amp; consists principally of one street on the
                    brow of a hill — the houses are poor — &amp; the inn tho’ not promising in
                    appearance is tolerably comfortable — The best houses are to be seen on the Quay
                    — but the harbour of <placeName ref="pl2913">Bally castle</placeName> does not
                    seem much frequented — the water is very deep — opposite to it is <placeName ref="pl3006">Church Bay</placeName> in the island of <placeName ref="pl3005">Raughlan</placeName> in which is better anchorage in most winds except
                    those from S.W.</p>
                <p><pb n="14"/>
                We slept at <placeName ref="pl2913">Bally castle</placeName>, &amp; hired
                        horses<note type="authorial">for these we paid seven shillings each —</note>
                    for the following morning to take us to <placeName ref="pl2913">Bally
                        castle</placeName>, the <placeName ref="pl2725">Giant’s
                    Causeway</placeName>, said to be nine miles distant — but in reality 10 ½ miles
                    English <add place="above">Irish</add> — or nearly 14 English — when we had gone
                    about 3 miles — we left our horses at some cabins near the road — &amp; walked
                    down a short distance towards the sea to the “<placeName ref="pl3007">flying
                        bridge of Carregarhiad</placeName>”<note type="authorial"><handShift/><hi rend="superscript">+</hi> Similar to <placeName ref="pl3008">South
                            Stack</placeName> —</note> which is formed of robes with two thin boards
                    about 18 inches wide <add place="above">lashed</add> upon them — &amp; one rope
                    for the hand to hold as you pass over — These ropes are belayed on each side of
                    a vast chasm &amp; connect a high perpendicular rock, &amp; the main land whose
                    front is equally bold &amp; perpendicular with the sea about 50 yards in breadth
                    dashing beneath, at a depth of perhaps 100 yards — This <pb n="15"/> bridge is
                    merely put up in the summer months for the use of the fishermen who rent a
                        <sic>consderable</sic> salmon fishery carried on, beneath the rock — to
                    which there is no access by across the flying bridge — the whole is not unlike
                    the <placeName ref="pl3008">South Stack light house</placeName> near <placeName ref="pl1018">Holy Head</placeName> — but is much more fearful—</p>
                <p>From hence — we kept on the Summit of the cliffs near the Coast — passed a castle
                    very curiously situated on a ridge of rock detached from the Cliff which
                    commands it — but before the invention of Powder it was probably a place of
                    Great Strength like other it is merely one square Tower — not large — we took
                    several views, looking from the summit of the perpendicular cliffs which
                    overhang the Sea — that of Pleaskin <pb n="16"/> is most fine — the columnar
                    forms of the rock is certainly very singular &amp; curious — Soon after this we
                    met with some<hi rend="superscript">x</hi><note type="authorial">The Two guides
                        whom we took from <placeName ref="pl2913">Ballycastle</placeName> did not
                        seem to know any thing of the country.</note> guides, who conducted us down
                    one of the steepest parts of the mountain by a little slippery dangerous path,
                    down immediately upon the <placeName ref="pl2725">Causeway</placeName> — The
                    first object shewn is a large stone called absurdly the Giant’s chair, not far
                    from this, a few columnar appearances in the side of a rock are called the organ
                    — There are 3 causeways — the larger one, stretches out about 250 yards into the
                    sea, from the base of a high cliff — the other two, are but very small — indeed
                    they properly form parts of the larger one — the basaltic columns forming the
                    causeway do not rise high — &amp; are merely to be considered as a great natural
                    curiosity — They have 4. 5. <pb n="17"/> 6. 7. &amp; 8. sides indiscriminately
                    but all compactly fitting into one another — &amp; some of them very perfect
                    &amp; regular. — The shore appears rough and dangerous even for boats to land. —
                    Leaving the <placeName ref="pl2725">Giant’s causeway</placeName> with some
                    little disappointment, we walked up the hill to an inn newly built, — where our
                    horses were ready for us — we were followed by about 20 men all claiming the
                    merit of having been our guides &amp; having <del unit="words" quantity="1"/>
                    conducted us — all of them it was impossible to satisfy — &amp; this attempt at
                    an imposition did not tend to make us more pleased with the <placeName ref="pl2725">Giant’s causeway</placeName> — we now took the high road back
                    again, and at 6 oClock in the Evening were happy to find ourselves on board our
                    vessel in <placeName ref="pl2913">Ballycastle Bay</placeName> — which we
                    instantly quitted — &amp; stood out for the <placeName ref="pl2915">mull of
                        Cantire</placeName> — at five oClock the next morning </p>
                <p><pb n="18"/></p>
                <p>the Tide began to flow so strong that we were fortunate in casting anchor in
                        <placeName ref="pl3009">Loch nakeel</placeName> — to wait the return of it —
                    here we took the large boat &amp; rowed to an island which we had just passed,
                    about 3 miles astern of us — one of <placeName ref="pl3010">M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi> Cormac’s</placeName> isles — in which we
                    found the remains of a building which has every appearance of a small chapel
                    attached to a dwelling House — within this we found an arched recess, with a
                    figure of a priest in his robes laying upon the stone below it. the figure is
                    only 4 feet 6 inches long — but the stone is 6<hi rend="superscript">ft.</hi> 6
                    in. — it is said to be the burial place of the priest of <persName ref="pe2100">M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi> Cormac</persName> — the Chieftain
                    himself is buried a little to the Eastward of the chapel, with <lb/>encircled by
                    a low wall</p>
                <p><pb n="19"/>
                Close to the South wall of the chapel is shewn a plain Grave without any stone,
                    or other mark — Said to contain the remains of <persName ref="pe2100">M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi> Cormac’s</persName> daughter — on the highest
                    part of the island which may perhaps be a quarter of a mile long — stands a
                    broken cross — which has once been beautiful — one side richly carved &amp;
                    ornamented — with a rude figure representing our Saviour on the Cross — &amp;c —
                    the other filled with writing which cannot now be easily decyphered — we were
                    told very seriously by a fisherman who lives in the neighbourhood — that an
                    Irishman once attempted to carry off this cross — but that so long as he had the
                    cross on board his ship — he was unable to get home — &amp; was tossed about,
                    until he threw it overboard near the <placeName ref="pl2915">Mull of
                        Cantire</placeName> — from whence the cross floated back to it’s own island
                    — but was broken in the manner now seen — The same <pb n="20"/> man also shewed
                    up what he called the preaching place — a sort of recess in the side of the hill
                    to the S.E. of the isle — where there is a cave — into which if any young lad or
                    lass ever enters, he can never have a wee ane — This he was assured of — he knew
                    many a one who had attempted it, &amp; he told us a long account of one who had
                    ridiculed the idea — &amp; rashly Entered the cave. —</p>
                <p>Returning from this island (where we found a number of fishing men with their
                    boats) we got under weigh — but were obliged to put into <placeName ref="pl3011">Crinan Bay</placeName> the same Even<hi rend="superscript">g.</hi> — we
                    went on shore — &amp; met with a Pilot, just returned from a Cruise in the
                        <placeName ref="pl0708">Hebrides</placeName> — whom we agreed to take with
                    us — we then walked about a quarter of a mile to see the canal which joins
                        <placeName ref="pl2953">Loch Crinan</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl2954">Loch Gilpie</placeName> —<note type="authorial">an extent of
                        nine miles —</note> &amp; ferried over to a small island, where there is a
                    salmon fishery — it does not seem to be a good one —<note type="authorial">The
                        Seathe is the only fish usually taken here — of these there are very great
                        numbers —</note> &amp; the few salmon they take are in general small — but
                        <pb n="21"/> they are cheap<note type="authorial">we paid 4.d per lb. 3d. is
                        the common price</note> — &amp; we found them very good — as soon as they
                    are taken, they are put into Salt<note type="authorial">Went to <placeName ref="pl0603">Greenock</placeName> —</note> — &amp; few if any are
                    attempted to be sold fresh — the Loch &amp; the Country about it, is exceedingly
                    pretty — tho’ the Castle belonging to M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>Callum —
                    who bought it a few years ago — is in the least pretty part of it — The weather
                    being unfavorable — we did not leave <placeName ref="pl2955">Crinan</placeName>
                    until the next morning — when we passed within about a mile &amp; a half of the
                    famous <placeName ref="pl0690">Gulph of Coryvrechhan</placeName> between the
                    rocky shore of <placeName ref="pl0716">Jura</placeName>, &amp; the high rocks of
                        <placeName ref="pl2956">Scarba</placeName> — the weather was very moderate
                    but we saw plainly the breakers. The Tide Eddies so strongly and so variously
                    round the innumerable rocks that crowd this part of the sea — that the
                    navigation is rendered Extremely difficult &amp; dangerous — Either in
                    boisterous weather, or in a calm — We <pb n="22"/> took what advantage of the
                    Tide we possibly could — but again we were obliged at the Turn of it to run into
                    a small bay in the island of <placeName ref="pl2957">Lunga</placeName> — All
                    this was exceedingly Tedious — but it gave us an opportunity of witnessing the
                    hospitality of <placeName ref="pe2153">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                        Brown</placeName> who rents the land from <persName ref="pe2154">M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi> Dougall</persName> of <placeName ref="pl2957">Lunga</placeName> — The sea was now more open to us — tho the slate
                    islands, with <placeName ref="pl0691">Eisdale</placeName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0267"><unclear reason="illegible">Seyl</unclear></placeName>
                        &amp;<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">c</hi></hi> seemed almost
                    to close together the passage between <placeName ref="pl2957">Lunga</placeName>
                    &amp; <placeName ref="pl2958">Loeng</placeName> — but at midnight we weighed
                    anchor — &amp; early in the morning were at the entrance into the sound between
                        <placeName ref="pl1077">Kerera</placeName> &amp; the main land<note type="authorial">having a fine view of <placeName ref="pl0722">Dunolly
                            castle</placeName> at the extremity of <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" quantity="1"/></note> — after laying to for a short time —
                    we got worked up the narrow sound, — &amp; just as we came in sight of
                        <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName> struck on a flat rock who runs a
                    considerable way out from the land — the Tide flowed gently &amp; in <pb n="23"/> little more than an hour carried us off without any injury — we landed at
                        <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName> — about Two oClock —</p>
                <p>July 20. — After dining we walked out to see the Argyleshire Local Militia at
                    Exercise in a field near the Town — they are about 800 strong — &amp; with their
                    Kelt &amp; Highland uniform have a very martial appearance — we had not been
                    long in the field, before several (whom we found to be the inhabitants of
                        <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName>) came up to us — one of them
                        <persName ref="pe2155">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>Leay</persName> accompanied us to our inn —
                    was anxious to shew us every civility — &amp; invited us to breakfast with him
                    the next morning — At his house we were introduced to the young <persName ref="pe1833">Laird of Coll</persName> — to <persName ref="pe2156">Capt<hi rend="superscript">n.</hi> Campbel of B<gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="several"/></persName> in the isle of <placeName ref="pl0974">Tyree</placeName> — &amp; one or two more — By them we were
                    invited to their mess — but being unable to return in Time from <placeName ref="pl0685">Dunstaffnage</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl2194">Beregonium</placeName> which we proposed to visit that <pb n="24"/> day —
                    we were prevented from dining with them — The day following we had a specimen of
                    the hearty reception which strangers may expect from the mess of Highland Reg<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> —</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl0722">Dunolly Castle</placeName> stands on a rock at the point
                    which to the N. of the chief entrance into the harbour of <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName> — it consists of one small square tower but
                    from it’s situation looks very commanding — &amp; is a fine object — Soon after
                    passing under this — we perceived the <placeName ref="pl0685">Castle of
                        Dunstaffnage</placeName> about 2 ½ miles to the Northward, near to the sea —
                    it is much larger than <placeName ref="pl0722">Dun<del>staffnage</del><add place="above">olly — </add></placeName>, &amp; was for some time a regal
                        residence<note type="authorial">It belongs to the chief of a clan M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi> Dougal <add place="above">who</add> lives
                        close to it —</note> — the Situation of it is not very bold, tho’ it is
                    built on a foundation of rock which seems to have been hewn to the dimensions of
                    the Castle, &amp; which makes it quite <pb n="25"/> inaccessible excepting at
                    the E. Side where a flight of steps leads to the Entrance thro’ a narrow archway
                    into the Castle — it is a square with Towers that do not project far at the
                    corners of it — at present nothing remains but the shell — within it is built a
                    high house with gable ends — not exactly according with the castle, — &amp; also
                    outhouses &amp;c — in these the Tacksman now lives — who rents the property from
                        <persName ref="pe2157">M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>Donald of
                        Dunstaffnage</persName> — the upper window &amp; the walk on the<hi rend="superscript">x</hi><note type="authorial">on these are placed to field
                        pieces one a brass 6 pounder belonging to one of the Spanish armada lost on
                        the Coast of <placeName ref="pl0729">mull</placeName> near <placeName ref="pl0681">Tobermory</placeName> in 15<gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="2"/></note> battlements of the Castle command a
                    very Extensive and Exceedingly beautiful prospect on every side — the <hi rend="superscript">x</hi><note type="authorial"><placeName ref="pl0686">Connel</placeName> signifies Rage —</note><placeName ref="pl0686">Connel</placeName> a narrow passage of the loch which runs up to <placeName ref="pl1249"><unclear>Bunawe</unclear></placeName> &amp;c — where the sea
                    dashes with great violence, (having the appearance of a wier across
                        <del>the</del> it) is seen plainly <pb n="26"/> the Mountains, especially
                        <placeName ref="pl0831">Cruchan Ben</placeName> rising magnificently beyond
                    &amp; indeed the whole Country appears astonishing fine — &amp; the view towards
                    the Sea is not less so. — within a short distance from the castle is a chapel
                    wherein Several of the Kings of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> are
                    said to be buried — it has had a sort of chancel added to the East End — which
                    disfigures it considerably — otherwise from the shape of the small Gothic
                    windows, narrow to the Exterior but large within, &amp; the remains of Gothic
                    ornaments within, it has boasted some elegance in it’s time — probably it is not
                    a very ancient building — There is a curious effect of an echo <del>with</del> A
                    person stands in a particular situation round the corner of a small rock which
                    is near the chapel, &amp; thence directing his voice<pb n="27"/> towards the
                    chapel — the sounds seems to proceed from the inside of the chapel — to those
                    stationed in front of the building — We could perceive no monuments of Early
                    date within — it is still used as a place of burial —</p>
                <p>From <placeName ref="pl0685">Dunstaffnage</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl2194">Beregonium</placeName> is about 3 miles, where the traces of an ancient
                    vitrified fort are to be discovered — they skirt the summit of a rock which is
                    not very high, &amp; like <add place="above">almost</add> all other very ancient
                    fortresses is commanded by a neighbouring rock, much larger &amp; higher than
                    itself — It is said that <placeName ref="pl2194">Beregonium</placeName> was once
                    the capital of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>, at the Time when
                    first the Kings resided at <placeName ref="pl0685">Dunstaffnage
                        Castle</placeName> — The specimens of vitrification found, are very curious
                    – &amp; of a variety of colours many of which are quite beautiful — They
                    resemble the burned kelp, <pb n="28"/> &amp; must have required very intense
                    heat, before they could have been reduced to their present state — It seems
                    evident that it was intentionally done — which the appearance of other similar
                    forts, particularly one near <placeName ref="pl0156">Inverness</placeName> the
                    walls of which now remain some feet above the surface of the ground — probably
                    it might be done, to consolidate the wall, before the use of cement was
                        known<note type="editorial">The first systematic description of Scotland's
                        vitrified forts was that given by the Welsh mineral engineer John Williams,
                        in <hi rend="italic">An Account of Some Remarkable Ancient Ruins, Lately
                            discovered in the Highlands, and Northern Parts of Scotland</hi>
                        (Edinburgh: 1777).</note> — </p>
                <p> We returned to <placeName ref="pl1076">oban</placeName> — &amp; in the Evening
                    went to <persName ref="pe2155">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>Leay’s</persName>, where we met with a
                        <persName ref="pe2158">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Bayard</persName>
                    just returned from <placeName ref="pl0652">Staffa</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl0651">Icolumkill</placeName> &amp;c — he was preparing to sail to his
                    native country <placeName ref="pl2959">America</placeName> together with a
                    number of Emigrants from the different islands, whom a <hi rend="superscript">x</hi><note type="authorial">a large brig resembling a Guinea man
                    —</note>vessel was then waiting to convey from <placeName ref="pl1076">oban</placeName> — We were no less surprized than sorry to find this system
                    of Emigration still continued — But we <pb n="29"/> were assured by <persName ref="pe2155">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>Leay</persName> that <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>
                    was totally unable to maintain it’s own encreasing population — &amp; that the
                    country was too poor — &amp; the quantity of arable land too small to allow of
                    much improvement — that the grazing system was becoming every day more prevalent
                    in the country, &amp; by consequence the labour of individuals less required —
                    that it remained therefore for those of the poor who could not find employment
                    in their own country either to emigrate — or to starve at home in the most
                    abject state of slavery &amp; degradation — for we were told that the state of
                    vassalage &amp; subjection in which several of the Lairds retain their inferior
                    tenantry, is at this present day, as bad if not more hateful that that of former
                    ages — <persName ref="pe1820">M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>Dougall of
                        Dunolly</persName> was quoted as a specimen if all that is said of him be
                    true, <pb n="30"/> no man can be censured for holding out encouragement to his
                    Tenants to quite such a chief — Those who hold land under him, are bound to pay
                    all the Laird’s Taxes, &amp; all that he may hereafter be levied upon him —
                    &amp; it is not long since he told his Tenants — that he had been obliged to pay
                    £900 for his son’s commission in the army — This he considered a Tax &amp; as
                    such they were bound to pay it forthwith — &amp; he instantly levied it — </p>
                <p> — A singular instance of the attachment of a clan to its chief was seen — one of
                    our boatmen, also a poor man, who had begged us to give him his passage from
                        <placeName ref="pl2194">Beregonium</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName> — happened to belong to <persName ref="pe1820">M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>Dougal’s</persName> clan — &amp; as we passed
                    under <persName ref="pl0722">Dunolly Castle</persName> &amp; were listening to
                    the accounts which our boatmen gave us of the Laird — we discovered that these 2
                    men were M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>Dougals — &amp; asked <pb n="31"/> if
                    they liked their chief, &amp; if they would obey his orders, were he to call on
                    them to fight for him — the both of them confessed they did not like him — but
                    the old man not at all pleased at the abuse he had heard of him, — declared he
                    would follow him, &amp; if he was young &amp; a fighting man — he would fight
                    for him — the other told us, the Laird’s Father was a good man, &amp; therefore
                    he w<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> fight for the Father’s Son — </p>
                <p> On Sunday morn<hi rend="superscript">g.</hi> July 22<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> — we attended the Parade of the Reg<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> of
                    local militia — for the purpose of hearing a Gaelic Sermon preachd in the open
                    field — when the square was formed, all persons who were desirous, were admitted
                    within — &amp; the greatest part joined in a hymn with which the service began —
                    The effect of it was peculiarly impressive — a precentor<pb n="32"/> gave out
                    each separate time — &amp; numbers joined, singing in the most perfect harmony,
                    the solemn swell of which was ecchoed from the surrounding Hills — &amp; could
                    not fail to raise emotions of piety altho’ the words were to us totally
                    unintelligible — During the singing, all excepting the military sat crowded
                    together — when the prayer followed — all stood up — this prayer was uttered
                    with much apparent devotion by the minister — it seemed once long continued
                    prayer — but of course we could not understand it — Again we sat down — &amp;
                    heard the Gaelic sermon — after which followed a hymn equally fine with the
                    former &amp; we departed after hearing the blessing of the minister — &amp;
                    adding our contribution to that of others — this we understood was for the sole
                    use of the minister himself —</p>
                <p><pb n="33"/>
                This evening we <del>went on board</del>
                    <add place="above">dined with</add> the mess — &amp; the morning following went
                    on board our vessel — but the wind &amp; weather proving very unfavorable — we
                    could not sail before the next morning, when at five oClock, we left <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName> — and passing under <placeName ref="pl0688">Lismore Island</placeName>, <unclear reason="illegible">&amp;
                        past</unclear> the <placeName ref="pl2205">Lady Rock</placeName> we entered
                    the <placeName ref="pl2195">Sound of Mull</placeName> — along the coast of which
                    on each side a regular line of communication was kept up by castles — of wh<hi rend="superscript">h.</hi> one, <del unit="words" quantity="1"/> the N.E.
                    end of <placeName ref="pl0729">Mull</placeName>, call<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>
                    <placeName ref="pl0684">castle Douart</placeName>, seems even larger than
                        <placeName ref="pl0685">Dunstaffnage</placeName> — the others are but small
                    &amp; uninteresting — we had some thoughts of landing at <placeName ref="pl0682">Arros</placeName>, &amp; walking across the narrow neck of Land to the head
                    of <placeName ref="pl1079">Loch <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" quantity="1"/></placeName> — &amp; to have taken boat from thence to
                        <placeName ref="pl0652">Staffa</placeName>, but we determined to attempt to
                        <pb n="34"/> sail round the island — &amp;therefore passed on to <placeName ref="pl0681">Tobermorey</placeName>, &amp; stood round the <del>Head</del>
                    <placeName ref="pl2960"><add place="above">P<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></add>
                        of Ardmore</placeName> — The wind not answering — we <unclear>beat</unclear>
                    up — but did not pass the <placeName ref="pl2961">P<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> of Treshenish</placeName>, or <placeName ref="pl2962">Fladda</placeName> &amp;c. &amp;c. before daylight the next morning — about
                    Seven oClock we were pretty close in with the isle of <placeName ref="pl0652">Staffa</placeName> — we then stood across towards <placeName ref="pl1078">Ulva</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl1080">Inch Kenneth</placeName>
                    &amp;c. &amp; again tacked to <placeName ref="pl0652">Staffa</placeName> — the
                    Surf was so high, that it was in vain to attempt to land on it, and we therefore
                    ran down to the island of <placeName ref="pl0651">Icolumkill</placeName> —
                    whence the vessel came to — we sailed to the town of <placeName ref="pl0651">Icolumkill</placeName> in the large boat — my expectations were not high —
                    &amp; so far from being disappointed, I was gratified particularly by a sight of
                    the ruins — I had no idea of their remaining in the state in which we found <pb n="35"/> them — they are indeed almost entirely unroofed — but most of the
                    outer walls remain &amp; within are found several curious and beautiful
                    specimens of architecture of different dates — for both the circular norman,
                    &amp; the pointed Gothic arches are found — &amp; one of two which appear to be
                    Saxon.</p>
                <p>— The Schoolmaster of <placeName ref="pl0651">Iona</placeName> came down to the
                    beach to us, &amp; attended us round the buildings as our Guide — &amp; we were
                    pleased to find both the <placeName ref="pl0975">Nunnery</placeName> &amp; the
                        <placeName ref="pl0978">Cathedral</placeName> no longer converted into Cow
                    houses — but on the contrary — every thing apparently in a state of preservation
                    — Owing to the attention of <persName ref="pe0232">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Pennant</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe0008">Sir Joseph
                        Banks</persName> — who first brought <placeName ref="pl0651">Iona</placeName> into notice<note type="editorial">Pennant describes the
                        ruins of Iona in <bibl><title ref="bi0008"><hi rend="italic">A Tour in
                                    Scotland and Voyage to the Hebrides 1772</hi></title></bibl>
                        (Chester: 1774), p.282. Finding that the Chapel of Iona was being used as a
                        cattle pen and consequently full of dung, Pennant employed one of the
                        islanders to clear it out. Pennnant's conservation efforts were only
                        temporarily effective however, with Sir John MacGregor Murray complaining in
                        his 1800 <ref target="0055.xml">Tour</ref> of the neglected state of the
                        site and surroundings.</note> — The Tomb stones are very numerous, &amp;
                    very many of them richly and skillfully carved — on many are <pb n="36"/> seen
                    recumbent figures of the Highland Chieftains — or the priests or Abbesses who
                    have been buried either at the <placeName ref="pl0975">Nunnery</placeName> or
                    the <placeName ref="pl0978">Cathedral</placeName> — on very many are to be found
                    inscriptions, most of which might probably be decyphered without much
                    trouble—</p>
                <p>Plain flat Stones, in general mark the burial places of the Kings but on that of
                    the French King may be traced a rich cross — &amp; at the head is a stone — the
                    date of which seems to be 900 — <del>but it is</del> of the crosses, there are
                    several remains, all of them handsome — particularly a large perfect one near
                    the <placeName ref="pl0978">Cathedral</placeName> — another close to it, has
                    perhaps been more wrought but it is mutilated — about 2 thirds of the way
                    between the <placeName ref="pl0975">Nunnery</placeName> &amp; the <placeName ref="pl0978">Cathedral</placeName> stands a perfect cross called <placeName ref="pl0981">M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi> Leans</placeName>. Erected
                    before the forfeiture of the <pb n="37"/> island in the Rebellion — It is very
                    thin &amp; tall &amp; appears to be a kind of hard slate — this also is
                    considerably ornamented — Besides the two buildings already mentioned, is the
                        <placeName ref="pl0976">chapel of S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi>
                        Owran</placeName> — &amp; several other small buildings, some connected with
                    &amp; others detached from the former — They are all fully described elsewhere
                    —</p>
                <p>In a bay about Two miles from the Town beautiful pebbles are picked up amongst
                    which the green steatites, which are said to be found in no other part of
                        <placeName ref="pl0777">G<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>Br<hi rend="superscript">n.</hi></placeName> — The children collect them,
                    &amp; bring them to you for sale, as soon as you land — <placeName ref="pl0651">Iona</placeName> boasts an inn, but it is not very capital in its
                    appearance —</p>
                <p>— The wind being rather more moderate — we steared for <placeName ref="pl0652">Staffa</placeName> — &amp; after once landing on it — took our boat, in
                    hopes <pb n="38"/> of being able to take it round to see the different caves
                    from the Sea — but the Swell &amp; the Surf were so great, that <add place="above">we</add> were compelled to return — we then walked to the top
                    of the Cliff above the caves — &amp; afterwards over the low basaltic columns
                    near the shore, until we reached the entrance into <placeName ref="pl1082">Fingals cave</placeName> — of which our expectations had been raised very
                    high, &amp; tho’ it exactly corresponded with what we had heard of it’s Grandeur
                    &amp; is similar to the interior of a Gothic Cathedral — yet the effect was even
                    more solemn &amp; grand than could have been conceived — the dashing of the
                    waves into the Cavern added to the whole — &amp; the sound of a gun fired at the
                    mouth of it, had an exceedingly fine effect — we now returned to our boat,
                    retracing our former steps over the bending columns <pb n="39"/> which form the
                        <placeName ref="pl1083">Ship rock</placeName> &amp; past a Cavern — our
                    vessel was lying to for us under the Lee of the island — we went on board &amp;
                    the wind blowing fresh from the NN. E. S. E — we soon passed the islands of
                        <placeName ref="pl2963">Lunga</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl2962">Fladda</placeName> &amp;c — &amp;c at 12 at night were abreast of the
                    island of <placeName ref="pl2707">Eigg</placeName> — in a short time the
                        <placeName ref="pl2707">point of Slate</placeName>, at the extremity of
                        <placeName ref="pl0715">Skye</placeName> was visible — we were at this time
                    running about nine miles an hour, with only our main sail topsail &amp; jib —
                    the gusts &amp; squalls from the Land obliging us to lower the fore sail &amp;
                    top gallant sail — we now lay to for a short time, waiting for the break of day
                    — as the wind continued to blow very fresh — and at five we came into <placeName ref="pl2964">Kilmoree Bay</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl2965">Loch
                        Slappen</placeName> — but finding no shelter from a S.S.E wind — were
                    obliged to run up to the extremity of the Loch, where we cast anchor in a
                        place<pb n="40"/> surrounded by immense rocks &amp; mountains, exceedingly
                    wild and picturesque — the mountains, are almost totally devoid of vegetation,
                    and seem impervious — in their forms they much resemble the <placeName ref="pl0639">Paps of Jura</placeName> — &amp; the whole scenery is not
                    unlike that of the <placeName ref="pl2147">Warfdale</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl0800">Cumberland</placeName> — the rugged summit <hi rend="superscript">x</hi><note type="authorial"><hi rend="superscript">x</hi>The Highest in the Islands</note>of <placeName ref="pl0840">Blavein</placeName> with the <placeName ref="pl2966">Skur na
                        Cullin</placeName> are just seen rising from the others. — We put the boat
                    out went on shore — &amp; having procured a guide from the house on the beach,
                    walked up the braes towards <persName ref="pe2159">M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi> Callister’s</persName> house — the <persName ref="pe2159">Laird
                        Strathaird</persName> — within half a mile of his house, we had the good
                    fortune to meet with the Laird, to whom we mentioned our desire of visiting his
                        <placeName ref="pl3078">cave</placeName><note type="editorial">The Spar Cave
                        of Strathaird, also known as Macalister's Cave after its proprietor, became
                        a popular tourist destination in the nineteenth century due to its striking
                        mineral formations. The cave came to widespread notice after an account of
                        it was written by Dr Kenneth MacLeay of Oban, whom the author of this tour
                        describes meeting above. The cave was later visited by Walter Scott, and it
                        forms the basis for one of the settings of his 1815 poem <hi rend="italic">The Lord of the Isles</hi>. Scott noted that the entrance to the cave
                        had been walled and gated by its proprietor to reduce further damage by
                        tourists. See Scott, <hi rend="italic">The Lord of the Isles</hi>, 2nd
                        ed.(Edinburgh: 1815), pp.362-64.</note> — he instantly turned back with us,
                    took us to his house, where he welcomed us with some white brandy — &amp; then
                    set out with us towards the cave. — we had been told that it was <pb n="41"/>
                    just five miles distant from the house whence we first started — but we had
                    walked nearly four miles to the Laird’s new built house &amp; it was at least
                    five more, to the Entrance in to the cave — in our way we had passed by a cairn
                    — &amp; also the remains of Danish Castle, it is circular — about 20 feet
                    diameter — the walls of it are very thick &amp; built entirely without any
                    cement — within a short distance from it, is seen another castle, called the
                        <placeName ref="pl3079">Princess’s castle</placeName>, being built by a
                    Danish Princess — it is said to have been exceedingly strong — There also in a
                    small hollow, with some trees in it and near to the coast, a part of a druidical
                    circle remaining — it does not appear to have been large — We were told by the
                    Laird, that there are numberless Danish remains, on his property — &amp; over
                    the whole island — <persName ref="pe2168">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                        Mc.Callister’s</persName> house stands immediately above the cave — so <pb n="42"/> much so, that when a large party were in the cave, their voices
                    were heard in the house above it — we called here &amp; the D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> gave us the welcome of the country — &amp; then
                    accompanied us down the rock to the sea where his boat was in readiness for us,
                    to row us round a large projecting rock to the entrance into the cave. — it may
                    be approached at very low Ebb, without a boat — but is very much better to take
                    the advantage of a boat — the avenue leading to the Entrance of the cave is
                    uncommonly Grand — on Each Side stand two vast projecting walls of the rock —
                    fifty or 60 feet high and perhaps 30 feet asunder — between these at high water,
                    the sea rolls in almost to the cavern’s mouth — this also is exceedingly fine —
                    it is rather narrow in proportion to the height &amp; is a little inclining to
                    the right — the roof is beautiful, with rough<pb n="43"/> coarse stalactytes
                    hanging from it — the water which constantly drops from the roof is beautifully
                    clear on entering you turn a little to the left, &amp; then proceed up <del unit="words" quantity="1"/>
                    <add place="above">a</add> roughish <del>steep</del>
                    <add place="above">ascent</add>, before you climb a height of about 30 feet
                    smooth &amp; slippery, covered with the whitest petrification resembling spar —
                    &amp; not unlike a <unclear reason="illegible">speit</unclear> of water
                    petrified in the act of falling — on the top of this you again proceed about 30
                    feet, before you descend a fall exactly similar to that which we had before
                    ascended at the bottom of which is a pool of the clearest water possible — this
                    is perhaps 18 feet diamater &amp; near the sides about 4 feet deep — the middle
                    is of course deeper — our guide waded thro’ this, <unclear reason="illegible">A.
                            <hi rend="superscript">sh.</hi></unclear> followed him &amp; when they
                    got to the opposite side the light from their candles shewed us the distant part
                    of the cave which as we were <pb n="44"/> told extends 46 feet beyond the two
                    pillars which stand at the narrow entrance into the inner part of it — one of
                    these pillars is particularly white &amp; beautiful, feathering in the most
                    elegant manner to the summit — from whence the petrifactions hang like icicles
                    of the utmost beauty — the whole Cave is adorned in like manner, in which is
                    full scope for the imagination to fancy forms &amp; figures of Every possible
                    variety — The whole is beautiful &amp; elegant quite beyond expression — &amp;
                    in our opinions was infinitely more striking than <placeName ref="pl0652">Staffa
                        Cave</placeName>, which we had seen the day before — This Cavern is said by
                        <persName ref="pe2168">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi> Callister</persName> to have been since
                    measured by <persName ref="pe2169">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                        Hooker</persName>, whose papers &amp; every note relating to it were lost on
                        <del>the</del> his return from <placeName ref="pl1478">Iceland</placeName> —
                    but according to the <persName ref="pe2168">Doctor’s</persName> account it is
                    870 feet in length — I should <pb n="45"/> imagine it to be from the beginning
                    of the avenue — it is probably 30 feet high and about 20 broad — but this varies
                    very considerably — for frequently it is very much higher — On our return from
                    the cave we again went to the <persName ref="pe2168">Doctor’s</persName> house
                    &amp; afterwards returned with the <persName ref="pe2159">Laird</persName> to
                    his House — Here he had Tea ready for us with plentiful dish of fine Trout just
                    caught for us — our bread was barley &amp; wheaten cakes very thin &amp;
                    excellent — His daughter was introduced to us — it was our intention to have
                    gone forward immediately to our vessel — but it was growing late &amp; our
                    friend declared the could not think of letting us depart at such an hour as Ten
                    oClock — when the road we had to travel was exceedingly rough &amp; bad — our
                        Cap<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> &amp; <persName ref="pe2171">Thomas</persName> returned with the guide — &amp; we remained with
                        <persName ref="pe2159">Strathaird</persName> — no sooner was Tea over, than
                        <persName ref="pe2172">Miss. M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>
                        Callister</persName> retired — &amp; the Toddy <pb n="46"/> was brought in,
                    of which there was no scarcity — In the morning, we had a capital breakfast with
                    eggs, Trout. &amp;c — The latter are very plentiful in all the small Lakes,
                    &amp; are caught just as occasion may require — they are large &amp; excellent —
                    Besides these — Codfish, whiting, Haddock, Skate &amp;c are caught in great
                    quantities — &amp; no Loch affords greater supplies of herrings — The mutton was
                    we were told, very capital — <persName ref="pe2159">Strathaird</persName> is the
                    only person now in <placeName ref="pl0715">Skye</placeName> who continues to
                    have the wild red deer in his mountains. The small black cattle, of which large
                    quantities are fed on these mountains are famous — &amp; we saw at <persName ref="pe2168">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>Callisters</persName> two dozen goats coming down in the evening to
                    be milked. The milk of these was we were told exceedingly rich, so also is that
                    of their cows, altho’ the quantity they give is but small — Potatoes they have
                    in abundance — but very little corn of any sort is sown — generally <pb n="47"/>
                    barely <add place="above">a</add> sufficient quantity of oats for their own
                    private consumption — Pasturage is what they chiefly attend to — &amp; yet
                        <persName ref="pe2159">Strathaird</persName> told us that he could any day
                    bring out to the field between one &amp; 200 men — He seems to be much liked by
                    his tenantry — &amp; has to us the appearance of one who justly deserved to be
                    so —</p>
                <p>He was going to send a runner to a Post office several miles distant for his
                    letters &amp; papers — which he has twice a week — &amp; he offered to send my
                    letter by the same man — after having written it — we prepared to take leave
                    notwithstanding his pressing invitation to remain a few days with him — He was
                    going to send eight men with Criels to <placeName ref="pl2967">Broadford</placeName> to carry back for him a hogshead of wine — which had
                    been two years there — he therefore walked with <add place="above">us</add> to
                    the point where our vessel lay — &amp; after going on board, crossed over the
                    ferry with his men, and proceeded with them — After putting him on shore — we
                    sailed with an idea of going to <placeName ref="pl2465">Dun Skye</placeName>
                    <pb n="48"/> but the wind being against us, we determined to explore some of the
                    numberless caverns on the coast of <placeName ref="pl0844">Strathaird</placeName> — we entered many of them — They were not very
                    large, but we found some beautiful petrifactions — a few of them little inferior
                    in whiteness or beauty to those of the large cave — but by no means bearing any
                    comparison with it — The whole of the coast down to the very point is perforated
                    with caverns — of which few have ever been explored — and are of course unknown
                    — The large cave itself was not discovered until two years &amp; a half ago —
                    when the <persName ref="pe2159">Laird</persName> being desirous of carrying to
                    his friends in <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName> a few specimens of
                    the fossils on his coast, went with two of his men to the shore for
                        th<del>at</del><add place="above">e</add> purpose<add place="opposite">of
                        picking up some</add>, when one of them going to the entrance of the cave as
                    far as the day light w<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> allow him <del>fancied he
                        could</del> perceived something <pb n="49"/> very white &amp; beautiful over
                    his head &amp; wished to explore further — but as there were no lights to be had
                    — the <persName ref="pe2159">Laird</persName> insisted on his returning until he
                    should procure some — in a day or two — he went with a party of friends — each
                    carrying a candle — &amp; to their surprise, discovered the who most amazing
                    Cavern, that has yet been found out in any part whatever — <del>A person to whom
                        an extraordinary cave</del><note type="authorial">an officer in the navy who
                        had seen a remarkable cave of great note in the <placeName ref="pl1723">Mediterranean</placeName> declared that it bore no comparison to this
                        —</note></p>
                <p>— Late in the evening <persName ref="pe2159">Strathaird</persName> came to us —
                    on his return from <placeName ref="pl2967">Broadford</placeName> — &amp; after
                    staying with us a short time — took his leave of us — we found in him all that
                    hospitality for which the islands are celebrated of which he gave us a further
                    proof the next morning — when seeing us under weigh in the Loch — he sent his
                    boat to us, with a cheese, a quantity of fresh butter, &amp; some cream — a most
                    acceptable present to sailors.</p>
                <p><pb n="50"/>
                July 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> —</p>
                <p>This morning, as we were tacking across to work out of <placeName ref="pl2965">Loch Sleppin</placeName>, we came near to <placeName ref="pl2465">Dun
                        Skye</placeName>, of which <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian</persName> makes
                    mention — &amp; we went on shore to see the ruins of the castle &amp; drawbridge
                    connecting it with the range of adjoining rocks — It is built on a solid rock
                    nearly a square — &amp; perpendicular on every side — a very high Sea may
                    perhaps occasionally dash between it &amp; the main land — but not often — it is
                    however a place very strong by nature — The walls of the castle are not
                    considerable <add place="above">nor are they thick —</add> they appear to have
                    been square, &amp; are built with lime — The mountains on the opposite coast of
                    the Loch, are very wild &amp; rugged, the forms of some of them particularly
                        <placeName ref="pl0840">Blavein</placeName> is very fine — &amp; they are
                    equally so after you clear the <placeName ref="pl0844">aird of
                        Strath</placeName> &amp; open upon <placeName ref="pl2968">Loch
                        Scavig</placeName> — Close to this Loch, is a fresh water Lake <pb n="51"/>
                    that from the appearance of the high bold Rocks that Environ it, must be
                    exceedingly well worth a visit — but we had not an opportunity of going to see
                    it — The harbour of <placeName ref="pl2968">Scavig</placeName> not being good —
                    &amp; the wind blowing into it — we steered for <placeName ref="pl0653">Canna</placeName>, passing a great part of the Northern Coast of <placeName ref="pl0718">Rum</placeName> — the mountains of which island are very lofty
                    &amp; pointed — The whole of it, as far as we could see appeared rocky, &amp;
                    unfruitful — At nine oClock in the evening when we were about four miles distant
                    from <placeName ref="pl0653">Canna</placeName> &amp; perhaps from <add place="above"><placeName ref="pl0718">Rum.</placeName> 1.</add> we saw a
                    whale which rose from the sea repeatedly &amp; sometimes very near to our
                    vessel, but we were not quick enough with our guns, to get a shot at him — At
                    half past eleven we cast anchor in the harbour of <placeName ref="pl0653">Canna</placeName> — under <placeName ref="pl2969">Compass
                        Hill</placeName>,<pb n="52"/> so called, because a compass when placed on a
                    certain spot on the summit of the hill, turns immediately from N. to S. — we
                    carried a small compass up with us early in the morning &amp; found this to be
                    the case, altho’ at the distance of about a foot, it did not vary in the least
                    —</p>
                <p>We had heard of the beauty of the Pebbles found on the coast of <placeName ref="pl0718">Rum</placeName> — we therefore took the boat &amp; crossed
                    over, to that island, about four miles distant — There is only one small spot
                    where it is possible to land — &amp; there we found the surf so excessively
                    high, that it was rather dangerous &amp; difficult to land we threw out a
                    longrope to a crowd of men &amp; women who came down to the beach to us — &amp;
                    a number of them, drew our boat high up on the shore — We found a number of
                    Pebbles, chiefly dark green — but some of agate — &amp; the people of the island
                    had others which they had collected from a spot about half a mile to the South,
                    where the pebbles are more plentiful — but <pb n="53"/> we did not see any that
                    were very beautiful or very curious — we now prepared to leave the shore — but
                    it was high water — &amp; and the surf dashed in with great violence — after
                    some time a great number collected round the boat — &amp; two of them got in —
                    when watching their opportunity — they launched the boat off into the surf &amp;
                    continued to bring it alongside of a rock — from which we all got in as quick as
                    we could — &amp; soon were clear out from the rocks — the wind was favourable
                    &amp;. we soon reached our vessel —</p>
                <p>At 5. in the evening we got under weigh — with an idea of going to <placeName ref="pl0665">Dunvegan</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl0715">Skye</placeName> — but in the morning we found that the wind had shifted a
                    little round to N. E — &amp; we agreed to go to <placeName ref="pl0853">North
                        Uist</placeName> — by some mistake, we came to the entrance into <placeName ref="pl2970">Loch Skiport</placeName> before we found out our mistake — The
                    high mountain of <placeName ref="pl2971">Hecla</placeName> had been mistaken for
                    that above <placeName ref="pl2446">loch Na Maddy</placeName><note type="authorial">Lake of the Two Dogs so called, from two rocks at the S.
                        Entrance —</note> — but the Loch itself is narrow with several<pb n="54"/>
                    islands &amp; points of land running into it — a little to the North of it a
                    wide bay opens, with low lands all around it &amp; a number of islands
                    interspersed in it — At the back of which rises a mountain in <placeName ref="pl2445">Benbecula</placeName> part of which is seen laying at the North
                    extremity of the Bay. — The island of <placeName ref="pl2972"><unclear reason="illegible">luia</unclear></placeName> lays extended almost at
                    the Entrance — &amp; beyond this again to the North is the high land of
                        <placeName ref="pl0853">North Uist</placeName> for which <placeName ref="pl2971">Hecla</placeName> had been mistaken — we coasted slowly along
                        <placeName ref="pl0853">North Uist</placeName>, which is exceedingly rocky
                    &amp; barren — without any pasturage even for sheep — It was quite calm, &amp;
                    we could not reach <placeName ref="pl2446">Loch Na Maddy</placeName> before the
                    next evening at six oClock — we put in here, for the purpose of getting
                    provisions, having been <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" quantity="1"/> that
                    the public house at <placeName ref="pl2446">Loch na Maddy</placeName> afforded a
                    shop where everything was to be had — on the contrary — we could <pb n="55"/>
                    procure nothing. <persName ref="pe2173">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                        Dingwall</persName> the Landlord was in <persName ref="pl0854">South
                        Uist</persName> with the Local Militia — his wife was either shy of us, or
                    unwilling to accommodate us — we were not able to buy butter, eggs, or in fact
                    any thing. excepting a sheep if we chose to wait until the next day for it — for
                    it was not convenient to let us have it, that same evening — We left this famous
                    inn at <placeName ref="pl2446">Loch na Maddy</placeName>, where nothing eatable
                    was to be found, &amp; immediately went on board our vessel &amp; weighed anchor
                    — the tide was against us, &amp; just as we made a tack close to the rocky
                    island at the entrance of the bay — the breeze quite failed &amp; as the vessel
                    would not answer the helm, we were obliged to wear her to save us from the rock,
                    which was done just in time — we now bore up again for our former station &amp;
                    cast anchor one more in <placeName ref="pl2446">Loch na Maddy</placeName> — a
                    harbour, affording as <pb n="56"/> little to praise either for its outward
                    appearance, or it’s means of sustenance as any place we ever saw — the Land is
                    poor &amp; miserable — &amp; even the sea gives nothing but the Seathe, one of
                    the poorest sort of fish — At a short distance from the head of the Lake, there
                    is capital fishing for Trout in the fresh water — numbers of which were brought
                    home by a party, who had gone out returned from a day’s excursion into the
                    interior — They had a vessel which they brought from <placeName ref="pl2973">Lynmouth</placeName> in the <placeName ref="pl2974">Bristol
                        Channel</placeName> — &amp; like ourselves were wind bound in <placeName ref="pl2446">Loch na maddy</placeName> — In the morning our hostess was in
                    better humour, for she sent a boat alongside of us, with a lamb alive — &amp; an
                    offer of a pint of Whiskey — but we in turn refused it — Before we were able to
                    set sail — we bought from her two Scotch pints <pb n="57"/> which to our
                    knowledge she diluted plentifully with water, &amp; charged us 15 shillings —
                    after all it proved quite different from what the Captain had tasted for us —
                    the one being Highland whiskey — the other Greenock whiskey &amp; water —
                    excessively bad — about 3 oClock. P. M. we were heartily glad to leave
                        <placeName ref="pl2446">Loch na maddy</placeName> — we had a pleasant light
                    breeze which carried us past the entrance of the sound of <placeName ref="pl0954">Harris</placeName>, along the miserable, rocky &amp; barren
                    coast — Of that island &amp; the <placeName ref="pl0712">Lewis</placeName> —
                    each equally bad — soon after we passed <placeName ref="pl2975">Scalpa</placeName> or the <placeName ref="pl2975">Glass-isle</placeName>,
                    the light was put up in the light House, which serves as a guide to vessels
                    thro’ this part of the channel which is rendered in many places dangerous by
                    rocks, unless you steer between the <placeName ref="pl2976">Glass</placeName>
                    <pb n="58"/> Light house, &amp; the <placeName ref="pl2977">chiant
                        Isles</placeName> — Early the morning following, we landed at <placeName ref="pl2914">Stornaway</placeName>, a considerable Town — which is the
                    metropolis of <placeName ref="pl2473">the long island</placeName> — &amp; is a
                    place much resorted to by vessels which frequent these northern Seas. — it
                    contains nearly 2,000 inhabitants<note type="authorial">The last parochial
                        estimate was 1800</note> — Some years ago the fishery was of importance —
                    but of late years it has failed — &amp; at present there is little or no trade
                    carried on — The house are in general very good — at least by comparison with
                    what we have seen — but in Canvas town, or the new Town, built at the E.
                    extremity of the old — nothing but the low huts are seen — such as we met with
                    every where in the islands — these are built around a square — in a double row —
                    the avenues thro’ which are dignified by the Title of Duke Street &amp;c. —</p>
                <p><pb n="59"/>
                They resemble a Hottentot village more than a British Town — &amp; the
                    inhabitants themselves are not much unlike in costume or appearance — the women
                    who seem much more numerous than the men — wear their hair very long &amp; loose
                    — their features are broad &amp; ugly — they carry immense weights on their
                    backs, generally in criles — a sort of panier — which is carried by a band of
                    straw that crosses their chest <del unit="words" quantity="3"/> They bend very
                    much forward — so that the lower part of the panier rest upon the bottom of the
                    back — but the chief weight is supported from the chest — In these criles they
                    carry their turf, or other burdens — &amp; go on barefooted — drudging like
                    slaves — an enormous <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/> cap,
                    something similar to the Irish cap — &amp; a square of coarse plaid thrown over
                    the shoulders, &amp; fastened in front with an antique broach, bespeaks a person
                        <pb n="60"/> above the lower order — with the men the ancient distinction of
                    the highland dress seems laid aside — occasionally you see a tartan short coat
                    or jacket — &amp; the trowsers which are worn are frequently of the Plaid — but
                    nothing like the Kelt is seen in the islands. Even the bonnet is rare — The
                    language also is on the decline — for <del unit="words" quantity="2"/> few are
                    met with on the coast who cannot speak English &amp; the coast is almost the
                    only part inhabited — we were told by a tradesman in <placeName ref="pl2914">Stornaway</placeName> who rents the land from <persName ref="pe2170">L<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> Seaforth</persName> at £3.10 — the acre —
                    that in the whole island of <placeName ref="pl0712">Lewis</placeName> you cannot
                    find one acre of arable land, which is out of view of the sea — &amp; yet
                        <placeName ref="pl0712">Lewis</placeName> is considered a very fertile
                    island — the rent now received for it is 7,000 — &amp; is shortly to be raised —
                        <pb n="61"/> This is exclusive of the Kelp, which <persName ref="pe2170">L<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> Seaforth</persName> keeps entirely to
                    himself — &amp; of which, last year he sold in <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> 800 Ton at £<hi rend="underline">15</hi>—p<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Ton — The expences of manufacturing the kelp
                    amounted to 1.800 — so that the clear produce was £<hi rend="underline">10.200</hi> —
                <note type="authorial">Rent of <placeName ref="pl0712">Lewis</placeName> —— 7.000.
                    <lb/>Deduct for Tacksman <hi rend="underline">—500–</hi>
                    <lb/> Kelp ————6.500 <lb/>
                    <hi rend="underline">10.200</hi>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="underline">16—700</hi>
                    <p>The same person is Tacksman to <placeName ref="pl0853">North</placeName>
                        &amp; <placeName ref="pl0854">South Uist</placeName> — &amp; almost the
                        whole of the <placeName ref="pl2473">long island</placeName> — &amp; of
                        course can only come occasionally to <placeName ref="pl0712">Lewis</placeName>.</p></note></p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl2978">Seaforth Lodge</placeName> where his Lordship house — is
                    a poor looking white-washed house, on a hill at the back of <placeName ref="pl2914">Stornaway</placeName> — it looks very bleak, not a tree near it
                    — &amp; the Ground quite wild &amp; uncultivated.</p>
                <p>— <persName ref="pe2170">L<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> Seaforth</persName><note type="authorial">N— By a person whom we took on board to go back to
                            <placeName ref="pl0729">Mull</placeName> — &amp; who had been employed
                        all the summer to superintend &amp; teach the manufacture of Kelp in the
                            <placeName ref="pl0712">Lewis</placeName> — we learned that all
                            <persName ref="pe2170">L<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi>
                            Seaforths</persName> tenants make the kelp which grows on their several
                        farms — &amp; when they bring it to the vessel appointed to take it receive
                        from <persName ref="pe2170">L<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> S.</persName>
                        £3— for every ton manufactured — so that 500 Tons would cost his L<hi rend="superscript">dp</hi> £<hi rend="underline">2,400</hi> of which he
                        sells again for £15 — a Ton—</note> had arrived in a cutter, about a week
                    before us — &amp; had made known his orders that a certain number of his Tenants
                    son would be required within a stated time as recruits for his regiments — Those
                    farmers who have sons of age for the army are compelled to send them — &amp;
                    dare not refuse to part with those whom <pb n="62"/>
                    <persName ref="pe2170">L<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> S.—</persName> may fix
                    upon — notwithstanding any inconvenience or mortification it may produce — on
                    such a tenure they hold their farms –––––</p>
                <p>We had great difficulty in procuring provisions even at <placeName ref="pl2914">Stornaway</placeName> — There are indeed two or three butchers — but they
                    seldom if ever kill their own meat — if they should chance to kill a beeve,
                    which was the case the day before we arrived — this event is made known, &amp;
                    it is generally portioned out to buyers before the beast is killed — For mutton
                    — each person who can afford to eat it — keeps his own sheep — &amp; when he
                    intends to regale his family — one is taken from the flock, &amp; the butcher
                    sent for — but it never happens, that meat is kept for public sale — &amp;
                    probably the poor do not know the taste of animal food — They have plenty <pb n="63"/>of fish — The Ling of which great quantities are salted &amp; dried
                    — Cod fish — Skates — congar eels — &amp;<hi rend="underline">c</hi> &amp;<hi rend="underline">c</hi> not far from <placeName ref="pl2914">Stornaway</placeName> we hailed a fishing boat from whom we bought two of
                    an excellent sort of fish — one a lythe — the other a silver eye — a fish not
                    unlike in colour or shape to the gold fish; — its flesh was exceeding white firm
                    &amp; sweet — we bought also a large ling about 15 lb<hi rend="superscript">s</hi> — <del rend="overstrike">two</del> codfish of equal weight — these
                    two smaller fish &amp; a congar eel for two shillings — &amp; <sic>one of
                        sailors</sic> gave a quid of tobacco for another eel ––––– At the <placeName ref="pl2914">Town of Stornaway</placeName> fish was nearly as cheap fish was
                    nearly as cheap — for a codfish &amp; two skates, weighing in all upwards of
                        £<hi rend="underline">30</hi>— <add place="above">we</add> were only charged
                        10<hi rend="italic">d</hi>––––– We were in hopes of getting good whiskey in
                        <placeName ref="pl2914">Stornaway</placeName> — we had enquired, &amp;
                    tasted in vain at every island which we touched at — but excepting at <placeName ref="pl0719">Arran</placeName>, where it was famous <pb n="64"/> &amp; at
                        <placeName ref="pl2957">Lunga</placeName> at the Factors — we could get no
                    good whiskey at all — At <placeName ref="pl2914">Stornaway</placeName> it was
                    the same — all the private Stills are prohibited — &amp; the good whiskey may
                    perhaps yet be made in secret — a stranger has little chance of finding it out —
                    There is a custom House — &amp; a Revenue Cutter stationed here — &amp; we were
                    told that the Excise officers were very strict &amp; frequent in their search
                    ––––– We were at last supplied with a few gallons, as a favour, at 15 shillings
                    the gallon — but it was quite new &amp; raw — This we got on board — &amp; in
                    the morning we set sail from <placeName ref="pl2914">Stornaway</placeName> on
                    our return to <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName> — <persName ref="pe2170">Lord Seaforth</persName> went out just before us in a cutter to the
                    northward on his way to the <placeName ref="pl2979">Flannen isles</placeName>,
                    which belong to him — they lay on the North West coast of the <placeName ref="pl0712">Lewis</placeName> –––––</p>
                <p><pb n="65."/>
                As we sailed along — we saw the whole extent of the N.W. coast of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> from the <placeName ref="pl0713">Cape
                        Wrath</placeName> the most Northern point — down past <placeName ref="pl0668">Loch Broom</placeName> &amp;c <hi rend="superscript">&amp;c.</hi> to the South of <unclear reason="illegible"><placeName ref="pl2980">Ruhe</placeName></unclear> the mountains seem uncommonly
                    Grand — in form &amp; size — The coast <placeName ref="pl0715">Skye</placeName>
                    also as we approached it, was exceedingly fine — the <placeName ref="pl2977">isles of Chiant</placeName> &amp; the line of dangerous Rocks &amp; small
                    isles which lay between them &amp; <placeName ref="pl0715">the isle of
                        Skye</placeName>, were to the South <add place="above">&amp; W.</add> of us
                    — We entered the narrow sound between <placeName ref="pl2981">Rona</placeName>
                    &amp; <placeName ref="pl0952">Rassay</placeName> islands, &amp; <placeName ref="pl0715">Skye</placeName> — the former is a small island very rocky
                    &amp; barren — not any fertile land is visible from the S.W. coast of it — &amp;
                    the adjoining <placeName ref="pl0952">Rassa</placeName> is scarcely better until
                    you approach <placeName ref="pl2982">the Lairds House</placeName> fronting the
                    South — it stands in a most beautiful situation with a number of trees near it —
                    &amp; a steep mountain to skreen off the N. winds at the back of it — it is by
                    much the most inviting situation we had yet seen in the islands — <placeName ref="pl0952">Rassa</placeName> is a small island &amp; tho' for the most
                    part <pb n="66"/> rugged &amp; unfruitful — yet possesses some very good land —
                    opposite to it, is a<del rend="overstrike">n</del>
                    <add place="above">large</add> extent of arable land on the mountainous coast of
                        <placeName ref="pl0715">Skye</placeName> which also <sic>form</sic> part of
                    the property of <persName ref="pe2174">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                        Macleod</persName> the Laird of <placeName ref="pl0952">Rassa</placeName> —
                    he is encircled by <persName ref="pe1619"><add place="above">L.</add> M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>Donald</persName> the proprietor of the
                    greatest part of <placeName ref="pl0715">Skye</placeName> ––––– much of the
                    coast <add place="above">of <placeName ref="pl0715">Skye</placeName></add> to
                    the N. abounds with basaltic columns, many of them uncommonly regular perhaps
                    not less so than <placeName ref="pl0652">Staffa</placeName>, but there is no
                    cave ––––– Above these is a vast mountain the shape of which is fine — &amp;
                    from it not very far the summit — stands out a singular pillar of Rock quite
                    detached &amp; separate from the mountain —<note type="editorial"><placeName ref="pl3080">The Old Man of Storr</placeName></note></p>
                <p>— As you trace the range of mountains from hence to the interior — they appear
                    particularly fine — those at the head of <placeName ref="pl2965">Loch
                        Sleppin</placeName> are seen rising from the East, &amp; <placeName ref="pl0840">Blavein</placeName> one of the <placeName ref="pl0841">Cuellein
                        Hills</placeName> is also seen –––––</p>
                <p>— At the End of <placeName ref="pl0952">Rassa</placeName>, &amp; between it &amp;
                        <placeName ref="pl2983">Scarba</placeName><note type="editorial">Here and
                        below, the author appears to confuse the name of the island of <placeName ref="pl2983">Scalpay</placeName>, between Raasay and Skye, with that of
                            <placeName ref="pl2956">Scarba</placeName>, north of Jura.</note> is the
                    sound, thro' which <pb n="67"/> vessels pass for the Southward — the narrow
                    channel between <placeName ref="pl2983">Scarba</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl0715">Skye</placeName> is shoal &amp; dangerous from the sandbanks —
                    we saw vessels lying there at the point of <placeName ref="pl2983">the isle of
                        Scarba</placeName> — where is a great herring fishery — we learned from a
                    boat belonging to one of them — that each boat was then <sic>taken</sic> about 3
                    barrels daily — altho' the season was scarcely begun ––––– <placeName ref="pl2983">Scarba</placeName> is not nearly so long as <placeName ref="pl0952">Rassa</placeName>, but it is broader &amp; higher — &amp; very
                    much more green — near to it, is another <add place="above">small</add> green
                    isle called <placeName ref="pl2984">Pabba</placeName> — we were told that the
                    immense number of Rats upon it, had driven off every inhabitant — &amp; that as
                    soon as the corn was ripe, it was necessary to carry it away immediately — there
                    are also many small islets &amp; rocks in this channel, which render it too
                    dangerous to <add place="above">be</add> attempted in the dark — &amp; the
                    entrance by <placeName ref="pl3081">Castle <unclear reason="illegible">Moylast</unclear></placeName><note type="editorial">Probably a
                        reference to Caisteal Maol at the entrance to Loch Alsh. The source of the
                        author's unusual rendering of this place name is unknown.</note> is also
                    exceedingly narrow<note type="authorial">The ruins of the Square Tower which
                        comprised <placeName ref="pl3081">the Castle of Moylast</placeName> are
                        inconsiderable — the rock on which they stand close to the sea, is by no
                        means high — but yet in some points it adds much to the beauty of the
                        scenery</note> — Here also the tide sets in with great force not less than
                    nine miles an hour <pb n="68"/>so that unless the wind is very favorable &amp;
                    blowing strong, it is not possible to make head against it. —<note type="authorial">The whole of which thro' the narrows down to the very point
                        of <placeName ref="pl0655">Slate</placeName> is exceedingly fine —
                        Especially above <placeName ref="pl0721">Glenelg</placeName> &amp;
                            <placeName ref="pl0678">Loch Hourn</placeName> — altho the views about
                            <placeName ref="pl3082">Caliach Stone</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl3081">Castle Moylast</placeName>, are very little inferior if at
                        all ––––– <placeName ref="pl0655">The point of Slate</placeName> is not
                        picturesque in itself — but near <placeName ref="pl3083">Castle
                            Knock</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl0679"><unclear>Isle
                                Aranso</unclear></placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl2476">Armydel</placeName>, it appears fertile &amp; good. <placeName ref="pl3083">Castle Knock</placeName> is rather finely situated on an
                        abrupt Rock above the sea but it is not large — most of the square towers or
                        Castles on the Scotch coast are very much alike –––––</note>
                </p>
                <p>In the narrows near <placeName ref="pl3082">Caliach Stone</placeName> where the
                    gut takes a sharp turn to the left, opposite to the entrance to <placeName ref="pl3084">Loch Duich</placeName> — two vessels were lost last year owing
                    to the wind failing them, &amp; the current of the tide bearing them down upon
                    the rocks — The passage thro' these narrows is generally more tedious than we
                    found it — altho' we were compelled to row our vessel up to <placeName ref="pl3082">Caliach Stone</placeName> &amp; there anchor until the morning
                    came, &amp; the tide turned in our favour — Then we were <hi rend="superscript">+</hi><note type="authorial">+ The Mountains on each side obstruct the wind
                        — occasionally it comes down thro the hollows in squalls — &amp; the wind
                        will be found to blow in almost every point of the compass — as you pass
                        along — </note> compelled to tow the vessel a very considerable distance, in
                    order to keep her head steady — Even this was not sufficient when we came
                    opposite to <placeName ref="pl0721">Glenelg</placeName> where it widens into a
                    bay — the eddier took us, &amp; carried us completely round about, three or four
                    times, with some rapidity — At length the tide carried us beyond the eddies,
                    &amp; we glided gently down, fully expecting that we should be <pb n="69"/>
                    obliged to put into <placeName ref="pl0679">Isle alornso</placeName> harbour on
                    the coast of <placeName ref="pl0715">Skye</placeName>, &amp; there wait until
                    the return of the Tide — Fortunately a light breeze sprang up, &amp; carried us
                    onward, till we came beyond the force of the stream — we had now some hopes, as
                    the breeze freshened that we might reach <placeName ref="pl0681">Tobermory</placeName> by break of day &amp; be able to land at <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName> about 3 or 4 oClock P.M — We had arrived off
                    the <placeName ref="pl0655">point of Slate</placeName> &amp; were fast nearing
                    upon <placeName ref="pl2707">Eigg</placeName> — when we went to bed at eleven
                    oClock — at 12 — The wind fell, &amp; it became quite calm — So that in the
                    morning when we hoped to have seen <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName> we
                    found ourselves precisely in the same spot, where we had seen the vessel the
                    night before –––––<note type="authorial"><placeName ref="pl2195">the Sound of
                            Mull</placeName></note></p>
                <p>It was now proposed to <add place="above">go on shore &amp;</add> see the <hi rend="superscript">x</hi><placeName ref="pl3085">Cave of
                        Eigg</placeName><note type="authorial">on the <del rend="overstrike">N.</del>E coast of <placeName ref="pl2707">Eigg</placeName> are several
                        caves — this celebrated one is the most Eastward, very small at the
                        Entrance, not 5 feet perhaps — it is within a few yards of the shore
                        —</note> — where the inhabitants of the isle were once suffocated by
                        <persName ref="pe2181">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Leod</persName> — of
                    which deed some of the bones in the cavern now bear witness<note type="editorial">During their long running feud with the Macdonalds, the
                        Macleods of Dunvegan and Harris murdered up to four hundred people on the
                        island of Eigg in the sixteenth century. Seeking retribution for the recent
                        mistreatment of some of their clansmen by the Macdonalds, a party of
                        Macleods landed on Eigg, causing the inhabitants of the island to take
                        refuge in a cave. On discovering the hiding place, they blocked the entrance
                        to the cave and started a fire, suffocating those inside. Tourists including
                        Hugh Miller and Walter Scott later visited the cave, and large numbers of
                        bones were discovered there as recently as 2016.</note> — but at the moment
                    we had decided a light breeze again rose — &amp; we <pb n="70"/>were determined
                    to avail ourselves of it — It carried us a short way &amp; again slackened —
                    &amp; in this way continued until we passed <placeName ref="pl2708">the isle of
                        Muck</placeName> — &amp; then it failed entirely</p>
                <p>— The Tide making against us, we were under the necessity of running into a small
                    creek called Carregadil Bay,<note type="editorial">Not identified. One of many
                        inlets on the north side of the <placeName ref="pl0680">Ardnamurchan</placeName> Peninsula.</note> &amp; there anchoring —
                        <persName ref="pe2183">Aston</persName> &amp; I went on shore — and walked
                    across to <placeName ref="pl3095">Killichoan</placeName> about 3 English miles —
                    the path is not very good, &amp; in some part rather difficult to trace but a
                    man from the village of <placeName ref="pl3094">Achnahay</placeName><note type="authorial">consisting of a dozen huts built in the rude way of the
                        country with the 4 angles, rounded off — all detached from one another —
                    </note> about half a mile from the coast, perceiving <sic>that were
                        strangers</sic>, ran after us, &amp; conducted us, until we came to a hill
                    from whence some of the houses in <placeName ref="pl3095">Killichoan</placeName>
                    were to be seen — with the <placeName ref="pl2195">Sound of Mull</placeName>
                    &amp; the entrance into <placeName ref="pl0681">Tobermory</placeName> on the
                    opposite side — Here he told us in broken <sic>us</sic>, that he must go back —
                    we thanked him for his trouble &amp; offered him money, which he received
                    reluctantly — saying that he did not follow us for that — he then asked us <pb n="71"/>our names — having already enquired where we came from, &amp;
                    whither we were going — we satisfied him, &amp; bid him good evening — We soon
                    found the want of him for not thinking of our road we lost the track &amp; came
                    to a boggy marsh — knowing however the bearings of the place — we soon reach
                        <placeName ref="pl3095">Killichoan</placeName> — where there is a
                    considerable village with an excellent house for the manse in a very fine
                    situation — commanding a view of <placeName ref="pl2195">the sound of
                        Mull</placeName>, up as far as <placeName ref="pl0682">the Bay of
                        Arros</placeName> — &amp; a clear view of <placeName ref="pl2198">Ben
                        More</placeName> which is seen almost from it's base –––––</p>
                <p>At the public House, the people could not speak English, but fortunately we met
                    with a person at the door who kindly became our interpreter, &amp; came in with
                    us — we had hot oaten cakes, with excellent cheese &amp; butter — &amp; capital
                    Farintosh Whiskey. — we now agreed with 2 men to row us across <placeName ref="pl2195">the Sound</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0681">Tobermory</placeName>
                    <pb n="72"/> — six miles — for altho' the sea is only 3 miles across — yet as
                        <placeName ref="pl0681">T.</placeName> lays to the Eastward of <placeName ref="pl3095">Killichoan</placeName> the remaining distance is made out in
                    coasting along the shore before you Turn <placeName ref="pl3096">the Priest's
                        point</placeName> into <placeName ref="pl0681">the bay of
                        Tobermory</placeName><note type="authorial">for this the charge is 5
                        shillings</note> — which is a most excellent harbour — shut in from the Sea
                    by a long island — which leaves only one entrance not very broad — but quite
                    safe — The water is <add place="above">in general</add> very deep — &amp; the
                    Bay capable of holding any vessels. — The inn kept by <persName ref="pe2182">Hugh M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>Leane</persName> is very comfortable
                    ––––– At half past Ten our vessel came into the Bay &amp; fired a signal for us
                    — They weighed anchor soon after 8 oClock the evening before — but the Tide made
                    against them — &amp; it was calm so that they could not reach the harbour sooner
                    — She <add place="above">now</add> hove to, &amp; we went on board — the breeze
                    then blowing finely for us — we soon sailed down the <placeName ref="pl2195">Sound of Mull</placeName>, &amp; at 4. P.M. once more anchor<unclear reason="illegible">ing</unclear> in the <placeName ref="pl1076">Bay of
                        Oban</placeName> –––––</p>
                <p><pb n="73"/>
                From <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1074">Tynuilt</placeName>
                    <lb/>12. Miles —</p>
                <p>It is 1 mile from <placeName ref="pl1249">Bunawe</placeName> — Iron works
                        <unclear reason="illegible">—</unclear> Home to the <placeName ref="pl2188">memory</placeName> of <persName ref="pe1435">Nelson</persName> –––––</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>