<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0059">
    <teiHeader type="s">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Charlotte Malkin, Journal of travels in Scotland 1814
                    <date>1814</date></title>
                <author>Charlotte Malkin</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Edited with an Introduction by Alex Deans</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
                <date when="1814"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>London</settlement>
                        <repository>British Library</repository>
                        <idno>ADD MS 85321</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents> </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <p/>
            </abstract>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p><pb n="f.1r"/> On Saturday July 2<hi rend="superscript">nd.</hi> 1814 — <persName ref="pe0002">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Malkin</persName>, <persName ref="pe0030">Benjamin</persName>, <persName ref="pe0071">Miss
                        Hall</persName> &amp; myself left our houses at <placeName ref="pl3272">Bury
                            S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Edmunds</placeName> with an intention of
                    making a Summer excursion to the <placeName ref="pl0711">Highlands of
                        Scotland</placeName>. We proceeded this day as far as <placeName ref="pl3273">Grantham</placeName> where we slept. — We found nothing that
                    much pleased or interested us in this day's journey, except the town of
                        <placeName ref="pl0790">Stamford</placeName> which we pressed through, which
                    is an handsome country town, well situated, and near to which is <placeName ref="pl0764">Burleigh</placeName>, the seat of the <persName ref="pe0096">Marquis of Exeter</persName>. —</p>
                <p>Sunday 3<hi rend="superscript">rd.</hi> July — We proceeded as far as <placeName ref="pl0763">York</placeName> — we found nothing beautiful in the country
                    through which we passed, except that the greater part of <placeName ref="pl0770">Yorkshire</placeName> is finely wooded. — The Town of <placeName ref="pl0768">Doncaster</placeName> is handsome. We slept at <placeName ref="pl0763">York</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Monday 4<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> In the morning before breakfast we
                    visited the Cathedral — We found nothing else in this city work devoting any
                    time <pb n="f.1v"/> to — There is a pleasant walk by the side of the river — the
                    Town is very <unclear reason="illegible">shabby</unclear>, having narrow streets
                    &amp; mean <add place="above">brick</add> buildings, generally speaking. The
                        <placeName ref="pl0932">Minster</placeName> is a fine pile of building, in
                    the Gothic style. The nave is extremely handsome. There is a great quantity of
                    very fine painted glass in all the windows, &amp; very exquisite carving in the
                    ornaments of the Choir &amp; Skreen. — We pursued our journey after breakfast,
                    &amp; reached <placeName ref="pl0052">Durham</placeName>, about 6 o'clock</p>
                <p>The situation of this City is very grand. The <placeName ref="pl0934">Cathedral</placeName> &amp; the <placeName ref="pl0934">Castle</placeName>
                    are built upon a high rock which overhangs the river <placeName ref="pl3017">Wear</placeName> — The <placeName ref="pl0934">Cathedral</placeName> is a
                    fine pile of the Saxon order of Architecture.</p>
                <p>There was formerly a fine Chapter House adjoining the Church, but the
                    Prebendaries some years back determined on taking down this part of the Ancient
                    structure &amp; then erected a Modern room for the purpose of their meetings,
                    which, however <pb n="f.2r"/> comfortable in itself, but ill accords with all
                    that surrounds it, &amp; remains a disgraceful monument to the wretched want of
                    taste &amp; feeling of those men, who could possibly consent to the destruction
                    of so ancient &amp; venerable a part of their Cathedral. Here is scarcely any
                    painted Glass nor any monuments worth mentioning. The huge Saxon Pillars give a
                    majesty &amp; solemnity to the Nave of this Church beyond which I have observed
                    in any other. The tomb of <persName ref="pe1299">S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi>
                        Cuthbert</persName> is seen in an adjoining chapel. —</p>
                <p>5<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> — We entered <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> this evening at <placeName ref="pl3274">Coldstream</placeName>, by a fine Stone bridge over the <placeName ref="pl0727">Tweed</placeName>.<note type="editorial">Malkin's route of
                        entry into Scotland is relatively unusual, with most tourists tending to
                        cross the border further east, at Berwick, or to the west, near
                        Gretna.</note> we slept at <placeName ref="pl0415">Kelso</placeName>, where
                    we saw the ruins of the <placeName ref="pl3275">Abbey</placeName> — There are
                    still considerable remains of the Tower of the Church, &amp; other parts of the
                    building — those parts partake of the Saxon &amp; the Gothic orders.</p>
                <p>At <placeName ref="pl0415">Kelso</placeName>, just above the Bridge, the two
                    rivers so often sung, the <placeName ref="pl0727">Tweed</placeName> &amp; the
                        <placeName ref="pl0414">Teviot</placeName>, unite their streams — On
                    Wednesday the 6<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> of July, we pursued the <add place="above">upward</add> course of the <pb n="f.2v"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0727">Tweed</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0405">Melrose</placeName>; fording it about two or three miles short of
                        <placeName ref="pl0405">Melrose</placeName>, to see <placeName ref="pl0410">Dryburgh Abbey</placeName>, the Seat of <persName ref="pe0040">Lord
                        Buchan</persName>.</p>
                <p>There are considerable remains of the Abbey still standing, close to which is a
                    modern built house, where <persName ref="pe0040">Lord Buchan</persName> resides
                    a good deal — he has already prepared his tomb there. — After seeing this, we
                    recrossed the <placeName ref="pl0727">Tweed</placeName>, &amp; soon found our
                    selves at <placeName ref="pl0405">Melrose</placeName> — in our way we saw the
                    celebrated hill of Cowden-knows.<note type="editorial">A reference to the
                        Scottish ballad, 'Broom of the Cowdenknowes' (Child 217). The reason for
                        Malkin's association of the work with a particular hill near Melrose is
                        unclear.</note></p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl0405">Melrose</placeName> is situated at the foot of the
                        <placeName ref="pl3276">Eildon Hills</placeName> — the <placeName ref="pl3277">Abbey</placeName> is by far the finest remnant of antiquity I
                    have ever seen — There is a very large portion still standing, &amp; the
                    ornamental parts of the architecture are in many places in perfect preservation.
                    The stone with which it is built, is of a fine mellow grey, with a roseate tint;
                    &amp; the hardness of it is such, that the carving is as sharp &amp; perfect as
                    if it were Marble. The vanity <pb n="f.3r"/> of exquisite patterns of border
                    work, round the cornices, pillars &amp;c. is quite astonishing &amp; all are so
                    tasteful &amp; elegant, that you can scarcely give a preference to either.</p>
                <p>We lingered long, &amp; knew not how to leave this enchanting scene, combining so
                    much natural beauty, with such interesting remains of days long gone by —
                    however we left it time enough to pursue our journey, &amp; reached <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName> late in the evening. We sent out our
                    letters of introduction, &amp; on <hi rend="underline">Thursday the 7<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> we were called upon by <persName ref="pe0121">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Burt</persName>, &amp; <persName ref="pe0084">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Charles Macdonald</persName>, who kindly
                    enlisted themselves in our service, &amp; walked with us to see many parts of
                    this very fine Town. I was quite astonished, &amp; delighted with the situation
                    of the place, the grandeur of the surrounding hills, their summits crowned by
                    the <placeName ref="pl1031">Castle</placeName>, the <placeName ref="pl2267">Pillar</placeName> erected to the memory of <persName ref="pe1435">Nelson</persName>, &amp; other superb buildings.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.3v"/> We also made acquaintance with the family of <persName ref="pe0070">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Gray</persName>, &amp;
                        <persName ref="pe0074">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Hogg the Ettrick
                        Shepherd</persName>. We had reason to be exceedingly pleased with all the
                    people we saw in <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName> — Nothing could
                    exceed the kindness of their deportment towards us, &amp; they contrived to make
                    us feel ourselves rather as brought among old friends, than introduced amongst
                    strangers — On <hi rend="underline">Sunday the 10<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> we went, accompanied by <persName ref="pe0070">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Gray</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe0074">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Hogg</persName> to see <placeName ref="pl0967">Roslyn Castle</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl0385">Hawthorndean</placeName>. We passed the morning most delightfully in this
                    sequestered &amp; romantic spot; &amp; wandered along the banks of the river
                        <add place="above">(the <placeName ref="pl2803">North
                        Esk</placeName>,)</add> amidst the finest rocks &amp; most romantic Scenery
                    — We also visited the <placeName ref="pl0386">Chapel at Roslyn</placeName>,
                    which is in better preservation than any remnant of antiquity I have ever seen —
                    The roof, from within, is perfect, &amp; all the pillars remain as <pb n="f.4r"/>they were first erected — It is a building of the Gothic order. There is very
                    little of the Castle remaining, &amp; what there is, does not give you an idea
                    of its ever having been magnificent. After having finished our morning excursion
                    to <placeName ref="pl0386">Roslyn</placeName>, we returned to dinner at
                        <persName ref="pe0070">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Grays</persName> at
                        <placeName ref="pl2275">S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Leonard's
                        Hill</placeName>. On Monday we visited what remained to be seen at <persName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe0070">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Gray</persName>, <persName ref="pe0074">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Hogg</persName> &amp; the two M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c. Donalds</hi> dined
                    with us at the <placeName ref="pl0659">Royal Hotel</placeName>.<note type="editorial">Throughout her journal, Malkin makes frequent reference to
                        the two young Mr Macdonalds. These are the aforementioned <persName ref="pe0084">Charles</persName> and <persName ref="pe0081">Matthew
                            Macdonald</persName>, sons of <persName ref="pe0079">Norman
                            Macdonald</persName>, who held the tack of the island of Scalpay, near
                        Skye.</note>
                    <persName ref="pe0124">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Burt</persName> came in
                    the evening, &amp; we all walked to <placeName ref="pl3285">S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Bernards Well</placeName>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">On Tuesday the 12<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> We all
                    left <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName> and pursued our journey
                    Northwards. We crossed <placeName ref="pl0082">Queens Ferry</placeName> &amp;
                    reached <placeName ref="pl0085">Kinross</placeName> where we slept. <add place="above">We walked on the banks of <placeName ref="pl0086">Loch
                            Leven</placeName> in the evening.</add> On Wednesday the 13<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> we came to <placeName ref="pl0235">Stirling</placeName>, where we slept. We visited in our way from <placeName ref="pl0085">Kinross</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0235">Stirling</placeName>, the <placeName ref="pl0088">Rumbling Brig</placeName>
                    <pb n="f.4v"/><add place="above">(<placeName ref="pl3286">the Devil's
                            Mill</placeName>,)</add> &amp; the <placeName ref="pl0089">Cauldron
                        Linn</placeName>
                    <add place="above">(on the <placeName ref="pl3287">River
                        Devon</placeName>.)</add> The Grandeur of the fall at the <placeName ref="pl0089">Linn</placeName>, and the sublimity of the Scenery which
                    surrounds it, quite overcame my spirits; nor were these improved by our visiting
                    afterwards the <placeName ref="pl0090">Castle of Gloom</placeName>, now called
                        <placeName ref="pl0090">Campbell's Castle</placeName>, at <placeName ref="pl3278">Dollar</placeName></p>
                <p>I rather wish I could visit scenes of this nature, without my sensibilities being
                    so much awakened. Perhaps if I felt their sublime beauties less
                    enthusiastically, I should behold them with <add place="above">a pleasure</add>
                    better adapted to the common course, &amp; the useful purposes of society. But
                    let me hope; that if feelings which excite an almost painful admiration of the
                    Author of all these wonders, a little unfit me at the moment for the purposes of
                    common life, <pb n="f.5r"/>the may at the same Time lead me to look beyond this
                    present world; &amp; teach <add place="above">me</add> to aspire to that perfect
                    happiness in a future state, which the changeable &amp; imperfect nature of all
                    things here forbids me ever to hope for on earth!<note type="editorial">Malkin's
                        self-chastisement at her powerful response to sublime scenery reflects the
                        complex and often gendered politics of the aesthetics of landscape
                        appreciation in the Romantic period. For Susan Matthews, the passage
                        suggests the disjunction between the impersonal, touristic voice of the
                        journal, Malkin's grief at the loss of her son, and her anxieties about the
                        ongoing war with Napoleon. See Matthews, 'Charlotte Malkin’s Waterloo Diary
                        and the Politics of Waterloo Tourism', <hi rend="italic">Literature
                            Compass</hi>, 11/3 (2014), 218–231, 222.</note></p>
                <p>On <hi rend="underline">Thursday the 14<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> we
                    walked before — breakfast to see the <placeName ref="pl1193">Castle of
                        Stirling</placeName>. On Mounting the heights we were greatly delighted to
                    perceive <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName>, its hills, its
                        <placeName ref="pl1031">Castle</placeName>, in the distance. I thought we
                    had before taken our last view of this delightful palace &amp; was greatly
                    rejoiced to recognise it once more. The <placeName ref="pl3279">Pentland
                        Hills</placeName> over <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName> were
                    also seen from this place, as well as the long &amp; beautiful range of the
                        <placeName ref="pl0812">Oichill Hills</placeName>, which extend between
                        <placeName ref="pl3278">Dollar</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl0235">Stirling</placeName>. — On looking Northward from the <placeName ref="pl1193">Castle</placeName>, we perceived the superb heights of
                        <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben-Lomond</placeName>, &amp; <placeName ref="pl1167">Ben-Ledi</placeName>, <pb n="f.5v"/>with others of various
                    magnitude &amp; beauty. Between us &amp; <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName> a fertile plain extended, through which the river
                        <placeName ref="pl1116">Forth</placeName> meandered beautifully. — After
                    breakfast we quitted <placeName ref="pl0235">Stirling</placeName>, &amp; within
                    a few miles of it, came close to the borders of the river <placeName ref="pl1115">Teith</placeName>, the course of which we often caught a
                    glimpse of, while we pursued our journey to <placeName ref="pl2324">Callander</placeName>, a little Town at the foot of <placeName ref="pl1167">Ben-Ledi</placeName>. Arriving here, the Mountain seems to shut out the
                    world on almost every side — The river <placeName ref="pl1115">Teith</placeName>
                    is become a large &amp; beautiful river, rapid in its course &amp; its waters
                    perfectly clear. We took a delightful walk after dinner to the <placeName ref="pl3288">Bracklin Brig</placeName><note type="editorial">The Bracklinn
                        Falls and their locale were recommended to tourists by the minister of
                        Aberfoyle, Patrick Graham, in his <hi rend="italic">Sketches Descriptive of
                            Picturesque Scenery on the Southern Confines of Perthshire, including
                            the Trossachs, Lochard, etc.</hi> (Edinburgh: 1806).</note>
                    <add place="above">over the little river <placeName ref="pl3289">Kelty</placeName></add> — Here the rocks the waterfall, &amp; the whole
                    of the surrounding scenery is wild &amp; beautiful, <pb n="f.6r"/> but after the
                        <placeName ref="pl0089">Caldron Linn</placeName>, it should seem to me, that
                    all other water-falls must seem comparitivly tame &amp; uninteresting. — In that
                    magnificent Scene, the body of water is so large, &amp; the rocks which
                    interrupt its progress are so stupendous, that the dash of waters is immense,
                    &amp; the foam that is cast upwards, becomes as if were embodied. It has not the
                    usual appearance of Water in a foaming state, but looks rather like ice, or
                    broken glass, tossed about in a most magnificent &amp; beautiful confusion.</p>
                <p>On <hi rend="underline">Friday the 15.</hi> we set out early to visit the
                        <placeName ref="pl2177">Trossacks</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl2170">Loch Katrine</placeName>
                    <add place="above">(passing in our way thither, <placeName ref="pl3280">Loch
                            Venachar</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl2179">Loch
                            Achray</placeName>,)</add> — The day was as fine as could be wished; it
                    afforded the varieties of clouds &amp; sunshine, &amp; showed the stupendous
                    Mountain, <placeName ref="pl1168">Ben Venue</placeName>, in all its grandeur
                    &amp; beauty. The <placeName ref="pl2170">Loch</placeName> was as calm as
                    possible, &amp; beautifully clear. The richly clothed hills, called the
                        <placeName ref="pl2177">Trossacks</placeName>, &amp; the highest craggy
                    point of <placeName ref="pl2175">Ben-An</placeName>, contrasted <pb n="f.6v"/>very finely with the serene beauty of the Lake below. — We hired a Boat, &amp;
                    rowed to the creek just below the <placeName ref="pl3316">Goblin's
                        cave</placeName>, which we visited — We then crossed to the Northern side
                    &amp; climbed a high point of rock, from which we viewed the Lake &amp; the
                    surrounding hills, &amp; commanded all their various beauties. — We took cold
                    provisions with us, &amp; landed on <placeName ref="pl2176">Ellen's
                        Isle</placeName> to eat out dinners there. The whole of this scene is so
                    poetically, &amp; at the same time so accurately described by <persName ref="pe1437">Walter Scott</persName>, that when I read his poem of "<bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0070">The Lady of the
                        Lake</title></bibl><note type="editorial">Walter Scott's poem, <hi rend="italic">The Lady of the Lake</hi> (Edinburgh: 1810), contributed
                        to the development of Loch Katrine and the Trossachs as a major tourist
                        site, although the area had previously been brought to the attention of
                        travellers in Sarah Murray's <hi rend="italic">A Companion and Useful Guide
                            to the Beauties of Scotland</hi> (London: 1799).</note> I shall always
                    be able I hope, to call to my recollection the very great pleasure I have
                    enjoyed this day. — We returned to <placeName ref="pl2324">Callander</placeName>
                    in the evening, &amp; slept there.</p>
                <p>Saturday, July 16<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> We came to <placeName ref="pl2180">Aberfoil</placeName> to breakfast, &amp; the day being very
                    fine we were tempted to hire Ponies, &amp; to send the carriage <pb n="f.7r"/>forward to <placeName ref="pl1067">Row-Ardennan</placeName> — Our purpose was
                    to see <placeName ref="pl2181">Loch Ard</placeName>, which lies between
                        <placeName ref="pl2180">Aberfoil</placeName> &amp; the Foot of <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben Lomond</placeName>. (We had seen, &amp; greatly admired the
                        <placeName ref="pl1117">Lake of Menteith</placeName>, in our road from
                        <placeName ref="pl2324">Callander</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl2180">Aberfoil</placeName>.)</p>
                <p>We proceeded, (<persName ref="pe0071">Miss Hall</persName> &amp; myself on our
                    ponies, <persName ref="pe0002">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                    Malkin</persName>, <persName ref="pe0030">Benjamin</persName>, <unclear reason="illegible">Huff</unclear>, &amp; the guide <del unit="words" quantity="2"/>
                    <add place="above">on foot</add>, all along the north side of <placeName ref="pl2181">Loch-Ard</placeName>. Scarcely any thing can surpass in beauty
                    the first view of this lovely lake; its scenery is very rich, rather pastoral
                    &amp; soft, than sublime. — We left the lake, &amp; soon began to wind round the
                    side of a hill, which having again descended by a narrow stoney track, we
                    advanced to the foot of <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben-Lomond</placeName>. The
                    river <placeName ref="pl1116">Forth</placeName> takes its rise in this mountain
                    &amp; we had to ford across it. — The poney upon which I rode, had shown a
                    strong inclination to turn towards Water, wherever we had pass'd it; but now it
                    felt the refreshing stream, all <pb n="f.7v"/>my efforts were ineffectual to
                    prevent its having the full enjoyment of it, &amp; when we were just in the
                    deepest part of the fort, it determined upon lying down in the river. I was well
                    aware that nothing was left for me, but to disengage my foot from the stirrup,
                    &amp; my knee from the pummel of the saddle; in these points I succeeded to my
                    wishes, &amp; gently rolled backwards into the water; receiving no other injury
                    than that of a complete — drenching. — This would have been a matter of no
                    consequence whatever, had I been within reach of a change of habiliments — but
                    out baggage had been sent forward with the carriage, so I could get nothing dry
                    to put on, till we reached the other side of the mountain, &amp; met the
                    carriage at <placeName ref="pl1067">Row-Ardennan</placeName>. It had been our
                    intention to ascend to the Top, but the accident which had <pb n="f.8r"/>befallen me, put this quite out of the question, &amp; we had reason
                    afterwards to think it had been a very fortunate one, as we soon found that our
                    guide was nearly as much in the dark as ourselves; &amp; we were very thankful
                    to obtain the guidance &amp; assistance of a Highland youth who lived in a cabin
                    on the mountain, to lead us safely over the southern shoulder of <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben-Lomond</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1067">Rowardennan</placeName>. We went about a mile or two beyond the <placeName ref="pl1116">Forth</placeName>, on our ponies; but we soon found that our
                    only safety lay in trusting to our own feet, &amp; the ponies were led for the
                    rest of the way, while we walked it: a — distance of about six or seven miles.
                    The people on the other side told us they would be quite astonished to see us
                    with the ponies, &amp; they believed it was the first time a horse had ever been
                    brought over that part of the mountain.</p>
                <p>In spite of all our fatigues, &amp; the weight of my wet clothes, I greatly
                    enjoyed the fine <pb n="f.8v"/>view we saw towards the East, from the highest
                    point to which we ascended. The Lochs of <placeName ref="pl1117">Mentieth</placeName> &amp; of <placeName ref="pl2181">Ard</placeName>,
                    which we had passed, lay in the plains beneath us: In the distance to the East,
                    we plainly perceived the ridges of the <placeName ref="pl3279">Pentland
                        Hills</placeName> by <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName>, &amp;
                    the <placeName ref="pl0812">Oichill Hills</placeName> near <placeName ref="pl0235">Stirling</placeName>, with <placeName ref="pl1193">Stirling
                        Castle</placeName> rising in full magnificence &amp; crowning the whole. —
                    The day was uncommonly fine, &amp; by the time we descended the mountain, my
                    clothes were nearly dry. I took no cold, nor did I feel any ill effects from
                    this little accident, beyond what the fatigue of so laborious a walk must
                    occasion me. <hi rend="underline">On Sunday the 17<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi>
                    <persName ref="pe0002">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Malkin</persName> &amp;
                        <persName ref="pe0030">Benjamin</persName> rose early, the morning being
                    very clear, &amp; ascended with a competent guide to the utmost top of
                        <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben-Lomond</placeName>. After their descent, we took
                    Boat, &amp; spent a couple of hours very delightfully <pb n="f.9r"/>on
                        <placeName ref="pl0223">Loch Lomond</placeName> — We landed at the Island
                    which is called Bell-Island,<note type="editorial">An alternative name for
                            <placeName ref="pl1113">Inchatavannach</placeName>, derived from the
                        historical presence of a bell known as St Kessog's Bell on the eminence of
                        Tom na Clog (The Hill of the Bell).</note> &amp; from a very high rock upon
                    it, we looked over a great portion of this beautiful Lake; our view took in all
                    the numerous islands, &amp; extended Southwards as far as <placeName ref="pl0226">Dumbarton</placeName> — We dined at <placeName ref="pl0224">Luss</placeName>, where we were quite astonished at seeing such multitudes
                    of well dressed persons male &amp; female, who we were told had come to take the
                    Sacrament at the Kirk, in the morning, &amp; had staid to dinner at the Inn. —
                    The solemnities of the morning seemed to be all forgotten, &amp; the assemblage
                    of men &amp; women, gave you rather the idea of a Wake than of a party assembled
                    for the fulfilment of any religious rite — however we saw nothing riotous or
                    improper; though the impression left upon our minds was not at all of a native
                    correspondent with the idea of a large assemblage of persons met for any
                    religious purpose. <pb n="f.9v"/>In this multitude of people, they were all
                    generally well dress'd, &amp; perfectly clean &amp; nice — A few only of the men
                    wore the genuine highland garb, which we regretted not to find more general.</p>
                <p>Almost all the women, the young ones more particularly, were dress'd in white
                    gowns; most of these also had hats or bonnets; but amongst the middle-aged,
                    &amp; elderly women, scarcely any wore a hat, but all had their large high mob
                    caps, which are as clean &amp; as white as snow. They all had shoes &amp;
                    stockings also; a circumstance which renders Sunday a very pleasant day in
                        <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>; for on all others, the large,
                    dirty, naked feet of all the women of the lower orders, make a most disgusting
                    &amp; offensive appearance. There seems to be a great inconcistency between the
                    clean <pb n="f.10r"/>Sunday garb of all these cottagers, &amp; the miserable
                    dirty hovels in which they live. These cabins look so wretched, that in
                        <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> we should not think them fit
                    places for our pigs to be fed in: &amp; yet at the doors of these wretched huts,
                    you see decent looking well dress'd men &amp; women, with their linen as white
                    as possible, &amp; their complexions blooming, &amp; perfectly healthy. After
                    dining at <placeName ref="pl0224">Luss</placeName>, we proceeded to <placeName ref="pl0222">Tarbet Inn</placeName> — We had a magnificent ride, close to
                    the <add place="above">western</add> side of the Lake the whole distance —
                    Nothing could be more superb than the scenery here. <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben-Lomond</placeName> stretching the whole length of our ride nineteen
                    miles, on the eastern side; &amp; our road winding along under the sides of
                    wooded &amp; craggy mountains, each rivalling the other in grandeur &amp;
                    beauty.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">On Monday the 18<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> We came
                    after breakfast <pb n="f.10v"/><placeName ref="pl1008">Aroquhar Inn</placeName>,
                    at the head of <placeName ref="pl0221">Loch-Long</placeName>. The craggy heights
                    of <placeName ref="pl1171">Ben-Arthur</placeName>, or <placeName ref="pl1171">Cobler</placeName>, over-hang the northern extremity of this Lake — We went
                    in the carriage about eight-miles down its eastern side, till we came within
                    sight of <placeName ref="pl3281">Loch-Goyle</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl0614">Loch-Gair</placeName>; the former falling into <placeName ref="pl0221">Loch-Long</placeName> from the west; the latter stretching out
                    towards the South, &amp; falling, as <placeName ref="pl0221">Loch-Long</placeName> also does, into the <placeName ref="pl0833">Firth of
                        Clyde</placeName>, which we ascended above the Lake. We had a delightful
                    ride back to our Inn at <placeName ref="pl1008">Aroquhar</placeName>, winding
                    along the sides of the Lake; having the grand range of the <placeName ref="pl1008">Aroquhar</placeName> Mountains, with their rude &amp; rocky
                    points, to the west &amp; north of our view. — Notwithstanding the very rugged
                    &amp; barren appearance of these heights, there are many little spots cultivated
                    at their bases, with little cottages, &amp; patches of corn growing which give a
                    variety &amp; beauty to the scene: <pb n="f.11r"/>On the whole, the character of
                    this Loch is that of extreme wildness; but it goes no further — there is nothing
                    terrific, though the rocks &amp; heights are stupendous. —</p>
                <p>One of the very great beauties, which characterises, in a greater or lesser
                    degree the scenery near all the Lochs which we here witness'd, is the profusion,
                    &amp; endless variety <add place="above">with</add> which some of the
                    neighbouring hills are covered. Birches, Alders, Mountain-Ash, Oaks, Firs; &amp;
                    Brush-wood of every description, grow on their steep sides in rich profusion;
                    and near to the road-side there is the greatest display of wild flowers I have
                    ever seen in any country. The wild-roses are particularly beautiful, &amp; are
                    of a deep rose coulour, almost crimson. The white roses are luxuriant &amp;
                    delicate; honeysuckles, heaths of every coulour &amp; description, &amp; various
                    other smaller plants, seem to grow out of the bare rock, &amp; give fragrance as
                    well as beauty to its sides &amp; tops. I have never seen any which could vie
                    with them in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>. <pb n="f.11v"/><hi rend="underline">Tuesday the 19<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> We
                    proceeded on our way to <placeName ref="pl1072">Inverary</placeName>. Our road
                    from <placeName ref="pl1008">Aroquhar</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1069">Cairndow</placeName> led through the wild &amp; sequestered passes of
                        <placeName ref="pl1068">Glencroe</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl1118">Glenkinglass</placeName>, the hill, called <placeName ref="pl0220">"Rest
                        &amp; be thankful"</placeName>, being between these two passes — The scenery
                    in these Glens is extremely dreary, and the very high hills which shut in the
                    traveller on both sides, are surmounted by tremendous rocks — their sides have
                    some verdure, mixed with large masses of rock; &amp; perpetually broken by
                    mountain torrents which force their way into the river below — In general the
                    hollow of the Glen is so narrow, as to leave room for little more than the road
                    which is carried through it — but here &amp; there, where there is a little
                    breadth of valley, there is a cottage erected &amp; a little patch of cultivated
                    ground enlivens the dreary scene. — What I have <pb n="f12r"/>said above,
                    relates principally to <placeName ref="pl1068">Glencroe</placeName>; <placeName ref="pl1118">Glenkinglass</placeName> is of rather a different character —
                    here the mountain sides to the right &amp; left, are more gentle in their
                    acclivities: they are covered with verdure, &amp; grazed by the beautiful sheep
                    of this Highland country. Their wool is much longer &amp; finer than that of the
                    sheep we see in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>; &amp; their faces
                    have the eager &amp; lively expression of the goat: they all have horns, which
                    grow in the same manner as those of the goat. At the end of this glen, we begin
                    to see trees again, &amp; were glad to return to something which indicated that
                    we were not very distant from a more inhabited country. We baited our horses,
                    &amp; refreshed ourselves at <placeName ref="pl2183">Cairn-dow</placeName>, a
                    nice comfortable little Inn at the Northern end of <placeName ref="pl1070">Loch
                        Fine</placeName>. We then proceeded to — <placeName ref="pl1072">Inverary</placeName>, going all the way by the borders of the Lake, on the
                    Western-side</p>
                <p><pb n="f12v"/> Nothing could be more delightful than the whole of our ride. The
                    first view of the <placeName ref="pl0217">Castle</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl1072">Town of Inverary</placeName>, standing at the border of a fine
                    bay in the Loch, is wonderfully striking. — Nothing can be imagined more
                    beautiful — the great expanse of Water, the pretty little Town, the hills on all
                    sides, some soft &amp; green, others finely wooded to their summits, &amp;
                    others barren &amp; rocky; form altogether an assemblage of all that is pleasing
                    to the eye, and delightful to the heart. — At the Inn, on our arrival, we were
                    met by the two M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Macdonalds, who had left
                        <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName> to accompany us in some part
                    of our tour, &amp; who had arrived at <placeName ref="pl1072">Inverary</placeName> for this purpose, the day before. — <hi rend="underline">Wednesday the 20<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> We all
                    set out together, four of us in the Carriage, &amp; two on the Barouche, to take
                    a drive through the beautiful <pb n="f.13r"/>grounds of the <persName ref="pe1433">Duke of Argyll</persName>. There is a great deal of natural
                    beauty in this place, &amp; all that can be added by — planting &amp;c. is done.
                    We enjoyed our ride exceedingly — After we had been round the park, we proceeded
                    a few miles down the border of this fine Lake — greatly as we had been pleased
                    in our more confined drive through the park, we were infinitely more delighted
                    with the <del unit="words" quantity="1"/> open, &amp; grand <del unit="letters" quantity="2"/> scenery of the Lake. There was a delightful breeze, which
                    filled the sails of the numerous little vessels which glided on its surface. It
                    was bounded on all sides, to our view at least, by lofty mountains — close to
                    our road on the other hand, were the finest trees, both beech and limes, as well
                    as most others sorts of forest trees; but the two first mentioned grow in
                    peculiar luxuriance here. We returned <pb n="f.13v"/>to our Inn to dinner, sorry
                    to find our delightful morning come to its close. In the evening we took a long
                    walk, &amp; finished the day as agreeably as we had commenced it. —</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Thursday July 21<hi rend="superscript">st.</hi></hi> The
                    weather which had hitherto been fine, but for the last two or three days, had
                    threatened rain, proved very wet this morning, &amp; continued so the — whole of
                    the day. We had settled our plan for leaving <placeName ref="pl1072">Inverary</placeName> after breakfast, which we did — We had a very dreary
                    ride for the first seven or eight miles, on the road towards <placeName ref="pl0214">Dalmally</placeName> — Our road lay between large barren hills,
                    with no pleasing feature except the river <placeName ref="pl0219">Ary</placeName>, which flowed through the valley; &amp; continually
                    received and increase to its waters from the torrents which fell foaming from
                    the sides of the Mountains. After this we began to ascend gradually, till we
                    attained a view of <placeName ref="pl0269">Loch-Awe</placeName>: it was a
                    delightful reverse from the <pb n="f.14r"/>barren &amp; uninteresting road we
                    had been travelling. The Loch has several beautiful small islands, and the
                    immediate banks are soft an pleasing — There is a handsome Gentleman's seat, the
                    grounds low &amp; well planted, <del unit="words" quantity="1"/> on the Western
                    side of the Lake — beyond this, the mountain rises, and as we proceeded on our
                    road on the opposite side of the Lake, we soon attained so great a height, as to
                    afford us the finest range of — Alpine Scenery which we had yest witness'd. —
                    Below us lay <placeName ref="pl0214">Dalmally</placeName>; a small village with
                    a beautiful small church, and, what is seldom met with in this country, it has a
                    high &amp; handsome tower. We took up our quarters here for the day &amp; night,
                    &amp; were confined entirely to the house by the heavy rains which fell the
                    whole of the evening. We left the two M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Macdonalds
                    at <placeName ref="pl1072">Inverary</placeName>, but it was their intention to
                    proceed today to <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName>. —</p>
                <p><pb n="f.14v"/>
                    <hi rend="underline">Friday July 22<hi rend="superscript">nd.</hi></hi> After
                    breakfast this morning we went to see the Church, which was built some years
                    back by <persName ref="pe0036">Lord Breadalbane</persName>, and is a very pretty
                    &amp; convenient structure, well calculated to accommodate a great number of
                    people — We should have been much pleased with it, had the — neatness with which
                    it was preserved, borne any proportion to the convenience &amp; judicious
                    arrangement of the interior: but this was far from being the case. The dirt
                    &amp; dust lay on the floors in the pews &amp; in the aisle, in such quantities
                    as to lead us to suppose the church could not have been swept for months. — The
                    windows were covered with splashes of white-wash, which upon enquiring we found
                    had disfigured them for a year past, as we were told it was full as long as that
                    since the <pb n="f.15r"/>Church had been whitewash'd. But the inhabitants of
                    this country do not seem to be still sensible of the comfort of cleanliness in
                    their dwellings, or neatness in any thing. — After visiting the Church we went a
                    few miles, following the course of the fine river <placeName ref="pl0988">Orchy</placeName>, in <placeName ref="pl0213">Glen-orchy</placeName>, to
                    see a salmon-leap; the river was uncommonly full of water, owing to the heavy
                    rains which had fallen the preceeding night, &amp; it fell foaming over the huge
                    rocks at the salmon-leap, in great fury &amp; magnificence. There was a
                    fisherman, taking the fish at the time we went there, &amp; during about an hour
                    that we looked on, we saw him catch seven fine Salmon in the pool immediately
                    below the fall: this he effected by use of a long pole, with a large strong
                    &amp; sharp hook at its <pb n="f.15v"/>end. He had no other apparatus, except an
                    open railed fence at the edge of the deep pool, which is placed there to prevent
                    the fish from escaping down the river. — After walking a little further into the
                    Glen, we returned to the carriage, &amp; came back to <placeName ref="pl0214">Dalmally</placeName> to dinner. —</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Saturday July 23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi></hi> We left
                        <placeName ref="pl0214">Dalmally</placeName> after breakfast, &amp; pursued
                    our journey towards <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName>, on the banks of
                        <placeName ref="pl0269">Loch Awe</placeName>. The first part of our ride was
                    very beautiful: the ruins of <add place="above"><placeName ref="pl0215">Kilchurn</placeName></add> Castle, formerly the abode of the
                    Breadalbane family, occupy a point of land stretching out into the Lake, at <add place="above">the</add> northern extremity of it — this is a most
                    picturesque object. — as you proceed farther, &amp; look back on the lovely vale
                    you have quitted, &amp; the river <placeName ref="pl0988">Orchy</placeName>
                    rolling majestically through it, the Castle, which is built on very low ground,
                    appears actually to stand in the Lake, &amp; has a very grand &amp; commanding
                    appearance. — two or three <pb n="f.16r"/>miles below this, the Loch separates
                    into two distinct branches: that which we followed pointing westward towards
                        <placeName ref="pl1249">Bunawe</placeName>. It is impossible to describe the
                    sublimity of the scenery which now gradually broke upon us: the Lake narrowed
                    considerably, but the sides became so high &amp; precipitous, that it seemed
                    like a stupendous mountain pass; the whole of its bottom occupied by the deep
                    waters of the Lake. Our road was cut through the over-hanging rocks <add place="above">(at the base of the superb Mountain, <placeName ref="pl0831">Ben-Cruachan)</placeName></add> generally low, near the edge of the
                    Lake; but sometimes necessarily carried upwards, to turn a point in the
                    mountain: for the space of about half a mile we had been gradually rising, till
                    we found ourselves at a height of three or four hundred feet from the base — the
                    rock below us was so precipitous, that when we sat down in the Carriage, we
                    could not see anything but the water in the abyss below us: except that some
                    branches of trees which grow out of the rock, jutted <pb n="f.16v"/>forward
                    &amp; took off something from the sublime horror which one might suppose such a
                    scene must inspire — We however were more sensible of its magnificence, than
                    scared by its terrors; &amp; I stood up in the carriage the whole of the way;
                    that I might lose nothing, amongst all the objects which excited my admiration,
                    &amp; raised my soul to the great source of all these wonders of creation. — The
                    Mountains under which our road lay, were of the grandest kind, very lofty; in
                    many parts well wooded, &amp; their summits covered with rude craggs, &amp;
                    broken continually by immense torrents of water, which crossed our road at very
                    frequent intervals, &amp; poured their foaming streams into the Lake below. On
                    the eastern side of the Loch the character of the hills was totally different —
                    There was neither rock, nor wood, to grace their sides; but a barren surface of
                    earths of various tints, with some loose stones which seemed to have been washed
                    down by mountain — <pb n="f.17r"/>torrents, and served to vary the wild &amp;
                    severe uniformity of this desart sweep: here &amp; there indeed a little patch
                    of verdure — seemed like a spot on the surface; but not a tree or a bush, or
                    even a little heath or fern, presumed to offer a softening feature on these
                    dreary elevations. As we proceeded towards the extremity of the Lake, we quitted
                    with regret the ruder beauties we had so much enjoyed, &amp; followed the course
                    of the beautiful river <placeName ref="pl3319">Awe</placeName>, till we arrived
                    at <del><placeName ref="pl1249">Bunawe</placeName></del><add place="above"><placeName ref="pl1074">Taynelt</placeName></add>, a village situated
                    at the northern end of <placeName ref="pl1075">Loch-Etive</placeName>. —</p>
                <p>This stage, from <placeName ref="pl0214">Dalmally</placeName> to <del><placeName ref="pl1249">Bunawe</placeName></del><add place="above"><placeName ref="pl1074">Taynelt</placeName></add> was certainly much the grandest
                    we have travelled — it combined every charm which can affect the imagination, or
                    elevate the soul. — I know not how to take my eyes from the point that shut out
                    this magnificent combination of all that is sublime &amp; beautiful, from my
                    view. I hope I shall ever retain it in my memory, &amp; think of it with renewed
                    pleasure &amp; admiration. —</p>
                <p><pb n="f.17v"/> The early part of our next stage, from <placeName ref="pl1249">Bunawe</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName>, was
                    extremely fine. We enjoyed as grand a Mountain view as can be imagined; but
                        <placeName ref="pl1075">loch Etive</placeName> which lay below was not
                    distinguished by any peculiar or picturesque appearance — the shores are flat
                    &amp; uninteresting. —</p>
                <p>The last few miles our road lay over a wild &amp; hilly waste, where immense
                    mounds of soil seemed scattered about in strange confusion, &amp; offered a very
                    unusual scene to our eyes — but there was neither <add place="above">beauty</add> nor grandeur here; &amp; we were very glad to finish our day's
                    journey by — arriving at <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName>, where the
                        M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Macdonalds were expecting us. The weather
                    improved much in the course of the day, &amp; we had good hopes held out to us
                    that we might have a favorable voyage to <placeName ref="pl0682">Aross</placeName> the next morning. <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName> is a paltry little fishing town, with nothing to recommend
                    it, except its situation on the sea-coast.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.18r"/>
                    <hi rend="underline">Sunday July 24<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> At seven
                    this morning we all set sail from <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName> — for
                    the first hour or two we were obliged to trust to our Oars; but soon a nice
                    breeze sprung up, which wafted us smoothly along, &amp; we sailed very
                    pleasantly through the <placeName ref="pl2195">Sound of Mull</placeName>*<note type="authorial">*As we sailed up the <placeName ref="pl2195">sound of
                            Mull</placeName>, I looked back to the Mainland, we were gratified by a
                        particularly fine view of the Mountain ridges: on every side of us indeed
                        they seemed to rear their heads to heaven — but those which looked the most
                        grand, were the rude &amp; craggy tops of <placeName ref="pl0831">Ben-Cruachan</placeName>. Their height appeared to be immense, and
                        their broken varied forms rendered them the most striking of any which we
                        now beheld. —</note> to <placeName ref="pl0682">Aross</placeName>, where we
                    arrived in about six hours. We procured a horse to convey the little luggage we
                    took with us, and all our party walked across a part of the island of <placeName ref="pl0729">Mull</placeName>, to a ferry at <placeName ref="pl1079">Loch-na-gael</placeName> head; where we again took boat, &amp; proceeded to
                        <placeName ref="pl1078">Ulva</placeName>. We arrived at this place, at about
                    four in the afternoon — after having dined we sauntered about, &amp; went to see
                    the House &amp; garden of <persName ref="pe1496">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                        Macdonald of Staffa</persName>; who had kindly sent letters from <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName>, desiring that every accommodation might
                    be afforded to us by his dependants at <placeName ref="pl1078">Ulva</placeName>.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.18v"/>
                    <hi rend="underline">Monday 25<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> We all set
                    forward in Boats this morning in the hope of being able to see <placeName ref="pl0652">Staffa</placeName> — We were fearful it might prove too
                    boisterous a day, but the Boatmen encouraged us to go on to the distance of
                    three or four miles from the sound of <placeName ref="pl1078">Ulva</placeName>;
                    here the breeze became so strong, &amp; the sea so very high, that our pilot as
                    well as ourselves saw the necessity of returning to <placeName ref="pl1078">Ulva</placeName> without completing our purpose — We therefore turned
                    about, &amp; were landed upon the first point we could make, walking afterwards
                    home to our Inn. — In the evening we took a long &amp; pleasant walk in the
                        <placeName ref="pl0729">Isle of Mull</placeName>, crossing the ferry to get
                    there.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Tuesday July 26<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> The
                    morning promising very fair, we made a second attempt to attain the object for
                    which we had come <pb n="f.19r"/>hither, and succeeded quite to our wishes. We
                    had engaged a large vessel than is commonly used on these occasions, that we
                    might be rather less dependant on the weather; but nothing could prove finer
                    than the day turned out, &amp; we were — gratified by seeing <placeName ref="pl0652">Staffa</placeName> with every possible advantage. We first
                    sailed nearly round it to see the various caves on its bluff &amp; lofty coast.
                    We then landed &amp; walked, or rather climed round its rugged base, till we
                    entered the <placeName ref="pl1082">Cave of Fingal</placeName>. If our wonder
                    had been raised by the outward appearance of this stupendous Mass of congregated
                    columns, for such it is; how was our admiration excited on entering the Cave,
                    the Aweful &amp; solemn "temple of the Western Main:"<note type="editorial">The
                        description of Staffa quoted here by Malkin has been attributed to James
                        Hogg, whom the Malkins had met while at Edinburgh earlier in their tour.
                        However, the poem in which it appeared was not published until 1833, in an
                        appendix to Lachlan Maclean's <hi rend="italic">A Historical Account of
                            Iona, from the Earliest Period</hi> (Edinburgh: 1833). Given the title
                        'Lines written in the Cave of Fingal, by James Hogg, Esq. the Ettrick
                        Shepherd', the piece was reported to have appeared in a visitor's book at
                        the Sound of Ulva Inn, alongside a poem by Scott, some further, derogatory
                        lines on the Mull natives by Hogg, and a retort by a local. Hogg's
                        breakthrough 1813 poem <hi rend="italic">The Queen's Wake</hi> included an
                        account of Staffa, but as H.B. de Groot notes in his edition of Hogg's <hi rend="italic">Highland Journeys</hi>, it has never been established when
                        and if Hogg himself actually visited the island. Malkin's apparent reference
                        to the line 'Great temple of the Western Main', predates the publication of
                        Macleod's <hi rend="italic">History</hi> by nearly two decades, providing
                        tantalising evidence of an otherwise unrecorded visit to Staffa by Hogg
                        before 1814. See James Hogg, <hi rend="italic">Highland Journeys</hi>, ed.
                        by H.B. de Groot (Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 2010),
                        pp.250-53.</note> It is impossible for the imagination to paint to itself
                    any <pb n="f.19v"/>thing so grand &amp; so sublime as this cave; it is entered
                    under a lofty Arch, of nearly perfect Gothic form — the whole of the — interior
                    is line <add place="above">as the outside is also covered</add> with basaltic
                    pillars, of which great numbers have from time to time fallen away, and left
                    their bases as a footing, by which we climed to nearly the innermost part of the
                    cave; a distance of about 250 feet from its mouth. We found many names inscribed
                    on the pillars, &amp; the M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Macdonalds &amp;
                        <persName ref="pe0030">Benjamin</persName> — added to the number, those of
                    all our party. Should any of us ever visit the Cave again, we shall look for
                    those names with interest. After we had given all the time we could afford to
                    this wonder of Creation, &amp; pay'd the tribute of devout admiration, (as I
                    hope we all did in our hearts) to the great <pb n="f.20r"/>Framer of its
                    majestic structure; we had the small Boat by which we were conveyed from the
                    Vessel, rowed into the Cave; &amp; we embarked again from its interior; rowing
                    out under its lofty portal with feelings which I believe are never excited,
                    without the heart's being improved. We quitted it very reluctantly; but the day
                    was wearing away, &amp; we had yet to visit <placeName ref="pl0651">I-Ona</placeName>, which we also effected. Here also we were much
                    gratified.</p>
                <p>There are still large remains of the <placeName ref="pl0977">Monastery</placeName> which formerly existed there; &amp; it has been the
                    burying place of many of the Kings of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>
                    <add place="above">&amp; <placeName ref="pl0889">Ireland</placeName></add> &amp;
                    many Highland Chiefs; whose tombs are still remaining, &amp; many of their
                    inscriptions still legible: these circumstances will always give a strong
                    interest to the place, and reward the curious traveller for the trouble it <pb n="f.20v"/>must necessarily give him to obtain a view of this interesting
                    ruin. The building also is curious as a good specimen of very ancient
                    architecture. We took to our Boat again about half past six in the evening,
                    &amp; in four hours more we were safely landed again at <placeName ref="pl1078">Ulva</placeName>; very much gratified at having been so fortunate as to
                    perform all we wished in the most comfortable manner, &amp; to have accomplished
                    both these objects in one day. —</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Wednesday July 27<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> We all
                    left <placeName ref="pl1078">Ulva</placeName> this morning, &amp; returned to
                        <placeName ref="pl0682">Aross</placeName> in the same manner that we had
                    gone to <placeName ref="pl1078">Ulva</placeName>. We found our little Boat which
                    we had brought from <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName>, ready to convey us
                    back again — at <placeName ref="pl0682">Aross</placeName>, we parted with our
                    friends the Macdonalds, as it was their intention to proceed by Water to the
                        <placeName ref="pl0715">Isle of Skye</placeName>, &amp; it was necessary <pb n="f.21r"/>we should return to <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName> to
                    meet the carriage again, &amp; go by land to <placeName ref="pl2450">Arisaig</placeName>. — We took to our Boat about half past twelve o'Clock,
                    &amp; found ourselves safe at <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName> in about
                    eight hours.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Thursday July 28<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> We
                    proceeded on our journey; crossing the ferries of <placeName ref="pl0686">Connel</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl2210">Sheean</placeName>, &amp;
                    baiting our horses at <placeName ref="pl2193">Appin</placeName> — We were very
                    much delighted with our ride, which lay through a fertile &amp; pleasing valley.
                    We came now in the district of <persName ref="pe0540">Fingal</persName>, &amp;
                    found much to admire in the softer features of this part of the Country. We took
                    a nice walk while the horses were feeding, and had a beautiful view of
                        <placeName ref="pl2213">Appin House</placeName>, &amp; of <placeName ref="pl2190">Loch Linnhe</placeName>, from a planted Hill which looks
                    immediately down upon the Lake. We afterwards pursued our journey to <placeName ref="pl2219">Ballychulish</placeName>, &amp; crossing the ferry there, we
                    took our abode till the next day <pb n="f.21v"/>at the <placeName ref="pl2226">Inn</placeName> on the Northern side of the ferry. From <placeName ref="pl2193">Appin</placeName> to this place, we had a most beautiful ride,
                    all along the side of <placeName ref="pl2190">Loch Linnhe</placeName>, which was
                    bounded on the opposite side by a very fine range of Mountains, which lie in the
                    district called <placeName ref="pl0683">Morven</placeName></p>
                <p>As we approached <placeName ref="pl2219">Ballychulish</placeName>, we wound round
                    the base of a very fine Mountain called <placeName ref="pl3282">Ben-a-vear</placeName>. This hill is exactly in front of the ferry house,
                    &amp; is a most grand &amp; beautiful object. We were all so pleased with the
                    place that we determined on staying to go up <placeName ref="pl2215">Loch
                        Leven</placeName> in the morning, though it had been our intention to go on
                    to <placeName ref="pl0206">Fort William</placeName> the same night. —</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Friday 29<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> We took a Boat
                    &amp; were rowed to the head of <placeName ref="pl2215">Loch Leven</placeName>,
                    where we got out, &amp; walked to see <pb n="f.22r"/>two very beautiful Water
                    falls. One of these is the highest I have ever seen; it is said to be 160 feet
                    from the beginning of the fall to the bottom; there was no great body of water,
                    but quite enough to let us see its beauty. From the manner in which it falls, it
                    spreads itself over a very wide surface of rock in a thin sheet, which is white
                    with foam, &amp; dashes its spray to a very considerable distance. The scenery
                    immediately around this fall is particularly fine. Rocks of a stupendous height
                    enclose it on three sides, &amp; these are beautifully ornamented with birch
                    &amp; other trees, which grow out of their sides at frequent intervals. The head
                    of the Loch is nine or ten miles from the ferry, about half way up, is the
                    entrance to <placeName ref="pl2433">Glencoe</placeName>, which we propose to
                    travel through after our return from the <placeName ref="pl0715">Isle of
                        Skye</placeName>.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.22v"/> Both sides of <placeName ref="pl2215">Loch Leven</placeName> are
                    bounded by magnificent ranges of Mountains, each differing from the other in
                    figure &amp; size, but the same general character is observable in all — There
                    is more verdure &amp; softness than we had lately seen, with a mixture of rock,
                    &amp; now &amp; then fine tufted woody sides, which added very much to the
                    beauty of the whole. There cannot be a grander scene, or a finer confusion of
                    Mountains, than is presented to the view on the — borders of this beautiful
                    Lake.</p>
                <p>We returned to <placeName ref="pl2219">Ballychulish</placeName> to dinner, &amp;
                    afterwards pursued our journey to <placeName ref="pl0206">Fort
                        William</placeName>, by the side of <placeName ref="pl0830">Loch
                        Eil</placeName>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Saturday July 30<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> We left
                        <placeName ref="pl0206">Fort William</placeName> after breakfast, &amp;
                    pursued our journey to <placeName ref="pl2450">Arisaig</placeName> through a
                    wilder &amp; bolder country than any we had yet seen. The distance between
                        <placeName ref="pl0206">Fort William</placeName> and <pb n="f.23r"/><placeName ref="pl2450">Arisaig</placeName> is about forty miles — there
                    was but one place which lay between them, where we could bait our horses, &amp;
                    the house was so wretched &amp; so dirty, that we could not remain in it — I
                    preferred sitting in the Carriage while the rest of the party walked on, till we
                    should over-take them — For several miles after leaving <placeName ref="pl0206">Fort William</placeName>, our road lay through a barren &amp; wretched
                    country: it was on both sides of the road a black boggy soil, &amp; the only
                    pleasing features were two or three rapid torrents from the mountains sides
                    which flowed into the Lake below us. But as we proceeded to the distance of
                    about eight or nine miles, we found ourselves surrounded by the greatest scenery
                    possible. The hills on either hand were of stupendous height &amp; their forms
                    &amp; surfaces beautifully varied by projecting rocks; large Scotch firs (by far
                    the finest we have seen any where <pb n="f.23v"/>of natural growth) and a
                    variety of — smaller trees, birches, alders &amp;c, the natural growth of the
                    soil; all contributed to render this part of our journey as picturesque &amp; as
                    magnificent as can be imagined. — We now soon opened upon <placeName ref="pl3283">Loch Shiel</placeName>, which we followed the bends of, for
                    some miles — All this part of our journey was exceedingly interesting; there was
                    — nearly as much beauty as in most places we have seen, &amp; more of sublime
                    &amp; terrific than in any district we had before visited — The road is very
                    excellent, &amp; carried as much as was possible, at the bases of the hills; but
                    in some parts of it, this was not practicable, &amp; we now &amp; then found —
                    ourselves at an aweful height above the Lake, looking perpendicularly down upon
                    it. — We arrived at <placeName ref="pl2450">Arisaig</placeName> to dinner, where
                    we found our young friend <pb n="f.24r"/><persName ref="pe0081">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Mathew Macdonald</persName> waiting to
                    receive us. <persName ref="pe0084">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Charles
                        Macdonald</persName> had — proceeded homewards, to prepare for our arrival
                    at <placeName ref="pl2983">Scalpa</placeName>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Sunday July the 31<hi rend="superscript">st.</hi></hi> We
                    all set sail this morning for the <placeName ref="pl0715">Isle of
                        Skye</placeName>, and were landed at the <sic>the</sic>
                    <placeName ref="pl0679">Isle of Oransay</placeName>, at the house of <persName ref="pe0125">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Elder</persName>, who kindly
                    furnished us with the means of proceeding by land to <placeName ref="pl0658">Corry-chatachan</placeName>, where we were welcomed by <persName ref="pe0099">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi></persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe0089">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>Kinnon</persName>, &amp; afterwards conveyed in one of <persName ref="pe0099">Corry's</persName> boats across the Ferry (about two or three
                    miles) to <placeName ref="pl2983">Scalpa</placeName>. We arrived about nine in
                    the evening &amp; were most kindly welcomed by <persName ref="pl2983">Scalpa</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe0092">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Macdonald</persName>. There was no other part of the family at
                        <placeName ref="pl2983">Scalpa</placeName>, except our kind friend <persName ref="pe0084">Charles Macdonald</persName>, &amp; one of the daughters
                        <persName ref="pe0094">Miss Francis Macdonald</persName>. —</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Monday August 1<hi rend="superscript">st.</hi></hi> We
                    enjoyed the refreshment of rest, in a comfortable house after our long continued
                    wanderings; &amp; only <pb n="f.24v"/>quitted it to walk a little about: after
                    the frequent rains that had recently fallen the country was too wet for much
                    walking if we had been so disposed. I had the very great pleasure of finding
                    letters from all I love (all of whom I was then so distant from,) at <placeName ref="pl2983">Scalpa</placeName>; to which place I had desired letters to be
                    address'd to me: this satisfaction, added to that of being greatly pleased with
                    the kind reception we met with from all the Macdonalds, rendered this a very
                    agreeable day. <persName ref="pe0079">Scalpa</persName> himself is a man of more
                    than seventy: he is lively, &amp; very intelligent: exceedingly kind &amp;
                    hospitable to his guests, &amp; full of conversation: he has travelled much in
                    early life, in foreign countries; &amp; is full of anecdote &amp; information on
                    most subjects. <persName ref="pe0092">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi>
                        Macdonald</persName> is perhaps a few years younger than <persName ref="pe0079">Scalpa</persName>. She has <pb n="f.25r"/>been a very beautiful
                    woman, &amp; still retains an uncommon portion <add place="above">of
                        beauty</add> for a woman at her years; She is very gentle &amp; affectionate
                    in her manner &amp; appears to be a most kind hearted excellent woman — She is
                    not lively &amp; she talks but little — but she carries an ease &amp; serenity
                    in her appearance that are very attractive. — In her youth she was thought so
                    beautiful, that she was called the Malvina of the Isles.<note type="editorial">Malvina is the name given to the lover of the ill-fated warrior Oscar in James
                        Macpherson's <hi rend="italic">Poems of Ossian</hi>.</note> She was niece to
                    the celebrated <persName ref="pe0119">Flora Macdonald</persName>. We saw at
                        <persName ref="pe0099">Corry's</persName>
                    <persName ref="pe0120">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Macleod</persName>,
                    daughter to <persName ref="pe0119">Flora Macdonald</persName>, who has also the
                    remains of much beauty. —</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Tuesday Aug. 2<hi rend="superscript">nd.</hi></hi> We
                    proposed on this day to visit the <placeName ref="pl3078">Cave of
                        Strath-Aird</placeName>;<note type="editorial">The Spar Cave of Strathaird,
                        also known as Macalister's Cave after its proprietor, became a popular
                        tourist destination in the early nineteenth century due to its striking
                        mineral formations. The cave came to widespread notice after an account of
                        it was written by <persName ref="pe2155">Dr Kenneth MacLeay of
                            Oban</persName>, who is mentioned by the author of an 1810 <ref target="0059.xml">'Journal of a Voyage to the Western islands of
                            Scotland'</ref>. The cave was later visited by Walter Scott, and it
                        forms the basis for one of the settings of his 1815 poem The Lord of the
                        Isles. Scott noted that the entrance to the cave had been walled and gated
                        by its proprietor to reduce further damage by tourists. See Scott, The Lord
                        of the Isles, 2nd ed.(Edinburgh: 1815), pp.362-64.</note> but the day
                    proving very rainy, we were obliged to abandon our project, &amp; find our
                    amusement within doors. — <pb n="f.25v"/><hi rend="underline">Wednesday August
                            3<hi rend="superscript">rd.</hi></hi> This morning, our own party, &amp;
                    the two young Macdonalds resolved, as the day was tolerable, to go to the Cave,
                    in spite of all difficulty, if it could possibly be accomplished. We set out
                    from <persName ref="pe0099">Corry's</persName>, (after crossing to his house in
                    a Boat,) some of the party on horseback, others on foot, to cross that part of
                    the <placeName ref="pl0715">Island of Skye</placeName>, which lay between us
                    &amp; <placeName ref="pl2965">Loch Slappin</placeName>; on the South-Western
                    side of which, the <placeName ref="pl3078">Cave of Strath-aird</placeName> is
                    situated. — The wind was contrary, &amp; the water very rough; but there seemed
                    to be no danger in attempting it, so we were all of us anxious to try it. We
                    crossed <placeName ref="pl2965">Loch-Slappin</placeName>, &amp; intended to have
                    proceeded to the Cave by water, keeping near the shore. — but, we found it so
                    very unpleasant, that we determined on landing, &amp; walking the three or four
                    miles which lay between us <pb n="f.26r"/>and it. We ordered the Boat to meet us
                    at the spot nearest to the Cave, where we might again enter it; &amp; then
                    proceeded on our walk. This we accomplished exceedingly well, &amp; on our
                    arrival just met the Boat at the spot. We then got into it, and were rowed into
                    the aweful chasm which forms the entrance to the <placeName ref="pl3078">Cave of
                        Strath Aird</placeName>. Our Boatmen were reluctant &amp; timid, &amp; said
                    they had never attempted to land a party there in such rough weather, or with so
                    high a Sea. In truth the swell was immense; but the M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Macdonalds are so well acquainted with all that relates to the Sea,
                    &amp; so active in overcoming every difficulty, that we felt quite safe while
                    they — thought us so; &amp; they enabled us to effect our purpose most
                    satisfactorily. The roughness of the weather, which seemed to be so great an
                    impediment, proved on the whole an advantage, as it added <pb n="f.26v"/>much to
                    the grandeur of the scene at the entrance of the Cave. The approach to it is
                    through a chasm in the cleft, of solid rock — the sides on either hand are
                    perpendicular 100 feet in height: the depth, from the entrance to the opening of
                    the cave, is 500 feet; the breadth is 30 feet. We landed a few yards from the
                    mouth of the cave, which forms, at the entrance, a pointed arch. As soon as we
                    had advanced a very little way beyond the entrance, we lost the light of day,
                    and had about a dozen large lights carried with us, to show us the wonders &amp;
                    beauties of the interior. We soon began to ascend, which was only to be
                    accomplished with labour &amp; difficulty — the continued dripping making every
                    place wet &amp; slippery. — The whole surface upon which we walked, or rather
                    climbed, is a white spar, &amp; has been compared, &amp; that not <pb n="f.27r"/>unaptly, to a frozen cascade; the roof above our heads was hung with
                    stalactites of the purest white, of various length &amp; sizes, but all having
                    the form of icicles. when we got to the top of the steep ascent, we were at once
                    surprized &amp; delighted to see the various &amp; fanciful forms which were
                    presented to our view. We could have imagined that the finest ornamental carving
                    met our eyes — resemblances to human figures, pieces of architecture, lofty
                    pillars, &amp; an endless variety of forms, lined the sides of this superb
                    cavern, while the roof from beginning to end was enriched by the same sort of
                    pendant stalactites we had observed below. The whole of the inside of the cave,
                    with all its beauteous ornaments, are of the purest white — At the further end
                    there is a pool of considerable depth, over which <add place="above">once</add>
                    hung, suspended from the roof above, what had the <pb n="f.27v"/>regular form
                    &amp; semblance of a chandelier. It can scarcely be believed that any person
                    could be so savage &amp; insensible as to dare to injure this most delicate
                    &amp; beautiful ornament, placed there as it had been by the hand of nature. But
                    unfortunately, a very few years back a traveller of this unfeeling description
                    struck at the chandelier, which soon yielded to the rude shock, &amp; sunk into
                    the pool below. It was afterwards recovered from the water, &amp; is still
                    preserved as a great natural curiosity: but it must lose greatly by not being
                    seen where nature first placed it — We were sorry to observe, that much injury
                    had been done to many parts of the Cave by persons, who, wishing to carry away
                    specimens, had broken the sides in many places, &amp; defaced <pb n="f.28r"/>the
                    surface most barbarously. After having accomplished our wishes, in examining the
                    magnificent cavern, we returned to our boat, which the high surge, &amp; the
                    rugged shore made it exceedingly difficult for us to re-enter — We however
                    effected it safely, &amp; returned to <placeName ref="pl2983">Scalpa</placeName>, arriving there at about a quarter before twelve at
                    night.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Thursday Aug. 4<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> A rainy
                    day confined us all to the house — We could not even get half an hours walk on
                    the sea shore close to the house.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Friday 5<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> We had fixed on
                    this day for leaving <placeName ref="pl2983">Scalpa</placeName>, but the morning
                    proving wet, &amp; the wind contrary, we were obliged to accept of our kind
                    friends' hospitality for another day.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Saturday August 6<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> The
                    morning proving tolerable, &amp; the wind favourable, we took leave of <persName ref="pe0079">Scalpa</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe0092">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi>Macdonald</persName>, &amp; set <pb n="f.28v"/>sail once more for the Main Land: our two kind &amp; indefatigable friends,
                        <persName ref="pe0084">Charles</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe0081">Mathew Macdonald</persName>, accompanying us, being resolved they said not
                    to quit their charge, till they saw us safely seated in the carriage, to pursue
                    our journey by land. — We hired a boat which <persName ref="pe0099re">Corry</persName> procured for us, to take us through the <placeName ref="pl0657">Kyles</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl2450">Arisaig</placeName>. —</p>
                <p>We were much gratified as we were approaching the <placeName ref="pl0657">Kyles</placeName>, to see water thrown up in such a manner, as to convince
                    us there were Whales near us in the sea; &amp; still were so when shortly after,
                    two or three rose so high, as to shew us their back-fin, &amp; a considerable
                    portion of their immense bulk above the sea. We watched them for several
                    minutes, &amp; saw them spout water, &amp; show themselves at frequent
                    intervals. — We had also <pb n="f.29r"/>the gratification of seeing large flocks
                    of the Soland geese flying immediately above our heads, &amp; continuously
                    darting down upon the fish in the water; this being the season of the herring
                    fishery the sounds in these seas abound with Herrings at this time. — During the
                    course of our voyage from <placeName ref="pl2983">Scalpa</placeName> to
                        <placeName ref="pl2450">Arisaig</placeName>, we passed the mouths of several
                    fine Sea Lochs; <placeName ref="pl3084">Loch-Dowie</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl0678">Loch Hourn</placeName>, &amp; <placeName ref="pl3284">Loch-Nevis.</placeName> — When we arrived about the point of the <placeName ref="pl0679">Isle of Oransay</placeName>, we looked back to take a parting
                    view of the highest Hills in <placeName ref="pl0715">Skye</placeName> — The
                        <placeName ref="pl0841">Cullin range</placeName> appeared particularly bold,
                    &amp; their broken rocky tips looked very magnificent. <placeName ref="pl0837">Ben-a-Caillish</placeName> also, with its conical summit, demanded a
                    farewell look; &amp; <placeName ref="pl2983">Scalpa</placeName>, just fading to
                    our view, called forth the tribute of a sigh, in grateful remembrance of its <pb n="f.29v"/>most kind &amp; hospitable inhabitants!</p>
                <p>We had on the whole a favourable voyage and arrived safe at <placeName ref="pl2450">Arisaig</placeName> at about seven o'clock. —</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Sunday August 7<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> at eight
                    o'clock this morning we parted with our two kind friends, <persName ref="pe0084">Charles</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe0081">Mathew
                    Macdonald</persName>; leaving them to return to <placeName ref="pl2983">Scalpa</placeName>, while we pursued our journey by land to <placeName ref="pl0206">Fort William</placeName>, where we staid the night.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Monday August 8<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> We
                    retraced our road from <placeName ref="pl0206">Fort William</placeName> to
                        <placeName ref="pl2219">Ballychulish</placeName>. — a great part of our ride
                    was dull &amp; uninteresting, but it improved as we proceeded, &amp; became very
                    beautiful when we gained a view of the fine Mountain <placeName ref="pl3282">Ben-a-vear</placeName>, with <placeName ref="pl2215">Loch Leven</placeName>
                    at its foot. — After breakfasting at <placeName ref="pl2219">Ballychulish</placeName> we proceeded through <placeName ref="pl2433">Glen-Coe</placeName> to an Inn on the <placeName ref="pl0209">Black
                        Mount</placeName>, called <placeName ref="pl0210">The King's
                        House</placeName>. The entrance to <placeName ref="pl2433">Glen-Coe</placeName> is very beautiful, &amp; is a plain of perhaps a third
                    part of a mile in breadth, the <placeName ref="pl2229">river Coe</placeName> —
                        <pb n="f.30r"/>winding along it, &amp; falling at its extremity into
                        <placeName ref="pl2215">Loch-Leven</placeName>. So much has been said about
                    the wonders &amp; horrors of <placeName ref="pl2433">Glen-Coe</placeName>, that
                    we were prepared for seeing something surpassing all that had yet fallen under
                    our observation; and as far as the terrific is capable of exciting admiration,
                    we certainly were not disappointed. As the Glen narrows, the Mountains on either
                    side rise to a gigantic height, &amp; their rude rocky sides present a picture
                    of horror &amp; desolation which can perhaps scarcely be equalled. The coulour
                    of the rock is so black, &amp; its consistence so solid, that is seems as if the
                    whole substance of the mountain was comprised of it — the bed of the river in
                    this part of the glen is also very rocky; &amp; as there is a considerable
                    descent, the noise of the water is excessive, &amp; adds greatly to the wild
                    horror of the scene. Many large streams are also seen falling from the sides <pb n="f.30v"/>of the Mountains, adding their noise &amp; their Waters, to the
                    foaming torrent below; which is here &amp; there seen to fall over so deep a
                    descent, as to afford many very grand waterfalls in its progress through the
                    Glen. — When we were nearly escaped from the awful horrors which the scene
                    presented, we turned again to take a parting survey, &amp; were more than ever
                    struck with the majestic grandeur of the scene we were quitting — The sides of
                    some, &amp; the tops of <add place="above">almost</add> all the mountains which
                    we had been passing, presented themselves at once to our view — We scarcely knew
                    how to quit a spot — which so completely arrested our attention, &amp; raised
                    our hearts to the Great Author of all this Magnificence — but it was necessary
                    to proceed, &amp; we made our way thoughtfully &amp; slowly over a <pb n="f.31r"/>wretched black &amp; boggy moor <add place="above">called <placeName ref="pl0751">Rannoch Moor</placeName>,</add> till we arrived at the
                        <placeName ref="pl0210">King's House</placeName>, where we were obliged to
                    take up our abode for the night, as the next stage to <placeName ref="pl0212">Tyndrum</placeName>, was more than our horses could well have performed;
                    &amp; besides this, it was too late in the day to undertake it. —</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Tuesday August 9<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> After
                    breakfasting at <placeName ref="pl0210">King's House</placeName>, we proceeded
                    by <placeName ref="pl2237">Inverouran</placeName> &amp; the braes of <placeName ref="pl0213">Glen Orchy</placeName>, to <placeName ref="pl0212">Tyndrum</placeName>, to dinner. — For the first few miles our road was
                    still over the <add place="above">same</add> boggy moor, near the <placeName ref="pl0209">Black mount</placeName>; but as we approached <placeName ref="pl2237">Inverouran</placeName> the scenery became far more pleasing,
                    &amp; a pretty little Lake, called <placeName ref="pl0211">Loch
                        Tollie</placeName>, gave a beauty &amp; softness to the scene, which we
                    observed with no small pleasure after the gloomy &amp; desolate track of country
                    we had been travelling.</p>
                <p>A fine Mountain, <placeName ref="pl2238">Ben Doran</placeName>, rises <pb n="f.31v"/>very high, with a sharp pointed top at a small distance north of
                        <placeName ref="pl0212">Tyndrum</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl0815">Ben
                        More</placeName> to the South East. — <placeName ref="pl2240">Ben
                        Lawers</placeName> is also seen towards the East.— After dinner we proceeded
                    to <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName>. (<placeName ref="pl0212">Tyndrum</placeName> is said to the be highest inhabited spot in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>.) The principal branch of the river
                        <placeName ref="pl0096">Tay</placeName>, rises in <placeName ref="pl2238">Ben-Doran</placeName> near to <placeName ref="pl0212">Tyndrum</placeName>;
                    it is here called the <placeName ref="pl3290">Fillan water</placeName> — We were
                    desired to look at <placeName ref="pl0990">S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi>
                        Fillan's pool</placeName>, at the distance of two or three miles from
                        <placeName ref="pl0212">Tyndrum</placeName> on the road to <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName> — it is rather a deep pool, but has nothing
                    worthy of notice about it, except that the Highlanders have a superstitious
                    notion, that maniacs will have their senses restored to them, if they are dipped
                    in <placeName ref="pl0990">S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Fillan's
                        Pool</placeName>: but this, like most other traditions of this sort is now
                    little thought of, &amp; never I believe acted upon.</p>
                <p>The road winds along the base of <placeName ref="pl0815">Ben-More</placeName>,
                    under which is a small Lake called <placeName ref="pl0817">Loch
                        Dochart</placeName>. There is in <pb n="f.32r"/>this Lake a beautifully
                    wooded little — island, on which are seen the ruins of <placeName ref="pl2365">S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Fillan's Chapel</placeName>. Below the
                    Lake, the river which we had seen under the name of <placeName ref="pl3290">S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Fillan's water</placeName>, is called by the
                    name of <placeName ref="pl0995">Dochart</placeName> — it now acquires
                    considerable size, &amp; flows through a wider &amp; better cultivated valley,
                    than any we had seen for some time past. We stopped to bait our horses at
                        <placeName ref="pl1121">Luib</placeName>, a tolerable Highland Inn about
                    seven miles from <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName>.</p>
                <p>The latter part of this day's ride improved greatly upon us — the scenery became
                    softer, &amp; much more pleasing; and as we approached <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName>, we were delighted to observe hills richly wooded,
                    plains finely cultivated, and a large collection of houses and cottages, of a
                    far more comfortable appearance than the wretched huts we had seen in the more
                    remote parts of the <placeName ref="pl0711">Highlands &amp;
                    Islands</placeName>.</p>
                <p>As we drove up to <placeName ref="pl2106">Cameron's Inn</placeName>, situated
                    just above the bank of the lovely river <placeName ref="pl1003">Lochy</placeName>
                    <add place="above">(which falls into the <placeName ref="pl0995">Dochart</placeName> a little way below)</add>, we passed a <pb n="f.32v"/>large church, which added not a little to the satisfaction we
                    felt, and seemed to — give conviction to the cheering idea, that we were once
                    more returned to the busy haunts of Men. — For the last two or three days we had
                    sustained a good deal of inconvenience from the very — wretched accommodation
                    the Inns we had been lodged at, had afforded us. At <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName> we were exceedingly comfortable in this respect — this
                    happened very fortunately for me; for I had undergone so much fatigue, that it
                    was — becoming too much for me, and I was so exhausted &amp; unwell in the
                    evening as to feel very thankful that we were arrived at such comfortable
                    quarters.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Wednesday August 10<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> My
                    langour &amp; fatigue continuing; I kept my bed till late in the day, and missed
                    the opportunity of enjoying as I otherwise should have done, the beautiful
                    walks, &amp; the enchanting views which render the <pb n="f.33r"/>neighbourhood
                    of <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName> so very delightful. The village
                    stands at the Western head of <placeName ref="pl0104">Loch Tay</placeName>, and
                    commands very fine views of the Lake — It is remarkable for having two private
                    burying grounds near it, one belonging to <persName ref="pe1375">Lord
                        Breadalbane</persName>, the great proprietor of almost the whole of this
                    district; &amp; the <placeName ref="pl2242">other</placeName> to M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> MacNab,<note type="editorial">A reference to the
                        historical burial site of Clan MacNab at <placeName ref="pl2242">Innes
                            Bhuidhe</placeName> on the River Dochart.</note> who also has a house
                    near <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin.</placeName> — These burying grounds are
                    both of them romantic &amp; beautiful; that belonging to <persName ref="pe1375">Lord Breadalbane</persName>, is the most so. The <placeName ref="pl2241">Mausoleum</placeName> is situated in a large Area, within which a Castle
                    formerly stood, ruins of which still grace the solemn scene — The ground within
                    the bounds of it, is beautifully kept; and besides the grand ornament of some of
                    the finest sycamore trees I ever beheld, it is burdened &amp; planted with
                    shrubs &amp; flowers. It commands a very <pb n="f.33v"/>fine view of <placeName ref="pl0104">Loch Tay</placeName>, and is in full front of a very pretty
                    Cottage, which is often visited by <persName ref="pe1375">Lord
                        Breadalbane</persName>, &amp; of which his <persName ref="pe0126">Lady</persName> is particularly fond. — On <hi rend="underline">Thursday
                        Aug. 11<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> after visiting the spot I have
                    been describing, and dining at <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName>, we
                    proceeded by the south side of <placeName ref="pl0104">Loch Tay</placeName> to
                        <placeName ref="pl0103">Kenmore</placeName>. The Lake runs so nearly
                    straight, from the East to West, that we saw almost the whole reach of it,
                    during the greater part of our ride, a stage of 16 miles. We were very glad
                    indeed not to lose sight of the lovely hills &amp; fertile valley of <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName>, till we had nearly arrived at the eastern
                    extremity of the Lake, &amp; entered the neat comfortable looking village of
                        <placeName ref="pl0103">Kenmore</placeName> — We found here a very good
                        <placeName ref="pl2104">Inn</placeName>, where we were soon provided <pb n="f.34r"/>with comfortable beds, one of which I was very glad to retire to,
                    being quite fatigued, but much gratified by the exertions of the day. I must not
                    omit to mention the beautiful &amp; singular appearance <placeName ref="pl2240">Ben-Lawers</placeName> had, during a part of our ride — This Mountain is
                    situated on the north side of the Lake — It was almost covered by thick clouds
                    the whole of the day; but now &amp; then the mist vanished from the highest
                    point of the mountain &amp; shewed a dark, &amp; nearly conical ridge, at so
                    great a height above every other terrestrial object, that it seemed like
                    something fixed in the firmament, &amp; it was difficult to persuade ourselves
                    that its foundation was on earth. —</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Friday Aug. 12<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> The
                    morning being fine, <persName ref="pe0002">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                        Malkin</persName>, <persName ref="pe0071">Miss Hall</persName> &amp;
                        <persName ref="pe0030">Benjamin</persName> determined <pb n="f.34v"/>on
                    ascending to the summit of <placeName ref="pl2240">Ben-Lawers</placeName>, which
                    they effected much to their satisfaction; though they had occasional mists and
                    showers to encounter. I did not attempt a task of so much labour; but was glad
                    of an opportunity of lying by for a day, in hopes that the rest it might afford
                    me, would a little recover my fatigue, &amp; recruit my strength.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Saturday Aug. 13<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi>
                    Immediately after breakfast this morning, we visited <placeName ref="pl0101">Taymouth Castle</placeName>, the seat of <persName ref="pe1375">Lord
                        Breadalbane</persName>. The grounds which lead to the Castle are as
                    beautiful as the imagination can conceive: they possess in themselves every
                    various charm which Nature can give them; the noble river <placeName ref="pl0096">Tay</placeName>, rolls majestically through the park, which is
                    ornamented by fine timber in vast profusion — the ground itself is full of
                    variety, here swelling into easy slopes, &amp; there sinking into lovely plains
                    — every high point which commands a view of <placeName ref="pl0104">Loch
                        Tay</placeName> to the <pb n="f.35r"/>West, &amp; of the superb Mountains
                    which surround this delightful scene, is made accessible by walks which are kept
                    in the nicest order. From one of these little eminences, you command a view of a
                    very beautiful Water fall, which falls a great depth on a rocky-steep, &amp; is
                    surrounded on all sides by richly wooded rocky scenery. This Cascade has a good
                    deal the same character, both in itself, &amp; its accompaniments, as the
                        <placeName ref="pl0440">Hermitage Fall</placeName>; which we had gone out of
                    our road to see, about two miles short of <placeName ref="pl0103">Kenmore</placeName>, on our drive from <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName>: but it is not equal to it in grandeur. The park is well
                    stocked with Deer; &amp; we were gratified by seeing two or three of the genuine
                    Red Deer, which is now become so very scarce, &amp; is very rarely to be met
                    with any where. After wandering with delight in this sylvan scene, we approached
                    the <placeName ref="pl0101">Castle</placeName>, which is not yet quite
                    compleated — It is a very beautiful pile of building, of a dark granite, which
                        <pb n="f.35v"/>the same greenish hue, we so much admired at <placeName ref="pl0217">Inverary Castle</placeName> — but <placeName ref="pl0101">Taymouth Castle</placeName> is very superior. The principal part of the
                    building is very nearly finished, but it is intended to add two wings to it
                    before the whole is compleated. The inside of the house is extremely handsome;
                    it is ornamented with very fine carving, in the entrance, the staircase &amp;c:
                    every thing within is in excellent taste, except perhaps the staircase, which
                    has many beautifully ornamented niches in the walls, which do not appear to have
                    any use; &amp; unless they are to be occupied by statues, they must appear to be
                    unmeaning &amp; superfluous. — The floors are all of the finest oak, beautifully
                    laid in the forms of a lozenge, &amp; filled up like mosaic, with small pieces —
                    The ceiling <add place="above">&amp; cornices</add> are also exceedingly
                    handsome, many of them of oak, &amp; finely wrought. The <pb n="f.36r"/>chimney
                    pieces are of fine marble, mostly black, or <unclear reason="illegible">dun</unclear>-colour, &amp; all the fitting up of the apartments, as far as
                    the architectural part may be called so, is in the gothic stile. — There are
                    some good pictures, but these are not very numerous. After having seen the
                    Castle, we took a drive through the beautiful glen of <placeName ref="pl0106">Fortingale</placeName>
                    <add place="inline">wound round the hill called <placeName ref="pl3291">Drummond
                            hill</placeName></add> &amp; followed for several miles the course of
                    the fine river <placeName ref="pl0279">Lyon</placeName>, leaving <placeName ref="pl0105">glen-lyon</placeName> to our right; when we wound round <add place="above">to</add> the side of <placeName ref="pl0104">Loch-Tay</placeName>, to return to <placeName ref="pl0103">Kenmore</placeName>. We then dined at our Inn, &amp; afterwards pursued our
                    journey to <placeName ref="pl1124">Aberfeldi</placeName>; where we turned out of
                    the high road, &amp; walked about a mile &amp; a half to see the magnificent
                    waterfall at <placeName ref="pl0280">Moness</placeName>. We were well rewarded
                    for our labour: this fall is altogether the longest, &amp; the finest of any we
                    had seen — the descent is not so precipitous, but it is of greater length, and
                    the rocks, &amp; the wood in the surrounding <pb n="f.36v"/>scenery are
                    particularly grand. This fall is also in <persName ref="pe1375">Lord
                        Breadalbanes</persName> grounds, &amp; the paths to it are made as easy
                    &amp; convenient as possible. — There was a very considerable body of water,
                    after the rains which had recently fallen; so that we had the pleasure of seeing
                    this — majestic torrent with every advantage, &amp; returned to the carriage
                    much delighted with what I had beheld. We went across the <placeName ref="pl0096">Tay</placeName>, over <placeName ref="pl0102">Wade's
                        Bridge</placeName><note type="editorial">The bridge over the River Tay at
                        Aberfeldy was completed under the supervision of General George Wade in
                        1733, as part of a military road network commissioned by George I to exert
                        greater control over the Highlands. An inscription on the bridge compares
                        Wade's achievement to the Roman conquest of Caledonia. See Nigel Leask, <hi rend="italic">Stepping Westward: Writing the Highland Tour
                            c.1720-1830</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2020),
                        pp.61-62.</note> to <placeName ref="pl2102">Weem</placeName>, where we were
                    very comfortably accommodated for the night. —</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Sunday, August 14<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> After
                    having — breakfasted at <placeName ref="pl2102">Weem</placeName>, we went to the
                    little village of <placeName ref="pl2247">Balnaguard</placeName>, where we
                    stopt, &amp; walked about a mile to see a very romantic &amp; picturesque,
                    (though very little known) waterfall — after this we crossed two ferries, one
                    over the <placeName ref="pl0096">Tay</placeName>, the other over the <placeName ref="pl0283">Tummel</placeName>; &amp; continued <pb n="f.37r"/>our journey
                    as far as <placeName ref="pl0110">Blair-Athol</placeName>, where we took up our
                    abode for the night. Our road <add place="above">(after crossing the second
                        ferry)</add> lay briefly through a beautiful valley, through which the fine
                    river we had last crossed, the <placeName ref="pl0283">Tummel</placeName>,
                    flowed. After following its course for some miles we left it, after passing
                        <placeName ref="pl0113">Fascally</placeName>; &amp; just at the point where
                    the <placeName ref="pl1129">Garry</placeName> falls into it. — We then pursued
                    the course of this latter stream, which rolls over a very deep bottom, through
                    the <placeName ref="pl0112">pass of Killycrankie</placeName> — This part of our
                    ride was uncommonly striking — We were surrounded on all sided by majestic
                    Mountains, some parts cover'd with the finest wood, others offering a rocky
                    &amp; barren surface to the view; others again looking verdant &amp; fertile,
                    &amp; appearing cultivated to a very great height. — We seemed once more to have
                    quitted the inhabited part of the world, &amp; to be shut out by <pb n="f.37v"/>lofty barriers, from the haunts of men, but as we entered the village of
                        <placeName ref="pl0110">Blair</placeName> we saw little groups of people,
                    and the happy smiling faces <add place="above">of</add> children: this gave an
                    air of cheerfulness to the scene, and we arrived at our Inn well pleased with
                    our day's journey; but I myself heartily glad to be advanced to the end of it,
                    having felt for the last two hours much fatigued &amp; exhausted. — (I should
                    not omit to mention the rich and fertile valley through which our road lay, the
                    whole of the way from <placeName ref="pl2102">Weem</placeName>, to the place
                    where we were ferried across the <placeName ref="pl0096">Tay</placeName>; on the
                    eastern side of which, lay the pretty little village of <placeName ref="pl0281">Logierait</placeName>. The whole of this low district is called <placeName ref="pl3292">Strath-Tay</placeName>. It is ornamented by a great many pretty
                    houses &amp; presents a picture of cheerfulness &amp; comfort which we
                    contemplated with great pleasure. The river <placeName ref="pl0096">Tay</placeName> which winds the <pb n="f.38r"/>whole length of this valley,
                    is in full view from the road, &amp; is become a very — large &amp; majestic
                    river — A little way below <placeName ref="pl0281">Logierait</placeName>, it
                    receives the <placeName ref="pl0283">Tummel</placeName> also, &amp; they then
                    flow in one united current towards <placeName ref="pl0099">Dunkeld</placeName>.
                    —) <hi rend="underline">Monday Aug. 15<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> It
                    was our intention this morning, after seeing all we wished to see at <placeName ref="pl0110">Blair Athol</placeName>, to set out early on our way to
                        <placeName ref="pl0099">Dunkeld</placeName> — but at the time we were
                    preparing for it, a fire broke out at <placeName ref="pl0110">Blair
                        Castle</placeName>, one of the Seats of the <persName ref="pe0548">Duke of
                        Athol</persName>. — This was so serious and alarming a circumstance, in a
                    place so much out of the way of all ready aid in such an event, that we could
                    not think of leaving the place, till we should see what was likely to be the
                    consequence, &amp; whether the fire could, by the assistance of the
                    country-people be got under. —</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe0548">The Duke</persName> himself was absent, being with a
                    shooting party on <placeName ref="pl3293">Ben-Gloe</placeName>. The <persName ref="pe0102">Dutchess</persName>, with some of the family were at the Castle
                        <pb n="f.38v"/>We all repaired to the place, to see if in any way we could
                    be of service, &amp; our three Man Servants were amongst the most active &amp;
                    useful in carrying water and pulling down parts of the building to prevent the
                    spreading of the flames to the Main body of the Castle, the fire having begun in
                    the Wing. — We had the pleasure of seeing that the efforts of the people, which
                    though not very meticulously directed, were very active, soon succeeded in
                    getting under the fire, and by four o'clock in the afternoon we felt assured
                    that all further danger to the building was over. This being the case, we
                    determined on prosecuting our original intention of leaving <placeName ref="pl0110">Blair Athol</placeName> — Our journey lay back again <add place="above">by</add> the road we had travelled the day before, through the
                    rich &amp; beautiful vale of <placeName ref="pl0283">Tummel</placeName>.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.39r"/> Near <placeName ref="pl0113">Fascally</placeName>, we quitted the
                    Carriage &amp; walked a mile out of the road, to see the very fine <placeName ref="pl0109">falls of the Tummel</placeName>: the quantity of water in these
                    falls, is said to be greater than in any other waterfall in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>. We were exceedingly delighted with this
                    magnificent spectacle. All the surrounding scenery, the rocks, the hills, the
                    woods, harmonized with each other; &amp; the loud noise of the foaming torrent
                    produced the grandest effect. — Our way to this fall, lay through the grounds of
                        <persName ref="pe0106">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Butter</persName>, of
                        <placeName ref="pl0113">Fascally</placeName>, a most beautiful &amp;
                    romantic place within a short distance from our road.<note type="editorial">The
                        house and grounds at Faskally are praised by Thomas Pennant in his <hi rend="italic">Tour in Scotland 1769</hi>, 3rd edn. (Warrington: 1774),
                        p.119. At the time of Pennant's visit, the inhabitant was a Mr
                        Robertson.</note></p>
                <p>We quitted the banks of the <placeName ref="pl0283">Tummel</placeName> at the
                    place where we had ferried over, &amp; then pursued the course of the <placeName ref="pl0096">Tay</placeName>, to the town of <placeName ref="pl0099">Dunkeld</placeName>; where we arrived after nine o'clock in the evening.
                    —</p>
                <p>We found a very comfortable Inn, &amp; took up our lodgings in it for the night.
                    —</p>
                <p><pb n="f.39v"/>
                    <hi rend="underline">Tuesday Aug. 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi> We spent
                    the morning in seeing the grounds of the <persName ref="pe0548">Duke of
                        Athol</persName> who has also a seat at <placeName ref="pl0099">Dunkeld</placeName>. The principal object is a fall on the <placeName ref="pl2095">River Brand</placeName>, which is called the <placeName ref="pl0440">Hermitage Fall</placeName>, in front of which a building has
                    been erected, which is whimsically called the <placeName ref="pl2093">Hall of
                        Ossian</placeName>; where the family sometimes make parties &amp; go to
                    dine. There is a very nice room, prettily fitted up, &amp; ornamented with
                    glasses, &amp; mirrors, which show the fall in various directions. Here is a
                    very considerable body of water, &amp; the rocks over which it tumbles are very
                    rude, &amp; very wide — the effect of the whole is very fine — We quitted this,
                    &amp; pursued the upper course of the stream to the <placeName ref="pl2094">rumbling brig</placeName>, where there is also another grand fall. The Town
                    of <placeName ref="pl0099">Dunkeld</placeName> is beautifully situated: the
                        <placeName ref="pl0096">Tay</placeName> is here become a very large river,
                        <pb n="f.40r"/>having a very handsome stone Bridge over it, built withing a
                    few years. —</p>
                <p>There are very considerable remains of the <placeName ref="pl2250">Cathedral</placeName> still standing, but they do not offer any thing
                    particularly curious to the observation — A part of the <placeName ref="pl2250">Cathedral</placeName> is still resorted to, as the parish Church; this is
                    in a wretched dilapidated state, &amp; the Ailes &amp; Pews are so ill kept,
                    &amp; so charged with dirt &amp; dust, as to look very forlorn &amp;
                    uncomfortable. It must appear to all english travellers, that it is a great
                    disgrace to the inhabitants of such a Town as <placeName ref="pl0099">Dunkeld</placeName>, to suffer their Church to <add place="above">be</add>
                    so shamefully neglected.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Wednesday Aug. 17<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> After
                    breakfast we quitted <placeName ref="pl0099">Dunkeld</placeName>, &amp; pursued
                    the course of the <placeName ref="pl0096">Tay</placeName> for some distance;
                    winding along under <placeName ref="pl2087">Birnam Hill</placeName>, which is a
                    fine craggy &amp; picturesque Mountain, but no longer boasts the wood attributed
                    to it <pb n="f.40v"/>by <persName ref="pe0494">Shakespear</persName>. We looked
                    back towards <placeName ref="pl0099">Dunkeld</placeName>, &amp; were more than
                    ever charmed with the beauty of its situation, &amp; the grandeur &amp; richness
                    of the surrounding Scenery — after we had advanced three or four miles, the face
                    of the country became less interesting, &amp; acquired quite a different
                    character. There is a great deal in the road between <placeName ref="pl0099">Dunkeld</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl0094">Perth</placeName>, which
                    strongly reminded us of <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>. The plains
                    are wider than any we had long seen, &amp; the enclosures here, were principally
                    hedges — the distant views also in this district were less marked by bold
                    mountain ridges, &amp; partook greatly of the tamer features of English
                    landscape. We had a pleasant ride to <placeName ref="pl0094">Perth</placeName>,
                    where we arrived about one o'clock; &amp; we passed two or three hours before
                    dinner in walking to see the beauties of this place. The town is considerable
                    but not of great extent — It has some <pb n="f.41r"/>handsome buildings,
                    particularly those which are upon the <placeName ref="pl3294">North-Inch</placeName>. Its situation is very beautiful, and the noble
                    river, the <placeName ref="pl0096">Tay</placeName>, forms one of its finest
                    ornaments. There is a handsome stone bridge over the river, which is a fine
                    object wherever it is seen; but in going over it, a person is surprized to find
                    it narrow, and shabby — having a foot pavement only on one side of the bridge.
                    The views up and down the river, as you stand upon the bridge, are exceedingly
                    rich; and the whole appearance of the Town &amp; neighbourhood gives the idea of
                    ease &amp; comfort. —</p>
                <p>At <placeName ref="pl0094">Perth</placeName> I had the great satisfaction of
                    receiving a large packet of letters, from my children, from <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>, &amp; from my Brother.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Thursday August 18<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi>
                    Having seen all we wished of <placeName ref="pl0094">Perth</placeName>
                    yesterday, we left it this morning, and visited <placeName ref="pl3295">Lyndock</placeName> the very pretty cottage of <persName ref="pe1454"><add place="above">General</add> Sir Thomas Grahame, now Lord
                        Lyndock</persName>. There is little in this place to render it worthy of
                    going much <pb n="f.41v"/>out of the road for; but the house is a low thatched
                    building, containing only two Good rooms, and several bed-rooms — It has however
                    the merit of being exactly what it is said to be, a perfect cottage; which is
                    rendered a very lovely little abode by the grounds in which it is situated — It
                    has a conservatory, into which the dining room opens, which had some of the
                    finest green-house plants I ever saw; &amp; they all bore a rich profusion of
                    blossom, which rendered it very beautiful. There were no curious plants in it,
                    but those which grow there, are the finest of their kind. — It was trained up
                    with Passion-flowers, &amp; other creepers, to the top of the conservatory,
                    &amp; the woody stalks were as thick as my arm. — The garden also was well
                    stored with flowers, &amp; there was <pb n="f.42r"/>very fine fruit in
                    hot-houses. The <placeName ref="pl3296">graves of Bessy Bell &amp; Mary
                        Gray</placeName>, are shown in these grounds.<note type="editorial">According to tradition, Bessie Bell and Mary Gray were two women who, in
                        1666, attempted to escape the plague by isolating themselves in a small
                        dwelling next to a tributary of the River Almond. They were said to have
                        died after contracting the plague from a young male visitor with whom they
                        were both enamored. The story is recounted in a popular song, and in
                        Alexander Campbell, <hi rend="italic">A Journey from Edinburgh through Parts
                            of North Britain</hi> (London: 1802), 2 Vols., i, p.358.</note> The
                    river <placeName ref="pl0306">Almon</placeName> flows through them, &amp; adds
                    greatly to their beauty. — On quitting <placeName ref="pl3295">Lyndock</placeName>, it was our intention to have proceeded by a new road
                    through <placeName ref="pl3297">Glen-Almon</placeName>, to <placeName ref="pl0295">Crief</placeName>: but our postilions were misinformed
                    respecting their way &amp; took us over a wretched barren moor for many long
                    miles, till at the end of four hours we found ourselves at <placeName ref="pl3298">Amulree</placeName>, where we baited our horses, &amp; took
                    some refreshment ourselves — We afterwards proceeded to <placeName ref="pl0295">Crief</placeName>, going through a part of <placeName ref="pl3297">Glen-Almon</placeName>, with which we were much pleased — this part of the
                    Glen was at the other extremity from that we had intended taking in the morning.
                    We all found ourselves much fatigued by this days journey, as our road for the
                    grater part was wholly uninteresting, &amp; the <pb n="f.42v"/>most laborious
                    &amp; stony of any we had travelled over in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>. The Country became pretty again, as we approached the
                    Town of <placeName ref="pl0295">Crief</placeName>, &amp; we were very glad to
                    find ourselves safely arrived &amp; lodged at a pretty good Inn; for we had been
                    apprehensive, lest from the extreme badness of the road, the Carriage might
                        <del>not</del> have met with some serious injury: this however did not prove
                    to have been the case.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Friday August 19<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> This
                    morning we pursued our journey towards <placeName ref="pl3299">Loch-Earn
                        head</placeName>. At the distance of about two or three miles from
                        <placeName ref="pl0295">Crief</placeName>, we entered the grounds of
                        <placeName ref="pl0296">Ochtertire</placeName>, the seat of <persName ref="pe0128">Sir Patrick Murray</persName> — Our first object was to see a
                    fine water fall here, which we visited, and were greatly pleased with: it is on
                    the <placeName ref="pl3300">Turret</placeName>, a river of no great size, but
                    the bed is rocky, the sides all wooded, &amp; the general character,
                    particularly at the fall, is very pleasing. The grounds are very beautiful; the
                    house, a good comfortable <pb n="f.43r"/>modern building, of a dark grey stone.
                    It is exceedingly well situated, about mid way up the side of a hill — high
                    enough to command a fine view of all the neighbouring country, &amp; yet
                    sufficiently below the summit, to be well skreened by the Mountain behind from
                    the North winds. There can scarcely be found a happier combination of the
                    grandeur of Highland scenery, with the softer beauties of more southern
                    landscape, than at <placeName ref="pl0296">Ochtertyre</placeName>. — Quitting
                    this lovely place, we proceeded to the pretty little town of <placeName ref="pl0298">Comrie</placeName>; which we quitted to visit the <placeName ref="pl3302">Pillar</placeName> which is erected to the memory of the late
                        <persName ref="pe0453">Lord Melville</persName>, on a very high &amp;
                    picturesque rocky hill, above the town. We were much gratified on ascending this
                    height, with the fine views which we beheld from it. On our descent from it we
                    visited the fine <placeName ref="pl3301">falls of the Comrie</placeName>, which
                    lie at a great depth in the glen, almost immediately below the pillar. The
                    effect of all these <pb n="f.43v"/>objects is very striking: &amp; the eye is
                    carried over a very richly wooded narrow Glen, through which the river murmurs
                    hoarsely, to the town of <placeName ref="pl0298">Comrie</placeName>, the pretty
                    Church appearing to close the scene — the river Comrie<note type="editorial">No
                        river with the name Comrie exists; Malkin may be referring to the nearby
                            <placeName ref="pl3318">Water of Ruchill</placeName></note> is not a
                    large stream, but very impetuous; falling over a rocky bottom, with frequent
                    interruptions, into the river <placeName ref="pl2256">Earn</placeName>, a little
                    below the town of <placeName ref="pl0298">Comrie</placeName>. —</p>
                <p>A little way beyond this place, we came to <placeName ref="pl3317">Dunira</placeName>, formerly the favorite seat of <persName ref="pe0453">Lord Melville</persName>, but now let to a gentleman of the name of
                        <persName ref="pe0130">Drummond</persName>. The grounds here are very
                    pretty, but are less attended to than they used to be in the time of the late
                        <persName ref="pe0453">Lord Melville</persName>. —</p>
                <p>In the afternoon we proceeded by the North side of <placeName ref="pl0299">Loch-Earn</placeName> to the Inn at the head of the Lake; where we took up
                    our abode, &amp; found ourselves very comfortably accommodated. — Our ride by
                    the side <pb n="f.44r"/>of the Lake was very beautiful: the hills on either side
                    being very lofty, &amp; finely varied by wood &amp; rock — those on the north
                    side being the commencement of the <placeName ref="pl1166">Grampians</placeName>
                    in this district, &amp; those on the south of the <placeName ref="pl2358">Balquihidder</placeName>. Above the highest top of those under which we
                    were passing (the <placeName ref="pl1166">Grampians</placeName>) we saw a very
                    large bird soaring, which we were told, (&amp; from the height at which we
                    observed it, we thought very probable) was an Eagle. We were fortunate in having
                    a very fine day, which admitted of our seeing the numerous objects we visited
                    to-day to the greatest advantage. — —</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Saturday Aug. 20<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> This
                    morning <persName ref="pe0002">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Malkin</persName>,
                        <persName ref="pe0030">Benjamin</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe0071">Miss
                        Hall</persName> ascended to the top of <placeName ref="pl3303">Ben
                        Voirlack</placeName>: the day was clear, &amp; they had a fine view of most
                    of the objects which are to be seen from that Mountain. They returned to dinner
                    at four o' Clock, after which we all took a drive as far <pb n="f.44v"/>as the
                    little Lake in <placeName ref="pl2349">Glen-Ogle</placeName>.<note type="editorial"><placeName ref="pl3320">Lochan Lairig
                        Cheile</placeName>.</note> On — arriving at this place, we were again —
                    withing the distance of about four miles from <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName> — We looked down upon the <placeName ref="pl0276">vale
                        of Dochart</placeName>, &amp; saw the tops of the hills above <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName>; but we could not see far enough to the
                    East, to catch another view of <placeName ref="pl0104">Loch-Tay</placeName>. —
                    On our road back to our Inn, we had a very fine view of <placeName ref="pl3303">Ben-Voirlack</placeName> whose lofty summit rose majestically above all the
                    surrounding hills — I could not help regretting that I had not felt equal to the
                    task of ascending it in the morning. — The scenery of <placeName ref="pl2349">Glen-Ogle</placeName> is very wild; the hills on either side are high, and
                    rocky; &amp; large — masses of stone have fallen from their <add place="above">tops,</add> which lie in the Glen, &amp; obstruct the course of the stream
                    below. The little Lake is a pretty softening feature in this wild &amp;
                    sequestered scene.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.45"/>
                    <hi rend="underline">Sunday Aug. 21<hi rend="underline">st</hi></hi> We left
                        <placeName ref="pl3299">Loch-Ernehead</placeName> after breakfast — At the
                    distance of three miles, we turned out of our road, to drive up to <placeName ref="pl3304">Loch-Noil</placeName>, or <placeName ref="pl3304">Loch
                        Voil</placeName>, for we could not exactly learn which was the proper name.
                    This is a small Lake, in a very pretty valley, West of our road from <placeName ref="pl3299">loch Erne-head</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl2324">Callendar</placeName>. — After having seen it, we returned to the high
                    road, &amp; soon came by the lovely vale of <placeName ref="pl2323">Strath-Ire</placeName>, to the north end of <placeName ref="pl3305">Loch
                        Lubnaig</placeName>, our way lying on the eastern side of the Lake. This
                    loch is also small but the scenery on both sides of it is very beautiful, &amp;
                    the hills rise in some parts immediately from the Lake, to a very great height:
                    they are partly rocky, &amp; a good deal covered with wood. Soon after quitting
                    the South End of the Lake, we entered the <placeName ref="pl2328">pass of
                        Lennie</placeName>, a fine romantic Glen — the river <placeName ref="pl1115">Tieth</placeName> flowing out of the loch, through this Glen, &amp; giving
                    a great deal of beauty to the scene. We followed the course of this fine river
                    to <pb n="f.45v"/><placeName ref="pl2324">Callander</placeName>, where we once
                    more took up our abode for the rest of the day &amp; night. It was here we first
                    entered the <placeName ref="pl0711">Highlands</placeName>, here also we bid them
                    adieu!</p>
                <p>Tomorrow we shall pursue our journey homewards through the <placeName ref="pl1139">Lowland districts of Scotland</placeName>. We shall I hope
                    carry with us a grateful remembrance of the kindness we have experienced, &amp;
                    the pleasures we have enjoyed, in the course of our very agreeable tour! —</p>
                <p>Monday Aug. 22<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">nd.</hi></hi> I was
                    much pleased to find this morning that the greater part of our road to
                        <placeName ref="pl0226">Dumbarton</placeName> still lay on the Highland
                    border — We took the same route by which we before left <placeName ref="pl2324">Callander</placeName>, nearly as far as <placeName ref="pl2180">Aberfoil</placeName> — about a mile short of this place we turned off into
                    the <placeName ref="pl0226">Dumbarton</placeName> road. — We had the pleasure of
                    again passing the lovely <placeName ref="pl1117">Lake of Monteith</placeName>,
                    which lost nothing in our estimation from being compared with many other we <pb n="f.46r"/>had visited since last we passed its borders — We kept it in view
                    for some time after we had quitted the <placeName ref="pl2180">Aberfoil</placeName> road — We were gratified by a very fine mountain on
                    the height above the Lake, &amp; enjoyed it the more from being now able to
                    recognise the different points of it. — After ascending to a considerable
                    height, over a heathy moor, south of <placeName ref="pl2180">Aberfoil</placeName>, we commanded a fine view of the Southern end of
                        <placeName ref="pl0223">Loch Lomond</placeName>; and had the high
                    gratification of seeing the superb Mountain <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben-Lomond</placeName>, free from any cloud, rising majestically from the
                    Lake below. — The day was at this hour of it, particularly favorable to mountain
                    scenery. The grand ridge of the <placeName ref="pl1008">Aroqhuar</placeName>
                    Mountains looked particularly fine, &amp; were seen in full majesty above the
                    tops of those immediately rising from the western side of <placeName ref="pl0223">Loch-Lomond</placeName>. All the scenery we now beheld, seemed
                    to be familiar to us, <pb n="f.46v"/>and this added greatly to the satisfaction
                    with which we contemplated it. We continued to enjoy the same prospect for a
                    great part of our road towards <placeName ref="pl0226">Dumbarton</placeName> —
                    The view of <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben-Lomond</placeName> is finer, &amp;
                    grander, from this side of it, than from any other. — We regretted much in the
                    morning, that the heavy clouds which hung over the summits of <placeName ref="pl1167">Ben-Ledi</placeName>, &amp; <placeName ref="pl1168">Ben-Venue</placeName>, prevented our seeing them in full beauty — but our
                    parting view of <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben-Lomond</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl0223">Loch-Lomond</placeName>, &amp; all the majestic features which
                    grace this most attractive &amp; interesting district, made us rich amends for
                    the disappointment; and I felt particularly gratified that the last Highland
                    scene I was likely to contemplate, was amongst the finest I had enjoyed. I knew
                    not how to turn away from it; but it was necessary we should pursue our journey,
                    &amp; I <pb n="f.47r"/>was well pleased on arriving at <placeName ref="pl0226">Dumbarton</placeName>, to find that <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben-Lomond</placeName> still reared his head above all other objects, &amp;
                    formed a grand feature in the view from the Town &amp; Castle.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl0226">Dumbarton</placeName> is a shabby Town, &amp; does not
                    appear to be well inhabited. It has a handsome Bridge over the river <placeName ref="pl2505">Leven</placeName>, which falls just below it into the
                        <placeName ref="pl0833">Firth of Clyde</placeName>. We walked to the —
                    singular <placeName ref="pl1104">Rock</placeName> on which the Castle — formerly
                    stood, and on which there is now a small Garrison, but no vestige of the Castle
                    now remains.<note type="editorial">Although largely subsumed by the eighteenth
                        and nineteenth-century military buildings, Historic Environment Scotland
                        notes that some of elements of older structures are extant.</note> We
                    ascended to the summit of the Rock, &amp; commanded a very fine view of the
                        <placeName ref="pl0833">Firth</placeName>, and of all the surrounding
                    country. The rich vale between this place &amp; <placeName ref="pl0223">Loch-Lomond</placeName>, &amp; <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben-Lomond</placeName> beyond it to the North, formed the most enchanting
                    features of this lovely scene. The <placeName ref="pl0833">Firth</placeName>
                    formed a fine expanse of Water under the rock on which <add place="below">we
                        stood.</add></p>
                <p><pb n="f.47v"/>
                    <hi rend="underline">Tuesday Aug. 23<hi rend="superscript">rd.</hi></hi> We left
                        <placeName ref="pl0226">Dumbarton</placeName>, and had a pleasant walk by
                    the banks of the <placeName ref="pl0600">Clyde</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> — but there was nothing particularly
                    interesting in our road. — <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> appears
                    to be a handsome well built Town, &amp; very full of business &amp; bustle; but
                    the afternoon proved so very rainy, that we had very little opportunity of
                    walking out — We saw from our Inn, that <placeName ref="pl3306">Argyll
                        Street</placeName>, in which it stands, is a fine handsome street, well
                    built with stone, as the whole of the Town is; &amp; having many very fine shops
                    in it. —</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Wednesday Aug. 24<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> We
                    went this morning to see the <placeName ref="pl1060">Hunterian
                        Museum</placeName> at the <placeName ref="pl1061">College</placeName>, &amp;
                    afterwards visited most parts of the Town — There are many handsome Streets,
                    &amp; a great deal of <pb n="f.48r"/>fine building in <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName>. — It possesses also an advantage which we rather
                    regretted the want of in <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName>; the
                    having many fine Church spires. These are in themselves very beautiful, and when
                    many buildings area clustered together, as in a large town; they tend perhaps
                    more than any other objects to give dignity &amp; effect to the whole. In
                    situation, and indeed in every other respect, <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName> appears to me to have a most decided superiority;
                    &amp; as a place to reside in, I should think <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> would bear no comparison with it. <placeName ref="pl3306">Argyll S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi></placeName> in
                        <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName>
                    <add place="above">&amp; the <placeName ref="pl2160">Trongate</placeName> which
                        is a continuation of it</add> is one of the handsomest I have seen any
                    where. There are two Stone Bridges across the <placeName ref="pl0600">Clyde</placeName> here, but these are not handsome — the arches being low,
                        <pb n="f.48v"/>and the whole of the architecture very heavy &amp; inelegant
                    — We were sorry to see, that the top of a <placeName ref="pl3307">pillar</placeName> which was erected a few years since to the memory of
                        <persName ref="pe1435">Lord Nelson</persName>, has been struck by lightning,
                    and appears to be in so disjointed a state, as to render it probable that a part
                    of it may fall. Near to this spot, there is a most magnificent new
                        <sic>Goal</sic> erecting. — At the other side of the Town there is also
                    building at this time, an Asylum for Lunatics. The Infirmary is also a handsome
                    modern building on the North side of the Town. — We went to see the <placeName ref="pl1059">Cathedral</placeName>, which is rather handsome, but very
                    negligently kept, like every other Church which we had yet seen in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>. —</p>
                <p><pb n="f.49r"/>
                    <hi rend="underline">Thursday Aug. 25<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi></p>
                <p>We left <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> this morning, and <unclear reason="illegible">came</unclear> by <placeName ref="pl0597">Hamilton</placeName> to Lanark — We followed the course of the <placeName ref="pl0600">Clyde</placeName> a good part of our road, and were gratified
                    by seeing so much of this fine river. — at the same time, I felt rather
                    disappointed. I had heard the <placeName ref="pl0600">Clyde</placeName> so often
                    mentioned with admiration, that I expected to see more beauty than we found on
                    its banks. There are however many parts of it, where its borders are richly
                    fringed with wood — but on the whole its shores are flat, &amp; much less
                    interesting than many of the rivers we have so much admired in the <placeName ref="pl0711">Highlands</placeName>. There is a fine fall of this river <add place="above">called <placeName ref="pl0594">Stone-Biers
                        fall</placeName></add> about two miles short of <placeName ref="pl0590">Lanark</placeName>, which we went to see, and were very much pleased with.
                    After dining at our Inn, we procured a <pb n="f.49v"/>guide to direct us on our
                    way to see the <placeName ref="pl0595">Cartland Craggs</placeName> — these are
                    fine romantic rocks, that rise to a great height above a small river, the
                        <placeName ref="pl2156">Mouse</placeName>, which falls into the <placeName ref="pl0600">Clyde</placeName> a little way below — We had a very delightful
                    walk — the scenery on both sides <sic>the</sic> stream was very grand, as well
                    as beautiful. — the rocks are richly — wooded, down to the edge of the water,
                    and the whole character of the place a good deal reminded <add place="above">us</add> of <placeName ref="pl0385">Hawthorn Dean</placeName>, with which
                    we had been so — much delighted when we visited it from <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName>. —</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Friday August 26<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> We went
                    this morning to breakfast at <persName ref="pe1420">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Owen's</persName> at <placeName ref="pl3308">Braxfield</placeName>; who afterwards conducted us through the several
                    departments of the cotton yarn manufactory which he conducts at the <pb n="f.50r"/>Village of <placeName ref="pl1052">New Lanark</placeName>. He
                    also took us to the Schools, the Store Warehouses &amp;c, and gratified us very
                    much by informing us of the principle upon which every thing here is conducted.
                    There is at present in the village a population of 2400 — persons, all of whom
                    are more decent in their appearance than I have ever seen the labouring classes
                    in other manufacturing places — Every thing possible is done, under <persName ref="pe1420">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Owen's</persName> benevolent
                    super-intendance, which may tend to improve <add place="above">the</add>
                    situation, and increase the comforts of the industrious poor — the happy effects
                    of his liberal system, are very observable in the civil deportment; &amp; happy
                    countenances of his dependants of all ages. The artisans &amp; their children
                    look healthy &amp; contented — the buildings in which the manufactory is
                    conducted are very airy &amp; spacious — the food which <pb n="f.50v"/>is
                    brought to the store-houses, for them to purchase, is of the best quality, the
                    situation of the village is exceedingly salubrious as well as beautiful; and
                    every circumstance appears to tend to the perfection of an admirable &amp;
                    liberal theory, which is here actually carried into practise with the best &amp;
                    happiest effects. — <persName ref="pe1420">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                        Owen</persName> has been settled here but fifteen years: he looks upon his
                    grand scheme as only yet in its commencement; &amp; hopes if life &amp; health
                    are granted him, to see a very great improvement in the space of a few more
                    years. every person who is so happy as to see this establish<add place="above">ment</add> will feel a strong interest in the further perfecting of it, and
                    wish most devoutly that it may be consistent <pb n="f.51r"/>with the plan of an
                    All Wise Providence to continue the life, &amp; assist the exertions of this
                    most excellent &amp; judicious Man. —</p>
                <p>After having been gratified by seeing as far as we were able, into the nature
                    &amp; effects of his institutions, we went accompanied by <persName ref="pe1420">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Owen</persName>, to see the <placeName ref="pl0593">falls of the Clyde at Boniton</placeName>. Here we enjoyed the
                    sublime &amp; the beautiful, in Nature's richest profusion. These falls
                    surpassed in grandeur any we had before visited — the great body of water, the
                    height &amp; grandeur of the neighbouring cliffs, the fine wood which ornaments
                    their sides and tops, and the great depth as well as breadth of the rocks over
                    which the torrent tumbles &amp; rages; all these circumstances, combined with
                    the immense foam &amp; spray, &amp; the thundering noise of the dashing waters,
                        <pb n="f.51v"/><add place="above">unite in</add> forming a scene the most
                    affecting &amp; impressive that can be imagined. Cold and insensible must be the
                    heart of that being, who could contemplate it without emotion; or admire it,
                    without paying the tribute of gratitude and devotion to the Great Author of all
                    beauty, the Divine Source of every good!</p>
                <p>Having been a little disappointed, in what we had before seen of the <placeName ref="pl0600">Clyde</placeName>, I was much pleased to find that by pursuing
                    its upward course to this place, <del><unclear reason="illegible">we
                            found</unclear></del> our expectations <add place="above">were</add>
                    more than answered. This was the last grand object, which we had to visit in
                        <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>, nor could we finish better. I
                    hardly knew how to quit this delightful spot, &amp; most reluctantly turned my
                    steps from the <pb n="f.52r"/>river's brink. — I had been a great many hours on
                    foot, but my mind &amp; heart had been so much interested, that I scarcely felt
                    any fatigue. We all returned to <placeName ref="pl3308">Braxfield</placeName> to
                    dinner, &amp; spent the rest of the day in the most agreeable manner with
                        <persName ref="pe1420">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Owen</persName> &amp;
                    his family; <persName ref="pe0134">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> William Aston
                        of London</persName>, &amp; <persName ref="pe0135">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Grahame of Glasgow</persName> making a very delightful addition
                    to the party. Thus have we passed our last day in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>, as satisfactorily as we begun our season of enjoyment
                    in this country. Our journey has been safe and agreable in all its
                    circumstances; we have met with the utmost kindness &amp; hospitality from all
                    the inhabitants to whom we have had the <pb n="f.52v"/>pleasure of being
                    introduced. We leave them with regret, and shall always remember them with
                    gratitude &amp; esteem. — To-morrow we set forward on our actual journey home,
                    which we shall perform in as short a time as possible — We shall hardly quit the
                    borders of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> to-morrow; but
                    travelling post, &amp; making no further delays any where, we feel that we have
                    already taken our leave of the Scotch people; and can only soften our regrets by
                    indulging the hope, that we may have the great pleasure &amp; satisfaction of
                    welcoming in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>, some of the friends we
                    most value in this delightful country! — <placeName ref="pl0590">Old
                        Lanark</placeName>, 12 at night <lb/>Friday Aug. 26<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> 1814. —}</p>
                <p><pb n="f.53r"/>
                    <hi rend="underline">Saturday Aug. 27<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> We
                    quitted <placeName ref="pl0590">Lanark</placeName>, &amp; came by <placeName ref="pl0587">Douglass Mill</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl2120">Elvan
                        Foot</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl0247">Moffat</placeName>, to
                        <placeName ref="pl0576">Dumfries</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Here we had the great pleasure of meeting again our kind <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName> friend, <persName ref="pe0070">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Gray</persName>. We did not arrive till eight
                    at night, but he found us out almost immediately; &amp; went with us to call
                    upon <persName ref="pe0131">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Burns</persName>;
                    afterwards we went to the Churchyard, to visit the tomb of him, who had read the
                    book of Nature with so much attention, and described its beauties with so much
                    tenderness: who had tasted the pleasures of life, and enjoyed them with a poet's
                    ardour; but who had also endured its miseries, &amp; sunk under the bitterness
                    of <add place="above">its</add> disappointments! We did not survey the grave of
                        <persName ref="pe1806">Burns</persName> without considerable emotion — it is
                    situated at the south <pb n="f.53v"/>east corner of the Churchyard. Every thing
                    around us was in harmony with the object we were contemplating, silent &amp;
                    still as the ashes of the dead: while a pale, but brilliant Moon, nearly at its
                    full, gilded the solemn scene, &amp; rendered legible the simple inscription
                    which records the early death of <persName ref="pe1806">Robert Burns</persName>!
                    —</p>
                <p>In thoughtful, pensive mood, we quitted the burying ground, &amp; turned our
                    steps to the banks of the lovely river which ornaments this town, the <placeName ref="pl0573">Nith</placeName>. The trees — its birches, &amp; the glorious
                    orb in the heavens, were finely reflected in <add place="above">the</add> broad
                    stream, over which we hung delighted; &amp; we continued wandering near it, till
                    a late hour reminded us that it was necessary <pb n="f.54r"/>to return to our
                    Inn. — Here we parted with <persName ref="pe0070">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Gray</persName>, much regretting that we were under a necessity
                    to proceed on our journey home early on the following morning; but highly
                    pleased with having had the pleasure of seeing him once more, though for so
                    short a time, before our final departure from <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>. —</p>
                <p>Sunday Aug. 28<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> We came to <placeName ref="pl0559">Annan</placeName> to breakfast; afterwards, passing by <placeName ref="pl0558">Gretna Green</placeName>, through <placeName ref="pl0251">Longtown</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl0253">Carlisle</placeName>,
                        <placeName ref="pl0254">Penrith</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl2125">Appleby</placeName>, to <placeName ref="pl3309">Brough</placeName>; where
                    we slept. The regret we felt on quitting the Scottish Border, was soon softened
                    by the cheering reflection that we were once again in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>, &amp; hastening to rejoin our dear children, &amp; to
                    enjoy the comforts of our much loved house. It was also a very gratifying
                    circumstance to us, <pb n="f.54v"/>after leaving the grand scenery of the
                        <placeName ref="pl0711">Highlands of Scotland</placeName>, to open upon
                    those of <placeName ref="pl0800">Cumberland</placeName>. A fine ridge of those
                    mountains claimed our admiration, &amp; we kept <placeName ref="pl1097">Skiddaw</placeName> in full view during almost the whole of our long days
                    journey. This magnificent Mountain is a fine object from whatever point it is
                    seen — it is a noble feature n the views from the elevations round <placeName ref="pl0254">Penrith</placeName>, which is a nice airy Town very agreably
                    situated — We passed through a very rich &amp; beautiful vale from this place to
                        <placeName ref="pl2125">Appleby</placeName>. —</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Monday Aug. 29<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> We left
                        <placeName ref="pl3309">Brough</placeName>, and came by <placeName ref="pl3310">Greta Bridge</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl3311">Catterick
                        Bridge</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl3312">Leeming Lane</placeName>,
                        <placeName ref="pl2040">Burrough Bridge</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl2041">Wetherby</placeName>, to <placeName ref="pl0767">Ferry
                        Bridge</placeName>; where we slept.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Tuesday Aug. 30<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></hi> From
                        <placeName ref="pl0767">Ferry Bridge</placeName> by <placeName ref="pl0768">Doncaster</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl2549">Newark</placeName>,
                        <placeName ref="pl3273">Grantham</placeName> and <pb n="f.55r"/><placeName ref="pl3313">Witham Common</placeName>, to <placeName ref="pl0790">Stamford</placeName>, where we slept. —</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Wednesday Aug. 31<hi rend="superscript">st.</hi></hi> We
                    terminated our long journey, and arrived at home about seven in the evening;
                    returning as we went, by <placeName ref="pl3314">Stilton</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl3315">Huntingdon</placeName>, and <placeName ref="pl2871">Cambridge</placeName>. —</p>
                <p/>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>