<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0060">
    <teiHeader type="s">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Miss Archibald Montgomerie
                    Williamson, A Tour to the West of Scotland
                    <date>1817</date></title>
                <author><persName ref="pe1699">Miss Archibald Montgomerie
                    Williamson</persName></author>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Edited with an Introduction by Alex Deans</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
                        <idno>Acc. 13028</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>7a-</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <additions><p>[f.1.r] William George H. T. Fairfax <lb/>from his
                                affectionate Mama <lb/>July 22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>
                                1843.</p>
                            <p>[f.3r]: By A. Montgomerie, Lady Fairfax — when Miss
                            Williamson.</p></additions>
                    </physDesc>
                    <additional>
                        <p>A slip in the item envelope notes that the paper of the journal is
                            watermarked 1815, and that the first entry is on Tuesday July 8, leading
                            to an inferred year of writing: 1817.</p>
                    </additional>
                </msDesc>

            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p><pb n="f.3r"/>
                Tuesday July 8<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></p>
                <p>My <persName ref="pe1701">Father</persName>
                    <persName ref="pe1702">Jane</persName> and I left <placeName ref="pl2518">Lixmount</placeName> on a little Tour to the West of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> ––––– the first place we stopped at was
                        <placeName ref="pl0383">Linlithgow</placeName> a distance of 16 miles. here
                    we should have walked out to the <placeName ref="pl2497">Palace</placeName> in
                    which the unfortunate <persName ref="pe0527">Queen Mary</persName> was born, but
                    a heavy rain confined us within the walls of an uncomfortable Inn ––––– <pb n="f.3v"/> As soon as the weather cleared up, we proceeded to <placeName ref="pl0236">Falkirk</placeName> where we slept.</p>
                <p>Wednesday. The day was very fine and we had a pleasant ride to <placeName ref="pl2498">Cumbernauld</placeName> ––––– while the horses were resting, we
                    walked towards the Seat of <persName ref="pe1703">Admiral Fleming
                        Elphinstone</persName>;<note type="editorial">Williamson's assiduous noting
                        of country seats and their owners probably indicates the use of a guidebook,
                        such as Daniel Paterson's, <hi rend="italic">A New and Accurate Description
                            of all the Direct and Principal Cross Roads in Great Britain</hi>, first
                        published in 1771 and revised and reissued into the late 1820s.</note> the
                    road from thence to <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> is extremely
                    good; but the scenery is not at all interesting –––––</p>
                <p>We walked this Place about 5 o'Clock, after finding our abode <pb n="f.4r"/>at
                    the <placeName ref="pl2499">Star Inn</placeName>, we called on M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>–––––, and then walked thro' different parts of
                    the Town, and along the Banks of the River, before we came in to Supper.
                    Thursday. We took a little tour thro' the town before Breakfast, and afterwards
                    went to see the <placeName ref="pl1060">Hunterian Museum</placeName> with which
                    we were much gratified. This is a very valuable collection of Minerals, Shells,
                    Coins, and Anatomical preparations, all finely arranged, besides an <pb n="f.4v"/>extensive Library and some good Paintings ––––– they were chiefly bequeathed
                    by the late <persName ref="pe1692">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Hunter</persName> of <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>. The
                    building in which they are deposited was built with money left by him for the
                    purpose, it forms the Eastern side of the University, and the front presents a
                    Doric Portico of six columns; amongst the Medals, we observed one similar to
                    ours of Edward the 2<hi rend="superscript">nd.</hi> tho' not in such high
                    preservation. <pb n="f.5r"/>My Father then parted from us to pay some visits,
                    and Jane and I were happy to avail ourselves of the opportunity to visit the
                        <placeName ref="pl2500">Botanic Garden</placeName> which has been lately
                    made ––––– it contains about five Acres, laid out with considerable taste, there
                    seems to be a good collection of Exotic plants, and in one corner of the Garden
                    is a Lecture room in which students of both sexes are admitted ––––– on our way
                    home we went into <pb n="f.5v"/><persName ref="pe1693">Harley's</persName>
                    celebrated <unclear reason="illegible">tea</unclear> house. After dinner we
                    thought our time could not be better employed than going to see <persName ref="pe1694">Madame Girardelli</persName> perform her wonderful experiments
                    with fire. which detained us till a late hour.</p>
                <p>Friday. We set off at 7 o' Clock and had a delightful ride to <placeName ref="pl0226">Dumbarton</placeName>, where we Breakfasted, the weather was
                    fine, and the objects that attracted our attention <pb n="f.6r"/>on this road
                    are too many to be enumerated. The Country is luxuriant the <placeName ref="pl0600">Clyde</placeName> runs on the left, and on both sides of the
                    road, are several neat Seats and Villas.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pe1704">Scotstoun</placeName>, belonging to <persName ref="pe1704">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Oswald</persName> on the left
                    about 5 miles from <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName>, appeared to me
                    one of the pleasantest. Near the opposite side of the <placeName ref="pl0600">Clyde</placeName> is <placeName ref="pl2520">Elderslie</placeName>
                    belonging to <persName ref="pe1705">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                        Spiers</persName> and which is noted for being the birthplace of <persName ref="pe1103">Wallace</persName>. <placeName ref="pl0606">Renfrew</placeName>
                    is seen at some <pb n="f.6v"/>distance among the trees, a few miles further on,
                    we ascended <placeName ref="pl1062">Dalnotter Hill</placeName> from which the
                    prospect is extremely beautiful presenting at once many interesting objects. The
                        <placeName ref="pl0833">Clyde</placeName> is here very much expanded, the
                    great <placeName ref="pl1102">Canal</placeName> flows into it ––––– at a little
                    distance <placeName ref="pl2521">Erskine</placeName> the Seat of <persName ref="pe1706">Lord Blantyre</persName> is delightfully situated on the
                    opposite <pb n="f.7r"/>Banks of the River, the <placeName ref="pl1104">rock of
                        Dumbarton</placeName> rises abruptly above the water, the ruined <placeName ref="pl0227">Fort of Dunglas</placeName> has a very picturesque effect, and
                    Vessels of different kinds enliven the scene. We then descended to <placeName ref="pl0601">Kilpatrick</placeName> where we understand is the termination
                    of the <placeName ref="pl0382">Roman Wall</placeName>, and at a mile and a half
                    distant are some other remains of this adventurous people <pb n="f.7v"/><placeName ref="pl2522">Glenarback</placeName> formerly belonging to
                        <persName ref="pe1707">Lord Web Seymour</persName>, and now to <persName ref="pe1708">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hamilton</persName>, is prettily
                    situated amidst trees on the right. We then passed <placeName ref="pl0227">Dunglass Castle</placeName> on the left — and on the right <placeName ref="pl2543">Auchintorlie</placeName> the Seat of <persName ref="pe1766">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Buchanan</persName>, on the same side
                    is the Printfield of <placeName ref="pl2503">Milton</placeName> belonging to
                        <unclear reason="illegible"><persName ref="pe1767">Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Mitchell</persName></unclear> — all in a
                    most romantic situation and a very lofty rugged rock called <placeName ref="pl2504">Drumbec</placeName>. <placeName ref="pl1104">Dumbarton <pb n="f.8r"/>Castle</placeName> next presents itself on a singularly shaped
                    rock 560 feet high divided into two summits, it is on a point of land formed by
                    the junction of the <placeName ref="pl0600">Clyde</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl2505">Leven</placeName> —</p>
                <p>The plant generally considered the scotch Thistle grows here very abundantly, and
                    it is curious that many parts of the rock are Magnetic, the Tower is small and
                    uninteresting. After taking breakfast, we very willingly resumed our journey <pb n="f.8v"/>as it was to lead us to <placeName ref="pl0223">Loch
                        Lomond</placeName>, the road crosses a Bridge over the <placeName ref="pl2505">Leven</placeName>; for several miles we rode along its Banks.
                    There is a <placeName ref="pl1064">Monument</placeName> erected near the place
                    where <persName ref="pe0536">Smolet</persName> was born. Every part of the
                    Country thro' which we passed is rich and picturesque, there are many elegant
                    Seats and neat Villages, the Country is finely wooded, and we observed a great
                    variety of wild flowers <pb n="f.9r"/>growing in the richest luxuriance.
                        <placeName ref="pl2508">Tillichuen Castl</placeName>e seems a beautiful
                    place in the Gothic style, further on is <placeName ref="pl2509">Woodbank</placeName>, and soon after leaving it, we had the first view of
                        <placeName ref="pl0223">Lock Lomond</placeName>, which even here is very
                    beautiful, it is partly concealed from the road by trees; but we seldom lost
                    sight of it altogether.</p>
                <p>Many Gentlemen have taken advantage of the attractive situation, by building
                    elegant Mansions on its Banks <pb n="f.9v"/>We particularly admired that of
                        <persName ref="pe0508">Sir James Colquhoun</persName> called <placeName ref="pl1065">Rosedou</placeName> it is on a Peninsula stretching into the
                    Lake, and commands a fine view of the surrounding scenery.</p>
                <p>We passed <placeName ref="pl2510">Camstradden</placeName> belonging to <persName ref="pe1768">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Colquhoun</persName>, then
                    crossed a Bridge over the <placeName ref="pl2511">River Luss</placeName>, and
                    soon afterre arrived at <placeName ref="pl0224">Luss</placeName>. We were now
                    all anxiety to have a full view of the far famed Lake, and as soon <pb n="f.10r"/>as we had engaged a Boat, we walked down to the Shore, which is beautiful
                    beyond description, the Boatmen ferried us over to <placeName ref="pl1113">Inch
                        Tavanach</placeName> which tho' not the largest of the Islands seems to be
                    most elevated, we ascended thro' the Woods and Heaths by which it is covered to
                    the Summit. — our guide was very intelligent, and able to answer all our
                    questions, he said the Island we were <pb n="f.10v"/>on was a mile and three
                    quarters long and half a mile broad, and the name means the Island of the two
                    women. From the Top we had a delightful view of almost the whole Lake embosoming
                    its verdant Islands. — there are about 30 of them some covered with pastures,
                    and others wooded from their summits to the water edge. <placeName ref="pl1205">Inch Murren</placeName> is one mile long and two broad, it belongs to <pb n="f.11r"/>the <persName ref="pe0174">Duke of Montrose</persName>, it seems
                    to be thickly wooded and contains 200 deer.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1110">Inch Caillaich</placeName> was the burial place of the
                    Macgregors.</p>
                <p>To the Eastward we saw <placeName ref="pl2512">Inch Cruin</placeName> used as an
                    Assylum for persons of dissipated habits whose friends send them here for
                    seclusion, and many local circumstances Render it well adapted to this purpose
                    We afterwards landed on <placeName ref="pl1112">Inch Lonay</placeName> further
                    to the North, used for a similar purpose, it is remarkable <pb n="f.11v"/>for a
                    natural wood of very old Yews, and it is stocked well with Deer — The property
                    of <persName ref="pe0508">Sir James Colquhoun</persName> after stopping here
                    about half an hour we again stepped into the Boat, which took us back to
                        <placeName ref="pl0224">Luss</placeName>.</p>
                <p>The weather being clear we had from the lake a very fine view of <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben Lomond</placeName>, which we should <add place="above">have</add> liked very much to ascend, as the prospect from it must be still
                    more magnificent than that <pb n="f.12r"/>from <placeName ref="pl1113">Inch
                        Tavanach</placeName> its perpendicular height is 3240 feet above the surface
                    of the Lake and 3262 above the surface of the Sea, our Guide pointed out to us a
                    narrow stream running down a hill on the edge of the Lake famous for being the
                    scene of a sanguinary conflict between the Colquhouns and Macgregors in the
                    beginning of the 17<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> Century.<note type="editorial">A reference to the 1603 battle of <placeName ref="pl1043">Glen Fruin</placeName> between the MacGregors and Colquhouns, as
                        controversially described in the quarto edition of Pennant, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0004">A tour in Scotland 1769</title>
                            (1774), <biblScope unit="page">pp.243-44</biblScope></bibl>.</note> The
                    Island containing <placeName ref="pl2169">Rob Roy's Cave</placeName> we observed
                    at a distance. It was with <pb n="f.12v"/>difficulty we could leave the lovely
                    Banks of <placeName ref="pl0223">Loch Lomond</placeName> and return to the
                    Inn.</p>
                <p>Saturday. We rose early to return to <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName>,
                    we passed over the same ground as we had done the day before.</p>
                <p>After arriving at <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> we walked about,
                    but observed nothing worth mentioning</p>
                <p>Sunday. After Breakfast we prepared to go to Church to hear <persName ref="pe1696">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Chalmers</persName> M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> ––––– gave us leave to use his seat, which <pb n="f.13r"/>being very near the Pulpit, we had an excellent opportunity of
                    seeing and hearing this celebrated Preacher — I had heard him before but never
                    to such advantage. The Text was in the 6<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> chapter
                    of Mathew and 29 Verse. The subject tho' a common one was treated in a very
                    striking and forcible manner. As the weather was fine we resolved on going to
                        <placeName ref="pl0603">Greenock</placeName> this Evening, and had no wish
                    to wait till the next day to go by the Steam Boat, as in our excursion to
                        <placeName ref="pl0224">Luss</placeName>, we had had a <pb n="f.13v"/>full
                    view of the finest parts of the <placeName ref="pl0600">Clyde</placeName>, the
                    road from <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> is excellent and the
                    Country pleasant and well cultivated, we passed several Seats <sic>but did not
                        to whom they belonged</sic> One called <placeName ref="pl2545">Lint
                        House</placeName> on the right particularly struck us. <placeName ref="pl0605">Paisley</placeName> is seen at a distance. We passed <placeName ref="pl2520">Elderslie</placeName>
                    <persName ref="pe1705">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Spier's</persName>, and
                    then entered <placeName ref="pl0606">Renfrew</placeName> consisting chiefly of
                    one narrow Street about half a mile in length — further on is <placeName ref="pl2546">South Bar</placeName> belonging to <persName ref="pe1770">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Alexander</persName>, which appears a very
                    pleasant <pb n="f.14r"/>place, and soon after stopped at a solitary Inn called
                        <placeName ref="pl2547">Bishopton</placeName>. while the horses were resting
                    we walked on about two miles. and had a delightful view of the <placeName ref="pl0600">Clyde</placeName> and the surrounding scenery, we now saw the
                    side of <placeName ref="pl1104">Dumbarton Castle</placeName>
                    <unclear reason="illegible">next</unclear> the River and the Bold Rock called
                        <placeName ref="pl2504">Dumbrec</placeName>. We passed thro' <placeName ref="pl0602">Port Glasgow</placeName>, near it is the <placeName ref="pl2549">old Castle of Newark</placeName> belonging to <persName ref="pe1771">Lord Belhaven</persName> 3 miles further on is <placeName ref="pl0603">Greenock</placeName>, where we remained all night.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.14v"/>
                Monday. After Breakfast my Father paid several visits, and then went with out
                    with us to look at the Town, it is situated on the sloping side of a high Bank
                    towards the South, and the Sea on the North. The principal Street is nearly a
                    mile long, and runs from East to West, has a commodious Harbour, and is the
                    finest Port in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>. About 2 o' Clock we
                    continued our journey thro' a beautiful <pb n="f.15r"/>and romantic Country —
                    the road excellent, and the weather was uncommonly fine. After travelling 3
                    miles we passed thro' <placeName ref="pl0603">Greenock</placeName>, a small
                    Harbour, and a resort for bathing. We had a view on the right of <placeName ref="pl0613">Roseneath</placeName>, belonging to the <persName ref="pe1433">Duke of Argyle</persName>. The property on this road is chiefly <persName ref="pe1773">Sir Michael Shaw Stewart's</persName>, and his Seat <placeName ref="pl2551">Ardgowan</placeName> is about 5 miles from <placeName ref="pl0603">Greenock</placeName>, 2 miles further on we crossed a small
                    Bridge <pb n="f.15v"/>called <placeName ref="pl2552"><unclear reason="illegible">Kelly</unclear> Bridge</placeName>, and entered <placeName ref="pl0736">Ayrshire</placeName>, the road now is close to the Shore, and on the other
                    side for a mile is a perpendicular rock, which in some Places seems nearly 100
                    feet high — soon after on the left are the Ruins of <placeName ref="pl2553">Knock Castle</placeName> on the <placeName ref="pl2554">Estate of
                        Brisbane</placeName>, we then arrived at <placeName ref="pl2555">Largs</placeName> a small Sea Port Town ––––– it is beautifully situated
                    and commands a fine view of the Islands of <placeName ref="pl2556">Cumbra</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl0714">Bute</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl0719">Arran</placeName>, and betwixt the <pb n="f.16r"/>Mainland and
                    the South end of <placeName ref="pl0719">Arran</placeName> is a distant view of
                    the <placeName ref="pl0632">Island of Ailsa</placeName>, which rises to great
                    heights in a Conical form. The weather being fine, we saw the place to great
                    advantage, and admired the situation of it extremely; near the Shore there is a
                    very neat building containing a reading room hot &amp; cold Baths.</p>
                <p>We ascended a Mound behind the Village, on which <persName ref="pe1774">General
                        Brisbane</persName> has erected a sort of Signal Tower for Astronomical
                    purposes — it commands a view of <placeName ref="pl2554">Brisbane <pb n="f.16v"/>House</placeName>, and the surrounding Country, and near it is a large
                    plain, which is said to be the scene of the defeat of the Danes in their last
                    Invasion.</p>
                <p>Tuesday. After leaving <placeName ref="pl2555">Largs</placeName>, we rode along
                    the Banks of the <placeName ref="pl0833">Clyde</placeName>, and on the other
                    side the Country is rich and diversified.</p>
                <p>We passed <placeName ref="pl2557">Kilburn House</placeName> the Seat of <persName ref="pe1775">Lord Glasgow</persName>, and soon after the Estate of
                        <placeName ref="pl2558">Fairly</placeName> now belonging to <persName ref="pe1446">Sir William <pb n="f.17r"/>Cunningham of Robertland</persName>,
                    on which are the Ruins of an old Castle. On the right is <placeName ref="pl2559">Hunterston</placeName> which appears a fine House, and 4 miles further on,
                    we passed thro' the Village of <placeName ref="pl2560">Kilbride</placeName>,
                    near which are the Ruins of <placeName ref="pl2561">Law Castle</placeName>.</p>
                <p>For some miles we had left the Shore, now the road goes along it to <placeName ref="pl2562">Ardrossen</placeName>, where there is a new Harbour for Ships.
                    — It belongs to <persName ref="pe1776">Lord Eglinton</persName> and the Houses
                    are newly built. <pb n="f.17v"/>In a height are the Ruins of a Castle which
                    seems to have been a Place of considerable strength, and South of it are the
                    remains of Danish encampments, we went off the usual road to see <placeName ref="pl2562">Ardrossan</placeName> and soon arrived at <placeName ref="pl2563">Saltcoats</placeName>, which is 2 miles distant. There we
                    Breakfasted, and after walking down to the Harbour and round the Village, which
                    consists chiefly of one long Street we again stepped into the Carriage.</p>
                <p>We now lost <pb n="f.18r"/>sight of the <placeName ref="pl0833">Clyde</placeName>, and passed on the left <placeName ref="pl2564">Seabank</placeName>, belonging to <persName ref="pe1777">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Cunningham</persName>, a little on the
                    Village of <placeName ref="pl2565">Stephenstoun</placeName>, and afterwards
                        <placeName ref="pl2566">Killwinning</placeName> a small Tower noted for
                    being the Seat of the first Mason Lodge in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> — and here are the remains of a <placeName ref="pl2567">Monastery</placeName>, — at some distance we had a view of
                        <placeName ref="pl2568">Eglinton Castle</placeName>.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl2569">Irvine</placeName> where we next stopped is a Sea Port
                    Town and stands on a rising ground — the Church is neat and has a handsome <pb n="f.18v"/>Spire. We went into the Church Yard from which there is an
                    extensive view — we likewise saw the new Academy a fine Building in an airy
                    situation, near it are the Ruins of a <placeName ref="pl2570">Castle</placeName>
                    the antient Residence of the Eglinton family.</p>
                <p>As the weather was extremely warm, we did <sic>not <placeName ref="pl2569">Irvine</placeName></sic> till 6 o'Clock it was a delightful Evening,
                    and at a distance out the left, we saw distinctly the <placeName ref="pl2572">Castle of Dundonald</placeName> from which the family <pb n="f.19r"/>of
                    Cochrane derive their Title, it appears a very large building eminence opposite
                    to it is a fine Bank of wood in which is situated the <placeName ref="pl2573">House of Auchans</placeName> a seat of the Earls of Eglinton. The Country
                    tho' not so picturesque as what we had lately seen, is far from being
                    uninteresting, some parts are barren, and others highly cultivated.</p>
                <p>The <placeName ref="pl0833">Firth of Clyde</placeName> continues in sight and the
                        <placeName ref="pl0632">Island of Ailsa</placeName> appears more distinctly.
                    We saw <placeName ref="pl2574">Troon</placeName>
                    <pb n="f.19v"/>which is a Promontory in <placeName ref="pl0736">Ayrshire</placeName> from which the <persName ref="pe1778">Duke of
                        Portland</persName> has extended into the <placeName ref="pl0833">Clyde</placeName> on a curved line to a very considerable extent so as to
                    form a safe Harbour for the shelter of Vessels in general, as well as for the
                    exportation of the Coals upon his Estate to <placeName ref="pl0889">Ireland</placeName>, this Harbour is thought to promise being of more
                    utility than the one erected by <persName ref="pe1776">Lord Eglinton</persName>
                    at <placeName ref="pl2562">Ardrossen</placeName>, further on the left is <pb n="f.20r"/><placeName ref="pl2584">Fullerton House</placeName>, belonging to
                    the <persName ref="pe1778">Duke of Portland</persName>.</p>
                <p>After travelling 5 miles thro' rather a bleak Country, and two inconsiderable
                    Villages, we crossed the <placeName ref="pl2585">River Ayr</placeName>, and
                    entered the Town of <placeName ref="pl2586">Ayr</placeName>. This is a very
                    ancient Town, and was formerly distinguished for military strength, — but we
                    could perceive no remains of antiquity except and old Tower, and round it is the
                    strong wall of a Fortress built by <persName ref="pe1391">Oliver
                        Cromwell</persName>.</p>
                <p>Wednesday. As my Father <pb n="f.20v"/>had several visits to make we remained
                    here all day, but regretted that owing to the excessive heat, we could not walk
                    much till the Evening, when we took a survey of the Town, and the new Prison,
                    and Count House that are building.</p>
                <p>Wednesday. We set off soon after six o'Clock in order to go one stage before the
                    heat of the day. but the Sun was already so powerful that we were almost <pb n="f.21r"/>afraid the horses could not reach <placeName ref="pl2587">Ochiltree</placeName> where we were advised to stop instead of proceeding
                    to <placeName ref="pl2588">old Cumnock</placeName>.</p>
                <p>We were very glad to find ourselves at the door of the Inn, and all required
                    resting as well as the horses. After getting an excellent Breakfast the Landlady
                    offered to accompany us on a walk to an old Castle near the Village, which
                    formerly gave the <sic>Tittle</sic> of Baron to a Branch of the Family
                        Stewart.<note type="editorial">Possibly <placeName ref="pl2589">Taringzean
                            Castle</placeName>.</note> The heat soon <pb n="f.21v"/>obliged my
                    Father to return to the Inn, but <persName ref="pe1702">Jane</persName> and I
                    unwilling to give up seeing the only curiosity that the Place afforded, went on,
                    and were somewhat gratified.</p>
                <p>The <placeName ref="pl2590">River Lugar</placeName> runs past this old edifice
                    which <persName ref="pe1797">Sir Alexander Don</persName> inherited from his
                    Mother <persName ref="pe1796">Lady Glencairn</persName>, but he has sold it to
                        <persName ref="pe1799">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Boswell of
                        Auchinleck</persName>. <persName ref="pe1801">Lord Bute</persName> is the
                    chief Proprietor in this Neighborhood. I must not omit to mention that we had
                    not any where seen <pb n="f.22r"/>such fine corn fields as between <placeName ref="pl2586">Ayr</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl2587">Ocheltree</placeName>. Soon after leaving this Place, we saw on the left
                        <placeName ref="pl2591">Dumfries House</placeName> surrounded by extensive
                    Plantations, then passing thro' the Village of <placeName ref="pl2588">old
                        Cumnock</placeName>, we went on to <placeName ref="pl2592">new
                        Cumnock</placeName>, where we stopped at a most wretched and uncomfortable
                    Inn. As soon as the horses were sufficiently rested, we again continued our
                    journey thro' a Country that differed in aspect to what we had been lately
                    accustomed ––––– it is generally <pb n="f.22v"/>Mountainous, some of the Hills
                    are covered with Heath and others affording pasture to flocks of Sheep and Black
                    Cattle. The road goes along the Banks of the <placeName ref="pl0573">Nith</placeName>, but we saw nothing interesting. <persName ref="pe1702"><unclear reason="illegible">Jane</unclear></persName> owing to the
                    extreme heat felt rather fatigued by the time we arrived at <placeName ref="pl2593">Sanquhar</placeName> which terminated our day's journey. This
                    is a small Town and at a short distance from it are the ruins of a very ancient
                    Castle.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.23r"/>
                Friday. We went to <placeName ref="pl2594">Eliock</placeName> about 3 miles off,
                    where we Breakfasted: in this house the <persName ref="pe0060">Admirable
                        Crichton</persName> is said to have been born, and there is a <rs ref="ar0005">Portrait</rs> of him in the drawing Room. After leaving
                        <persName ref="pe1803">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Veitch's</persName>
                    we found the road very pleasant keeping along the East Bank of the <placeName ref="pl0573">Nith</placeName> which in some parts is extremely Picturesque,
                    we then passed the fields and Plantations of <placeName ref="pl0579">Drumlanrig</placeName>, and had a good <pb n="f.23v"/>view of this
                    beautiful Mansion we now lost sight of the <placeName ref="pl0573">Nith</placeName>, and passing <placeName ref="pl2596">Closeburn</placeName>, <persName ref="pe1804">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                        Monteith's</persName> on the left reached <placeName ref="pl2597">Brownhill</placeName>, a tolerable Inn, where we rested two hours, the
                    first part of the next stage is very delightful, the <placeName ref="pl0573">Nith</placeName> again appears in picturesque windings, the Banks prettily
                    wooded and the surrounding Country well cultivated ––––– agriculture being now
                    apparently more attended to than pasturage</p>
                <p><pb n="f.24r"/>
                The Evening was uncommonly fine, and added to the beauty of the scenery. Soon
                    after crossing <placeName ref="pl2598">Alquith Bridge</placeName>, we saw on the
                    left a very pleasant Place called <placeName ref="pl2599">Friar's
                        Carse</placeName>, belonging to <persName ref="pe1805">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Chrighton</persName>. As we approached
                        <placeName ref="pl0576">Dumfries</placeName> nothing struck us as remarkable
                    till we crossed the River by a handsome Bridge and entered the Town, being
                    rather fatigued with the excessive heat of the weather, we ordered supper as
                    soon as <pb n="f.24v"/>and deferred looking at the Town till the next day.</p>
                <p>Saturday. We walked before Breakfast to <placeName ref="pl2600">S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Michael's Church</placeName> where a
                        <placeName ref="pl2601">Monument</placeName> has been lately erected to the
                    Memory of <persName ref="pe1806">Burns</persName>, the design is rather elegant.
                    in the form of a Temple, and a Statue of the Poet, leaning on a Plough, is to be
                    placed in the Centre. <placeName ref="pl0576">Dumfries</placeName> appeared to
                    us the pleasantest Town we had seen. It is situated <pb n="f.25r"/>on the
                        <placeName ref="pl0573">Nith</placeName>, about 9 miles above, where it
                    discharges itself into the <placeName ref="pl1098">Solway Firth</placeName> — it
                    contains many excellent houses, and handsome public buildings. We went into the
                    Court house, and then walked along the Banks of the River towards the Harbour.
                    About 3 o'Clock we resumed our journey, but instead of going on to <placeName ref="pl0247">Moffat</placeName> we stopped for an hour at a small Inn called
                        <placeName ref="pl2602">Park-gate</placeName> about 8 miles and a ½ from
                        <placeName ref="pl0576">Dumfries</placeName> — while we were <pb n="f.25v"/>here a shower came on, which cooled the air, and made it pleasanter for
                    travelling, but owing to the rain we did not see the Country to such advantage:
                    the surface of it is generally rugged and Mountainous we passed over a very
                    pretty Bridge, called <placeName ref="pl2603">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>
                        Ann's Bridge</placeName> thrown over the <placeName ref="pl0559">Annan</placeName>,<note type="editorial">St Ann's Bridge spans <placeName ref="pl2604">Kinnel Water</placeName>, at tributary of the Annan.</note>
                    we saw on the left <placeName ref="pl2605">Raehills</placeName>, the Seat of
                        <persName ref="pe1807">Sir William Johnstone Hope</persName>. It was almost
                    dark before we arrived at <placeName ref="pl0247">Moffat</placeName>, but this
                    we did not regret intending <pb n="f.26r"/>to remain here all next day.</p>
                <p>Saturday. The weather in the Morning was tolerably fine, and had not much the
                    appearance of rain, but just as we were setting off to Church a very heavy
                    shower came on, and obliged us to remain within doors till the Afternoon, when
                    we went to the Parish Church. <placeName ref="pl0247">Moffat</placeName> has
                    been long celebrated for its Mineral Water, which was discovered about 150 years
                    since. There is also a petrifying spring about 4 miles distant, but this we did
                    not see <pb n="f.26v"/>and we regretted that the badness of the weather
                    prevented us from going to the curious cascade called <placeName ref="pl2607">"Gray Mare's Tail"</placeName></p>
                <p>Monday. We rose before 6 o'Clock, and as the weather was favorable we determined
                    on going to the <placeName ref="pl2152">Well</placeName>, and had a very
                    pleasant expedition. The <placeName ref="pl2152">Well</placeName> is covered
                    with only a sort of hut, and the surrounding scenery is rather picturesque — by
                    the time we returned to the Inn the Carriage was ready, so immediately set off,
                    and got to <pb n="f.27r"/><placeName ref="pl2608">Crook Inn</placeName> to
                    Breakfast — a few miles from <placeName ref="pl0247">Moffat</placeName> on the
                    right is a deep hollow in the rock, where the <placeName ref="pl2121">Annan</placeName> rises, and from the opposite side of the same Hill, the
                        <placeName ref="pl0600">Clyde</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl0727">Tweed</placeName> have their source. After Breakfast we ascended the steep
                    hill behind the Inn, and saw beneath us, the windings of the <placeName ref="pl0727">Tweed</placeName>, now of considerable breadth. one hill
                    appears beyond another, partly covered with heath, and partly with pasturage The
                    Country thro' which we afterwards passed has the same unvarying <pb n="f.27v"/>aspect, the <placeName ref="pl0727">Tweed</placeName> for some miles continues
                    in sight, and on the Banks are the ruins of the <placeName ref="pl2609">old
                        Castle of Drummelzier</placeName> near which was buried the celebrated
                        <persName ref="pe1656">Merlin</persName>,<note type="editorial">A tradition
                        of unknown origin, though perhaps dating as far back as the fifteenth
                        century, holds that the legendary Merlin was buried near Drumelzier Castle.
                        The 1793 parish entry for Sinclair's <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0169">Statistical Account of Scotland</title></bibl> 21
                        vols., (Edinburgh: 1791-1799) pithily notes: 'The celebrated Merlin is
                        buried here; but no other person of great distinction', vii, p.155.</note>
                    we next passed the Estates of <placeName ref="pl2610">Broughton</placeName>,
                        <placeName ref="pl2611">Cairnmuir</placeName> and rested the horses at a
                    small Inn on the road, the Country now becomes more flat, and nothing appears
                    worthy of notice on the road to <placeName ref="pl2612">Noble House</placeName>,
                    which ended this day's journey.</p>
                <p>Tuesday. As the weather had <pb n="f.28r"/>the evening before the appearance of
                    rain we were agreeably surprized when we arose to find it was fair, tho' the
                    road shewed there had been rain during the Night — Almost opposite to the Inn is
                        <persName ref="pe1808">Sir George Montgomery's</persName> on the same side
                        <placeName ref="pl2613">La Mancha</placeName> belonging to <persName ref="pe1809">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Basil Cochrane</persName> and
                        <placeName ref="pl2614">the Whim</placeName> to <persName ref="pe1810">Sir
                        James Montgomery</persName>; much of the Country about here seems barren and
                    neglected, before entering <placeName ref="pl0726">Pennycuick</placeName> there
                    are the Ruins of an old Castle on a height <pb n="f.28r"/>overlooking the
                        <placeName ref="pl2615">Esk</placeName> which rises in this Neighborhood.
                    from thence we beat our course to <placeName ref="pl2518">Lixmount</placeName>
                    where we arrived after being three weeks absent.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>