<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0062">
    <teiHeader type="s">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Tour in Scotland by Elizabeth Susannah Graham
                    <date>1818</date></title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Edited with an Introduction by Alex Deans</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
                        <idno>Acc. 13509</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <additions>
                            <p>JOHN SMITH &amp; SON <lb/>BOOKSELLERS <lb/>GLASGOW</p>
                            <p>WM 1815 <lb/>A. bottom case</p>
                            <p>Is date of this journal circa 1819 perhaps? RS</p>
                            <p><handShift/>1819 confirmed <lb/>6 September was a Sunday in 1819</p>
                        </additions>
                    </physDesc>
                    <additional>
                        <p>A date of 1818 has been assigned to this document due to the author's
                            reference to the death of Lady Anne Hope Johnstone, which occurred in
                            that year.</p>
                    </additional>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p><pb n="f.2r"/> Aug. 31. <persName ref="pe1501">Maria</persName> and I started
                    from <placeName ref="pl2150">E.C.</placeName> at 1/2 past 7 this morning &amp;
                    reached <sic>called <placeName ref="pl0253"><add place="above">Carlisle</add></placeName></sic> a little before 9 when I called on
                        <persName ref="pe1502">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Normans</persName>
                    &amp; settled with him about the school conveyance. At <placeName ref="pl0558">Gretna</placeName> stopped to see the Inn where runaways are married; an
                    opposition blacksmith has lately started up there. Pretty banks of the
                        <placeName ref="pl2151"><unclear reason="illegible">Kirtle</unclear></placeName>; looking back we had a fine view of <placeName ref="pl1098">Solway frith</placeName> &amp; the <placeName ref="pl0800">Cumberland</placeName>
                    <pb n="f.2v"/> mountains. The cottages are in general built of mud, but new ones
                    are rising here and there built of stone and slated. Harvest a good deal got in
                    — chiefly barley &amp; oats. No wheat to be seen. Passed close to <placeName ref="pl0563">Burnswark</placeName> and shortly after reached <placeName ref="pl0564">Ecclefechan</placeName>. Funeral just over — Small two wheeled
                    hearse with small <hi rend="underline">tow</hi> feathers at the corners.</p>
                <p>Passed a sort of Paddingtonian Gothic chateau with three pasteboard clumps in
                    part <pb n="f.3r"/> of it and a Strait channel cut In a mountain Stream running
                    on one side. Pretty situation of <placeName ref="pl2319">Castle <unclear reason="illegible">Milk</unclear></placeName> — neat village of
                        <placeName ref="pl0248">Lockerby</placeName> with two Kirks Stairs on the
                    outside of one of them leading up to the Gallery. We were detained some time for
                    horses &amp; got off at 3. Passed old burying place by the side of a river
                    without church annexed. Spaces inclosed by walls for family sepulchres with
                    their arms over the entrance. Hay made into large cocks <pb n="f.3v"/> Mountains
                    approach nearer. Many fir plantations. Pretty approach to <placeName ref="pl0247">Moffat</placeName>. A vale inclosed by mountains tall spire of
                    the church rising from trees. Plaid caps begin to appear as do bare legged and
                    bare footed women — white haired children — rustics wrapped up in coarse plaids.
                    Neat houses. Curious chimneys bound round with twisted <unclear reason="illegible">straw</unclear>. We arrived at <placeName ref="pl0247">Moffat</placeName> too late to set forward on the next long <pb n="f.4r"/>
                    stage the same evening; but had just time to walk up a mile &amp; half through a
                    valley to <placeName ref="pl2152">the mineral well</placeName> kept by an old
                    woman. The water tastes much of Sulphur. It flows from rocks a pint in a minute.
                    By it's <unclear reason="illegible">dike</unclear> is a ravine thro' which flows
                    a rapid mountain stream. The wells belonged to <persName ref="pe1418">L<hi rend="superscript">y.</hi> Hope</persName> who is just dead and her
                    remains are expected here on their way to <placeName ref="pl2316">Johnstone</placeName> between here &amp; <placeName ref="pl0248">Lockerby</placeName>. <pb n="f.4v"/> She was attending her daughter-in-laws
                    accouchement in <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName>. We had arrived at
                        <placeName ref="pl0247">Moffat</placeName> at 6, and got back from our walk
                    at 1/2 past 8 — Bed at 10. –––––</p>
                <p>Sep. 1. Left <placeName ref="pl0247">Moffat</placeName> at 1/4 past 6. Rain.
                    Steep ascent &amp; descent to Pretty wooded valley — first view of <placeName ref="pl0600">the Clyde</placeName> — <placeName ref="pl2120">Elvan
                        Foot</placeName> Breakfast. Sheep in great numbers following their leader
                    over the hills. Fine green <pb n="f.5r"/> downs. <placeName ref="pl0587">Douglas
                        Mill</placeName>. Turned off to the right towards <placeName ref="pl0590">Lanark</placeName> — <placeName ref="pl2153">Tinto</placeName> cloud
                    capped. Crossed <placeName ref="pl0600">the Clyde</placeName> by <placeName ref="pl2154">Hyndford bridge</placeName>, a very handsome one built by the
                    family of that name who have a seat a few miles on the right. Before reaching
                        <placeName ref="pl0590">Lanark</placeName> we walked down to the lodge of
                    the late <persName ref="pe0512">L<hi rend="superscript">y.</hi>
                        Ross's</persName> grounds, and Sent on the carriage to the town, Tho' the
                    day was rainy we met a good deal <pb n="f.5v"/> of Company. <placeName ref="pl0592">Corra</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl0593">Boninton</placeName> were very fine. In our way from thence we stopped at
                    the <placeName ref="pl1052">manufactories</placeName> and were shown over them
                    by <persName ref="pe1419">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                        <unclear reason="illegible">Gleck</unclear></persName>. They have a building
                    where they manufacture their machinery for spinning &amp;c. We saw their <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="2"/> instruments made of earth.
                    There are four cotton mills and we saw all the process they are kept remarkably
                    neat. The population is about 2400. The people buy their food <pb n="f.6                         r"/> at a large depot much cheaper &amp;
                    better than they could any where else. They subscribe 1<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> out of every <add place="above">five</add> shillings they earn for
                    the support of the sick &amp; old. A large house is now building where those who
                    like it may dine together in public — it will be a great saving to them of
                        <unclear reason="illegible">pies</unclear> in the summer. The school is
                    excellent and contains a number of rooms. One of them is for very small children
                        <pb n="f.6v"/> who are thus taken off their parents hands for some hours
                    every day and placed under the care of a person — but are not taught anything.
                    The children in the School learn besides reading &amp; writing — dancing piping
                    and the manual exercise. They begin at 7 — breakfast — come again at 10 — dine
                    come again at 3 and stay till five. There are about 700 here <pb n="f.7r"/> at
                    present and the boys and girls are taught together. In the same building is a
                    chapel where service is performed for the children every Sunday; in week days it
                    is used as a School<unclear reason="illegible">room</unclear> The Contrivances
                    In their slates which slip down in grooves at the back of the desks and of the
                    inkstands w<hi rend="superscript">h.</hi> have little covers to keep out the
                    dust are very neat. The children who are <pb n="f.7v"/> imployed in manufactures
                    during the day and are in want of education taught in the evening and are
                    allowed to sit down. Having finished our inspection of all the buildings we went
                    down to see the large water wheels which turn all the works and are of immense
                    size. We then proceeded up the hill by a steep path and met an old rustic who
                    spoke <pb n="f.8r"/> much in praise of <persName ref="pe1420">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Owen</persName>, he has been <add place="above">here</add> 19 years, and is one of the partners of the works
                    and the principal manager. The other three partners do not reside here. A large
                    garden is Cultivated by them &amp; vegetables from it sold at a low price to the
                        manufacturers.<note type="authorial">N.B. We saw different tokens hung up at
                        the <del rend="overstrike">
                            <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" quantity="1"/>
                        </del>
                        <add place="above">prospective stations</add> of the artisans marking their
                        degrees of merit for which they receive prizes. —</note></p>
                <p><pb n="f.8v"/>Sep. 2. We got up at 1/2 past 5 this morning but the people were so
                    lazy that we could find neither guide waiter or ostler stirring. In about 1/2 an
                    hour we procured the Cicerone and walking thro' the town turned off by a path to
                    the right and came down to <placeName ref="pl2155">M<hi rend="superscript">Lockhart's</hi> house</placeName> opposite which there is a very
                    distinct echo. Then walking up the Hill on <pb n="f.9r"/> the opposite side we
                    came to <placeName ref="-3.7979428">the Crags</placeName>. Here there is a
                    pretty Moss seat but the walk along the precipice is a mere footpath. We saw
                        <placeName ref="pl1055">Wallace's cave</placeName> a small cleft in the rock
                    opposite not more than 20 feet above the river. Near where <placeName ref="pl2156">the Mouse</placeName> joins <placeName ref="pl0600">the
                        Clyde</placeName> are two bridges; one of them is very picturesque &amp; has
                    a large semicircular arch and is called <placeName ref="pl2158">Roman</placeName>; but is now disused as a <pb n="f.9v"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl2157">flatter stronger and broader one</placeName> has been
                    built to supply it's place. Soon after we crossed <placeName ref="pl0600">the
                        Clyde</placeName> and stopped at <placeName ref="pl0594">Stonebyres</placeName>.</p>
                <p>I scrambled down to the rocks in the bed of the river from whence is the best
                    view. The vale of <placeName ref="pl0600">the Clyde</placeName> beyond
                        <placeName ref="pl0594">Stonebyres</placeName> grows very beautiful, there
                    is a great deal of wood and a number <pb n="f.10r"/> of gentlemen's seats. Col
                        <gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="1"/> is rebuilding his
                    house which has been consumed by fire, in the Gothic style. We arrived about 10
                    at <placeName ref="pl0597">Hamilton</placeName>, breakfasted and inspected
                        <placeName ref="pl0231">the palace</placeName>; there is <rs ref="ar0268">a
                        very fine Coregio of Christ Scourged</rs>; <rs ref="ar0273">portrait of the
                        handsome Duke of Hamilton in regimentals</rs>, and <rs ref="ar0078"><add place="above">of</add> his mother</rs> a most beautiful <pb n="f.10v"/>
                    woman. Leaving it we crossed <placeName ref="pl0600">the Clyde</placeName> by
                        <placeName ref="pl0230">Bothwell Bridge</placeName> famous for the battle
                    with the Convenanters and then stopped at <placeName ref="pl0599">Bothwell
                        Castle</placeName> which is a most lovely place; you see nothing of it's
                    beauty from the high road. The house is very large built of red stone and
                    commands an extensive view towards <pb n="f.11r"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> — one end looks down upon <placeName ref="pl0600">the Clyde</placeName>. We walked all over the grounds &amp;
                    spent some time in exploring the ruins. On leaving this place the vale of
                        <placeName ref="pl0600">the Clyde</placeName> continues very rich and the
                    spires of <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> begin to appear in the
                    distance — but as you approach the city the country is spoilt by the smoke and
                    manufactories. <pb n="f.11v"/> We arrived at <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> about 4 and put up at <placeName ref="pl2159">the Black
                        Bull</placeName>. Walked up <placeName ref="pl2160">the Trongate</placeName>
                    and saw some of the principal features of the town. In evening went to a meeting
                    house to hear <persName ref="pe1422">Wardlaw</persName>, but were too late as
                    the service had begun and the doors were shut. —</p>
                <p><pb n="f.12r"/> Sep. 3. Went down to <placeName ref="pl1099">the
                        Green</placeName> and saw <placeName ref="pl2161">the Courthouse</placeName>
                    and Bridges — thence went up to <placeName ref="pl1059">the
                        Cathedral</placeName> which is divided into two churches; the fine Gothic
                    architecture is spoilt by pews and galleries — The Church below is now disused.
                    Near to <placeName ref="pl1059">the Cathedral</placeName> is a new <pb n="f.12v"/> Hospital for the recovery of Typhus fevers. We then descended to <placeName ref="pl1061">the College</placeName> but did not go over <placeName ref="pl1060">the Museum</placeName>. We saw the process of Singeing and also
                    a carpet manufactory. Met <persName ref="pe1423">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                        <unclear reason="illegible">Baker</unclear></persName> and went with them to
                    see a <pb n="f.13r"/> tambour manufactory where the work is done by machinery,
                    but we could not get admittance. Having been to the <unclear reason="illegible">Bankers</unclear> and engaged a pair of horses and driver from <placeName ref="pl2159">the Black Bull</placeName> for our Highland tour at the rate of
                    £1..19..0 a day we got some dinner and started at 5.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.13v"/> Met reapers coming home from their work. Fine view of <placeName ref="pl2162">the Campsie</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl2163">Kilpatrick
                        hills</placeName>; just reached <placeName ref="pl1062">Dalnottar
                        hill</placeName> in time to see the view before it <unclear reason="illegible">gone</unclear> dark. Wound along <placeName ref="pl0600">the Clyde</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0226">Dumbarton</placeName>
                    which we reached about 8, and found the Inn dirty and swarming with bugs. —</p>
                <p><pb n="f.14r"/> Sep. 4. The first Bulletin this morning was that it was raining.
                    During breakfast the waiter told us that the Steam boat would set off from the
                    foot of <placeName ref="pl0223">Loch Lomond</placeName> on a tour round the lake
                    at 10 o clock; as the weather looked better we therefore preferred this novelty
                    to waiting till we had visited <placeName ref="pl1104">the castle</placeName>
                    and started immediately after breakfast. The banks of <placeName ref="pl1063">the Leven</placeName> are very picturesque and have a flourishing
                    appearance; cornfields (the corn generally cut) with fine trees fringing the
                    river, neat cottages, and hills rising at a little distance from the <pb n="f.14v"/> scenery. <placeName ref="pl1064">Smollet's monument</placeName>
                    remains in it's place, but no pains seem to be taken to keep it in repair, and
                    the marble tablet which contains the inscription and is inlaid in the Pedestal
                    is broken in half and one piece seems ready to tumble out. We passed a number of
                    shearers going to their work the rain having ceased. The women were a good
                    specimen of Scotch beauty; they walked very upright, and their hair was neatly
                    braided behind without any cap. Before we had any glimpse of <placeName ref="pl0223">the Loch</placeName> we turned <pb n="f.15r"/> down sharp to
                    the right and found ourselves on the banks of <placeName ref="pl1063">the
                        Leven</placeName> a little below the spot where it flows out of the Loch.
                    The steamboat was just going off and the horn blowing for a signal. A punt
                    carried us to it and we seated ourselves on a bench near the stern and soon put
                    off. At this moment a volume of thick smoke issued from the chimney and the
                    steam issuing with great force from the pipe covered half the deck with a
                    shower; but this soon ceased and we went quietly at the rate <pb n="f.15v"/> of
                    seven miles an hour. This velocity is not quite agreable to the Sketcher, as the
                    same view continues for so short a time, and no halt is made except for a minute
                    or two at a very few places to take up passengers. But then you have the
                    advantage of visiting every part of the lake and forming an excellent idea of it
                    which in a common boat with rowers it would be impossible to accomplish in a
                    day. It has been established three months and answers very well. We had <pb n="f.16r"/> about 20 passengers who were more select than we expected to
                    find. We first passed <placeName ref="pl1205">the D. of Montrose's deer park
                        Inch Murin</placeName> where are about 200 head of deer; next <placeName ref="pl2164">Crainch</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl2165">Taminch</placeName>, and <placeName ref="pl1110">Inch Callich</placeName>,
                    the latter is very high, abrupt rocky and woody; these four are in a strait line
                    and stretch across the lake in it's greatest breadth. On <unclear reason="illegible">doubling</unclear> the extreme point of <placeName ref="pl1110">Inch Callich</placeName> we proceeded strait up the lake and
                    passed <placeName ref="pl2166">Inch fad</placeName>, low and without wood &amp;
                    with corn upon it.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.16v"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl1113">Inch Tavanach</placeName> on our right I regretted to
                    see had been spoiled of it's beautiful wood. All these Islands we saw to great
                    advantage but <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben lomond's</placeName> head continued
                    veiled in clouds and most of the mountains followed it's example. We stopped at
                        <placeName ref="pl0224">Luss</placeName> and took up some more passengers
                    and small rain soon came on but not bad enough to drive us from deck. Passing
                    close to the base of <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben lomond</placeName> we stopped
                    at <placeName ref="pl1067">Row Ardennan</placeName> and took up some youths who
                        <pb n="f.17r"/> just come down from an unsuccessful expedition to the top of
                    the mountain.</p>
                <p>Passed <placeName ref="pl2167">Rob Roy's rocks</placeName> not large or striking
                    objects and came to a small cottage with a mountain torrent rolling down in a
                    fine cascade close to it: on the hill above is <placeName ref="pl2168">Inversnaid</placeName>. We then went on about a mile further to a bold
                    rocky point which is the farthest place the boat goes to <del rend="overstrike">it</del> and here about 40 yards from the shore is <placeName ref="pl2169">Rob Roy's Cave or Cove</placeName>. The path up to it is very <pb n="f.17v"/> steep and bad and I think too bad for a lady to attempt, but <persName ref="pe1501">Maria</persName> with a good deal of scrambling and difficulty
                    contrived to reach the mouth of it. There is not much to be seen it is very
                    small and the form very rude being caused by great stones which have fallen down
                    from the heights above and in such <add place="above">a</add> way as to form a
                    cavity beneath them. Here we turned back and heavy showers coming on we were not
                    sorry to land at <placeName ref="pl0222">Tarbet</placeName> at three, and the
                    boat <pb n="f.18r"/> proceeded in it's course down to the foot of <placeName ref="pl0223">the Loch</placeName> which it would reach at 6. The distance up
                    to <placeName ref="pl2169">the Cave</placeName> they call 23 miles. The inn is
                    small and at first we thought indifferent but the attentive and officious
                    innkeeper conducted us to another house at a little distance which is very clean
                    and comfortable. <persName ref="pe1501">Maria</persName> and I walked a couple
                    of miles on <placeName ref="pl2182">the Tyndrum road</placeName>, and returned
                    to Dinner at 7. The evening turned out fine and we saw <add place="above">the
                        top of</add>
                    <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben Lomond</placeName>. Bed at 10.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.18v"/> 5<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> We had given orders last night
                    to have a boat and guide read at 1/2 past 6. to proceed on an expedition to
                        <placeName ref="pl2170">Loch Katrine</placeName>, but so lazy were the
                    innkeeper and his train that it was passed that time before we could obtain
                    breakfast, and 20 minutes to 8. before we were seated in the boat where we were
                    immediately joined by two gentlemen who were afterwards found to be <persName ref="pe1425">Col<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> Austen</persName> and
                        <persName ref="pe1424">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Cazalet</persName>.
                    The day promised to be very fine, we reached the cottage and waterfall where we
                    had touched in the Steam boat the <pb n="f.19r"/> preceding day, at a little
                    after eight and began to climb the hill; and after ascending for about ten
                    minutes we dipped down a little and lost sight of the lake but not of the fine
                    mountains <placeName ref="pl2171">Benvein</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl2172">Beneim</placeName> which are seen from <placeName ref="pl2170">Loch Katrine</placeName> and are a principal feature in the views on that
                    lake though they rise from the opposite bank of <placeName ref="pl0223">Loch
                        Lomond</placeName>. We now had to ascend another but less steep hill upon
                    which are <placeName ref="pl2173">the remains of a fort</placeName> (nothing
                    more however than a fortified <pb n="f.19v"/> house, without any battery or
                    works, which was originally placed there by Government as a check upon the
                    lawless clan of the Macgregors of which <persName ref="pe0538">Rob
                        Roy</persName> was so well known an individual. A guard was kept there till
                    about 17 years ago and the house is now falling to ruins. One of our Guides told
                    us a marvellous story of one of the Macgregor's having once upon a time taken
                    the fort by his own will <pb n="f.20r"/> and courage without assistance from any
                    body. He appeared at night before the outer centinel at whose heart he suddenly
                    pointed a dirk threatening to stab him instantly if he did not lay down his
                    arms, which he obliged him to do bound him hand and foot obtained from him the
                    key of the garrison which he entered and took the whole armoury away with him
                    and all the weapons he could find about the soldiers who it appears <pb n="f.20v"/> remained fast asleep all this time. Having performed this feat
                    he appeared before the fort next morning <add place="above">with a few of his
                        followers</add> and demanded <add place="above">of</add> them to give up the
                    garrison, threatening to massacre them all if they refused to comply, and which
                    to complete the story they of course acceded to. To corroborate this statement
                    the <sic>narator</sic> said he had known the agent of all this when very old and
                    had the story <pb n="f.21r"/> from him, but he is unfortunately not living still
                    (I should rather say fortunately) to be catechised by the hundreds and thousands
                    who frequent <placeName ref="pl2170">Loch Katrine</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl0223">Loch Lomond</placeName>. Our talk on this and other local
                    subjects occupied us as we walked thro' the valley between the two lakes, w<hi rend="superscript">h.</hi> only boasts a single house all the way and has no
                    very striking features. The road is tolerably level, and a very fair mountain
                    horse road.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.21v"/> Soon after we had got half way we came to a small piece of water
                    called <placeName ref="pl2174">Loch Arkil</placeName>, and at the very end of
                    this came in sight of <q><placeName ref="pl2170">Loch Katrine</placeName>
                        blue</q><note type="editorial">Walter Scott, <hi rend="italic">The Lady of
                            the Lake</hi> (Edinburgh: 1810), III, ii, l.2. Scott's poem contributed
                        to the development of Loch Katrine and the Trossachs as a major tourist
                        site.</note> but with out any other accompaniments than mountains wood being
                    almost entirely excluded from the picture. <placeName ref="pl2175">Benan</placeName> is seen from hence with the top of <placeName ref="pl1168">Benvenue</placeName> to the right of it and <placeName ref="pl1167">Benledi</placeName> in the distance. After waiting half an hour
                    a boat was seen shooting <pb n="f.22r"/> across the lake to us, not piloted by
                    an Ellen,<note type="editorial">A reference to the central character of Scott's
                            <hi rend="italic">The Lady of the Lake</hi>.</note> but by an old
                    weather beaten Highlander, accompanied by a guide we had sent on before to
                    secure it, as it is the only boat to be met with at this end of the lake. We
                    embarked about 11 and had a very pleasant sail to the other end of the lake; no
                    houses are to be seen but a small white one beautifully situated and belonging
                    to a <persName ref="pe1426">Graham</persName>, his property was formerly
                    intermixed <pb n="f.22v"/> with <persName ref="pe0174">the Duke of
                        Montrose's</persName> and he gave the Duke a good deal of trouble by
                    interfering with his shooting and other things, till at the last his Grace was
                    glad to make a bargain with him by which the Statesman gained a much better
                    property and a much prettier situation for his house; the other mansion is now
                    more humble being without a chimney and the owner a shepherd fills it with a
                    family of 15 Children who we saw <pb n="f.23r"/> working in a field near the
                    flight of steps. <placeName ref="pl0609">Ben Lomond</placeName> looks well from
                    hence and a stone at the top looks like a man who has just ascended it. On
                    reaching the last bend of the lake <placeName ref="pl1168">Benvenue</placeName>
                    burst upon us but not in all it's former glory on account of some of the wood
                    having been cut down and the whole that remains being doomed to the same fate by
                        <persName ref="pe0174">the Duke's</persName> order who has sold it for the
                    paltry sum of £200; the elegant birches fit for <pb n="f.23v"/> little but to
                    ornament the sides of their native mountains have been stripped of their bark
                    (which by the by they say is worth half us much as oak)<note type="editorial">The demand for tree bark for use in the tanning industry had a significant
                        impact on Scottish woodland in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries; see
                        T.C. Smout, Alan R. MacDonald and Fiona Watson, <hi rend="italic">A History
                            of the Native Woodlands of Scotland, 1500-1920</hi> (Edinburgh:
                        Edinburgh University Press, 2005), pp.248-53.</note> look very sickly and
                    this autumn will be cut down for posts and rails: observed on the shore a little
                    to the left of <placeName ref="pl2176">Roderick's Island</placeName> a bold rock
                    on which was formerly planted a maison de plaisance but was blown away one
                        night.<note type="editorial">This site was apparently intact when visited by
                        Dorothy Wordsworth and her companions in 1803: 'just as we came in sight of
                        two huts, which have been built by Lady Perth as a shelter for those who
                        visit the Trossachs, Coleridge hailed us with a shout of triumph from the
                        door of one of them, exulting in the glory of Scotland. The huts stand at a
                        small distance from each other, on a high and perpendicular rock, that rises
                        from the bed of the lake.' Dorothy Wordsworth, <hi rend="italic">Recollections of a Tour Made in Scotland</hi> (New Haven, London: Yale
                        University Press, 1997), pp.102-103.</note> All this side belongs to
                        <persName ref="pe1428">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> D. Burrell</persName>
                    <pb n="f.24r"/> who obtained it by marrying <persName ref="pe1427">the heiress
                        of the Perth family</persName>. We walked thro' <placeName ref="pl2177">the
                        Trossachs</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl2178">Stewart's</placeName> at
                    the head of <placeName ref="pl2179">Loch Achray</placeName> and partook of some
                    apartment in his dirty quarters. Much of the wood here too is cut down but it is
                    allowed to grow for 21 <choice>
                        <abbr>y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                        </abbr>
                        <expan>years</expan>
                    </choice> a few large ones are left always to grow into fine trees. They say
                        <persName ref="pe1428">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Burrell</persName> if
                    he wished could not build an Inn here as <persName ref="pe1429">Stewart</persName> has a lease of all the ground hereabouts for some <choice>
                        <abbr>y<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>years</expan>
                    </choice> to come <pb n="f.24v"/> and he is very glad to pocket money from
                    visitors without paying a licence though he is at perpetual war with the
                    excisemen about it. <persName ref="pe1501">Maria</persName> and I wished to ride
                    over to <placeName ref="pl2180">Aberfoil</placeName> and return by <placeName ref="pl2181">Loch Ard</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl1067">Rowardennan</placeName> but we found it would be 21 miles and besides this
                    could hire no ponies; we therefore were obliged to give it up and returned with
                    our companions thro' <placeName ref="pl2177">the Trossachs</placeName> and
                    reembarked at 4. There was <pb n="f.25r"/> more wind then incoming and it came
                    down from the mountain in eddies and sometimes brought down the side of our boat
                    close to the water, but we had an experienced pilot who brought us safe to shore
                    in an hour and a half. Rain came on and increased in violence as we reached
                        <placeName ref="pl0223">Loch Lomond</placeName> when it was dark. Two of the
                    party joined the boatman in pulling and we with difficulty reached the opposite
                        <pb n="f.25v"/> banks where we landed and walked thro' a little wood into
                        <placeName ref="pl2182">the Tyndrum road</placeName>. Pursuing this for two
                    miles (the same walk we had taken the evening before) we reached <placeName ref="pl0222">Tarbett</placeName> a little before ten, and after changing our
                    clothes sat down to a good supper.</p>
                <p>
                    <gap reason="authorial" unit="lines" quantity="5"/>
                </p>
                <p><pb n="f.26r"/> 6<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> The Drenching of last night made
                    us rather late at breakfast this morning when we found it still raining. The
                    landlady and her children and several other people in their Sunday clothes
                    (which were as good and handsome as any in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>) trotting off to church with their umbrellas shamed us
                    a little as we had decided not to go, but I thought it would not do to let
                        <persName ref="pe1501">Maria</persName> have the benefit of another cold
                    bath. At 12 we set off and <pb n="f.26v"/> drove thro the narrow and gloomy vale
                    to <placeName ref="pl1008">Arroquhar</placeName>. The road for these two miles
                    is as bad as possible and an exception to the usual good roads of <placeName ref="pl0711">the Highlands</placeName>. The beauty of the Inn has been a
                    little impaired by some of the trees in front of it having been cut down, but
                        <placeName ref="pl1171">the Cobler</placeName> remains in status quo hard at
                    his work. Passing on to the head of the <placeName ref="pl0221">Loch</placeName>, the fishermen's nets spread on large upright s<unclear reason="illegible">ev</unclear>ens to dry had a picturesque effect.
                        <placeName ref="pl1068">The valley of Glencroe</placeName> looked <pb n="f.27r"/> as wild as ever but the wind was not high enough to annoy us in
                    ascending to <placeName ref="pl0220">Rest and be thankful</placeName>. We
                    reached <placeName ref="pl1069">Cairndow</placeName> at 4 oclock and found
                        <placeName ref="pl2183">the Inn</placeName> very full from a large party
                    having just arrived from <placeName ref="pl1072">Inverary</placeName> which
                    place they had come to in the steam boat from <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName>. These steamboats bring a good deal of company on
                    Sundays but on the whole diminish the profits of the Innkeepers on this road the
                        <placeName ref="pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> cits enjoying <pb n="f.27v"/> a
                    sea voyage and the sight of the <placeName ref="pl0719">Islands of
                        Arran</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl0714">Bute</placeName>. <persName ref="pe1430">Col. Callander</persName> the proprietor of <persName ref="pl1071">Ardkinglas</persName> has lately built a very neat <placeName ref="pl2185">Kirk</placeName> close to the Inn which has cost him £1000. The
                    Kirk is octagonal and it has a very handsome Gothic tower perhaps too good for
                    the other part of the building. He is rather embarrassed in his affairs and
                    lives near <placeName ref="pl0235">Stirling</placeName> till an incumbrance on
                    the estate is paid off. <placeName ref="pl1070">The loch</placeName> looked very
                    fine <pb n="f.28r"/> as the clouds cleared off at sunset. <persName ref="pe1505">William</persName> and <persName ref="pe1506">Jane</persName> came up in
                    the evening and we had the church prayers.</p>
                <p>7<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> We started soon after six without rain; saw some
                    herons and Sea Gulls at the head of the lake, began to hear gaelic spoken;
                    sketched <placeName ref="pl2186">Dundanan castle</placeName> and wound round the
                    beautiful bay of <placeName ref="pl1072">Inverary</placeName> to the town where
                    we got some letters and breakfasted. We then visited <placeName ref="pl0217">the
                        Duke's house</placeName> where some repairs are going on; it was built by
                        <pb n="f.28v"/>
                    <persName ref="pe1431">Archibald</persName> son to <persName ref="pe1432">the
                        great John</persName>, his son <persName ref="pe0086">the late
                        Duke</persName><note type="editorial">Archibald Campbell, third duke of
                        Argyll was not succeeded by his son but his cousin, John Campbell
                        (c.1693-1770), the fourth duke. The fourth duke was in turn succeeded by his
                        son, also John, the 'late duke' mentioned here.</note> removed the town to
                    it's present situation; and the whole thing being made perfect <persName ref="pe1433">the reigning Duke</persName> deserts it and scarcely ever comes
                    to enjoy it's beauties. He is however now expected with <persName ref="pe1434">his Duchess</persName> to stay a few weeks. There is here <rs ref="ar0275">a portait of the handsome Duke of Hamilton</rs> a relation of the family's
                    by marriage, and <rs ref="ar0274">of the beautiful Lady Charlotte Campbell by
                            <pb n="f.29r"/> Laurence</rs> which was a good deal damaged by the fire
                    at <placeName ref="pl0613">Roseneath</placeName>. Having inspected the house
                    which was shown us by a very civil woman with the Cumberland accent we wound
                    round the base of <placeName ref="pl0218">Dunicoich</placeName> and had the
                    beautiful view of <placeName ref="pl1072">the bay and town</placeName>. You
                    cannot now go the regular footpath from <placeName ref="pl2187">the
                        Inn</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0217">the Castle</placeName> which is
                    shut up; and you are obliged to enter the path by the road thro' a pine avenue;
                    we perceived a large stone sticking up in <pb n="f.29v"/> the lawn which was
                    probably a monument to some chief. A fine avenue extends from <placeName ref="pl1072">the town</placeName> to the South west terminating in something
                    worth seeing but we had not time to explore it. Leaving <placeName ref="pl1072">Inverary</placeName> we entered the Duke's park drove by his stables and
                    farm buildings and ascended thro the vale of <placeName ref="pl0219">Aray</placeName> with fine woods on each side. After mounting two miles we
                    stopped to see a beautiful fall of the river with a very rustic bridge thrown
                        <pb n="f.30r"/> across. Soon after we emerged from the woods and entered a
                    very barren tract with rugged mountains on each side constantly ascending and
                    the river still roaring by our side; when we had almost traced it to it's source
                    and reached the summit of the mountain we had a magnificent view down upon
                        <placeName ref="pl0269">Loch Awe</placeName> and it's Islands; <placeName ref="pl0831">Ben Cruachan</placeName> rearing it's tremendous form on the
                    opposite side</p>
                <p><pb n="f.30v"/> Descending a steep road to <placeName ref="pl0216">Clady</placeName> that village <add place="above">with it's trees</add>
                    made a fine foreground, two islands<note type="editorial"><placeName ref="pl0272">Fraoch Eilean</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl0271">Inishail</placeName>.</note> in the lake had a striking appearance, one
                    rocky and covered with deep green wood and enveloped in shade, another of a fine
                    undulating outline covered with grass and a yellow light playing upon it, behind
                    the branch of the lake which goes North towards <placeName ref="pl1249">Bunawe</placeName> and has gloomy mountains on each side of it had a
                    singular appearance. From <placeName ref="pl0216">Clady</placeName> we had a
                    fine drive to <placeName ref="pl0214">Dalmally</placeName>, black mountains of
                    fine outline opening in front; <pb n="f.31r"/> we passed over a dreary moor with
                    a number of miserable cottages, and the inhabitants now assuming the highland
                    costume made the scene wild &amp; romantic. We descended to <placeName ref="pl0214">Dalmally</placeName> after <unclear reason="illegible">Supp<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></unclear> where we found tolerable
                    accommodation; and walked before supper to <placeName ref="pl0213">Glenorchy</placeName> Kirk by moonlight, <placeName ref="pl0988">the
                        Urchay</placeName> rolling rapidly along, the corn in the meadows cut &amp;
                    in sheaves and the dark mountains towering behind just as I had seen <add place="above">place</add> three years before.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.31v"/> 7<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> We set of at 7, and passing
                        <placeName ref="pl0213">Glenorchy</placeName> church and crossing <placeName ref="pl0988">the river</placeName> we drove down to the head of <placeName ref="pl0269">the Loch</placeName>, and perceived on an island at this
                    extremity the romantic <placeName ref="pl0215">castle of Kilchurn</placeName>;
                    skirted around the base of <placeName ref="pl0831">Cruachan</placeName>; road
                    hilly and thro' young wood but always close to <del rend="overstrike">it</del>
                    and overhanging <placeName ref="pl0269">the Loch</placeName>; we passed the
                    Northern branch of the lake where the scenery becomes closer and the mountains
                    opposite <unclear reason="illegible">low</unclear> and abrupt, it narrows
                    gradually and then the current increases and it <pb n="f.32r"/> changes into a
                    river which runs on impetuously of a beautiful blue colour and foams like the
                    sea. We arrived at <placeName ref="pl1074"><unclear reason="illegibe">Tynuilt</unclear></placeName> a single house to a late breakfast; and
                    then walked up a hill infront where a large tall <placeName ref="pl2188">natural
                        pillar</placeName> of grey granite has been placed in memory of <persName ref="pe1435">Lord Nelson</persName> by the workers in the iron<hi rend="superscript">*</hi><note type="authorial">* called the <placeName ref="pl1249">Lorn works</placeName> from the name of this mountainous
                        district.</note> furnaces at <placeName ref="pl1249">Bunawe</placeName> just
                    below; the iron is bought from <placeName ref="pl1044">Lancashire</placeName>
                    the inducement is the plentifulness of charcoal in this neighbourhood.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.32v"/> Below is <placeName ref="pl1075">Loch Etive</placeName> a sea
                    loch, which insinuates itself in a chain of mountains terminating in <placeName ref="pl2189">Ben Starive</placeName> a most picturesque mountain where
                    Cairngouram stones are found. Proceeding onwards we went thro' a hilly but more
                    open country with a good deal of young wood; rudely made <unclear reason="illegible">birch</unclear> gates here and there to keep in cattle;
                    at length we wound down to the margin of the lake and caught a view of
                        <placeName ref="pl0685">Dunstaffnage Castle</placeName> and <pb n="f.33r"/>
                    beyond of the picturesque mountains of <placeName ref="pl0729">Mull</placeName>;
                    at <placeName ref="pl0686">Connell Ferry</placeName> the lake is very narrow and
                    rapid and soon after widens into <placeName ref="pl2190">Loch
                    Linnhe</placeName>; here the mountain views are extensive in every way, but
                    looking Backwards <placeName ref="pl0831">Ben Cruachan</placeName> beats them
                    all. We here turned off from the Loch and went over a hilly tract of 5 miles to
                        <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName> where the land is strangely thrown
                    about <unclear reason="illegible">in varyed</unclear> masses of rock without any
                    picturesque outline. <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName> is a neat white
                    village; <pb n="f.33v"/> lining the shore of a little bay, with a castle at one
                    extremity bold crags at the other and the <placeName ref="pl1077">island of
                        Kerrera</placeName> almost closing it up in front. We had a charming evening
                    walk in the environs. Herring boats coming in immensely loaded. There are a
                    number of small sailing boats kept here and a larger vessel a cutter is kept by
                    some people connected with the Custom house; hearing some people had hired it we
                    asked to join them which they agreed to. <placeName ref="pl2191">The
                        Inn</placeName> is very bad</p>
                <p><pb n="f.34r"/> 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> A Delightful morning but we found
                    our intended companions had taken fright and given up their voyage, we therefore
                    took the cutter to ourselves. At <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" quantity="1"/> we rowed out in a boat to it,<hi rend="superscript">*</hi><note type="authorial">* a very pretty setter belonging to our pilot
                        swam off from land more than a quarter of a mile and reached the
                        ship.</note> and had to take a good many tacks before we could get out of
                    the harbour. The <placeName ref="pl1077">Island of Kerrera</placeName> protects
                    it a good deal from the tempests of <placeName ref="pl2190">Loch
                        Linnhe</placeName> but it is still very rough in winter. Passing under the
                        <placeName ref="pl0722">castle</placeName> we observed the <placeName ref="pl2192">Dogstone</placeName> a large upright rock to which <persName ref="pe0544">Bruce</persName> used to tie his hounds. The greatest part of
                    the <placeName ref="pl0722">Castle</placeName> was pulled down for it's
                    limestone about 30 <choice>
                        <abbr>yr<hi rend="superscript">s.</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>years</expan>
                    </choice> ago. On emerging from the harbour we had a fine view up <placeName ref="pl2190">Loch Linnhe</placeName>
                    <pb n="f.34v"/> and at some distance on the right is the <placeName ref="pl2193">plain of Appin</placeName> overshadowed by mountains where <placeName ref="pl2194">Beregonium</placeName> the ancient Capital of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> or at least of the Western <placeName ref="pl0711">Highlands</placeName> is said to have stood.<note type="editorial">A site near the fort of Dun Mac Sniachan on Ardmucknish Bay
                        was spuriously identified with the royal city of Fergus II by the
                        fifteenth-century Scottish historian, Hector Boece. Despite the unreliabilty
                        of the attribution, it was taken up by subsequent writers and travellers and
                        is marked on James Dorret's <hi rend="italic">A general map of Scotland and
                            islands thereto belonging</hi> (London: 1750). Beregonium is also
                        mentioned in Sinclair's <hi rend="italic">Statistical Account of
                            Scotland</hi> (Edinburgh: 1791-1799) and (with a degree of scepticism)
                        in Pennant, <hi rend="italic">A Tour in Scotland and Voyage to the Hebrides
                            1772</hi> (Chester: 1774), p.411. See also Richard Pococke, <hi rend="italic">Tours in Scotland 1747, 1750, 1760</hi>, ed. by Daniel
                        William Kemp (Edinburgh: Scottish History Society, 1887), p.69 and Robert
                        Angus Smith, <hi rend="italic">Loch Etive and the Sons of Uisnach</hi>,
                        (London: 1879).</note> We soon approached the <placeName ref="pl0688">Island
                        of Lismore</placeName> which is long <add place="above">low</add> and narrow
                    and stretches lengthways up the Loch dividing it nearly equally. It is
                    excessively fertile and has patches of corn all over it but the principal part
                    is pasture. A Catholic Bishop who resided here for many years is just dead;
                    there is also <add place="above">a</add> seminary for young Catholics in which
                    400 are educated. Crossing the loch we entered the <placeName ref="pl2195">sound
                        of Mull</placeName> with <pb n="f.35r"/> that Island on the left hand and on
                    the right the <placeName ref="pl0683">Morvern</placeName> Hills. Close to the
                    entrance of the Sound is <placeName ref="pl0684">Dewart Castle</placeName> where
                        <persName ref="pe1436">Joanna Baillie</persName> has laid the scene of her
                        <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0293">legendary tale</title></bibl>
                    founded in events which occurred there. A little further on the opposite side is
                    the <placeName ref="pl2196">Castle of Ardtornish</placeName> celebrated by
                        <persName ref="pe1437">Scott</persName> in His <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0295">Lord of the Isles</title></bibl>. The Hills on each side
                    are bleak without any wood and very few habitations. The wind came down in
                        <unclear reason="illegible">hidden</unclear> strong eddies as we passed any
                    opening in them. Passed several low rocky Islands completely covered with
                    Seagulls who feast on the herrings. We reached <placeName ref="pl0682">Aross</placeName>
                    <pb n="f.35v"/> at 2, where the waves were rippling up it's smooth beach. Two or
                    three old walls with a few loopholes in them called a castle stand on a hill
                    near the shore around which are the few houses which compose the village.
                    Winding around it's base we came to the <placeName ref="pl2197">Inn</placeName>
                    in front of which an impetuous stream rushes along and empties itself into the
                    Sound. The <placeName ref="pl2197">Inn</placeName> has only one floor but has
                        <add place="above">a</add> shop adjoining which belongs to the landlord who
                    ingrosses all the custom of this part of the Island. We were surprised to find
                    here 3 or 4 fine ladies dressed in white with their hair done up without caps;
                    it appeared this was not the every day dress of these damsels <pb n="f.36r"/>
                    who were come over from a neighbouring village on a visit to the Landlady. We
                    got mounted in about an hour's time, I on a stout grey poney, and <persName ref="pe1501">Maria</persName> on a little Shetland; our saddles and bridles
                    were as bad as possible; one of the natives walked by our side and carried some
                    of our baggage. Having ascended a long hill we had an extensive view from the
                    top down to the other side of the Island with <placeName ref="pl1079">LochnaKeal</placeName> and the <placeName ref="pl0815">Benmore</placeName>
                    range of mountains on the opposite side of it, with <placeName ref="pl2199">Knock</placeName> at their base. We descended to a cottage where we waited
                    till the return of a messenger I had sent with <pb n="f.36v"/>
                    <persName ref="pe1439">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Smith's</persName> letter
                    to <persName ref="pe1438">Col. Campbell</persName> who <add place="above">returned an answer</add> giving us a kind invitation to his house. We now
                    trotted along the banks of the Loch to <placeName ref="pe1438">Knock</placeName>
                    which we reached at Sunset and were hospitably revived by the Col. and his three
                    sisters. He has seen a good deal of service in the <placeName ref="pl2072">East
                        Indies</placeName> and returned a few years ago to this his native spot and
                    has made a very comfortable house. It stands at the base of <placeName ref="pl2198">Benmore</placeName> the highest mountain in <placeName ref="pl0729">Mull</placeName>, and at the opening of the valley formed by
                    this mountain and another ridge, thro' which flows a river forming a fine lake
                    in it's course a mile or two beyond the house. In front is seen <placeName ref="pl1079">loch na Keal</placeName>. <pb n="f.37r"/> and the shores
                    opposite, together with the Island which is placed at the Mouth of the Loch and
                    shelters it from storms. We drank tea as soon as we arrived, and soon after grew
                    very sociable: and concluded by a regular hot supper.</p>
                <p>10<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> We hailed a fine morning with great delight and
                    after fortifying ourselves with an excellent Scotch Breakfast; <persName ref="pe1501">Maria</persName> rode and I walked a quarter of a mile from the
                    house to the Loch where we found our sailing boat ready. Two women followed us
                    bearing a small trunk which our kind entertainers had filled with provisions and
                    the key was given to me. The shores here <pb n="f.37v"/> are covered with coarse
                    light brown and yellowish seaweed with a good many pods in it like the
                        <placeName ref="pl2200">Rottingdean</placeName> Seaweed. This is turned into
                    a very lucrative article; it is cut and then thrown into a trough and burnt, and
                    after being stirred about a good deal with iron prongs it becomes liquid, when
                    it is left to cool and it then turns into solid cakes which are used in the
                    manufactory of soap</p>
                <p>The <persName ref="pe1433">Duke of Argyle's</persName> farms here are all let
                    with the <add place="above">portion of</add> Shore adjoining them. They are
                    generally let low and are not above £20 a year. We embarked at 9 and set off
                    with a very <unclear reason="illegible">favourable</unclear>
                    <pb n="f.38r"/> haze. On the right parallel horizontal rocky strata; farther on
                    a few rough columns appeared. Came to the Island of <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" quantity="1"/><note type="editorial"><placeName ref="pl2201">Eorsa</placeName></note> at the mouth of <placeName ref="pl1079">Loch
                        na Keal</placeName> and soon afterwards began to coast along <placeName ref="pl1078">Ulva</placeName>, where we saw the House of <persName ref="pe1496">Macdonald of Staffa</persName>, and soon afterwards had a view
                    of <persName ref="pe1497">Miss Clephane's</persName>
                    <persName ref="pe1498">L<hi rend="superscript">y.</hi> Compton's</persName>
                    mother in a distant part of <placeName ref="pl0729">Mull</placeName>. The wind
                    being so favourable our boatmen had no trouble in rowing and became merry and
                    sang songs. We were particularly pleased with "Hatyin foam eri" mentioned in
                    Johnson's tour.<note type="editorial">Boswell records that during a voyage by
                        rowing boat to the island of Raasay, their pilot Malcom MacLeod 'raised an
                        Erse song, Hatyin foam foam eri'. Ronald Black writes "Hatyin foam eri' is
                        'Tha Tighinn Fodham Éirigh' ('I am Minded to Rise'), a well-known song of
                        which various translations exist.' Samuel Johnson and James Boswell, <hi rend="italic">To the Hebrides: Samuel Johnson's Journey to the Western
                            Islands of Scotland and James Boswell's Journal of a Tour to the
                            Hebrides</hi>, ed. by Ronald Black (Edinburgh: Birlinn, 2007), p.148,
                        p.317n.</note> We had now the Island <pb n="f.38v"/> of <placeName ref="pl0649">Colonsay</placeName> on our left, and soon after came to <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" atLeast="1"/><note type="editorial"><placeName ref="pl2202">Gometra</placeName>.</note> on our right an
                    Island separated from <placeName ref="pl1078">Ulva</placeName> by a narrow
                    strait. Here we perceived an eagle standing boldly on a perpendicular cliff, we
                    passed close by it, but it kept it's station without taking any notice of us. We
                    now had <placeName ref="pl0652">Staffa</placeName> full in view, the waves grew
                    very rough as we got into a more open sea. at one we reached this extraordinary
                    Island and landed at <placeName ref="pl1088">Clamshell cave</placeName> where we
                    sketched and then walked round the Southern point to <placeName ref="pl1082">Fingal's cave</placeName> over the tops of columns. We were not <pb n="f.39r"/> the least disappointed in this wonderful place, after admiring
                    the view from the entrance we walked along a ledge of broken columns to the
                    farther end; there is one awkward gap here where you are obliged to make an
                    awkward side leap and a false step would send you reeling into the water beneath
                    which is many feet deep. The water was now very calm as the wind was from the
                    North, and we perceived a pink tint over the rocks which lay under it. The roof
                    is arched and formed of perpendicular columns broken off. Some green appeared
                    between the crevices of the columns. While we were standing here the boat rowed
                    in and our piper struck up but the pipes made too great a noise from the
                    loudness of the echo. A flute answers better. It's proper name is the melodious
                        cave.<note type="editorial">The volcanologist Barthélemy Faujas de
                        Saint-Fond visited Staffa in 1784 and argued that Joseph Banks's 1772
                        identification of the cave as 'Fingal's' stemmed from a mistranslation of
                        the similar-sounding Gaelic name for 'melodious cave'. See Nigel Leask,
                        'Fingalian Topographies: Ossian and the Highland Tour, 1760-1805' <hi rend="italic">Journal for Eighteenth‐Century Studies</hi>, 39 (2016),
                        183-196, p.185.</note> There are a number of large anemonies and jelly fish
                    floating about in the water here. We descended to the boat and rowed out of the
                    cave to the South West where the view of the pillars and caves is most
                    magnificent. Next to <placeName ref="pl1082">Fingals</placeName> comes the
                        <placeName ref="pl1087">Boat cave</placeName> and then <placeName ref="pl1089">Cormorant's</placeName>. The base of the Island is a rocky
                    ledge in which are placed a line of pillars in oblique direction and intersected
                    by these caves. In this part they are about 50 feet high and above them is a
                    large mass also composed of pillars but comparatively very small imperfectly
                    formed and lying across one another in all directions. above this curious mass
                    is fine verdant pasture. The northern part of the Island is not <sic>to</sic>
                    high and has two rows of <add place="above">small</add> columns one above the
                    other. The pillars on the outside of <placeName ref="pl1082">Fingal's
                        cave</placeName> on the South side are bent in at the top as if sinking
                    under the pressure of the weight above them. In one place we observed serpentine
                    pillars. Having <unclear reason="illegible">repassed</unclear>
                    <placeName ref="pl1088">Clamshell cave</placeName> we landed and walked up to
                    the
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="Alexander Deans" timestamp="20180918T140904+0100" comment="missing page break?
"?>top
                    of the Island where we spread a cloth on the turf and ate our dinner. Columns
                    protrude their heads everywhere. A Shepherd the father of one of our boatmen
                    once lived here, but he has left it and no traces of any habitation are to be
                    seen. at present about 1<?oxy_comment_end?>5 cows and a few sheep pasture here.
                    We walked to the highest point of the Island and had a fine <pb n="f.39v"/> view
                    on all sides. To the North <placeName ref="pl0718">Rum</placeName> and very
                    distant <placeName ref="pl0715">Skye</placeName>. To the west a number of small
                    Islands some quite flat with low cliffs, one with a hump sticking up in the
                    middle called the <placeName ref="pl1086">Dutchman's cap</placeName>, and more
                    distant <placeName ref="pl0896">Coll</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl0974">Tiree</placeName>; South <placeName ref="pl0651">Iona</placeName> and it's
                        <placeName ref="pl0978">Cathedral</placeName> with the <placeName ref="pl0639">Paps</placeName> of <placeName ref="pl0716">Jura</placeName>
                    seen faintly in the distance; to the East we had <placeName ref="pl1078">Ulva</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl0729">Mull</placeName>. After
                    having devoted two hours and a half to <placeName ref="pl0652">Staffa</placeName> which we saw in great perfection from the fineness of
                    the day we reembarked and had an equally favourable <pb n="f.40r"/> breeze to
                    carry us back. In our way we observed at some distance <placeName ref="pl2203">Mackinnon's cave</placeName> in the <placeName ref="pl0729">Mull</placeName> coast opposite <placeName ref="pl1078">Ulva</placeName>.
                    Our boatmen again entertained us with singing and the piper played in his turn.
                    To give proper effect to the chorusses of Gaelic songs they each take hold of
                    the corner of a handkerchief and pull it up and down in proper time. They talked
                    of whales and seals frequenting these coasts but we saw none. They believed in
                    second sight, which they believe a person to be born with, but that the faculty
                    is not developed <pb n="f.40v"/> 'till they are grown up. <placeName ref="pl0652">Staffa</placeName> has not been discovered above 50 years.<note type="editorial">A reference to Joseph Banks's description of the island in
                        the journal of his voyage to Iceland in 1772, printed in Thomas Pennant, <hi rend="italic">A Tour in Scotland and Voyage to the Hebrides 1772</hi>
                        (Chester: 1774), pp.299-309. </note> The heights of <placeName ref="pl2198">Benmore</placeName> looked fine rising in the evening sky. We reached
                        <placeName ref="pl2199">Knock</placeName> before six. <persName ref="pe1438">Col. Campbell</persName> entertained us in the evening with some of the
                    natural history of the Island. He has caught 100 salmon in a day in the river
                    above his house, but they have now much fallen off in number, owing to the
                    sheepwashings, steam boats, and use of lime. The grouse are very much destroyed
                    by the eagles and the grey crows who eat the eggs and also the young <pb n="f.41r"/> grouse; their numbers are also diminished by the heather being
                    burnt to increase the pasture for sheep. The Ptarmigan which are grey in summer
                    turn white in winter; and the hares undergo the same change; foxes there are
                    none. The Eagles also feed on young lambs, some of them are as large as 10 feet
                    from wing to wing. There has been a fine herring fishery here this year; the
                    fisheries established in the North of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> for the employment of the natives succeed in general
                    very well. There are many red deer <pb n="f.41v"/> which are driven out of the
                    copses by dogs and shot at as they rush out; they may be killed at 100 yd<hi rend="superscript">s.</hi> distance, but sometimes run on a long time after
                    they have several balls in them. The bark of the Birch is used for charcoal and
                    yields £20 p<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> tun; the oak is cut every 10 years —
                    from the facility of procuring this the <placeName ref="pl1249">Lorn
                        works</placeName> are established on <placeName ref="pl1075">Loch
                        Etive</placeName>; the iron being bought from <placeName ref="pl1044">Lancashire</placeName>. <persName ref="pe1438">Co. Campbell</persName>
                    spoke much in praise of the <persName ref="pe1433">Duke of Argyle</persName>
                    whose pensions to poor <pb n="f.42r"/> people amount to £1600 a year when his
                    creditors wanted him to make some reduction on this head he said he would sooner
                    make a reduction in any other expence. The <persName ref="pe0086">old
                        Duke</persName> used to make the Innkeepers keep Post Horses. The population
                    of the Island is about 8000 and there are 30 Schools in it — the people are
                    averse to begging and scrape up 9 or 10 pounds to leave behind them for their
                    funeral when a grand fête takes place. <persName ref="pe1438">Col.
                        Campbell</persName> recollects an old man who used to chaunt <pb n="f.42v"/>
                    <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian's</persName> poems in Gaelic. The <placeName ref="pl2204">Caledonian canal</placeName> is entirely conducted and paid for
                    by Government; but is said not to be very likely to succeed. The Navigation of
                    the Lochs is difficult on account of the contending eddies of wind. The Canal
                    will be large enough to admit frigates. <persName ref="pe1501">Maria</persName>
                    had two of the women servants up after supper who sung some plaintive Gaelic
                    airs with great Effect.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.43r"/> Sep. 11. At 10 we took leave of our kind friends who supplied us
                    with horses to carry us to <placeName ref="pl0682">Aross</placeName> where we
                    arrived at ½ past 11. and found the cutter waiting for us. We did not get under
                    way till 1. Coasted along the <placeName ref="pl0680">ardnamurchan</placeName>
                    mountains with <placeName ref="pl2196">Ardtornish castle</placeName> on the left
                    — afterwards passed <placeName ref="pl0684">Dewart</placeName> on the r<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> and <placeName ref="pl2205">the lady's
                        rock</placeName>. From this point we had a fine view up <placeName ref="pl2190">Loch Linnhe</placeName> the mountain forms being excessively
                    grand and <placeName ref="pl2206">Ben-nevis</placeName> in the background.
                    Having passed the <placeName ref="pl0688">Island of <pb n="f.43v"/>
                        Lismore</placeName> we saw <placeName ref="pl2207">Loch Nell bay</placeName>
                    to the North of <placeName ref="pl0686">Connel ferry</placeName> where there has
                    been the greatest draught of herrings this year. A favourable breeze bought us
                    to <placeName ref="pl1076">Oban</placeName> at 5. We left it at 6 and had a fine
                    sunset ride to <placeName ref="pl0686">Connel ferry</placeName> which we crossed
                    ourselves but as it was growing dark I left <persName ref="pe1505">William</persName> with the carriage to come over in the morning. The
                        <placeName ref="pl2208">Inn</placeName> is close to the opposite shore and
                    we reached it at half past 7. it is very clean and we found civil people and
                    excellent accommodation.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.44r"/> Sep. 11.<add place="above"><handShift/>12</add><handShift/>A
                    heavenly morning. The carriage was safely ferried over at 7; we had it opened
                    and proceeded under some cliffs with the bay, promontory, lighthouse, and
                    mansion of <placeName ref="pl0987">Loch Nell</placeName> — <persName ref="pe1440">Gen<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> Campbell's</persName> on our
                    left. Soon after we arrived on the banks of <placeName ref="pl2209">Loch
                        Curan</placeName> the ferry is called <placeName ref="pl2210">Shean</placeName>. While the boat was coming over from the opposite side I
                    walked along a reef of rocks projecting into the Loch where I found a number of
                    shells anemonies and marine <pb n="f.44v"/> productions. The ferry is about ½ a
                    mile across. On landing we entered a pretty wood and descending again as we
                    emerged from it we perceived a small bay with a Gothic house on a hill opposite
                    called <placeName ref="pl2211">Loch Eil house</placeName>. At the mouth of the
                    bay is the picturesque <placeName ref="pl0689">tower of <unclear reason="illegible">Stacha</unclear></placeName> on an Island and fine
                    mountains behind on the other side of <placeName ref="pl2190">Loch
                        Linnhe</placeName>. The postillion here made a mistake and went strait
                    instead of going up to the house. We met two fishermen who informed us of our
                    error and <pb n="f.45r"/> conducted us across the sands of the bay which were
                    safe enough to cross the tide being out and we arrived at <placeName ref="pl2212">Portnacrosh</placeName> entering it by a fine line of beach. It
                    is a neat white village. Ascended a hill and came to the plantations of
                        <placeName ref="pl2213">Appin House</placeName> which rise up a bold bank
                    the trees of all kinds about 50y<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> old and very
                    thriving tho' close to this arm of the sea. The house is white and square and
                    stands on a green eminence. The road now winds close to the margin of the Loch
                    and <placeName ref="pl2206">Ben-nevis</placeName> appears in the distance.<pb n="f.45v"/> We turned off at <placeName ref="pl2214">Kiel</placeName> where
                    a promontory interposes itself between the road and the sea and met it again at
                        <placeName ref="pl2215">Loch Leven</placeName>. Opposite this point is
                        <placeName ref="pl2216">Ardgoar</placeName>, consisting of fine plantations
                    and a white house standing on a flat sloping gently to the water, and tucked by
                    Lofty hills in which there is a gap to the left and a glen opening to <placeName ref="pl2217">Loch Sunart</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl2218">Strontian</placeName>. The lake narrows and fine rugged mountain forms with
                    some wood upon them present themselves as you approach <placeName ref="pl2219">Ballyhulish</placeName>. Here is another <pb n="f.46r"/> ferry about a
                    furlong across; the boat is very small and bad and the boatmen were so drunk
                    that I though the carriage w<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> have been overturned
                    into the water. Some people with a number of cows went over before us. There is
                    an Inn on each side but the opposite kept by <persName ref="pe1441">Cameron</persName> is much the best where we got luncheon. We were just
                    setting off again at 6 when we saw the owner of the ferry boat suddenly strip
                    himself and plunge into <pb n="f.46v"/> the water as the drunkards had forgot to
                    fasten it to the shore and it was drifting down with the tide, but he being
                    drunk himself had not strength to get to it and was carried some way down the
                    stream himself and some fears were entertained for his safety and a boat sent
                    after him, but at length he reached the opposite shore in safety tho' without
                    accomplishing his object. A most brilliant sunset lighted us on our departure
                    from <pb n="f.47r"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl2219">Ballyhulish</placeName> and shed purple and lilac tints
                    over the mountains. passed a slate quarry with iron railways and waggons. A
                    number of cottages many of them turf. Receded from the Loch and met it again at
                        <placeName ref="pl2317">Coran Ferry</placeName> where we sh<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> have crossed over to <placeName ref="pl2216">Ardgoar</placeName> had <persName ref="pe1499">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Maclean</persName> been at home. The road now goes close to the
                    Loch built up in many places, sometimes along steep precipices but in general
                    narrow but as <pb n="f.47v"/> good as possible. As we crossed a bridge and
                    looked up a Glen to our right we descried <placeName ref="pl2206">Ben
                        Nevis</placeName>. Fine starlight and moon rising lovelily from behind a
                    mountain. Boats here and there in the loch*<note type="authorial">* The
                        fishermen today told me they had caught a barrel full sometimes they catch 7
                        or 8 barrels — at <placeName ref="pl2219">Ballyhulish</placeName> some boats
                        came in loaded which they c<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> not get sale for.
                        You may buy a barrel for 7<hi rend="superscript">S.</hi> –––––</note> — many
                    people out at their doors and walking as in a fine evening in <placeName ref="pl1164">Italy</placeName>. Reached <placeName ref="pl0206">Fort W<hi rend="superscript">m.</hi></placeName> at 9. and found the best Inn
                    full, we got taken <add place="above">in</add> at the other end of the town
                    close to the <placeName ref="pl2220">fort</placeName>.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.48r"/> Sep. 13. This Inn is very dirty but the situation is pretty; it
                    stands at one end of the village which consists of a longish street of white
                    houses neat for <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> — the backs of one
                    side of them look to the beach. To the right we had a view of a new Episcopalian
                        <add place="above">church</add> erected close by, with hills rising behind
                    it. In front is the <placeName ref="pl2220">fort</placeName> which is small but
                    has a moat bastions &amp;c; and governor's house, <unclear reason="illegible">storerooms</unclear> &amp;c inside. The English banner waves over all; and
                    the lake washes one side of the walls. Beyond the <placeName ref="pl2220">fort</placeName> are seen the Loch and mountains. The <pb n="f.48v"/>
                    <hi rend="underline">village</hi> is properly called <placeName ref="pl0206">Gordonsburgh</placeName> as it pays some dues to the <persName ref="pe1442">D. of Gordon</persName> tho' formerly it was called <placeName ref="pl0206">Mary's burgh</placeName> from having portions of land granted out at a low
                    rate by <persName ref="pe1443">Q. Mary</persName>. The houses have some of them
                    picturesque staircases in front with iron balestrades. There was no service in
                    the Protestant Church to day, in the Presbyterian they had Gaelic service at 12
                    and English at 2. We therefore set off in a boat rowed by 4 boys at 11 to go
                    across the bay to visit the <placeName ref="pl2204">Caledonian Canal</placeName>
                    which <pb n="f.49r"/><unclear reason="illegible">debranches</unclear> at a
                    village called <placeName ref="pl2221">Corpach</placeName>. As we rowed over,
                        <placeName ref="pl2206">Bennevis</placeName> opened upon us, very rugged and
                    grand but with not so fine an outline as I had expected, the top is flat. At the
                    mouth of the Canal is an engine house. You first come to a floodgate 20 feet
                    high and afterwards pass several others; the locks are well lined with stone and
                    the gates are built in the most solid manner. We walked on about a mile to see
                    eight locks which are close to each other and are called <placeName ref="pl2222">Neptune's Staircase</placeName>.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.49v"/> They cost £50,000. This end of the Canal extending from
                        <placeName ref="pl0830">Loch Eil</placeName> (the branch of <placeName ref="pl2190">Loch Linnhe</placeName> into which it runs) to <placeName ref="pl0198">Fort Augustus</placeName> is finished except a little bit which
                    is sufficient to prevent the water coming in for the present. The <placeName ref="pl2223">Lochy River</placeName> runs all the way to the east of it and
                    it crosses the river by a small aqueduct. The banks are very high and planted
                    with different forest trees and quicks<gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" atLeast="1" atMost="3"/> at the top. From <placeName ref="pl0156">Inverness</placeName> to <pb n="f.50r"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0193">Loch Ness</placeName> is also finished and Ships can
                    come up from thence to <placeName ref="pl0198">Fort Augustus</placeName>. The
                    branch from <placeName ref="pl0198">F<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Aug<hi rend="superscript">s.</hi></placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0202">Loch
                        Lochy</placeName> thro' <placeName ref="pl0200">Loch Oichy</placeName>
                    remains to be done and will occupy two years more. We crossed the canal by one
                    of the floodgates which have causeways defended by iron balustrades at the top,
                    and returned on the other side to <placeName ref="pl2221">Corpach</placeName>
                    visiting in our way a turf cottage which seemed more comfortable than I expected
                    but it is not so warm as one built of stone. The people made us taste whiskey
                    sipping <pb n="f.50v"/> it first themselves. They wear here the Highland
                    costume; our Landlord was dressed in a splendid suit of it this morning. Barrels
                    hereabouts supply the place of chimneys. Near <placeName ref="pl2221">Corpach</placeName> is a pretty <placeName ref="pl2224">obelisk</placeName>
                    erected to <persName ref="pe1444">Col. Cameron</persName> who died at <placeName ref="pl2225">Waterloo</placeName>. On the hill above it is a pretty kirk. We
                    had hard pulling on leaving this place to get back to <placeName ref="pl0206">Fort William</placeName> as the wind was much against us being changed to
                    the West. We shipped several heavy seas and regained the <placeName ref="pl0206">Fort</placeName> at 2. We immediately hastened to Kirk which we found full
                    and service had just begun. Minister with a black tasselled gown praying in the
                    pulpit, clerk beneath, gallery round three sides of the building and pews
                    underneath with an aisle left in the middle. The text was Blessed are the
                    merciful; after the sermon came a prayer, then a Psalm after which boxes were
                    handed round for alms for the poor. The clergyman then pronounced a short <pb n="f.51r"/> dismissal. At half past three we set off, and not having time to
                    go farther Northward we were obliged to retrace our steps back to <placeName ref="pl0206">Ballyhulish</placeName>. Some boys followed the carriage whom I
                    caught making a hole in the Postillion's sack tied behind and stealing beans out
                    of it. Passed a tent pitched by some people while their house was pulled down
                    and rebuilt. This being Sunday the people looked as clean as in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> and were standing at their doors with their
                    families. Rain now came <pb n="f.51v"/> on and lasted all the way to <placeName ref="pl0206">Ballyhulish</placeName> were we arrived at 6 and found good
                    accommodation at the <placeName ref="pl2226">Inn North of the Ferry</placeName>,
                    which was provided with coals, a coach house and –––––</p>
                <p>Sep. 14. Rain early. The people on the opposite bank were very lazy and we could
                    not get the carriage over till 9, when we were going to cross ourselves but the
                    landlord <persName ref="pe1441">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Cameron</persName> proposed our going to see some falls at the head of
                        <placeName ref="pl2215">Loch Leven</placeName> 9 miles off — as <pb n="f.52r"/> the clouds were clearing we agreed to go — and having got two
                    good rowers we proceeded up towards <placeName ref="pl2227">Glencoe</placeName>,
                    and passed the <placeName ref="pl2228">Island of S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi>
                        Mungo</placeName> with the small remains of a kirk on it. This S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> was originally a rotter but ended in becoming
                    good and building 7 Churches. We saw a good many seals who followed the boat and
                    had black heads shaped like dogs but a good deal larger they sometimes are seen
                    in great numbers bathing <pb n="f.52v"/> on the rocky Island here. They
                    sometimes catch them in nets made of Whipcord the meshes of which are three
                    inches square. Just where the <placeName ref="pl2229">Coe</placeName> flows into
                    the loch is the pretty house and plantations of a laird; the right bank of the
                    loch is <placeName ref="pl0818">argyllshire</placeName> the left <placeName ref="pl2230">Inverness</placeName>. Tide against us but wind in our favor.
                    Before reaching <placeName ref="pl2227">Glencoe</placeName> are slate quarries —
                    private property. The people who work them get 12<hi rend="superscript">s.</hi>
                    a week; the slates are about 12.<hi rend="superscript">s.</hi> a 1000; few of
                    the cottages however are slated. Here is a school established by the society in
                        <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName>, but the parents of all
                    (except those who are absolute paupers) pay something for their education. about
                    1/6 a year for reading alone, and more for the other branches. One of the
                    boatmen said he rented about 5 acres of <persName ref="pe1445">Col.
                        Cameron</persName> the Laird on the <placeName ref="pl2230">Inverness</placeName> side, and said he had not has such a crop for 20
                    years. On the left is <pb n="f.53r"/> a very noble mountain with trees spreading
                    up it to a great height and birches shooting out of the crags below. Fine tints
                    of fern and heath on the mountains to the right. Hard pulling as we passed the
                    narrow part of the lake. At length we disembarked on the left side and walked up
                    to a waterfall called <placeName ref="pl2231">Eisnathic or the Fall of the
                        Serpent</placeName>. Here is a curious rocky arch overhanging the river as
                    it falls and a little below the water has forced its way thro' a rock and pours
                    thro' a round hole in the middle of it. Rowing on from hence quite to the top of
                    the Loch, we stopped again to see the fall of another river which falls between
                    45 50 feet between very fine slats of rock with much wood about it.<note type="editorial">Possibly the <placeName ref="pl2232">Grey Mare's
                            Tail</placeName> near Kinlochmore.</note> The water tumbles in an
                    oblique direction and it is a most picturesque scene. At <placeName ref="pl2233">Kinlochmore</placeName> a little beyond are the shooting boxes of <persName ref="pe1446">Sir W. Cunningham</persName> and another Squire. On the hills
                    on the South Side of the Loch are red deer which become lighter in winter. They
                    never attack people. There is much grouse here <pb n="f.53v"/> and our boatmen
                    informed us that the Gamekeeper at the <placeName ref="pl0209">Black
                        Mountain</placeName> was in the habit of selling days of shooting to
                    travellers. As we came back the tide turned and we had much hard pulling to
                        <placeName ref="pl2227">Glencoe</placeName> which we reached at 4. We
                    changed our clothes at a cottage and then wound thro' the famous valley; the
                    blackness and perpendicularity of the crags and the gloominess of the scenery is
                    beyond every thing I have seen in my home travels. After a steep ascent <add place="above">of 4 miles</add> we at length reached the head of the Glen
                    where <pb n="f.54r"/> the road turns, but we still went thro' very wild tho'
                    less striking scenery, passing on our left the mountain called the <placeName ref="pl2234">Devil's staircase</placeName> over which went the old road to
                        <placeName ref="pl0206">Fort William</placeName>. As it grew dark we
                    descended to <placeName ref="pl0210">King's House</placeName> which we reached a
                    little before 8.</p>
                <p>Sep. 15. <placeName ref="pl0210">The Inn</placeName> here is slated and has two
                    floors but is comfortless enough and has beds stuffed into the sitting rooms. We
                    however got some good grouse. The House stands in a dreary moor with a <pb n="f.54v"/> semicircle of rugged mountains to the West and North. We got off
                    early and wound round the <placeName ref="pl0209">Black mountain</placeName>
                    where I perceived some snow. Much rain. Discerned in the distance the forms of
                    the <placeName ref="pl1166">Grampians</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl1167">Benledi</placeName>. Descended and crossed the <placeName ref="pl2235">water of Bae</placeName> w<hi rend="superscript">h.</hi> falls into
                        <placeName ref="pl2236">Lochbydoch</placeName> w<hi rend="superscript">h.</hi> we saw to our left, and beyond it is <placeName ref="pl0814">Loch
                        Rannoch</placeName>. Came in sight of <placeName ref="pl0211">Loch
                        Tilly</placeName> and soon after arrived at <placeName ref="pl2237">Inverounan</placeName> a single house thatched, and with only a ground
                    floor. Got some good boiled trout for breakfast. A very large rough greyhound
                    kept us company all the while</p>
                <p><pb n="f.55r"/> Leaving this place we ascended thro' firs, and had a long pull up
                    a mountainous tract; skirted along the base of <placeName ref="pl2238">Bendoran</placeName> and descended to <placeName ref="pl0212">Tyndrum</placeName>. Saw <placeName ref="pl0815">Benmore</placeName> with
                        <hi rend="underline">young</hi> snow upon it. Reached the <placeName ref="pl2107">Inn</placeName> at 1. and staid there 2 hours and a half to
                    bait. In the hall are some stuffed animals caught here a wolf, a large mountain
                    cat and a <unclear reason="illegible">forrest</unclear>. Got a parcel containing
                    some books we had left behind us at <placeName ref="pl1072">Inverary</placeName>. Leaving <placeName ref="pl0212">Tyndrum</placeName> we
                    came to <placeName ref="pl0817">Loch Dochart</placeName> in which <pb n="f.55v"/> is a pretty island with a <placeName ref="pl2239">castle</placeName>. We
                    reached <placeName ref="pl1121">Luib</placeName> at 1/2 past 6. and found a good
                    Inn, where we got an excellent supper of mutton, chickens, pancakes rice
                    pudding, eggs, cauliflower &amp;c &amp;c. A noisy Irishman and his wife who
                    almost came to blows began to annoy us with their clamour about bed time, but
                    were soon overawed by the peacable of the house. He was driving some poneys to
                        <persName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</persName>, and I found he was the man I
                    had seen at <placeName ref="pl2226">Ballyhulish</placeName>
                    <pb n="f.56r"/> threatening to pull <persName ref="pe1441">Cameron's</persName>
                    roof off his house if he did not get them ferried over immediately.</p>
                <p>Sep. 16. Set off at ¼ to 7. and came in sight of <placeName ref="pl2240">Benlawers</placeName>, descended to <placeName ref="pl0277">Killin</placeName> — the approach to it is wonderfully romantic. Stopped at
                        <placeName ref="pl2106">Cameron's Inn</placeName> to breakfast the kirk is
                    hard by, on the other side of the Inn is the burying ground, close under which
                    rolls the <del rend="overstrike"><placeName ref="pl0096">Tay</placeName></del>
                    <add place="above"><placeName ref="pl1003">Lochy</placeName></add> which we
                    crossed after breakfast in walking to <placeName ref="pl2241">Lord Breadalbane's
                        burying place</placeName>, all his family are buried here. and according to
                    our guide he is presbyterian <pb n="f.56v"/> and no funeral service is performed
                    here. The <placeName ref="pl2241">Mausoleum</placeName> is plain and handsome
                    and is overshadowed by a gigantic sycamore. The <placeName ref="pl0999">old
                        Castle <unclear reason="illegible">Finlaric</unclear></placeName> is close
                    to it. Thro' the trees is a beautiful peep of the vale and of a village of
                        <placeName ref="pe1375">Lord B's</placeName> on the opposite side of the
                    river. We stopped at <persName ref="pe1447">M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>Alpine</persName> the pearl merchants<note type="editorial">In a
                        letter to Thomas Pennant on <ref target="0432.xml">April 7 1774</ref>, John
                        Stuart of Killin wrote that the River Dochart 'a few years ago answered
                        better for pearl-fishing than perhaps any other in the Highlands. Some of
                        the largest and best were found in it, and sold mostly to merchants in
                        Perth.'</note> as we left the village, passed the <placeName ref="pl2242">burying place of the M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>Nabs</placeName> and
                    then ascended thro woods and passed close to <placeName ref="pl1001">Lord B's
                        romantic villa</placeName>. Passed people reaping — very fine crops and <pb n="f.57r"/> a great deal cut. the harvest has not been so fine for 20 years.
                    This time last year it was all green. The opposite banks of the Loch are as much
                    cultivated and the inclosures reach a good way up the side of <placeName ref="pl2240">Benlawers</placeName>. Much flax lying to dry. Good crops of
                    potatoes &amp; turnips. Stopped at <placeName ref="pl2105">Acharn</placeName>
                    where there was but a small stream dripping over the large slab of rock. In
                        <placeName ref="pl1122">the Hermitage</placeName> are some good stuffed
                    animals and a white fox from <unclear><placeName ref="pl2243">Lochabber</placeName></unclear>. Many wild cats are here caught <pb n="f.57v"/> in traps. They do not attack man unless provoked. They live a
                    great deal on game. The approach to <placeName ref="pl0103">Kenmore</placeName>
                    is very pretty, on each side are heights covered with fir and in the valley
                    between the summit of <placeName ref="pl0101">Taymouth Castle</placeName> is
                    seen rising out of wood. The stone walls are topped with a neat turf coping.
                        <placeName ref="pl0103">Kenmore</placeName> is a neat white village standing
                    on a knoll with half a dozen small houses on each side of a green; the church at
                    one end and <persName ref="pe1375">B's</persName> Park <pb n="f.58r"/> gate at
                    the other. Below the church and almost washed by the lake stands the schoolhouse
                    a picturesque building with two fine sycamores uniting their branches over it.
                    Walked down to the Bridge close on the other side of which is the Kitchen garden
                    and a long line of glass with an elegant Gothic entrance. Having got the
                    gardiner to come to us we entered the Park and walked up to a knoll whence we
                    had a fine view of the lake just as the sun was gone down, every <pb n="f.58v"/>
                    thing looking very clear. <placeName ref="pl2240">Benlawers</placeName> has
                    still some of last year's snow upon it which is very extraordinary after the
                    heat of the present summer; but it was much deeper than usual last winter. They
                    had snow 30 feet deep in the hills by <placeName ref="pl2105">Acharn</placeName>
                    and some in the valleys even in May. Descending we entered a grass walk as
                    smooth as <unclear reason="illegible">a velvet</unclear> between fine beaches
                    with the river murmuring on our left. The walks here are all grass and are mown
                    every week and swept every <pb n="f.59r"/> other day. The park railing is very
                    heavy and it is to be hoped will be altered. The park contains red as well as
                    fallow deer but they are kept separate. The Hills on the left have six square
                    miles of planting on them. This was done by the <persName ref="pe0036">late
                        Earl</persName> and took 16 millions of trees. More than this quantity is
                    planted on the opposite bank. <persName ref="pe1375">Lord B.</persName> plants
                    annually employing as many hands as he can get. He can go 105 miles along his
                    property which takes in all <placeName ref="pl0104">Loch Tay</placeName> &amp;
                        <placeName ref="pl0299">Loch Earne</placeName>
                    <pb n="f.59v"/> and great part of <placeName ref="pl0269">Loch Awe</placeName>
                    and reaches nearly as far as <placeName ref="pl1072">Inverary</placeName>. He
                    has 1700 families who pay rent and in the Irish Rebellion raised without
                    difficulty three battalions of 700 men each. We went up to the house which has
                    three stories besides the basement one. The two upper ones are all bedrooms.
                    Round the basement runs an arcade which is to connect the wings with the body of
                    the house, the ground for the latter is staked out and they will be begun
                    immediately. In front of the <pb n="f.60r"/> house is an ample flat lawn beyond
                    which are woody heights on which is a fort with a battery of 34 Guns. Two of
                    them are 24 pounders. The drawing room occupies the whole length of the front
                    taking in five windows and seems a delightful room. We looked into the hall and
                    staircase which was just lighted by two magnificent candelabras and looked
                    beautifully light and airy. In it are two <rs ref="ar0276">busts of George
                        III</rs> and <rs ref="ar0277">William III</rs>. The house has <pb n="f.60v"/> been finished six years.</p>
                <p>We went down a lime avenue a quarter of a mile beyond then wound round to the
                        <placeName ref="pl2103">Chinese bridge</placeName> which we crossed and
                    returned by a broad green walk to the bridge at <placeName ref="pl0103">Kenmore</placeName>. The entrance for carriages is near the Fort, and when
                    guests arrive a bugle is sounded which echoes finely. <persName ref="pe1375">Lord B.</persName> also keeps a piper and a band of wind instruments. The
                    patches of land I observed in <placeName ref="pl2240">Benlawers</placeName> this
                    morning inclosed by stone walls are each of them let to a small <pb n="f.61r"/>
                    tenant. <persName ref="pe1448">Lord Glenorchy</persName> came of age last year
                    when they had rejoicings for 7 days. They had the <persName ref="pe1449">Russian
                        Duke</persName> here the other day when a royal Salute was fired from the
                    Battery. There is a school of 150 children at the village kept by <persName ref="pe1450">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Armstrong</persName>; he
                    receives £30 a year from the Highland Society and the rest of his emolument is
                    made up by quarter pence. The children pay for reading and writing 3<hi rend="superscript">s.</hi> a year for Latin 6<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>
                    and many learn latin and Greek. Both boys and girls are taught here; the girls
                    learn needlework at other small schools. There is no Sunday School, but they are
                    all taken to Kirk by their Parents. The <unclear reason="illegible">bridge</unclear> built here was all at the expence of the <persName ref="pe0036">late Earl</persName> except £1000 4/<hi rend="superscript">6.</hi> was paid by Government. The <persName ref="pe1375">present
                        Lord</persName> is s<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> to distribute £2000
                    annually among the poor and gave £500 on his son's coming of age. The family
                    generally stay here from July to January. Tomorrow <pb n="f.61v"/> a market is
                    expected here for cattle, butter, cheese wool &amp;c — We our reached auberge at
                    8. after a delightful walk.</p>
                <p>Sep. 17. Our Inn here was the <placeName ref="pl2104">Breadalbane
                        arms</placeName> the crest of which is a Boar's head and the motto "Follow
                    me." The only shops in the place are a Baker's, Haberdasher's, and Watchmaker's.
                    We got up early and found the green crowded with pedlars and other people
                    putting up their booths. Sketched the school house while the horses were getting
                    ready and then took <pb n="f.62r"/> the road to <placeName ref="pl0099">Dunkeld</placeName> which goes on the South Side of the <placeName ref="pl0096">Tay</placeName> and is very Superior to the other w<hi rend="superscript">h.</hi> is rather less hilly.</p>
                <p>We ascended a steep hill and stopped at the foot in front of which are two lines
                    of guns on a smooth lawn. Hence is a magnificent view of the <placeName ref="pl0101">Castle</placeName>, woods &amp; Loch. Beneath us we saw the
                    grooms bringing round the shooting poneys to the door. The sweep of the
                        <placeName ref="pl0096">Tay</placeName> seen from hence is also very fine.
                        <pb n="f.62v"/> A little further on we came to the Porter's Lodge which is
                    handsome Gothic and irregular. The park wall has a coping of schist built in the
                    form of battlements w<hi rend="superscript">h.</hi> has a good effect.<note type="authorial">The description of the park wall is accompanied by a small
                        ink sketch showing its crenellated top.</note> Soon after we came to a
                        <placeName ref="pl0102">Druidical temple</placeName> on the right consisting
                    of three circles of stones the largest of which is 50f<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> in ,<choice>
                        <abbr>Diam<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>Diameter</expan>
                    </choice> Descended to the <placeName ref="pl0096">Tay</placeName>; <placeName ref="pl2244">Castle Menzies</placeName> on the opposite bank an old
                    turretted house belonging to <placeName ref="pe1451">Sir O Neil
                        Menzies</placeName> who has <pb n="f.63r"/> an estate of 5 or 6000 a year
                    here. <placeName ref="pl0102">Gen. Wade's Bridge</placeName> on the left. Got to
                        <placeName ref="pl1124">Aberfeldy</placeName> at 1/2 past <unclear reason="illegible">11</unclear>. The Muslin manufactories there are broken
                    up. There are a number of Inns. The maid who waited on us at breakfast has "sair
                    e'en" and wore a necklace made of Druidical beads which are sometimes picked up
                    in this neighbourhood as a charm to cure them. We walked afterwards to the
                        <placeName ref="pl0280">falls of the Moness</placeName> where there <pb n="f.63v"/> is but little water, but a fine glen and very high crags. The
                    Landlord of the <placeName ref="pl2245">Inn</placeName> told us that <persName ref="pe1375">Lord B.</persName> had £72000 a year, and that the land on
                        <placeName ref="pl2240">Benlawers</placeName> was let for £3 a Scotch acre.
                    This gentleman <add place="above">whose name was <persName ref="pe1452">M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>Naughton</persName></add> sported a
                    splendid escutcheon of his own, with stags for supporters, a castle for his
                    crest and "I hope in God" for his motto. Past <placeName ref="pl1124">Aberfeldie</placeName> the vale widens; there is much corn and most if cut.
                    Met a number of people <pb n="f.64r"/> going to <placeName ref="pl0103">Kenmore</placeName> market. Came to <placeName ref="pl2246">Grand
                        Tulloch</placeName> on the right a picturesque castle belonging to <persName ref="pe1453">Sir G. Stewart</persName>. Several villas on the opposite bank
                    all white with plantations stretching up the hills behind. This vale is very
                    much like the vale of the <placeName ref="pl0600">Clyde</placeName> between
                        <placeName ref="pl0590">Lanark</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl0597">Hamilton</placeName>, perhaps less rich &amp; more wild &amp; romantic.
                    Stopped a short time to bait at <placeName ref="pl2247">Balnaguard</placeName>
                    and then ascending a hill had a view of <placeName ref="pl0281">Logierait</placeName>
                    <pb n="f.64v"/> The <placeName ref="pl0283">Tumel</placeName> joining the
                        <placeName ref="pl0096">Tay</placeName> and the vale of the former river up
                    to <placeName ref="pl0112">Killicranky</placeName>. Here we turned our backs on
                    the romantic scenery which leads to <placeName ref="pl0110">Blair
                        Athol</placeName>, and the <placeName ref="pl0099">Dunkeld</placeName> woods
                    began to open in front. Passed several pretty places, particularly <placeName ref="pl2248">Kinnaird</placeName> with high crags behind and a view of the
                    vale in front. The wood becomes luxuriant as we descended lower into the valley.
                    Saw some stacks thatched with broom. Before <pb n="f.65r"/> reaching <placeName ref="pl0100">Inver</placeName> returned to the right and walked up a mile to
                    the <placeName ref="pl2094">Rumbling Brig</placeName>, where the fine cleft in
                    the rock and the impetuous pouring of the torrent called forth our admiration.
                    From the bridge is a distant view of the town of <placeName ref="pl2094">Dunkeld</placeName> — returned by path thro' larch wood 25 y<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> old and very tall for that age. Went along the
                    Banks of the <placeName ref="pl2095">Bran</placeName> where there is a seat with
                    a circle of Larches round it. <placeName ref="pl2249">Ossian's cave</placeName>
                    a small hollow formed <pb n="f.65v"/> by some pieces of rocks. Farther on is a
                    pretty little plot of ground ornamented with a great variety of different kinds
                    of heath. Came to <placeName ref="pl2093">Ossian's hall</placeName> where the
                    water pours down a large slap of rock in three parallel streams. We went from
                    hence thro' a nursery and into the great road which soon brought us to
                        <placeName ref="pl0100">Inver</placeName> where we met the carriage and soon
                    reached <placeName ref="pl0099">Dunkeld</placeName>. The woods and ways here
                    look as fine <pb n="f.66r"/> as ever. The South Side of the bridge was built on
                    dry land and the channel made under it for the river which before pressed too
                    close upon the town and overflowed it. The town is very neat and great part was
                    rebuilt by <persName ref="pe0548">the Duke</persName>. It is all of grey stone.
                    We immediately proceeded to make the tour of the <placeName ref="pl1127">Duke's
                        grounds</placeName>. The paddock extending from the house is nothing like so
                    large as the Park at <placeName ref="pl0101">Taymouth</placeName>. <pb n="f.66v"/> We descended by the flower garden filled with American plants which do not
                    thrive here to the river, where the view is most beautiful. <persName ref="pe0548">The Duke</persName> is now at <placeName ref="pl0110">Blair
                        Athol</placeName>, between w<hi rend="superscript">h.</hi> and <placeName ref="pl0099">Dunkeld</placeName> he spends all the time from June to Jan<hi rend="superscript">y.</hi> He has 100000 acres of wood some of w<hi rend="superscript">h.</hi> was planted by <persName ref="pe0087">the late
                        Duke</persName> but the greater part by him as he has been planting
                    constantly for the last 40 years. He has now <add place="above">been</add>
                    selling larches to Government for building frigates.<note type="editorial">Despite the duke's aspirations, only a single naval prototype was built
                        using Atholl larch. By 1818 the end of the Napoleonic wars and a plentiful
                        supply of timber from the empire rendered the Atholl plantations largely
                        redundant. See Fredrik Albritton Jonsson, <hi rend="italic">Enlightenment's
                            Frontier: The Scottish Highlands and the Origins of
                            Environmentalism</hi> (New Haven; London: Yale University Press, 2013),
                        pp.147-164</note> Here are some excessively fine firs and larches and among
                    the latter are the two first ever planted in <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> each containing about 200 solid feet of timber and 15
                    feet span at the bottom. A House has <add place="above">been</add> built close
                    to his own by <placeName ref="pe0548">the Duke</placeName> for his children's
                    Governess, which spoils his view very much and blocks up the ground between <del rend="overstrike">it</del>
                    <add place="above">him</add> and the river. The ferry where <pb n="f.67r"/>
                    people used formerly to cross the river was in the middle of the lower walk —
                    this was altered when the bridge was built and made to wind up the hill above
                    the town. The old ferry house still forms a picturesque object. Observed a
                    singular larch tree in which a branch had again grown into the trunk of the
                        tree<note type="editorial">At this point in the manuscript there is a simple
                        ink outline of the tree branch rejoining the trunk.</note></p>
                <p>The largest fish here are about 90 y<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> old. We got
                    in at ½ past 7. Soon after a stage came in w<hi rend="superscript">h.</hi> in
                    summer was 3 times a week from <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName> to
                        <placeName ref="pl0156">Inverness</placeName>. Took a moonlight walk in the
                        even<hi rend="superscript">g.</hi> below bridge down left bank of the river.
                        <pb n="f.67v"/> Sep 18. Fine morning — Breakfasted at ½ past 7 and went to
                    inspect the East end of the <placeName ref="pl2250">Cathedral</placeName> which
                        <persName ref="pe0548">the Duke</persName> is repairing assisted by
                    Government. It was fitted up some years ago as a church but in a poor miserable
                    style with common wooden windows. Stone window frames according to the old
                    design are now put and the inside is stoothed and stuccoed and has a groined
                    ceiling. The most eastern extremity where there is a <pb n="f.68r"/> large
                    window is parted off for the vestry, the church being quite large enough without
                    it. In the nave of the <placeName ref="pl2250">Cathedral</placeName> which is
                    unroofed is a pulpit from whence the sacrament is given once a year when this
                    ruinous pile is quite filled. At half past eight we crossed the bridge and bade
                    adieu to Highland Scenery; passed under <placeName ref="pl2251">Birnam
                        wood</placeName> — people quarrying and rolling stones down the hill to
                    build a wall at it's base. A road on the opposite <pb n="f.68v"/> side of the
                    river follows the windings of the <placeName ref="pl0096">Tay</placeName> to
                        <placeName ref="pl0094">Perth</placeName>. Ascending a hill we had a lovely
                    view of a bend of the <placeName ref="pl0096">Tay</placeName> it's course thro'
                    a rich vale with <placeName ref="pl2252">Murthly castle</placeName>, and the
                        <placeName ref="pl0812">Ochils</placeName> in the distance. <placeName ref="pl2253">Auchtergaven</placeName> is a thriving manufacturing village
                    with pink stone houses roofed with blue slate. Soon after passed a high pole
                    surmounted with a weather cock placed on a high mound in honor of it's being a
                    boundary of <persName ref="pe1454">Lord Lynedoch's</persName> estate to the
                    North. <placeName ref="pl2084">Extensive bleaching grounds</placeName>; <pb n="f.69r"/> crossed the <placeName ref="pl0306">almond</placeName>; Scone
                    opposite a handsome irregular pile of brown stone with many towers. There is a
                    fine strait approach to <placeName ref="pl0094">Perth</placeName> w<hi rend="superscript">h.</hi> is a very handsome town; the houses on the green
                    as you enter are extremely dashing with their stone pillars and ornaments. We
                    walked about the town and shopped there was a great bustle being a market day
                    and a number of Highland Soldiers with their music playing. We afterwards went
                    up to <placeName ref="pl0310">Kinnoul Hill</placeName>; the latter part of the
                    walk is thro' wood and very steep; when you emerge from this you stand at the
                    edge of a precipice 600 f<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi>
                    <choice>
                        <abbr>perp<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>perpendicular</expan>
                    </choice> and have a magnificent bird's eye view of the river and vessels below,
                    and of the <placeName ref="pl0812">Ochil</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl2254">Lomond Hills</placeName> in the distance. Got back at 1/2 past 2 — Lunched
                    and started again. We next passed some handsome barracks on entering the town
                    and on leaving it came to an immense and well <pb n="f.69v"/> constructed
                    building which was made for a <placeName ref="pl2255">depot for French
                        prisoners</placeName> and contained some thousands of them. It is now used
                    for stores. <placeName ref="pl0098">Dunsinane</placeName> we left far on our
                    left but perceived it's hill in the distance. There is a fine avenue to the town
                    on this side which puts one in mind of <placeName ref="pl0925">France</placeName>. Wound along the base of <placeName ref="pl0093">Moncrief</placeName> a fine ridge of wood and rocks — <placeName ref="pl0812">Ochils</placeName> in front. Their Eastern extremity is sloping
                    and woody. Crossed the <placeName ref="pl2256">Earn</placeName>; children with
                    light blue caps. Turned <pb n="f.70r"/> to the right through glen with close
                    rocky banks and ash trees growing luxuriantly. Workmen blasting rock to widen
                    the road. Crossed the <placeName ref="pl2257">Fargo</placeName> and entered
                        <placeName ref="pl1190">Fifeshire</placeName> and soon after <placeName ref="pl2258">Kinrossshire</placeName>. Asking an old man what was the
                    separation between them, he replied "this sma' burnie decides the business."
                    Ascended a hill and came in sight of <placeName ref="pl2254">Lomond</placeName>
                    a pointed mountain, which a countryman who overtook me on horseback <pb n="f.70v"/> told me was rich in gold silver coal lime and some other
                    valuable productions which I forget. The Road is dull &amp; barren for some
                    miles when it comes in sight of <placeName ref="pl0086">Loch Leven</placeName>.
                    Passed <placeName ref="pl2259">Forth Mills</placeName> a thriving village and
                    stopped at <placeName ref="pl2318">Kinross Green</placeName> a good inn before
                    you come to the town. <persName ref="pe1503">Graham</persName> is the principal
                    proprietor — <persName ref="pe1504">Blair</persName> is another — they divide
                    the take between them. We got excellent accommodation here. The <placeName ref="pl0089">Caudron Linn</placeName> &amp;c are between this place and
                        <placeName ref="pl0235">Stirling</placeName>.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.71r"/> Sep. 19.</p>
                <p><pb n="71v"/></p>
                <p><pb n="72r"/>We made our entrée into <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName> by <placeName ref="pl0959">Princes Street</placeName>
                    where a fine new Gothic church stared me in the face close to the old one at the
                    base of the <placeName ref="pl1031">Castle</placeName>. Drove to <placeName ref="pl2260">Dumbeck's</placeName> where we secured rooms &amp; then walked
                    out. The <placeName ref="pl2261">North loch Bridge</placeName> has been
                    disfigured by some large houses built from the <placeName ref="pl2262">Register
                        office</placeName> to the bridge which intercept the view. The improvements
                    on <placeName ref="pl0811">Calton hill</placeName> are astonishing. The road has
                    been blasted along the rock and is now almost completed. It is paved with square
                    cubes <pb n="f.72v"/> of granite taken from <placeName ref="pl2263">Salisbury
                        Crags</placeName>, on each side is a footpath and towards the precipice a
                    low parapet wall. From the end of <placeName ref="pl0959">Princes
                        Street</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0811">Calton Hill</placeName> has
                    been thrown the <placeName ref="pl2264">Regent's bridge</placeName> a single
                    arch of immense span and depth. Above the Parapet on each side is a triumphal
                    arch &amp; colonnade. Passing over it you come to <placeName ref="pl2079">Hume's
                        monument</placeName> rising from the burying ground on the right; and then
                    approach the <placeName ref="pl2266">Gaol</placeName> behind which rises the
                        <placeName ref="pl2265">Governor's house</placeName> composed of some <pb n="f.73r"/> fine towers irregularly built upon the verge of the precipice.
                    Next to the Prison comes the <placeName ref="pl2266">Bridewell</placeName> and
                    beyond that <add place="above">will be</add> the Debtor's Gaol, the entrance to
                    which from the road is just completed. Above us on the left we had <placeName ref="pl2267">Nelson's pillar</placeName> near which is the observatory — a
                    Grecian lodge of very pretty architecture is being built close to it. Fine
                    sunset — succeeded by a shower.</p>
                <p>Sep. 20. Rain all day. At 11 we went to <placeName ref="pl2268">S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Paul's church in York place</placeName> close
                    by. It is <pb n="f.73v"/> Gothic with a small tower at each of the four corners.
                    The inside is very neat with a groined roof and a handsome window; the galleries
                    on each side add to the accommodation but spoil the look of the building. They
                    are supported by Gothic ornaments. The organ and singing were very fine.
                        <persName ref="pe1455">Alison</persName> preached; an oldish and respectable
                    looking man. His text was "Lord what shall I do to inherit eternal life?" Called
                    on <persName ref="pe1456">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bell</persName> and
                    went in his carriage to<placeName ref="pl2269"> S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi>
                        George's Charlottes Square</placeName>, for the evening service. <pb n="f.74r"/><persName ref="pe1457"> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Thomson</persName> preached. The service began with a Psalm, then followed a
                    long Prayer and the Sermon; after which was a Christening for which every body
                    staid the father came up to the pulpit with his child to have it baptised. after
                    this there was a prayer and a psalm &amp; lastly a few words of dismissal. We
                    dined at our hotel at 5. —</p>
                <p>21. A fine morning. Breakfasted and walked out at ½ past 8. We went under the
                        <placeName ref="pl2264">Regent's bridge</placeName> and thro' dirty streets
                    into the <placeName ref="pl2270">High street</placeName> — <pb n="f.74v"/>
                    thence to <placeName ref="pl0724">Holyrood</placeName>. The palace is nearly all
                    of the time of <persName ref="pe1458">Charles II</persName>. except the old
                    towers which were built by <persName ref="pe1328">James V</persName>; but the
                    chapel which is now in ruins was built by <persName ref="pe1459">David</persName> in 1100. He founded it on being saved from being gored by
                    a stag in hunting. In the long Gallery or ball room are the pictures of all the
                    old Scotch Kings and the line is brought down to <persName ref="pe1458">Charles
                        II</persName>. The <persName ref="pe0250">Duke of Hamilton</persName> is
                    hereditary <choice>
                        <abbr>Gov<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>Governor</expan>
                    </choice> of the Palace and has a suite <pb n="f.75r"/> of rooms as have several
                    other noblemen. The state rooms are occupied by <persName ref="pe1460">Colonel
                        Nairne</persName>. The Gallery was used as a chapel by the <persName ref="pe1461">French Princes</persName> during their stay here. In the
                    adjoining rooms saw pictures of <rs ref="ar0080">Mary</rs> — Earl of Lennox
                    father of <persName ref="pe1463">Bothwell</persName><note type="editorial">Graham appears to be confusing Mary's second consort, <persName ref="pe0456">Henry Stewart, Lord Darnley</persName>, son of the earl of
                        Lennox, with her abductor and third consort, James Hepburn, fourth earl of
                        Bothwell. The painting referred to might be <rs ref="ar0002">Hans Eworth's
                            portrait of Darnley</rs>.</note> — <rs ref="ar0288">Bothwell</rs> — <rs ref="ar0286">D. of Hamilton</rs> beheaded in <persName ref="pe1391">Cromwell's</persName> time. The beautiful <rs ref="ar0287">miniature of
                        Mary</rs> is gone as it belonged to one of the <add place="above">ladies in
                        the</add> train of the French court who took it away when she quitted this
                    place. —</p>
                <p>Above are <persName ref="pe0527">Mary's</persName> state <pb n="f.75v"/> and
                    private bedrooms; her dressing room and the boudoir where <persName ref="pe0455">Rizzio</persName> was murdered. A private staircase leads down to the
                    Chapel from whence the conspirators ascended. Here are the boots of <persName ref="pe1463">Bothwell</persName> and his iron helmet and cuirass — The
                    (beaver) hat of <persName ref="pe0533">James I</persName>. child linen basket of
                        <persName ref="pe0527">Mary</persName> —and French dressing box of hers with
                    partitions and pincushions. That part of the bedroom where <persName ref="pe0455">Rizzio</persName> was murdered was parted off by the Queen as
                    may be seen <pb n="f.76r"/> by the ceiling. Here are portraits of <rs ref="ar0290">J. Shore</rs> and <rs ref="ar0289">N. Gwynne</rs>.<note type="editorial">Jane Shore and Nell Gwyn were mistresses to Edward IV and
                        Charles II respectively.</note> Went down to the Chapel founded by <persName ref="pe1459">David</persName> all the Nobility of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> have a right to bury here. The <unclear reason="illegible">Ballusses</unclear> on the North Side are all gone except
                    two; the chapel has been repaired lately or wd have fallen to pieces. The
                    Skeletons of some of the old Scotch Kings were shown here till lately.<note type="editorial">See <ref target="0052.xml">'A Tour through part of England
                            and Scotland By Eliza Dawson in the Year 1786'</ref>.</note> We walked
                    from hence in to the <placeName ref="pl2274">King's park</placeName>, and had
                        <placeName ref="pl2275">S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Leonard's
                        crags</placeName> opposite, behind rises <placeName ref="pl1028">Arthur's
                        seat</placeName>
                    <pb n="f.76v"/> We went along the valley between it and <placeName ref="pl2263">Salisbury craigs</placeName> which is as still and desolate as possible.
                    Winding thro' this we at length came to that part of the crags where they are
                    quarrying and then walked along the <unclear reason="illegible">way</unclear>
                    traversed by Butler<note type="editorial">The minister Reuben Butler, a
                        character in Walter Scott's 1818 novel <hi rend="italic">The Heart of
                            Midlothian</hi>.</note> and descended by a steep and almost
                    impracticable track to the Southern <unclear reason="illegible">Bar</unclear> of
                        <placeName ref="pl2276">Cannongate</placeName> which leads to <placeName ref="pl2277">Cowgate</placeName>. This <add place="above">latter</add> is
                    very narrow and leads under the <placeName ref="pl2278">South bridge</placeName>
                    to the <placeName ref="pl1039">Grass market</placeName>. <pb n="f.77r"/> We
                    however turned up to the left and walked round by the <placeName ref="pl2279">College</placeName> which they are going on with and ornamenting with
                    pillars the Shafts of which are composed of a single block. Crossing over the
                        <placeName ref="pl2278">South bridge</placeName> we came to <placeName ref="pl2280">Hunter's square</placeName> and the <placeName ref="pl2281">Tron church</placeName>. We then went up <placeName ref="pl2270">High
                        Street</placeName> to the <placeName ref="pl2284">Commercial
                        Bank</placeName> and afterwards to the <placeName ref="pl1031">Castle</placeName>. The day was not fine enough to show us the distant
                    view. <pb n="f.77v"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl2282">Heriot's Hospital</placeName> forms a fine feature in
                    the foreground. A new turret has been built at the highest part of the castle
                    and rather spoils the effect by it's modern appearance. A keeper has been
                    appointed for the regalia discovered here and has a salary of £100 a year. They
                    are not yet shown to the public. Returned in the rain at 1. Got Luncheon and
                    went to <persName ref="pe1464">Fraser's the Jeweller's</persName> in <placeName ref="pl0959">Prince's Street</placeName> just opposite the <placeName ref="pl2262">Register Office</placeName>. Then to <pb n="f.78r"/>
                    <persName ref="pe1465">Saunderson's</persName> another trinket merchant in
                        <placeName ref="pl2280">Hunter Square</placeName>. Saw a large loadstone
                    supporting a weight of some stone. a curious fish caught with herrings with
                    peacock colours upon it — preserved in spirits. a boat made by the Esquimaux.
                    Went to <persName ref="pe1466">Allan's</persName> a good painter in <placeName ref="pl2283">Parliament Square</placeName>. Here we saw an excellent
                    painting of a conquered <rs ref="ar0293">family sold by a Circassian chief to a
                        Turkish Bashaw</rs>. <rs ref="ar0292">A Jewish Marriage from the life</rs>
                    price 100G<hi rend="superscript">s.</hi>
                    <rs ref="ar0294">Inside of cottage</rs> 40G<hi rend="superscript">s.</hi> both
                    these much in the style of <persName ref="pe1467">Teniers</persName>.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.78v"/>
                Went at 5 to dine with <persName ref="pe1456">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Bell</persName>. Met there <persName ref="pe1468">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gregory</persName> and a Danish
                    Doctor travelling for information. <persName ref="pe1437">Walter
                        Scott</persName> is a commissary of <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" quantity="1"/> and has a salary of £100 a year — the place is almost a
                    sinecure. I heard of his talking of spending Sunday on <placeName ref="pl1176">the Continent</placeName> so much more gaiety &amp;c than in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>. A million of Bolls of potatoes have been
                    sent for from <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>, &amp; some in this
                    neighbourhood have been taken up too early <pb n="f.79r"/> and spoilt. The
                    Danish D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> wo<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> not
                    allow that the English conquered at <placeName ref="pl2225">Waterloo</placeName>. Came away at a little past 9.</p>
                <p>22. Wrote letters. Breakfast at 8. Young <persName ref="pe1456">Bell</persName>
                    called and we walked up <placeName ref="pl0959">Princes Street</placeName> over
                        <placeName ref="pl2315">the Mound</placeName>; passed by the <placeName ref="pl2284">Bank</placeName> and came to <placeName ref="pl2283">Parliament
                        square</placeName>. The <placeName ref="pl2285">Tolbooth</placeName> was
                    only pulled down eight months ago. It stood North of the Church and there was a
                    narrow passage between it <add place="above"><hi rend="underline">and</hi> the
                            <hi rend="underline">latter</hi>;</add> and the <placeName ref="pl2286">Luckenbooths</placeName>
                    <pb n="f.79v"/> were between it and the North side of the Street. Part of the
                    church which was divided into 4 was devoted to the <placeName ref="pl2285">Tolbooth</placeName>. Walked on a little farther and turned down the
                        <placeName ref="pl1037">West Bow</placeName> a street winding down a steep
                    hill, and came to the <placeName ref="pl1039">grass market</placeName> which
                    does not extend so far to the Westward as formerly. Thence to <placeName ref="pl2282">Heriot's Hospital</placeName> where a number of children all in
                    the same dress were playing on the green before it. The building not designed by
                        <persName ref="pe1159">Inigo <pb n="f.80r"/> Jones</persName>. It is
                    ornamented with a number of little picturesque turrets. In the inner court is a
                    statue of the founder who it is said made a large fortune not by very fair means
                    and left it all in this way. The number of boys is 175 who are all fed and
                    clothed; they learn Latin and Greek and must be orphans of decayed tradesmen.
                    There is a beautiful view from hence of the <placeName ref="pl1031">castle
                        rock</placeName> which rises in a bold perpendicular manner. We returned up
                        <placeName ref="pl2277">Cowgate</placeName> and mounted a flight of steps to
                        <placeName ref="pl2283">Parliament square</placeName>. <pb n="f.80v"/> We
                    went in to see the <placeName ref="pl2287">Courts</placeName>. In the center is
                    a large hall something like <placeName ref="pl0776">Westminster</placeName> with
                    an old wooden ceiling — it contains a <rs ref="ar0295">statue of Lord
                        Forbes</rs>. On each side is a Court. The Hall is soon being repaired; on
                    it's walls are paintings of the <rs ref="ar0296">Stewarts, William III and
                        Anne</rs>, and statues of the <persName ref="pe0453">late Lord
                        Melville</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe1102">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hugh Blair</persName> are to be put up in it. Adjoining are the
                        <placeName ref="pl1022">Advocate's and Writer's Library</placeName>, one
                    over the other and both adorned with pillars <pb n="f.81r"/> supporting
                    Galleries for reaching the upper shelves. This building has some <unclear reason="illegible">steeples</unclear> at the top and is not in good taste.
                    In the Square is a <rs ref="ar0297">bronze equestrian statue of Charles II</rs>.
                    adjoining the libraries is a fine new wing with an Ionic Portico. Went back to
                    the <placeName ref="pl2075">New Town</placeName> and past the Catholic Chapel
                    with a Gothic port — called at <persName ref="pe1469">Nasmyth</persName> a
                    landscape painter where we saw <rs ref="ar0300">views of Glencoe</rs>, <rs ref="ar0299">L<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> Roseberry's park</rs>, <rs ref="ar0298">Loch Katrine &amp;c</rs>
                    <persName ref="pe1470">His son</persName> who lives in <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>
                    <pb n="f.81v"/> paints much better. We went afterwards to <persName ref="pe1471">Raeburn's</persName> and saw a number of portraits more remarkable for
                    likeness and expression than beauty of attitude. There is an excellent one of
                        <rs ref="ar0301">M<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi>Nab chief of a clan</rs>, in
                    a Highland dress; belonging to <persName ref="pe1375">L<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> Breadalbane</persName>. Little <rs ref="ar0302">L<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> Montgomery on a poney</rs> — <rs ref="ar0304">Lord Hopeton leaving on his horse</rs>. <rs ref="ar0303">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Brougham</rs>. We here took leave of
                        <persName ref="pe1456">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bell</persName>, and
                    after buying some plaids and ascending <placeName ref="pl2267">Nelson's
                        Tower</placeName> we returned to <placeName ref="pl2260">Dumbecks</placeName> &amp; having paid our reckoning started at 4.<note type="authorial">N.B. The floors of the houses in <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinbr'</placeName> are called <hi rend="underline">Lands</hi> in the
                            <placeName ref="pl2076">old Town</placeName>, <hi rend="underline">flats</hi> in the <placeName ref="pl2075">new</placeName>.</note></p>
                <p><pb n="f.82r"/>
                The street by which we left <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName> is
                    wretchedly dirty &amp; miserably paved; no town wants a new entrance more. We
                    passed close by <placeName ref="pl1028">Arthur's Seat</placeName> &amp; the
                        <placeName ref="pl2274">King's Park</placeName>. Approached the <placeName ref="pl0083">Firth</placeName> at <placeName ref="pl0075">Musselburgh</placeName> — fine view from the hill beyond of <placeName ref="pl0074">Preston Pans</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinbu</placeName> &amp;c. <placeName ref="pl0948">Haddington</placeName>
                    neat town &amp; clean Inn. Passed by <placeName ref="pl2288">Lord Wemyss's
                            <unclear reason="illegible">staring</unclear> old chateau</placeName>
                    and came thence by Starlight to <placeName ref="pl0070">Dunbar</placeName> which
                    we reached at 8. &amp; stopped at the <placeName ref="pl2289">new
                        Inn</placeName>.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.82v"/>
                23. We took a walk after breakfast this morning to see the <placeName ref="pl2290">castle</placeName> which stands on some bold rocks, thro' which
                    are two natural arches; the views of the coast, with <placeName ref="pl2291">N.
                        Berwick Law</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl2292">Bass</placeName> are
                    very Romantic. <placeName ref="pl2293">Lord Lauderdale's house</placeName>
                    stands at one end of the town facing the street — and the other front has a
                    beautiful view to the <placeName ref="pl2290">Castle</placeName> &amp; sea.
                    There is a pier here; which runs up to a mass of basaltic columns. The Solan
                    Geese which frequent the <placeName ref="pl2292">Isle of Bass</placeName>
                    <pb n="f.83r"/> are very little eaten being fishy and strong 3 sell for 1<hi rend="superscript">s.</hi> a peice. We had the carriage open on leaving
                        <placeName ref="pl0070">Dunbar</placeName> &amp; had fine coast views, but
                    missed <placeName ref="pl2071">Pease bridge</placeName> the road being carried
                    over a levelled tract more inland. The people here are much dirtier and envelop
                    themselves in mantles. Passed <placeName ref="pl2294">Broxmouth</placeName>
                    <persName ref="pe1473">Duke of Roxburgh's</persName> Windmills with double sails
                    — large inclosures — sea weed spread on fields for manure. after passing
                        <placeName ref="pl2295">Ayton</placeName>
                    <persName ref="pe1474">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        <pb n="f.83v"/> Fordyce's</persName> on our left we ascended a high hill and
                    had then a fine ride along the brows of high cliffs; and soon obtained a distant
                    view of <placeName ref="pl2295">Northumberland</placeName> the <placeName ref="pl0066">Fern Islands</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl0064">Bambrough Castle</placeName>. <placeName ref="pl0067">Berwick</placeName>
                    is in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> it has one large church but
                    contains also a number of Scotch Kirks. We got luncheon at the Inn and called on
                        <persName ref="pe1475">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Forster</persName>
                    where we staid half and hour. Rain came on as we left <placeName ref="pl0067">Berwick</placeName>. <pb n="f.84r"/> Crossed the <placeName ref="pl0727">Tweed</placeName> — passed <persName ref="pe1476">Sir C.
                        Haggerstone's</persName> — arrived at <placeName ref="pl2296"><unclear reason="illegible">Newham</unclear></placeName> about 7. <persName ref="pe1477">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Dinning</persName> in bed but
                    came down to us to tea when <persName ref="pe1478">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Selby</persName> also joined us.</p>
                <p>23.<note type="editorial">The dating of entries inconsistent at this point in the
                        journal.</note> Rainy morning. <persName ref="pe1479">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> N.D.</persName> rode over about 11. and I went
                    over the estate with him. Inspected new plantations — &amp; projected a large
                    square one near <placeName ref="pl2297">Warnton</placeName>. Buildings there in
                    excellent order. Walked in garden with the farmers. Fine <pb n="f.84v"/> horse
                    they had for sale. Came down from high ground passed <persName ref="pe1480">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Pratts</persName>, &amp; crossed the road to
                        <placeName ref="pl2298">Adderstone</placeName> &amp; returned along the road
                    to <unclear reason="illegible"><placeName ref="pl2296">Newham</placeName></unclear>. Afterwards <persName ref="pe1501">Maria</persName> &amp; I took a walk up the high ground and in the evening
                    went to see the threshing machine. Poor <persName ref="pe1477">D.</persName>
                    complained much &amp; went to bed very early.</p>
                <p>24. We breakfasted early and the morning being fine determined to take <placeName ref="pl0064">Bambrough <pb n="f.85r"/> Castle</placeName> in our way to
                        <placeName ref="pl0062">Alnwick</placeName>. It was a very bad road and I
                    walked the greater part of the way before the carriage. We called on M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    <gap reason="authorial" unit="words" quantity="1"/> at the <placeName ref="pl0064">Castle</placeName> who very civilly showed us over it. It
                    originally belonged to a Trustee whose daughter &amp; heiress married Lord
                        Greave<note type="editorial">Apparently a reference to <persName ref="pe1311">Nathaniel, third Baron Crew</persName></note> who paid off
                    a heavy mortage laid on it by Trustee and left the estate to charitable uses.
                    Sixty years ago <persName ref="pe1482">Archdeacon <pb n="f.85v"/>
                        Sharpe</persName> grandson of the <persName ref="pe1481">Archbishop</persName> cleared the sand from the Donjon tower &amp; fitted
                    up a room in it in a <unclear reason="illegible">rude</unclear> manner — the
                    beds being made of masts and Sailcloth. He founded the library and put a gill
                    tip on the conducter of the tower. Succeeding Trustees built up the remainder of
                    the castle upon the old foundations. A certain number of children are always
                    taught fed &amp; clothed here. and there are all sorts of <pb n="f.86r"/> of
                    assistance for shipwrecked people. Including <persName ref="pe1500">Captain
                        Manby's</persName> invention of fixing a rope. There is a small armoury here
                    with some old pikes in it. The walls are 11 feet thick; and there is a well cut
                    155 feet deep in the solid rock. The Castle has often been besieged. Corn is
                    distributed here at a low rate in times of scarcity. In the library are some of
                    the books of <persName ref="pe1483">Archbishop Sharpe</persName>. We went out by
                        <pb n="f.86v"/> the Sally port and rejoined our carriage at the Inn. Passed
                        <placeName ref="pl2299">Twizell Hall</placeName> — <persName ref="pe1478">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Selby's</persName> — and afterwards
                        <persName ref="pe1480">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Pratts</persName>. At
                        <placeName ref="pl2065">Charlton</placeName> we turned off a quarter of a
                    mile to the left and called on <persName ref="pe1479">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                        <unclear reason="illegible">N</unclear>. D.</persName> and his bride. From
                    their house you see <placeName ref="pl2300">Falloden</placeName> a good sized
                    red brick building rising out of wood. The Country improves and becomes more
                    woody on approaching <placeName ref="pl0062">Alnwick</placeName>. Three pillars
                    are seen as you come near it — <placeName ref="pl2301">one of them</placeName>
                    erected <pb n="f.87r"/> by the <persName ref="pe1309">D. of
                        Northumberland's</persName> tenantry in gratitude to him in 1815. It <del rend="overstrike">his</del><add place="above">is</add> of the Doric Pestic
                    order and is surmounted by an iron railing and a Lion; with Esperance en Dieu on
                    the pedestal; it cost £3000 and subscriptions as small as 5<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> were contributed to it. Crossed handsome bridge
                    over the <placeName ref="pl2064">Aln</placeName> and ascended hill to town.</p>
                <p>We went all over the <placeName ref="pl1729">castle</placeName> which till 60
                    years ago (when it was rebuilt in the old style by <persName ref="pe0442">the
                        Duke</persName>) was a <pb n="f.87v"/> ruin with only a few old towers;
                    figures are placed along the top in imitation of the old style; few of the
                    original remain. We entered by an old Saxon Gateway into the Court in w<hi rend="superscript">h.</hi> stands the body of the building. To the right of
                    the entrance is the Dungeon in which are placed some Roman antiquities; an altar
                    &amp; the heads of some deities — Underneath is a still worse place of
                    confinement, on the outside <pb n="f.88r"/> are the marks of where the rack used
                    to be fixed. Here is the proper measure of the Winchester bushel in bell Metal.
                    In the Chapel is the long line of <persName ref="pe0442">the Duke's</persName>
                    ancestors emblazoned on the walls. <persName ref="pe1095">Charlemagne</persName>
                    is at the head; some of his successors married Counts of Louraine who
                    intermarried with the Percys. <hi rend="underline">The</hi> ancestor of the
                    Percy's is called <persName ref="pe1485">Mainfred</persName> A.D. 870. The
                        <persName ref="pe1486">first Earl of Percy</persName> was in 1100. <pb n="f.88v"/> At the farther end of the Chapel is the tomb of the <persName ref="pe0443">late Duchess</persName> who was daughter of the <persName ref="pe1487">D. of Somerset</persName> and heiress by her mother's side to
                    the Earls of Northumberland She was Countess in her own right and married
                        <persName ref="pe0442">Sir H. Smithson</persName> who was created Duke in
                    1786. The <persName ref="pe1309">late Duke</persName> was their son. The <rs ref="ar0243">Portrait of the late Duchess</rs> is haughty &amp; dignified.
                    In the armoury are suspended the Bugles of the Percy corps <pb n="f.89r"/>
                    raised by the <persName ref="pe1309">late Duke</persName> and which he commanded
                    at <placeName ref="pl2304">Bunker's Hill</placeName>. Here is the canoe and
                    dress of an Esquimaux princess with a double oar. In one part of the walls along
                        w<hi rend="superscript">h.</hi> is a walk is a seat called Hotspur's chair.
                    There are some old cannons in the lawn but too old to be fired without danger of
                    bursting. The <persName ref="pe1488">Duke</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe1489">Duchess</persName> are at present at a shooting Box in the West
                    Side of the Country. <pb n="f.89v"/> After leaving <placeName ref="pl0062">Alnwick</placeName> the Country is rich but hilly. Passed <placeName ref="pl2305">Nelson's pillar</placeName> in <persName ref="pe1490">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Davison's</persName> grounds. Several
                    Gentlemen's seats; <placeName ref="pl0061">Felton Hall</placeName> on the right
                    side of <placeName ref="pl2306">Feltonbridge</placeName> a pretty
                        <unclear>situed</unclear> hamlet; <persName ref="pe1491">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> deLisle's</persName> on the left. Ascended a
                    steep hill &amp; reached <placeName ref="pl0059">Morpeth</placeName> at 7. and
                        <placeName ref="pl0057">Newcastle</placeName> ¼ to 10. lighted with gas from
                    the streets &amp; houses <placeName ref="pl2307">The Queen's head</placeName>
                    being full we drove to <placeName ref="pl2308">the Turk's head</placeName> kept
                    by <persName ref="pe1492">Cumberland Fletcher</persName>.</p>
                <p><pb n="f.90r"/>
                25. The morning was very rainy. <persName ref="pe1493">Old Hindmarsh</persName>
                    came to the Market and I found him out and at 1 oclock <persName ref="pe1501">Maria</persName> &amp; 1 set off in a chaise for <placeName ref="pl2309">Callerton</placeName> with him as our outrider. The country is pretty and
                    the day clearing up I was able to walk all over the estate and we returned to
                        <placeName ref="pl0057">Newcastle</placeName>
                    <pb n="f.90v"/> to dinner. In the evening I saw <persName ref="pe1494">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thomas</persName> heard from him the acc<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> of the fire at <placeName ref="pl0441">Hexham</placeName> (<persName ref="pe1495">Col Beaumonts</persName>)
                    –––––</p>
                <p>26. This morning we started early — and took the road by <placeName ref="pl0443"><add place="above">Corbridge</add></placeName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0441">Hexham</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl2310">Haltwhistle</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl2311">Brampton</placeName> and
                    thence to <placeName ref="pl2150">E.C.</placeName> w<hi rend="superscript">h.</hi> we reached about 6. and walked up to <placeName ref="pl2312">Stone
                        House</placeName> before dinner where we found all well. —</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>