<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0407">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Donald MacQueen to Thomas Pennant</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP297</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>1</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0069">Donald MacQueen</persName>
                    <date when="1772-10-29"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0742">Kilmuir</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct0408"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Sir</salute></opener>
                <p>I had the honour of your Letter on <add place="above">my</add> Arrival in
                        <placeName ref="pl0742">Kilmuir</placeName>, inclosing Another from
                        <persName ref="pe0109">Mr Archibald Macdonald</persName> to Whom I ow a
                    great deal of Respect. Had I come home two days Sooner I would have the pleasure
                    of Over takeing you near My Place and would have tryed to prevail with you to
                    Stop a Litle to Survey further, the face of this Countrey, where you wou'd meet
                    with some Natural Curiosities, the dismal dwellings of the first Inhabitants,
                    Caves or Subterraneous houses, Several Danish Edifices, Many Inclosures of
                    Different Forms, wh had been consecrated to Druidical Worship And Many More
                    Christian Chapels where Service was performed by the Monks of the Monastery in
                    My Neighbourhood on <placeName ref="pl1621">Columba's Lake</placeName>, the only
                    one in the Island. You woud be the <del rend="overstrike"><unclear reason="illegible">only</unclear></del> proper Judge how far Any of
                    these things deserved Any Regard or how far they were connected with your
                    Design; I woud however have attempted to Write you something if I had not been
                    some how Employed in a More disagreeable Way. In the Mean time, I would Chuse to
                    know, whether you have picked up in your Travels or whether your own Countrey
                    may not Afford the Elf-arrow or the Elf-spade, so Called; both of the flint kind
                    of Stone. The former was surely the Point of An Arrow As the Later seems to have
                    been Used in Smoothing Stone or Timber. I have Also found a stone in a Druid's
                    house which from that Circumstance I conceive Might have been Used in their
                    Sacrifice Operations for it is very Sharp at the broad End, Smooth And Oblong at
                    the Other which was the handle. I take it that before the Discovery of Mettals
                    our Ancestors were Under a Necessity of Useing some such tools from any hard
                    stuff that offered itself. Superstitions And prejudice might Also give them an
                    Immaginary Sanctity or value that would preserve them After better Materials<hi rend="superscript">+</hi><note type="authorial">+ <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0067">Exod. 4.25</title></bibl></note><note type="editorial">A reference to a tool used in Biblical verse: 'Then
                        Zipporah took a sharp stone, and cut off the foreskin of her son, and cast
                            <hi rend="italic">it</hi> at his feet, and said, Surely a bloody husband
                            <hi rend="italic">art</hi> thou to me.'</note> were discovered. In fact,
                    Some of the Ignorant Farmers Amongst Us applyed these stones to the Cure of Some
                    diseases when the help of man failed. And Whoever had the Arrow About him woud
                    never be Elf-shot for Whoever dyed of an Apoplexy whether Man or beast was
                    Supposed to be shot by the Fairies; which are Vulgar Errors that can be
                    accounted for without Much difficulty from the Beliefs which prevailed in former
                    Ages. If you have Any Taste for these stones I will take the first Occasion to
                    Convey them to <persName ref="pe0978">Mr William Macdonald</persName> writer to
                    the Signet <placeName ref="pl0076">Edin<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi></placeName>.</p>
                <p>I will write some kind of answer to <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0528">Your Printed Papper</title></bibl></p>
                <closer>I am with Much Esteem Sir <lb/>Your Very Obedient and humble Servant
                            <signed><persName ref="pe0069">Don: Macqueen</persName></signed>
                    <dateline><placeName ref="pl0742">Kilmuir</placeName> Oct. 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                        <lb/>1772.</dateline></closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>If you are pleased to write direct for Me ––––– Minister in <placeName ref="pl0715">Sky</placeName>
                        <lb/>by <placeName ref="pl0660">Sconsar</placeName>.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><handShift/><persName ref="pe0069">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Macquin</persName>
                    <lb/>oct. 29 1772.</p>
                <p><handShift/><address>
                        <addrLine>To</addrLine>
                        <addrLine><persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant Esqr.</persName></addrLine>
                        <addrLine>to the care of <persName ref="pe0018">Mr
                            Jackson</persName></addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Secretary to the Post-Office</addrLine>
                        <addrLine><placeName ref="pl0076">Edin<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi></placeName></addrLine>
                    </address></p>
                <p><stamp type="handstamp"><placeName ref="pl0660">SCONSER</placeName></stamp></p>
                <p><handShift/>4</p>
                <p><handShift/><persName ref="pe0069">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Queen</persName></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>