<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0408">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Donald MacQueen to Thomas Pennant</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP297</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>2</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0069">Donald MacQueen</persName>
                    <date when="1773-01-15"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0742">Kilmuir</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct0409"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct0407"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gd">Gaelic</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="enclosed">
                <fw>p. 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi></fw>
                <p>of Buildings.</p>
                <p>I amused myself for a Peice of a day very Lately in opening up one or two of our
                    Subterraneous houses Which are numerous <del rend="overstrike">on the Face</del>
                    on the face of the Islands — the dreary unwholesome habitations of the first
                    Adventurers into it. They are something about six and twenty feet Long, three
                    feet wide And four feet deep. The Side are regularly faced with stone to keep
                    the Earth from falling in And covered over with Flags which are overlaid with
                    Turf so As to be Upon a Level with the Ground around it. There is a passage to
                    it at one of the Ends two feet And one half Square, by two Steps of a
                    Stone-stair, which if covered with Turf or bundle of heather woud bid defiance
                    to the Narrowest Search for discovery. A rising ground And a dry Mould were
                    chosen for these dismal Seats. I can Easyly see they never Made Use of Feuel
                    within them, for a blast of Smoak woud Smother the Whole Miserable family within
                    the narrow Vault; And it is Uncertain whether the Savage Inhabitant knew Any
                    thing of the Use of fire for it is Certain the forced fire with which they
                    burned their Sacrifices in a Later Period was raised Up by the Uninterrupted
                    burning of a stake or wimble of hard wood into a peice of Oak; at which
                    Operation Nine Men Assisted. Be that how it will, this retreat of Security from
                    the Inclemency of Winter, which must have been very Severe in a Northern
                    Uncultivated Countrey, And from the bloody violence of a starving undisciplined
                    Neighbourhood, was, when Society was a Litle more Regularly formed and some
                    faint rude Attempts made in the Art of Husbandry, converted into a Granary for
                    keeping Up their Corn. To Secure it from the Ravenous Claws of their Neighbours
                    And to keep <add place="above">it</add> for Long preservation, at a distance
                    from the heat of the Sun, Untill they returned from any of their foreign
                    Expeditions it was properly Judged to Lay it Up in these dark Recesses. In the
                    Gaulic Language <del rend="overstrike">Gradan</del> the burnt corn is called <hi rend="underline">Gradan</hi>, the Kiln-dryed Tirigh. You will find by <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0079">Q. Curtius</title></bibl>
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0635">Pliny</title></bibl> And others that
                    the Artificial Caves of which I speak were by the Antient Inhabitants of
                        <placeName ref="pl1176">Europe</placeName> called Siros or Siris; it is then
                    Natural to Suppose that the Kiln-dryed which is latest for keeping derived it's
                    name from the common name of the Granary And that <hi rend="underline">Aran</hi>-(bread)-Tirigh is the bread of Siros or Siris. for Immediate Use they
                    burned the Corn, As we do to this day, tho indeed in face of the Proprietors
                    Commands. <del rend="overstrike">But I return from this digression to consider
                        the Habitations of our Ancestors</del>. Nature indeed offered them caves for
                    their Lurking places but As commodious ones of that Sort are not Numerous And
                    Might be Easyly found out, Necessity taught them to Make Use of their hands on
                    dry Ground As Above or to fortify the Cave with a Stone wall where that coud be
                    conveniently done. There is a remarkable <pb/><fw>p.2<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi></fw> One of this kind on the East Side of <placeName ref="pl0950">Troternish</placeName>. It is a Cave in the face of a Rock
                    towards <add place="above">the</add> Sea, to which they might Scramble up by
                    climbing but As the mouth of it was wide they raised a Strong wall Upon the
                    Precipice which brought it to a narrow compass And by a few steps of stone stair
                    on the Inside they got into a Warm Spacious Hall. They must have made Use of
                    Ladders to get Up to the top of the Wall or have Learned the Art of Climbing
                    better <add place="above">than</add> We of this Generation. One man with a
                    Lap-ful of Small Stones coud keep off a <del rend="overstrike"><gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" atLeast="4" atMost="6"/></del> Army
                    furnished with all the Artillery of that day.</p>
                <p><del rend="overstrike">The next Improvement in building of which there <unclear reason="illegible">are</unclear></del> I must Observe here that the
                    Gaulic vocable for a Cave is <hi rend="underline">Ŭagh</hi> And that the Only
                    word which our Copious Language affords for Giant is <hi rend="underline">Uagher</hi>, that is, the Inhabitant of a Cave. In the old tales &amp;
                    poems in which these savages Are Mentioned, they Are represented As Cannibals
                    who Eat all sort of Fleshes raw in No degree better Civilized than <persName ref="pe0673">Polypheme</persName> in <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0224">the Odessey</title></bibl> And if they knew Any thing about
                    fire they were quite Ignorant of the Principal use of it. Men unfurnished with
                    suiteable Arms for hunting or with tacle for fishing sticks And Stones being the
                    Only Weapons of that Time And when afterwards they Invented Arrows they were
                    only pointed with flints I say, with these clumsy weapons they must often have
                    been Exposed to the horrors of Famine the more so, that they did not know the
                    Way of Laying up provisions Against a time of Scarcity. In a terrible Extremity
                    when Every Source of Relief was shut up we cannot wonder that they <unclear reason="illegible">devoured</unclear> their visitors; what Unnatural Motions
                    hath Famine in time of a Siege raised in the Human heart And in the heart of
                    that Mother in <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0067">2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Kings Chap. 6. v29.</title></bibl> These
                    Savages are represented in Fable as Men of Mighty Stature — Fear hath Also
                    taught the Grecians &amp; Romans to point out the Scythians And Gauls After the
                    Same Manner.</p>
                <p>The next improvement in building of which there are Any traces remaining, is that
                    of the Danish Dūns. History (<bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0087">Torfæūs</title></bibl>) bears testimony to the Arrivals of the Danes or
                    rather Norwegians, in <placeName ref="pl0708">the Western Isles</placeName> in
                    the beginning of the Ninth Century. If <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian's</persName> Authority can be depended on they made Several Descents
                    on them And on <placeName ref="pl0889">Irland</placeName> in a much Earlyer
                    Period for the Sake of Plunder or of shewing their Heroism in these Military
                    days; but in the Ninth Century After conquering the Islands they setled in the
                        <del rend="overstrike"><gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" quantity="3"/></del>
                    <add place="above">where they were</add>
                    <del rend="overstrike">and</del> governed <del rend="overstrike">them</del> by a
                    Viceroy from the Mother-countrey. A litle Experience woud have Instructed them
                    in the propriety of Living within Strong holds among their Enemies who 'tho they
                    were Obliged <pb/><fw>p.3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></fw> To yield to a
                    Superior force preserved that Spirit of Liberty and Independancy which was
                    Natural to all Celtic Tribes. A rising ground faced on all sides with A Rock was
                    generally chosen for the seat of the Burgh for so our Duns were called in the
                    Language of the Builders And the word is preserved and frequent in the compound
                    Names of these places Where Such buildings have been Erected. on the brink of
                    this Rock they put up a thick Strong Wall of Uncommon height And thickness, in
                    which they Employed <add place="above">stones</add> of a prodigious Size by mere
                    Strength of Arm for they knew of no Machine proper for raising And transporting
                    Weighty bodies. The Inclosure is perfectly Circular and the Stones Laid on the
                    out and Inside with great Art And Skill for tho they were Ignorant of the Use of
                    Cement it stands firm And Unmoved to this day Except where <add place="above">it</add> is pulled down for modern work. There is an opening in the heart
                    of the wall all round, thro which they coud get Up to the Top by an Easy Ascent
                    from a passage <del rend="overstrike">near</del>
                    <add place="inline">or</add> Entry near the foundation. This vacancy served to
                    keep their Arms and Utensils safe from the Injuries of the Weather As well as to
                    give them access to the Summit of the wall to Observe the Motions of their
                    Enemies or drive them off in case of a near approach. In the wide Space which is
                    surrounded by this fortification they built their huts or Cabins where the men
                    with their wives And Children Lodged together And this is what they called a
                    Burgh or Town in the same Manner as the Antient Brittans cut a Large Circle
                    within a wood where after they had fortifyed it with a ditch And heaped Up trees
                    all round they built huts And Stables for themselves And their Catle And this
                    they Called a Town (<bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0248">Cæsar 5.2<unclear reason="illegible">1</unclear>.</title></bibl> and <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0252">strabo 4.200</title></bibl>).These Duns
                    are very numerous in this Island And Each within sight of Another that in case
                    of Any Sudden Assault they might convey a general Alarm to their friends by the
                    signal of a Torch. They had besides much more Spacious Duns for their Cows,
                    called Boaghun Answering in point to the Cuballum of <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0261">Livy</title></bibl> among the Gallogræcians, for
                    the Use names mean an Inclosure for Cows and I reckon they were as well
                    contrived for the Security of the Catle among these ferocious, Lawless
                    Itinerants into <placeName ref="pl1622">Asia</placeName>, As here, tho they
                    might happen to need cow's dung for feuels in the Absolute want of better.</p>
                <p><placeName ref="pl1621">The Monastery on Columbas Lake</placeName> in My
                    Neighbourhood, mentioned in the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0339">Chronicle of Man</title></bibl> under the year 1223 If I remember, did
                    not trust <add place="above">so far</add> to the Sanctity of the Inhabitants or
                    the place, tho Surrounded with water, As to neglect the Precaution
                            <pb/><fw>p.4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></fw> of being fortifyed in
                    the same manner With the Danes within a Strong wall without Cement Where the
                    Several Cells And appartments Are still very apparent. From Which Circumstance I
                    conclude that at the time of founding it Druidism prevailed in the Islands, for
                    the Superstition of the People, the common attendant of Barbarity and Ignorance,
                    woud have Otherwise been fence Enough without the trouble of Lending an Immense
                    heap of Large Stones for their further protection from the bands of Ruffians.
                    The <placeName ref="pl1621">Chapel Upon the Island</placeName> adjacent to this
                    Monastery is made Up with Lime which is Argument Enough for its being a much
                    Later Work for the Chapels round the Countrey Which <add place="above">are</add>
                    Many in Number, one in Every district And in Every Island Upon the Coast Are for
                    the most part built without Cement. to these Chapels a monk from the Monastry
                    repaired, Each in his turn, for the Performance of Religious Services to the
                    Inhabitants in the Neighbourhood. The place Where the Monks Landed when Entering
                    Upon their Mission is called <placeName ref="pl2655">Pein-oran</placeName>, that
                    is, the Land of Prayer, Whence they Set out Every one to his Appointment, After
                    Solemnly committing themselves And their Work to the Blessing And Protection of
                    the Most High. This Monastery As well As all the Monasteries And Bishops too in
                    the Kingdom And North of <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> was Under
                    the Jurisdiction of that of <placeName ref="pl0651"/> Whence Christianity was
                    first propagated Amongst Us. From the Monasteries, Abbacies And Priories
                    Established by that Antient And Religious Community Missionaries were Ordered
                    out to the different districts where they were thought Most Necessary for the
                    Division of Parishes is a Late Work And did not take place in this Island Untill
                    the End of the Reign of <persName ref="pe0533">King James the 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></persName> or the beginning of <persName ref="pe0600">K. Charles</persName> his Reign. It is Certain the Priests,
                    preceeding that Period, did not take the vow of Celibacy for Many of them were
                    Marryed. Besides the Tradition which Assures Us of this fact the names of
                    Several Clans bear testimony to it — MacNab (the Abbot's son) Macphrier (the
                    prior son) MacPherson (the Parsons son) Macvean, the Vicars son. <add place="above">mac</add>Haggart the Priests Son. I am Much of Opinion that
                    the distinguishing Tenets of the Popish Superstition were never deeply <unclear reason="illegible">rivetted</unclear> in this Part of <placeName ref="pl0711">the Highlands</placeName> for <placeName ref="pl0651">Icolumbkill</placeName> conformed to them very Late And that faintly. And
                    when our Kings and some of our Nobles began to travell Abroad &amp; imported
                    that Expensive ruinous Superstition, <placeName ref="pl0708">the Western
                        Isles</placeName> were As independant of the Public Seat of Administration
                    As of the See of <placeName ref="pl1623">Rome</placeName> itself, And may Justly
                    be supposed to have kept by the Instructions they received at first, which were
                    founded on the writings of the prophets Evangelists And Apostles As were those
                    of all the Culdees in the Kingdom (in the Charters called Killedei that is,
                    Gille-dhe, the Servants of God) who wore out in the fourteenth Century As did
                    the Monastery of <placeName ref="pl0651">Icolumbkill</placeName> being gradually
                    striped of all its Extensive Possessions, for the <placeName ref="pl1026">Monastery of Holy-rude house</placeName> As appears by the <pb/><fw>p.5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></fw> Foundation Charter was Endued with the
                    Lands belonging to it in <placeName ref="pl1624">Galloway.</placeName> The
                        <placeName ref="pl1625">Church of Snizort</placeName> which stands on an
                    Island in the River which divides the Estate of Macdonald from that of MacLeod
                    is a Large Fabric made Up of Stone &amp; Lime and was dedicated to <persName ref="pe0066">Columba</persName> And Possessed by a Parcel of his Monks but
                    at Length fell into the hands of the Templars who, it is said, were burned
                    together with it for Stealing the Cows in the Neighbourhood, much about the
                    time, I suppose when <persName ref="pe0117">Pope Clement the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></persName> suppressed that Order at the
                    desire &amp; by the Contrivance of <persName ref="pe0152">Philip the fair of
                        France.</persName></p>
                <p>Here I will remark that the <add place="above">oldest</add> Churches have been
                    dedicated to the Family of <persName ref="pe0236">Christ</persName> or to
                        <persName ref="pe0066">Columba</persName>, Such As the <placeName ref="pl1631">Church of the Family</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl1632">Carenish</placeName> of <placeName ref="pl0853">Uist</placeName>,
                        <placeName ref="pl0843">Kil-Christ</placeName> of <placeName ref="pl0839">Strath</placeName> And to <persName ref="pe0066">Columba</persName>, Many.
                    In the Later times when Saintship peeped in to our Corner. <persName ref="pe0334">St Mary</persName> St Clement<note type="editorial">Possibly a
                        reference to <placeName ref="pl1633">St Clement's Church</placeName>,
                            <placeName ref="pl1634">Rodel</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl0954">Harris</placeName>. The exact identity of the dedicatee is
                        uncertain.</note>
                    <persName ref="pe0394">St Asaph</persName> and more of them were honoured with
                    Religious Edifices. The Gaulic name of a Church is Clachan, from a Stone which
                    was originaly put up in the place and consecrated, next, Kile from Cella where a
                        <add place="above">hut</add> was put up for some Culdee but now it is
                    Generally called Eglish which is Surely derived from the Greek.</p>
                <p>Some of our Lakes have been Also consecrated — there is a remarkable one of them
                    in this Parish, <placeName ref="pl1635">Loch Shiant</placeName>, which is
                    distilled from Other two Lakes from which there is no Visible Run, thro a hill,
                    by four And twenty Springs Which fall into a pretty bason And so the Lightest
                    And most transparent Water I Ever saw. Sick people have often come to bath in it
                    And by the power of Imagination As much As by the virtue of the Water have
                    returned home in much better health than before.</p>
                <p>Of Incantations</p>
                <p>There is none of the common Maladies or distressful Accidents incident to Man or
                    Beast but they had a particular Charm cut out for Each of them. And tho they Are
                    Mostly made Up of Unmeaning Jargon And a Religious Address to the Deity or to
                    Some of the Saints, the Love of Health and the power of Superstition have
                    reconciled many to the Use of them but they are now thorowly cured of that
                    folly. I have picked up Several of these Charms When I was a boy And will here
                    Subjoin the translation of that for the Toothach: "<persName ref="pe0674">Abraham</persName> Stood on the Summit of <placeName ref="pl1636">Mount
                        Pesselane (Montpelier)</placeName> grievously tormented with the Toothach
                    And complained. <persName ref="pe0236">Jesus Christ</persName> answered And
                    said, Let Neither Worm, nor Cold Rheum, nor pain Lodge in you Gums Any Longer —
                    All Countries, the most Civilized have had their Vulgar Errors And Incantations
                    were Every Where Much practised. Those amongst Us Seem to have been fitted by
                    designing priests to the Religious System they taught.</p>
                <pb/>
                <fw>p.6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></fw>
                <p>The Extreme Ignorance of the people made way for the most Extravagant
                    Superstition without fearing Any contradiction on the part of Phylosophy, to
                    which Palmistry, presages by the flying of Birds, the prophecy of Dumb persons,
                    the Second Sight, the taking away the Substance of a Neighbour's Milk &amp;c
                    owed <add place="above">also</add> their Existence and a Long-lived Custom
                    prolonged their <unclear reason="illegible">date</unclear> When we were a Little
                    more Enlightened, but of all this Trumpery their are no traces now remaining,
                    tho in my Memory the Belief of some Silly persons was Strongly Tinctured with
                    it.</p>
                <p>Of Salt</p>
                <p>In all the Islands their Salt was Originally made of burnt Sea ware. I have Often
                    Eaten Cheese cured with it. They Seldom Use it now Except in <placeName ref="pl0737">St Kilda</placeName> And Among poor people in the Smaller
                    Isles. I remember <persName ref="pe1913">Old Kingsburgh</persName> told me that
                    he Saw flesh Cured after this Manner in his Stepfather's House in <placeName ref="pl2473">the Long Island</placeName>. We call it in our Language
                    Mur-Luah that is the Ashes of Mur. Any Solid body fallen into Ashes or Small
                    particles is Mur. Thus we Learn from <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0635">Pliny</title></bibl> that the Germans burned Oaks And Other woods And
                    Extinguished the Coals with Salt water or When at a distance from the Sea with
                    Mineral Water And Used the Ashes for Such under the Name of Muria. They thought
                    a Well impregnated with Nitre so very Necessary in An Operation of this sort
                    that <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0342">Tacitus</title></bibl> informs
                    Us that the Hermondurians &amp; Catti fought a horrid rather than a bloody batle
                    for the property of One of them. From this it appears that this kind of Salt was
                    once in general Use.</p>
                <p>Of Husbandry</p>
                <p>When a Stranger comes in to the Isles in the summer season and sees our fine
                    Expansive fields, Such as we have in this Parish where I now reside, he will be
                    Apt to imagine that it is owing to the Ignorance or Indolence of the People or
                    to both together that they can want bread from themselves or provender for their
                    Catle: but no Conclusion can be more Unjust than this, for they have As much
                    Sense And Sagacity As Any common people can pretend to And it is owing to their
                    health And Strength that they Are Able to beat the toil they Undergo. The soil
                    they strugle with in my Neighbourhood is not of the Light Loose kind which they
                    coud Easyly turn With the Plough, it is for the Most Part, of a deep Clay of a
                    Strong texture which they must till with crooked Spades that it might be fairly
                    Laid out before the Sun And Air, Which by this Management yields a plentiful
                    Crop without Any Manure. The Second And third Crop they raise by Means of the
                    Plough And Where they think its Necessary help the Growth <pb/><fw>p.7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></fw> By laying on Dung from their Bires or
                    Middens or if they Are near the Shores &amp; mean to raise Barley by plenty of
                    Seaware. This Expence of Labour on a rich Soil woud seem to promise a Plentiful
                    harvest but nothing can be more uncertain than that. Indeed When the spring is
                    dry, the Summer warm And <del rend="overstrike"><unclear reason="illegible">fine</unclear></del> harvest free of continual rains &amp; storms we
                    have not only plenty for ourselves but Are Able to Supply our Neighbours but
                    this Seldom <add place="above">is</add> the Case. In this very <placeName ref="pl0715">Island of Sky</placeName>, we rarely have one Week of fair
                    Weather If I Except the Summer Season. We Seldom Sow our Seeds Untill our fields
                    begin to dry Up in the month of April And As Seldom have a hot Summer Which must
                    needs retard our Harvest. Our Hay, which is for the most part the Natural Growth
                    is Generally gathered <add place="above">in</add> About the End of August And
                    then Rains <sic>beginn</sic> attended with Moderate Winds which blow stronger as
                    the Season proceeds Untill the Equinoxial Storms, who seldom fail to visit Us,
                    come on And Shake all our Standing Corn And damage Such As Are cut down. When
                    the Weather casts up in this stile As it often doth, there remains great
                    Scarcity for Man And Beast. It may be Said that the Injuries of the Climate
                    might be in a great Measure <add place="above"><del rend="overstrike">be</del></add> prevented by skillful Management; And that the Fields shoud
                    be twice tilled over, — that great Quantities of Manure shoud be Laid on them
                    And that they shoud be plated with the Earliest Corn. Experience is the best
                    Guide in Every Countrey — our Landlords And others have sometimes been very
                    Unsuccessful in Attempts of that kind And indeed the Generality of the People
                    are by this time too poor to quit the beaten Track And must decline to run into
                    Uncertainties. That Maxim of old <persName ref="bi0663">Cato's</persName> holds
                    good here in a Particular Manner Nihil Minus Expedire, quam Agrūm Optime colere.
                    The Small oats hath, by the Experience of Ages, been found the fitest for our
                    Climate, as being less lyable to Shakeing; the Barley indeed woud prevent the
                    storms but they are deficient the Article of Manure to raise Any considerable
                    Stock of it. In short the people drudge<unclear reason="illegible">'s</unclear>
                    on in mending their Inclosures which are made of Turf, in makeing folds for
                    their Catle, in Cutting And drying their Peats, in weeding their Corns, in
                    Mowing their hay, in Shearing in thatching their houses And tillage And if
                    thorow bad weather or Any other Accident they Are Late in Any of these Articles
                    that Inconvenience rūns tho' the whole work of the year. I must not forget that
                    potatoes, the best present we Ever had from <placeName ref="pl0697">America</placeName>, is Lately become a great source of Relief — that And
                    the Herring-fishing when it casts Up in a Neighbourhood is now a Mighty
                    preservative from Want.</p>
                <p>The Foggy Uncertain Climate hath Certainly contrived this Country for Pasturage —
                    that high Cluster of hills in the heart of the Island <add place="above">(<placeName ref="pl0841">Kullen</placeName>)</add> us So very prolific
                    of Rain And Storms that we can depend Upon Nothing but our Catle And that Only
                    in a <pb/><fw>p.8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></fw> Good or Middling year for
                    if the Crops set upon the Ground or the hay — harvest is too Late, they will
                    certainly yield to the Severity of a bad Spring. Yet our Rents, our implements
                    for tillage, our drink, our Everything must be derived from the Sale of black
                    Catle. The General Marrain which prevailed Among the in Spring Last, the great
                    fall in the price of those that remained the purchasing of meal from distant
                    Countries And the Absolute want of Specie' which hath all gone to <placeName ref="pl0697">America</placeName> hath reduced the people to a Most dismal
                    Situation.</p>
                <p>You are So good As to Mention the Hospitality you met with; had You come ten
                    years Ago you had Seen Every thing wear a different face — You had been conveyed
                    from district to district by a <hi rend="underline">Cavalcade</hi> of the better
                    sort of Men And their Sincere attempts to make you happy woud make you really
                    So. The people seem apprehensive that these days will not soon return — they are
                    much fallen from their Usual Chearfulness and Industry, being Uncertain whether
                    it is their fate to Pass <placeName ref="pl1084">the Atlantic</placeName> after
                    their Friends or Stay at home Strugling with difficulties Among the Beggars
                    &amp; Bastards And Other Silly Connections of those who went Abroad As well As
                    Among the poor which naturally cast up And must Multiply pretty fast in Such a
                    Land As ours.</p>
                <p>There is an Emigration to <placeName ref="pl0697">America</placeName> Sett on
                    foot on the 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> past in this Countrey to Which Some
                    from <placeName ref="pl2656">Kintail</placeName> on the Continent have acceded
                    tho there is no Return from the Ship which Sett out in September Last for
                        <placeName ref="pl2657">N. Carolina.</placeName> The spirit of Emigration is
                    now become a distemper of a Most <add place="above">contagious</add> Kind — the
                        <hi rend="underline">Enthusiasm</hi> flies from face to face, Which took
                    it's rise from an Injudicious Augmentation of Rents. Add to this that the
                    Leading Clan or in other words the Cadets of the Proprietor's family had more
                    Respect And favour Shewed them than the Inferior Tribes And in particular Made
                    up their Chief's Privy Council And were Generally Employed As his Factors and
                    Drovers, the Only Offices of profit &amp; Respect in his Gift. If one were all
                    at once to break with his <sic>olds</sic> friends &amp; put himself into the
                    hands of a few of the Smaller Tribes the Former had no Cause to Look for Mercy
                    or favour And woud probably put themselves at the head of the discontented and
                    Lead them Away While Any One of them Remained. <unclear reason="Illegible">Amicitiæ Magis Sunt descendæ quam descindendæ</unclear> is a good General
                    Rule. How these Evils can be remedyed is to the wrong side of My comprehension —
                    I was one of the very few who declined to declined to buy Repentance at the rate
                    at which it Sold at our Sell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <opener>Sir</opener>
                <p>I received your polite Letter by Last Post and sat down to write the Enclosed
                    Papper, Which only contains what Offered itself at the time without that
                    Regularity and Order which the Honour and Respect I bear You woud require at My
                    hands. I had no Amanuensis near me and the Emigration now on foot to <placeName ref="pl0697">America</placeName> And the Relaxation in Public Discipline
                    Employs Many of Us not Much to our Taste. I am Upon the whole Obliged to send
                    You the Papper As it came warm from my head — You can however Make Something of
                    it And fil a Paragraph here And there from it, to Your Design. I will next send
                    you some Account of the Monuments of Druidism which lie thick Scattered over the
                    face of the Countrey And from their Numbers declare that the Antient Inhabitants
                    were Religious over Much; yet before I give you further trouble I woud Incline
                    to know Whether you Immagine that in My way of Writing, it may be worth your
                    reading.</p>
                <p>Your <sic>Humany</sic> and public Spirit determined you to take some Concern in
                    the Misery of this Countrey — May Every Attempt for relieving it Prosper.
                    Whatever Information My Prudence and Abilities will permitt me to good will not
                    be wanting</p>
                <closer><salute>As I am with <lb/>Sincere Esteem Dr Sir <lb/>Your most Obedient
                        humble Servant</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0069">Don: Macqueen</persName></signed>
                    <dateline><placeName ref="pl0742">Kilmuir</placeName> January 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                        <lb/>1773.</dateline></closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Near the Seat of Every great Man, there stands a hill called Cnock an Eirich
                        that is the hill of pleas, where they held their General Council and the
                        Chieftain with the Assistance of his best friends, his Assessors determined
                        all the differences that subsisted within his Tribe.<note type="editorial">MacQueen's account of the 'hill of pleas' is integrated into Pennant's
                            description of Duntulm in <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0008">A
                                    tour in Scotland and Voyage to the Hebrides 1772</title></bibl>
                            (1774), p.350.</note> There is one of these hills at <placeName ref="pl0666">Kingsburgh</placeName>, at <placeName ref="pl0667">Duntulm</placeName>, at <placeName ref="pl2658">Ulimsk</placeName>.
                        When our <persName ref="pe1914">King Malcom</persName> feūed out his Lands
                        to his Barons, he Only reserved for himself <placeName ref="pl2659">Mote-hill</placeName>, now called <placeName ref="pl2659">Muthill, of
                            Scoon</placeName>
                        <add place="above"><placeName ref="pl2659">mons placiti de
                            Sconâ</placeName></add> where he determined the Pleas betwixt his
                        Barons, for Mote is the Gaulic word for a Court.<note type="editorial">The
                            legend of an ancient constitution Scottish constitution founded on a
                            feudal community of the realm as an important article of Boece's <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0134">Scotorum
                                historiae</title></bibl> and the fourteenth-century legal digest
                                <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0739">Regiam
                                Majestatem</title></bibl>. These documents form the basis of
                            Pennant's account of the Moot Hill of Scone in <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0010">A tour in Scotland 1772, part
                                II</title></bibl> (1776), p.115. See also Colin Kidd, <hi rend="italic">Subverting Scotland's Past</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge
                            University Press, 1993). </note> Of Old they held their Civil And
                        Religious Assemblies in a grove or in the Top of a Mountain consecrated to
                        the Supreme or to Some of the Subaltern Divinities, Which was a Sanctuary
                        Where Peace And Civility Must be Observed Under the Eye And Protection of
                        the Guardian of the State. A precaution the Absolutely Necessary Among these
                        ferocious Military Mortals And from this practice surely our <hi rend="underline">Cnock an Eirich</hi> derived all its Importance.</p>
                    <p>There is near <placeName ref="pl2660">the house of Aird</placeName> in My
                        Neighbourhood, a vein of Limestone of Considerable Extent Which is no Other
                        than An Aggregate of Various Shells — Some of them we know And Others Are
                        not to be met with on our Coasts.</p>
                    <p>Burning the Bodies of the dead was a practice in this Island in a very
                        distant Period — It was done <add place="above">in</add> honour of the great
                        men among them Who had Signalised themselves in Military Prowess. Their
                        Ashes were Laid up in Urns made of Clay which covered with a thin stone were
                        put into a Stone-coffin covered over with a prodigious heap of stones. Many
                        Urns have been found within One of these heaps. They Are very Numerous in
                        this Island. called in our Language Barp, <add place="above"> or Cairn</add>
                        whence perhaps the English word Barrow.</p>
                    <p>I have been often Surprized to hear the Old men in the Isles Speak As if
                        their Ancestors had Some faint Knowledge in Astronomy. They Are Still
                        Acquainted with the Pole, Charles-wain Which they call Seackeran, ie the
                        Seven Stars, the Pleiades And a few more. In the Heroic times when Robbery
                        was attended with not Infamy but reckoned honourable if committed with out
                        their own Tribe Men for the Sake of Secrecy were Obliged to keep the Sea All
                        Night in their Long Boats Whither they carryed their Plunder from one Island
                        to Another Or from the Continent. Necessity, the Mother of Invention Put
                        them on takeing Up Some of the Stars for their Guides And for knowing the
                        Progress of the Night. I woud indeed rather attribute their Knowledge in
                        this Respect to Tradition but that I find no traces of it Upon the Main Land
                        Where they had Litle or no Occasion for it, And Indeed that want of Occasion
                        to Use it might be The Cause of the Tradition's dying away among them. Be
                        that how it will, our People Regulate many of their Operations by the Course
                        of the Moon. one thing Succeeds better in the Increase and another in the
                        Decrease and of this Error, if it be an Error, the common Tennants cannot be
                        cured, nor woud I presume to Extirpate it Altogether for if <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0351">Dr mead's Theory of the flux and
                                Reflux of the Atmosphere analogous to that of the Sea</title></bibl>
                        be true, as I believe it is, it must be a Matter of Certainty that the
                        Increase and Decrease have a considerable Influence Upon Many things here
                        below but As that Influence May be counteracted by several other Causes I am
                        sure our people keep too close to their Rule.</p>
                    <p>I trouble you with too much of this Trash. Adieu.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><handShift/>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Macqueen <lb/><placeName ref="pl0715">skye.</placeName></p>
                <p><handShift/><address>
                        <addrLine>To</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Thomas Pennant Esqr.</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>of Downing.</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>To the care of <persName ref="pe0018">Mr Jackson</persName> Secretary to
                            the Post Office</addrLine>
                    <addrLine><placeName ref="pl0076">Edin<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                            —</placeName></addrLine>
                    </address></p>
                <p><stamp type="handstamp"><placeName ref="pl0660">SCONSER</placeName></stamp></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>