<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0409">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Donald MacQueen to Thomas Pennant</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP297</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>3-4</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <additional>
                        <p>The enclosure to this letter is written in a different hand, suggesting
                            the use of an amanuensis.</p>
                    </additional>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0069">Donald MacQueen</persName>
                    <date when="1773-02-28"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0742">Kilmuir</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct0410"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct0408"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gd">Gaelic</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="grc">Ancient Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="enclosed">
                <fw><unclear reason="illegible">p. 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi></unclear></fw>
                <p>On Druidism</p>
                <note type="editorial">A precis of the following treatise on the ancient religion of
                    the Celts appears in Pennant's <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0008">A tour
                            in Scotland and Voyage to the Hebrides 1772</title></bibl> (1774),
                    pp.341-42.</note>
                <p>The most ignorant and barbarous Nations, have had some knowledge of a Deity, whom
                    they worshiped after some one form or other, whether their Notions were born
                    with them, gathered up from Speculations on the Works of Nature or conveyed
                    traditionally from remote Ancestors hath been made a Question. The
                    thoughtlessness and Ignorance of the human Mind, when void of Culture, would
                    determine one to think, that Religion is derived rather from the Instruction and
                    Practice of Ancestors, one after another and if the Religion of our Celtic
                    Fathers be inquired into, it will appear in all its Branches, to be formed on
                    the Belief and Practice of the Eastern Nations where they drew their original
                    which is a Strong and Irrafragable Proof of our proceeding from one Stock, and
                    of our being instructed by one Father; I therefore propose to attempt
                        <sic>deliniating</sic> the Celtic Religion from such traces as remain of it
                    in <placeName ref="pl0711"><add place="above">the</add> Highlands of
                        Scotland</placeName>, and in the Gaulic Language, compared with what can be
                    picked out of the Classical Writers who have transiently touched upon some
                    Articles of their Faith &amp; Practice —</p>
                <p>The Greeks and Romans had assigned Names to their Numerous Gods to distinguish
                    them from one another in the croud; but the object of Worship among the Pelasgi
                    was, said <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0664">Herodote</title></bibl>,
                    the God without a Name, nor had the Supreme Caledonian Divinity any other Name
                    than <persName ref="pe1919">anTi</persName>, that is the Being by way of <del rend="overstrike">En</del> Eminence. The Worship paid him under Druidism is
                    to this day called anTi-oraough that is, the Worship of Ti. The Hills
                    consecrated to religious Services Shian and Tian in the oblique Cases, the
                    Worshiper himself anShieaorah and Ti-eaorah in the other Cases, now an
                    appellation of the last contempt. The well known sharp pointed Flint commonly
                    called the Elf arrow passes in the Gaulic under the Name Saghoid Ti, that is the
                    Arrow of Ti, the spade Caba-shi and the Sacrificial Knife Skian-Ti the Knife of
                    Ti; which three Implements I have just now on the Table before men and are made
                    of Stone. The Worshipers of Ti having in the absolute want of Iron made use of
                    Flint Tools. as the Finni in Ancient <placeName ref="pl1472">Germany</placeName>
                    pointed their Arrows with Bone for the same Reason, and to mention one more
                    compound let me add from memory, that Bhen-Ti or the Wife of Ti <persName ref="pe1918">Bendis</persName> is the proper Name of some Women among the
                    Islanders. Ti or <pb/><fw>2</fw> Dis with a latin tetmination is also the God
                    and Father of the Ancient Gauls. The Germans celebrated in their Songs Teuiston
                    a God according to <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0342">Tacitus</title></bibl> born of the Earth, that is the Son of Teu by Mother
                    Earth, and is no other than the Gaulic Name Heuiston (Hew) which according to
                    the Genius of the language changes the T of the Nominative into H in the oblique
                    cases as Tomois into <unclear reason="illegible">Homirs</unclear> in the other
                    cases. Further the Teutons the Teuatamides of <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0665">Homer</title></bibl> with a Greek termination are the sons
                    or descendants of Teu as the Taurisei are no other than the Inhabitants of the
                    Kingdom of Teu, the debatable <placeName ref="pl2661">Crimea</placeName> of this
                    day. This was the Incorporeal, the inalterable, the God without a Name whom the
                    Pelasgi called Θεos; but as the Greek had no <unclear reason="illegilbe">Listame</unclear> in the time of the Pelasgi θεoς, zεuς, in the Genetive
                    δioς the Latin Deus and Gaulic Dia are derived from the Celtic anTi making but
                    moderate allowance for the Genius of the different languages.</p>
                <p>Man sensible of his own frailty and incapacity and of the boundless Nature of the
                    most high split, as it were, his Idea of Him into many Portions, dwelt on and
                    Worshiped that Portion which was for the present most suited to his own
                    occasions and Necessities. Thus in time of War they worshiped anTi the God <add place="above">of</add> Armies who had the disposal of Victory: in time of
                    Peace anTi the God or good one who blesseth the Fields with Plenty, in time of
                    Despair anTi who infuseth the needful quantum of thought Spirit and Resolution
                    into the Mind. The Superintendant of the Weather who wields the Thunder was anTi
                    horanich Taranis or Fulminator and he who ruleth the World anTu-oirn that is the
                    Being over in a Designation now appropriated to the Highland Lairds. The same
                    Supreme Being was alone equal to all these offices among the Celts though the
                    other Pagans soon degenerated into the Practice of worshiping a Multitude of
                    Gods under distinct Names with distinct Temples and Images. But anTi the Being
                    th I AM, who is co existent with all the points of time and Space could not be
                    inclosed within Walls or drawn under the appearance of Mortal Man. All Space was
                    his Temple among our Ancestors; and when they joined into one all the
                    Perfections they had any Notion of, they were Sensible that this assemblage was
                    an inadequate Representation <add place="above">of</add> him, they therefore
                    Worshipped Him on the Tops of Hills or in secret Groves or in time of War by
                    fixing a Spear or Sword wherever <pb/><fw>3</fw> the General was pleased to
                    Stop, and the Emblem of the Divinity was the Spear or Sword in the later case
                    for by it they Swore and the Practice was brought down to our own times. In the
                    other Caves a rough <sic>shapless</sic> stone or the trunk of a Tree more
                    generally the Oak put them in mind of what they were about.</p>
                <p>The One, the Eternal, the incomprehensible was the Father of Gods And Men in the
                    Creed of our old Fathers, for they allowed indeed of Subaltern Divinities who
                    guided and ruled over the different Departments of Nature according as they were
                    assigned them. The Sun the Moon the Fire the Sea the Lakes the Rivers were
                    committed to the care of different Intelligences who as well as Man were formed
                    by the Supreme Being out of the Earth, for these rough spun Mortals wholly
                    guided by <add place="above">the</add> undistinct tradition of their Progenitors
                    seem never to have bestowed a thought upon the nature of Matter, that be it
                    purified, exalted, Sublimated by the nicest chemical operation it can never give
                    Birth to Spirit, yet as anTi is the Father of all, the Earth in the Celtic
                    Theogony represents <del rend="overstrike">our</del>
                    <add place="above">the</add> common Mother Ben-ti <add place="above">i.e. the
                        wife of Ti</add>. To preserve the Memory of the Creation the Thracian and
                    Scythian Sovereigns affirmed the Name of Colis that is God-li or Coli' Son and
                    the Queen for her honour went by the Name of <placeName ref="pe1918">Bendis</placeName>, which according to Hesubius means the Earth. It is
                    easie to shew that the different Tribes piqued themselves upon their divine
                    descent; among the rest <persName ref="pe1915">Hengist</persName> and <persName ref="pe1916">Horsa</persName> Leaders of the Saxons to <placeName ref="pl2003">South Britain</placeName> asserted their almost <del rend="overstrike">their</del> immediate descent from <persName ref="pe1917">Odin</persName>, the Good one: as well as a tribe of Warriors in a Song of
                        <persName ref="pe0557">Ossians</persName> boasted their being of the
                    Children of Ti, the conceit of the divine origin will only account for that
                    almost universal belief which prevailed among the Pagans of their being Indigend
                    for they cannot <del rend="overstrike">themselves</del> imagined themselves
                    risen up like Mushrooms from the Earth.</p>
                <p>In the Places appointed to public Worship they drew a Circle of Stones to mark
                    out the Sacred Ground, which, though it was a secure Sanctuary to the Wretched
                    whom it was counted Sacriledge to disturb in their passage to it and lay always
                    open to the Priests, was not under the Severest penalties to be profaned by the
                    unhallowed footsteps of the people. Sometimes the Sacred ground was bestrewed
                    with Stones a Signal to the Husbandmen &amp; others not to touch the
                        <pb/><fw>4</fw> Mould for fear of disturbing the operations of the Divinity
                    who was Supposed to be more peculiarly employed there than any where else. In
                    other places there stands a pillar of Stone upon a plain where the Grove which
                    probably set limits to the Sanctuary is no-more to be seen, there are also
                    prodigious Cairns or Barrows in <placeName ref="pl0715">Sky</placeName> which an
                    inconsiderate traveler would be apt to Mistake for a Mercurius Teutatis such as
                    stood near <placeName ref="pl2662">new Carthage</placeName> in <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0261">Livy</title></bibl>, but by the Urns
                    found in the appear to be certainly burial places. The surprising Number of
                    these consecrated placed in this Island bears the strongest Testimony to the
                    religious Zeal of the barbarous Inhabitants, whose idleness and ignorance with
                    the Aid of a little Priestcraft galled them with <add place="above">the</add>
                    chains of a cruel Superstition, every little district which Nature had bounded
                        <add place="above">with</add> Rocks Rivers or Rising ground being an
                    independent Sovereignty and very probably in a declared State of War with the
                    Neighbourhood supplied itself with a place of Worship.</p>
                <p>As in some one period or other the people were equally engaged in the Same
                    religious Solemnities all over <placeName ref="pl1176">Europe</placeName> it is
                    not to be wondered that in different dialects of the same Language or in
                    Languages perhaps quite different the same Divinity should go under different
                    Denominations especially as it was customary to give the Name of the Mount or
                    Grove which was the Seat of Worship to the Spirit of the place. The Greeks and
                    Romans also who made but Slight Observations upon the religious Ceremonies as
                    having come up on more interesting Errands to the barbarous Nations would be apt
                    to find their own Gods where they met with any Similarity in the Worship, and
                    thus our Ancestors are universally charged with Polytheism, and if <persName ref="pe1920">Agricola</persName> his Fleet had stoped in the Harbours of
                        <placeName ref="pl0715">Sky</placeName> when they were sailing in our Seas
                    his son in Law might have pointed out foreign Gods here as well as in <placeName ref="pl1472">Germany</placeName> or <persName ref="pe1921">Cæsar</persName>
                    in <placeName ref="pl2663">Gaul</placeName> though the religious Monuments which
                    remain obviously declare that <persName ref="pe1919">anTi</persName> was the
                    principal Object of Worship as observed above.</p>
                <p>The next object of adoration to <persName ref="pe1919">Ti</persName> was Earth
                    the Mother of all who seems to have been conjoined with the Supreme Father in
                    the August &amp; awfull Solemnities of her Worship, to which She, the Earth,
                    could only be intitled, <pb/><fw>5</fw> being but a rude insensible Lump, by
                    being supposed the Mother on whom <persName ref="pe1919">Ti</persName> begat his
                    Children or the passive Principle from which the Father of all extracted the
                    best of his works. The Solemnities observed in this Worship I shall attempt to
                    delineate when I have only observed that there is no other Monument besides, of
                    the Druidical Divinities preserved here, not even in language alusions, but of
                    the Sun, Fire, Water and very little of the Moon which were considered as the
                    Seats or Temples of inferior Spirits who had some Respect paid them on account
                    of their Usefulness to the human Race</p>
                <p>Anait is a common Druidical place of Worship in <placeName ref="pl0711">the
                        Highlands</placeName> which I suppose hath been instituted in honour of the
                    Earth. There are four of them in <placeName ref="pl0715">Sky</placeName> which
                    go under the Name, and as they are all much of the same situation and
                    Construction, I will only described that near <placeName ref="pl0665">the Castle
                        of Dunvegan</placeName> as being the most intire. It lies in the heart of a
                    plain extensive Muir betwixt the Confluence of two Waters; to the East side of
                    the Muir their stands a Hill and another to the West which gradually
                        <sic>slop</sic> down towards the Plain and from which a full &amp; clear
                    Prospect might be had of all the Motions and Ceremonies that passed below. From
                    the one of these Waters to the other there is a Strong Stone wall built which
                    forms an equilateral Triangle, which by the rocks forcing it towards the Waters
                    where every break and Crevice is filled up with Stones regularly laid seems to
                    have been inaccessible in former days; near the middle of this triangular
                    Inclosure there is erected a Small square Edifice of quarried Stones and on each
                    side of the Gate which leads to it from the above mentioned Wall there are the
                    Remains of two houses both within and without, where it seems the Priests and
                    their Wives and their Servants put up together: the Servants more probably on
                        <add place="above">the</add> out side who were also inclosed within a Strong
                    Turf Rampart from Water to Water, across a rising ground which hath been cut
                    through by an Artificial road, leading from <placeName ref="pl2664">Tempŭl na
                        Hanait</placeName>, for so the Edifice is called, a great way into the Muir.
                    To decypher the <pb/><fw>6</fw>
                    <unclear reason="illegible">Intent</unclear> of this religious Fabrick it is
                    necessary to look into the Antiquities of other Nations for neither our own
                    traditions or Language cast any light upon it</p>
                <p><bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0635">Pliny</title></bibl> speaks of a
                    Country in <placeName ref="pl2665">Armenia</placeName> called <placeName ref="pl2666">Anaitica</placeName> from <persName ref="pe1922">Anaitis</persName> a Goddess in great repute there, where a noble Temple
                    had been built for her which was plundered of all its immense Riches by
                        <persName ref="pe1923">Anthony's</persName> Soldiers in his Parthian
                    Expedition. A Veteran of that Army afterwards entertained <persName ref="pe1924">Augustus</persName> and <add place="above">his</add> Court on the Leg of
                    the golden Goddess. The Temple and the Statue were surely Innovations introduced
                    by the Eastern Settlers on that coast. <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0667">Pausanias</title></bibl> speaks of the Temple of <persName ref="pe1925">Diana the Anait</persName>, <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0668">Plutarch</title></bibl> and others affirm that <persName ref="pe1925">Diana</persName> was called <persName ref="pe1925">Anait</persName> among the Persians where <persName ref="pe1926">Artaxerxes</persName> built Six or Seven Temples for her: so that if we
                    find out the original Worship of <persName ref="pe1925">Diana</persName> before
                    it was corrupted by the improvements and fancies which the Adventurers from
                        <placeName ref="pl2667">Phœnicia</placeName>
                    <placeName ref="pl2668">Ægypt</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl2669">Babilon</placeName> imported into <placeName ref="pl2670">Greece</placeName> we may seem not to have missed our Aim, for <persName ref="pe1925">Diana</persName> was a Celtic Divinity whose Worship was
                    introduced to <placeName ref="pl2670">Greece</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl2671">Asia Minor</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1164">Italy</placeName> from the <placeName ref="pl2661">Taurica
                        Chersonesus</placeName> and <add place="above">there were</add> several
                    stone Representations of her in <placeName ref="pl2663">Gaul</placeName>. <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0669">Hesubius</title></bibl> says that
                        <persName ref="pe1925">Diana</persName> is the same with <persName ref="pe1918">Bendis</persName> and that the Athenians thought so and
                        <persName ref="pe1918">Bendis</persName> was the Earth the Wife of Colis or
                    the God Ti the same with <persName ref="pe1927">Cybele</persName>
                    <add place="above">so called from a mountain in <placeName ref="pl2671">Asia
                            Minor</placeName></add> the Mother of the Gods. The Representation of
                        <persName ref="pe1927">Cybele</persName> brought from <placeName ref="pl2672">Phrygia</placeName> by an honourable Roman <unclear reason="illegible">Dignitation</unclear> at the Suggestion of the Sybilline
                    Priests as an effectual <sic>mean</sic> to drive <persName ref="pe1928">Hannibal</persName> out of the State was no other than a rough unpolished
                    Stone such as the religiosa Silex of Rhea (in Gaulic the Queen) on <placeName ref="pl2673">Mount Ida</placeName> whom the Greeks called also the Earth
                    this Emblem of the Mother of the inferior Gods and of Men was brought to
                        <placeName ref="pl1623">Rome</placeName> after being washed in the
                        <placeName ref="pl2674">Almo</placeName>
                    <add place="above">a small river Which falls into the <placeName ref="pl2675">Tyber</placeName> below that City</add> whither also she was <del rend="overstrike"><gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" quantity="4"/></del> led to be washed in an Annual Procession sometime after the Vernal
                    Equinox until Christianity prevailed over the Pagan Superstition. This Goddess
                    was carried out in a covered Chariot from the Temple on <placeName ref="pl2676">Mount Palatin</placeName> by Patricians and Plebeians and by the Emperor
                    himself when the Government was changed; every one appearing <pb/><fw>7</fw> in
                    what Dress or Attitude he pleased without Distinction of persons, around the
                    Noise of Trumpets Cymbals Pipes the Gambols and songs of the people forming a
                    kind of Concert, to the Air of which the rambled Merrily in a Dance clashing
                    their Arms against their Shields in a regular well timed Measure. To the Sober
                    Spectators the actors in this busy ludicrous Scene appeared as if they were
                    possessed with the Spirit of Distraction. The most valuable part of the people's
                    Riches Jewels precious Curiosities furniture were carried in pomp before the
                    Chariot of the Goddess while two Phrygians went about among the people and T<del rend="overstrike"><gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" atLeast="4" atMost="7"/></del><add place="above">owns</add> in their way like
                    Mendicants applying for an Offering less or more to their Mother who came to
                    Visit them and whose Gifts they all enjoyed. The incessant plague of these
                    squeesing Solicitors became disagreeable to such as were less tinctured with the
                    Enthusiasm I do not, said <persName ref="pe1929">Antistines</persName>, Maintain
                    the Mother of the Gods, for the Gods themselves are able to Support her. Here I
                    would hazard a Conjecture, which I will Submit to the judgement of any
                    Highlander. There is a practice prevaild very much in this Country for time
                    immemorial, that every young Gentleman setting out in the World, or any of the
                    better rank who met with distress, should go about to seek Help, attended with
                    some retainers sometimes to the Number of Ten or twelve. The principal person of
                    this gang was Sollicitor for the Gentleman, explained his Connections Respects
                    and Friends, and in particular the Dependance he had on the person he was
                    applying to at the time, when he left no Argument untouched that ought to
                    Stimulate the Generosity of his Vassals on that occasion. This Engine of civil
                    Extortion was called Bleidoir from the Substantive Blehd, which means unwearied
                    squeesing and is Used in this Country in a bad sense. If ever the Procession
                    above described was practised in this Country in any form, I doubt not the
                    Medicant for the Goddess was called Bleidoir, the rather that there is an
                    unknown Druidical Divinity barely mentioned by some of the Antients called
                        <persName ref="pe1930">Plestorūs</persName>, who seems to be no other than
                    the Bleidoir of the <persName ref="pe1927">Terra Mater</persName>. Be this how
                    it will, the Procession of <persName ref="pe1927">Cybele</persName> went on to
                    the <placeName ref="pl2674">Almo</placeName>, where the Nigellus lapis was taken
                    out of her <pb/><fw>8</fw> Chariot and washed in the pure Stream as formerly
                    according to the Phrygian custom observed in her Purification in <placeName ref="pl2677">the River Gallus</placeName>, and then returned amidst the
                    joyful acclamation and Songs of the possessed Votaries into her Seat on
                        <placeName ref="pl2676">Mount Palatin</placeName>.</p>
                <p>If it appears a certain fact that <persName ref="pe1918">Anait</persName>
                    <persName ref="pe1925">Diana</persName>
                    <persName ref="pe1918">Bendis</persName> and the Mother of the Gods under her
                    several Designations in various Languages and Countries are all on the
                    Ceremonies above described and those of oūr <persName ref="pe1918">Anait</persName> must be in some degree Similar, though the Romans as well
                    as Grecians might have added some in a course of time, and pared off others to
                    give them a less barbarous cast and reconcile them to their own more civilized
                    Manners as they Substituted Men of Straw in place of the human Sacrifices
                    formerly practised and these two Nations were as ready to introduce the Worship
                    of Strange Gods into their Country as the former of them was lavish of the
                    Freedom of their City, and the later too when the State number of their
                    Inhabitants was diminished in any of their Republics, for then they received
                    even Slaves and Bastards, as they believed in a Multiplicity of Gods they were
                    afraid of offending any of them by Neglect, and had a Pantheon or Temple for all
                    the Gods that none of them might be ōmitted as the Athenians besides a Temple of
                    this sort had erected an Altar to the unknown God. To the Description already
                    given I will subjoin another from <placeName ref="pl1472">Germany</placeName>
                    when in a state of Barbarity of the Procession in honour of the Earth, which I
                    will not venture to translate, from an Author so deep in Sentiment and so frugal
                    of his words <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0342">Tac. de Mor
                            Germ.</title> 40</bibl> In commune Herthum id est, Terram Matrem colunt
                        <gap reason="authorial" unit="lines" quantity="3"/> Arcanus hinc terror
                    sanctaque ignorantia quid sit illud quad tantus perituri vident. It is obvious
                    to the first reflection that the Goddess which lay covered in the Chariot was
                    the Emblem of the Earth a Stick or a Stone which they carried about to visit the
                    Neighbourhood which they washed in the Lake to Whom they Sacrificed her
                    Attendants and carried triumphantly to her Sacred Grove again. Thus the Square
                    Chappel within the double fortification of <persName ref="pe1918">Anait</persName>, to which the <pb/><fw>9</fw> Priests only who lodged in
                    the house close by, seem to have had access, was erected for hiding the Goddess
                    from the Eyes of the profane Vulgar where probably the Sacrificial Implements
                    were laid up in company with her, and the artificial road from it to the Moor
                    hath been contrived to make the Procession easy to the Priests untill they met
                    the unhallowed Votaries at a Distance and the <persName ref="pe1918">Anait</persName> is always upon a Water or the Confluence of two more
                    frequently, that they might have the Convenience of her Purification near them.
                    On this solemn occasion all lawsuits all Pleas of whatever kind were hushed:
                    Love, Friendship, Generosity, Hospitality and Charity reigned over all as being
                    the Children of the same Father &amp; Mother Here a Doctrine was figured out,
                    that must have been a necessary restraint upon these ferocious Mortals.</p>
                <p>This same Festival under the Name of Bendideia or Kotittiæ was from <placeName ref="pl2678">Thrace</placeName> introduced to <placeName ref="pl2679">Athens</placeName> where the Priests according to <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0670">Juvenal</title></bibl> were called Baptæ, I suppose
                    from their being plunged in the Water along with the Goddess instead of being
                    drowned as at <placeName ref="pl2680">Sparta</placeName> on the Solemnity of
                        <persName ref="pe1925">Diana</persName>
                    <add place="above">the same Divinity</add> the Boys only underwent a
                    Flagellation instead of being Sacrificed according to the original custom. This
                        <persName ref="pe1925">Diana</persName> had a Feast somewhere else called
                    Limnatidia from her being Situated near a Pond and the same was the Situation of
                    the <persName ref="pe1925">Diana</persName> Taurica if we believe <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0671">Ovid</title></bibl> who staid in time
                    of his banishment at <placeName ref="pl2683">Tomos</placeName> in the
                    Neighbourhood where according to <persName ref="bi0672">Ammianus
                        Marcellinus</persName> the Goddess went under the Name of <persName ref="pe1925">Orsilochi</persName> or <persName ref="pe1925">Orilochi</persName> and I doubt not but this Circumstance is mentioned on
                    Account of her Ablation in the <unclear reason="illegible">Eupine</unclear> Lake
                        <add place="above">when the Strangers whom came to the Court were offered
                        her</add>. It comes very near to a sort of Demonstration that <persName ref="pe1918">Anait</persName>
                    <persName ref="pe1925">Diana</persName> and <persName ref="pe1925">Orsiloch<unclear reason="illegible">é</unclear></persName> are the same
                    Celtic Divinity and their Names have much the same import in Gaulic Anait
                    Ain-ait, that is, the place by the Water, <persName ref="pe1925">Diana</persName> Dia-ian the God by the Water, <persName ref="pe1925">Orilochi or Orsilochi</persName>, Oir or Orse-a-loch the brink of the
                    Lake.</p>
                <p>The primitive Inhabitants of <placeName ref="pl1176">Europe</placeName> giving
                    neither Names or Surnames to their Gods called them Simply <persName ref="pe1919">anTi</persName> the Being to which they joined in the place of
                    Worship or the occasion on which they marked them, which as the Places and
                    occasions were many gave rise to the Conceit <pb/><fw>10</fw> of their
                    Polytheism and the Superstitious Greeks and Romans naturallized the different
                    Designations one after another as so many strange Deities. The Solemnities also
                    of <persName ref="pe1919">Terra Mater</persName> in so many different places
                    gave cause to their introducing so many Female Deities which upon Examination
                    are found all one. The Names were imported from <placeName ref="pl2668">Egypt</placeName> — The Priests of <placeName ref="pl2704">Dodona</placeName> were the first who were prevailed on to adopt them and
                    thereby insensibly overturned their own Religion when Men became the Objects of
                    their adoration instead of Him who is coexistent with all time and Space and
                    thus as far as the Greeks and Romans carried their Victorious Arms among the
                    Celtic Tribes they atempted to bring their own Religion along with them. It was
                    surely after penetrating into the depths of Antiquity that the judicious <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0670">Juvenal</title></bibl> delineating the
                    simple honesty in <persName ref="pe1944">Saturn's</persName> Reign when
                        <persName ref="pe1943">Jupiter</persName> and <persName ref="pe1945">Juno</persName> were Infants and Several other gods had not Existence cried
                    out</p>
                <p><quote>Nec turba Deorum <l>Talis, ut est hodie, contentaque sidera paucis</l>
                        <l>Numinibus miserum urgebant Atlanta minori</l>
                    <l>Pondere ––––– &amp;c.</l></quote><note type="editorial">Juvenal, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0670">Satires</title></bibl>, XIII.
                            Rev. M. Madan's <hi rend="italic">A New and Literal Translation of
                                Juvenal and Persius</hi> 2 vols. (London: 1789), renders the lines
                            thus: <l>'nor was the crowd of gods</l>
                            <l>Such as it is at this day and the stars content with a few</l>
                            <l>Deities, urged miserable Atlas with a less</l>
                            <l>Weight'</l>, ii, p.139.</note></p>
                <p>I shall end with one or two reflections on this Subject just as they offer
                    themselves in my Way. First our Ancestors properly speaking worshiped but one
                    God the Father of all to whom alone and when conjoined in the Annual Solemnities
                    of <persName ref="pe1918">Anait</persName> Human Sacrifices were offered though
                    they paid a Subordinate degree of respect to inferior Intelligences who they
                    supposed were charged with the Care and Superintendance of the several
                    Departments of Nature and the Worship paid the Earth who they knew to be a dead
                    insensible Lump of Matter can arise solely from its being the passive Subject
                    whence they supposed every thing created by the Almighty hand and it is
                    observable that the Divination by Water of the noble Cascade <placeName ref="pl2706">Bereraig</placeName> in the Neighbouring Parish was called
                        <placeName ref="pl2706">Ti-ghairm an-Uisk</placeName>, that is calling on
                    the Name of <persName ref="pe1919">Ti</persName> by Water though it was an
                    Article of their Creed that the Water itself was committed to the care of a
                    particular Spirit. It can therefore be no mistake to believe that the Solemnity
                    above described was originally meant to preserve the Memory of the Creation, in
                    which the Earth when she opens her Bosom in Spring to produce Subsistance for
                    Man and <pb/><fw>11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></fw> Beast represents a Mother
                    after Childbearing who upon her Recovery visits her Relations, is with all her
                    Attendants chearfully and hospitably received by them and because the Women in
                    this case were thought polluted by Jews and Gentles before Purification, this
                    Goddess was Washed before she would be received into her holy Seat. This
                    Universal Tradition of a Creation among barbarous unconnected Tribes adds to the
                    Credibility of the Mosaic history. Next, the practice of Sacrificing animals and
                    among these Prisoners, Slaves or Freemen to <persName ref="pe1919">Ti</persName>
                    and at the Festival in honour of the Earth could only be conveyed by Tradition
                    and that Tradition could arise but from Precept: for who could prevail with
                    himself to think that destroying an innocent Creature could honour God or
                    anciliate his favour if he were not assured upon infallible Authority that
                    sheding of Blood was an acceptable Atonement when attended with a proper
                    Disposition of Mind in the Sacrificer; the whole Ceremony consisting in Prayer
                    to <persName ref="pe1919">Ti</persName>, shedding the Blood and Eating the
                    Victim for people who had but <add place="above">a</add> scanty livelihood did
                    well not to burn the Flesh to no purpose and the Poor among the Greeks were
                    indulged in the same peice <add place="above">of Economy</add>. Human Sacrifice
                    upon a Search into <add place="above">the</add> histories of different Sects and
                    Countries would be found almost universally practised from <placeName ref="pl2707">Mexico</placeName> to the <placeName ref="pl2708">Ultima
                        Thule</placeName>.<note type="editorial">Ultima Thule was the name given by
                        ancient geographers and cartographers to the northern-most island of the
                        world, and was used more symbolically by later writers to refer to the
                        extreme north, though it is also occassionally identified with specific
                        landmasses such as Iceland.</note> The Jews themselves did not escape the
                    infection when the numerous Nations around them were given to this barbarous
                    Inhumanity. Upon the whole the Inhabitants of <placeName ref="pl1176">Europe</placeName> brought their Religion from the East in an early period,
                    but not untill they began to offer Human Sacrifices and to kiss their hands to
                    the Sun and Moon, nor were the Grand Sons or great grand sons <add place="above">of</add>
                    <persName ref="pe1625">Noah</persName> under any Necessity on Account of
                    Multiplied Numbers to exchange the pleasant extensive Plains of <placeName ref="pl1622">Asia</placeName> for the cold Mountainous country of <placeName ref="pl2671">Asia minor</placeName> or the Still more inhospitable Lands of
                        <placeName ref="pl1176">Europe</placeName> ––––– <lb/>turn over</p>
                <pb/>
                <fw>12</fw>
                <p><handShift/>I might properly Enough remark here that their Religious Festivals
                    were Always attended with Songs and dances — that tho Many of the Heroic Songs
                    are preserved As the Military spirit subsisted after the Change of Religion, yet
                    the Zeal of our first Reformers very probably destroyed all Memory of the Sacred
                    Hymns which I am apt to believe is no great Loss to the Curious, for their
                    Religio consisted all in External Ceremonies being very different in Speculation
                    &amp; delicacy. I have heard a Fragment of a Dance song they used at watching
                    their Dead which is Utterly void of Sentiment And the Chorus consists only of
                    bawlings &amp; Exclamations which Animated the dance. I have also hear a more
                    Sober Song contrived to help the Moon out of Labour When Under an Eclipse in
                    concert with the Additional noise of pans &amp; Ketles. They Address themselves
                    to the Golden Queen — the fair one — crying Loud to her in Chorus to Awake — to
                    roll herself — to raise — to Shake off her Covering. The words are Significant
                    but void of Sentiment — Labour and Move stars As the moon gradually clears off
                    her Mask — And I am affraid that Tradition hath brought down to our Herds a
                    small Fragment of that which was sung at the Festival of Anait — It is the
                    Essence of Filthyness and coud not touch any Chaste Ear — the Chorus is a kind
                    of <unclear reason="illegible">Jo Bàche</unclear>. Our old Friends coud form no
                    Idea of a Creation but a very course One And their Indelicacy is still preserved
                    in the Names which they gave to some places in <placeName ref="pl0711">the
                        Highlands</placeName> yet their Chastity was more Pure that of the Present
                    Age. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <opener>Sir</opener>
                <p>I am Sensible how Litle you will be Entertained by the Inclosed Papper Where you
                    will meet with so many words of a Language to which you Are an Utter stranger
                    And a Subject much out of the common road of the Learned: but you have Laid your
                    Commands Upon Me and I obeyed and found so Many Allusions to the Druids And
                    their Custos Ingrained in the Gaulic that I coud not help, sparingly indeed, to
                    Pick Up some of them. There is none of them however, strained to serve the
                    Purpose — they Are the Plain, Literal words without Undergoing the Least degree
                    of Torture. If the subject was worth the Pursuing And my way of managing it
                    Passable you will see there is a great deal more remains Untouched. Confinement
                    by a Cold gave me Time to throw this trouble in Your Way before I <del rend="overstrike"><unclear reason="illegible">received</unclear></del><add place="above">had</add> an acknowledgement of Your having received My Last,
                    for the Confusion we are put into by this Emigration for <placeName ref="pl0697">America</placeName> woud perhaps take Up too Many of My hours which would
                    have been more agreeably Laid out Upon Any the Most barren, obsolete
                    Subject.</p>
                <p>If this comes to Your hand at <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>, you
                    will please present My most humble respects to <persName ref="pe0109">Mr
                        Archibald Macdonald</persName>, who I had Expected woud have made some
                    Effort to Make us Easy. This and the Other Islands in my Neighbourhood Are much
                    in the same situation.</p>
                <closer><salute>I wish You health And Prosperity And I am with much Esteem <lb/>Dr
                        Sir, <lb/>Your very humble &amp; Obedient Servant</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0069">Don: Macqueen</persName></signed>
                    <dateline><placeName ref="pl0742">Kilmuir</placeName> February the 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                        <lb/>1773. <lb/>direct. . . . . by <placeName ref="pl0660">sconser</placeName></dateline></closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>turn over <pb/>I have been informed that you picked up in your Travells in
                            <placeName ref="pl0711">the Highlands</placeName> what we call the
                        Serpent-Stone, found, it is said, among a Cluster of Serpents twisted
                        together in the Open fields and holed thro by their tails when the Substance
                        of it was soft. To this stone our common people attribute many virtues, Such
                        As cūring the bite of a Serpent, Sucess in an Undertaking And particularly
                        Ease And safety to women in Child bed when tyed about the thigh. If it hath
                        not Already Occurred to You, Please to cast your Eye Upon <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0635">Pliny book the 29<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> Chap. 12<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></title></bibl> And You will find this peice of
                        Priest-craft was not confined to our Country — the Gauls had it among them
                        and I am not so much <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" quantity="1"/>urprized that the Stupid Blockhead, the Ludibrium Aulæ augusti Augusti,
                        the <persName ref="pe1946">Deifyed Claudius</persName> shoud Put a Roman
                        Knight to Death for carrying this Bauble about him on an Interesting
                        Occassion As that Millions of Rational Creatures shoud in a Long Succession
                        of Ages reckon this peice of Painted Glass or Any Other insignificant
                        Materials a valuable Acquisition because a Druid passed his word for it
                        Several Centuries ago.<note type="editorial">Pennant describes the '<hi rend="italic">Glain-naidr</hi>' or '<hi rend="italic">Serpent-stone</hi>' in <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0008">A
                                    tour in Scotland and voyage to the Hebrides 1772</title></bibl>
                            (1774), pp.342-43, where, following MacQueen's suggestion, he makes
                            reference to the anecdote from Pliny.</note> An Elderly woman brought me
                        one fo the stones some Litle time since which she had Left her by a Grand
                        mother — the Crust of it was worn Away in different places having been Long
                        And Much Used.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><handShift/>96 <lb/>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Macqueen. <lb/>Druidism.
                    <lb/>glainnaidr.</p>
                <p><handShift/><address>
                        <addrLine>To</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Thomas Pennant Esqr</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>of Downing in Flintshire</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>To the care of <persName ref="pe0018">Mr Jackson</persName>
                            Secretary to the Post Office</addrLine>
                        <addrLine><placeName ref="pl0076">Edin<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                                —</placeName></addrLine>
                    </address></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>