<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0410">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Donald MacQueen to Thomas Pennant</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP297</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>5</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0069">Donald MacQueen</persName>
                    <date when="1773-06-23"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0742">Kilmuir</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct0411"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct0409"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
                <p>I am really Ashamed to Write you at this distance of Time After receiving your
                    last friendly Letter. The confusion, disorder, Law-suits And Emigration in Which
                    My Countrey men are Involved have Arrested our Whole attention at Least have so
                    Shattered And disconcerted Every Serious peice of Study that tho I shoud have
                    had Leasure I had difficulty Enough in Mustering together My thoughts, which
                    were dissipated on different disagreeable Scenes. Our Emigrants from this
                        Isle<del rend="overstrike">s</del> and some parts in the Neighbourhood
                    Exceed six hundred And have Last week Employed one of their Number to fraught a
                    couple of Vessels to Waft them over to <placeName ref="pl2657">N.
                        Carolina</placeName> a considerable deduction of Rents Which <persName ref="pe0447">Sir Alexander Macdonald</persName> was pleased to make in
                    favour of the Small Tennants hath stoped Several who meant to go and had he
                    taken this step Earlier and begun with the Farmers of the first Class
                    particularly with those of his own Tribe who thorow an Indulgence for Time
                    Immemorial had more vigour and Spirit Left them, Matters at this time woud have
                    worn a different face Upon his Estate but he surely hath begun where he ought to
                    have Ended And I do not know but the same may have been the Case among other
                    Proprietors, which if I do not fail much in Point of Sagacity will put a new set
                    of Adventurers in Motion Next year, for some, of the people we call Gentlemen
                    are so much offended at the <add place="above">preposterous</add> preference
                    given to Small Tennants, who in a Countrey void of Trade and Manufacture cannot
                    stand Long, for they acquired their Litle stock in the Service, Only, of their
                    More Opulent Neighbours, who as Standing Alone upon an Extensive grazing woud
                    have raised more Catle, the staple of this Countrey, than a Cluster of Small
                    people with throng families, Unassisted with the foggage And favour of an
                    Obliging Neighbour — but Surely these litle men are more Passive to Every kind
                    of order and whoever Means, Factor, Drover &amp;c to take Any advantage of them
                    will find them Much more Manageable than Others who had some sparks of ambition
                    And Independance in their Constitution. If I take it right <pb/>The Highland
                    Estates shoud have been in a certain proportion parcelled out Among Great and
                    Small Farmers. It is the former gave rise to the Later by being Employed in
                    their Service and by the Countenance they Afterwards gave them — it was they
                    Also keeped Up the Breed of black Catle, who will soon degenerate in the hands
                    of the Later, thorow and Intire inability of grazing them properly, being
                    Obliged to till the best Part of the Soil for the Subsistence of their Numerous
                    families And thorow want of good Bulls which they will not be disposed to
                    purchase from Others. This in a Litle time will affect the payment of Rents, the
                    Education of Children And the Rise of Any of our people abroad who know their
                    Meeting with good Success Supported And Assisted Many of their Friends and
                    Relations at home." Something of this too much.</p>
                <p>Our people do not keep regular Registers of their Parishioners. By the best
                    Information I coud pick up <placeName ref="pl0715">the Isle of Sky</placeName>
                    with the Adjacent Small Isles <placeName ref="pl0718">Rum</placeName>,
                        <placeName ref="pl2707">Egg</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl0653">Canna</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl2708">Isle of Mūck</placeName>
                    contains at present about 12800 Souls <unclear reason="illegible">tho</unclear>
                    <persName ref="pe1947">Captain Salt</persName>
                    <add place="above">Late</add> of <persName ref="pe1948">Skeltons</persName>
                    Regiment told me about a Couple of years after the Last Rebellion that they came
                    Up to fifteen thousand for he caused the Numbers to be taken in the different
                    Parishes when he was Stationed here. I take the decrease to be owing to a Course
                    of bad years And to their fears from the Late Augmentation of Rents which
                    affected their Minds rather than their pūrses and put them Upon Looking after a
                    more benign Climate — It is to the same Course our Clergy Impute the decrease in
                    Marriages &amp; Christenings, as it is owing to the same cause that by the Loss
                    &amp; Sale of black Catle they at Least come one fourth Short of their Numbers
                    in the year 1769. Some years ago it was computed that five or six thousand Cows
                    were annually driven to Market from <placeName ref="pl0715">Sky</placeName> but
                    among these were some Catle from <placeName ref="pl0955">Uist</placeName> And
                    the Sale of the Stock of our Adventurers to <placeName ref="pl0697">America</placeName>, keeps still Up to Something Like that Number but the
                    dealers in Catle Suppose that in a Litle time the Numbers will become fewer And
                    Worse.</p>
                <p>I am informed by the Principal dealer in Kelp among Us that the Annual produce in
                    that Article doth not in <placeName ref="pl0715">Sky</placeName> Much Exceed 215
                    tuns. In <placeName ref="pl0853">North Uist</placeName>
                    <persName ref="pe0447"><unclear reason="illegible">Sir</unclear> Alex<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Macdonald</persName> Part of <placeName ref="pl2473">the Long Island</placeName> they Annually Manufacture about 700
                    tuns And As much on Clan Ranalds part of it &amp; <placeName ref="pl2444">Barra</placeName>. I know nothing of <placeName ref="pl0712">Lewis</placeName> And <placeName ref="pl0954">Harris</placeName>. I have
                    Also got a Note out of the Factor's books of the Multūre <pb/>Paid by the Milns
                    in <placeName ref="pl0715">Sky</placeName> to the Several Land Lords and Judging
                    by this Standard, by the Portions Allowed the Millars themselves And takeing for
                    grantd beside, according to the Judgement of a Sagacious Farmer that a hundred
                    Bolls are annually grinded without Paying Any Multure at all to the poor and
                    others; I conclude that the Annual produce of the Island may be something about
                    8986 bolls two ferlets one peck. There is no Certain Rule to go by in computeing
                    What of our Corns are Laid out Upon our Cows And horses, if I was to form a
                    conjecture I woud not Exceed four hundred bolls one year with another. potatoes
                    are Lately so carefully Cultivated in his Island that they Serve the common
                    people at Least a quarter of a Year in Stead of bread — the Exhalations from the
                        <placeName ref="pl1084">Western Ocean</placeName> which break down in
                    Showers &amp; Storms from the Summits of our hills, <placeName ref="pl0841">Cullin</placeName> in Particular in the Month of September or beginnig of
                    October is Surely the Cause of our frequent Scarcity And to the Poverty of the
                    People the Shortness of their Leases And the Uncertainty in Which they hovered
                    About three or four Years back.</p>
                <p>A friend promised to send me Some sort of draught of the Anait but I have not yet
                    received it, if it be worth the sending you will have it but if I mistake not
                    you <add place="above">may</add> Make it out from the description I sent you
                    which was Exact And Particular.</p>
                <closer><salute>I wish you health &amp; happyness And Am with much Esteem <lb/>Dr
                        Sir <lb/>Your very Obedient And Very humble Sert</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0069">Don: Macqueen</persName></signed>
                <dateline><placeName ref="pl0742">Kilmuir</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl0715">Sky</placeName>
                    <lb/>June 23<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>
                    <lb/><hi rend="underline">1773.</hi></dateline></closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>I Shoud perhaps have observed above that the Westerly <add place="above">wind</add> blows more frequently here than the Other Winds taken
                        together. I heard an Old Farmer account for it in this way: that the Skies
                        are Supported by four Pillars And that <persName ref="pe1949">Hercules</persName>
                        to Shew his Strength put<add place="above">ing</add> his Shoulders to the
                        Western one, removed it a Litle out of its place And there by the Skies
                        which he took for Something Like the roof of a house, inclining that way
                            <del rend="overstrike">was</del> the reason <add place="above">was
                            Obvious</add> Why So Many drops &amp; blasts came from that <unclear reason="illegible">act</unclear>. — </p>
                    <p>Kelp-making</p>
                    <p>The Kelp Manufacturers raise What they call a Kiln near the Shore. It is 12
                        feet Long 4 wide And 3 feet high in the wall which is of Stone, faced on the
                        out Side with turf that Neither wind or rain May get into it. When the
                        Sea-Ware which they cut with Sharing hooks <lb/>turn over <pb/>Is dryed
                        before the Sun they burn it within this Inclosure And Spread the Ware
                        regularly in this fiery furnace with a two pronged fork. When it is
                        Sufficiently burnt into Ashes they work it backwards And forwards with an
                        Iron Like a Garden how And then Only it runs into a Liquid Substance Like
                        Melted glass Which When it cools becomes very hard. Thus they continue their
                        Operation by puting in one Layer After Another Untill the Kiln is filled up
                        And hen they cover it Close with turf that the Air or rain may have no
                        access to it thro Any Crevice for the One or the Other would Soon Moulder it
                        Away. Adieu.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><handShift/>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Macqueen.</p>
                <p>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Macqueen <lb/>Numbers. <lb/>migrations. Kelp</p>
                <p><handShift/><address>
                        <addrLine>To</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Thomas Pennant Esqr.</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>of Downing, Flintshire</addrLine>
                    </address></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>