<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0413">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Donald MacQueen to Thomas Pennant</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP297</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>8</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0069">Donald MacQueen</persName>
                    <date when="1774-02-19"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0742">Kilmuir</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct0414"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct0412"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gd">Gaelic</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="enclosed">
                <fw>p.1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi></fw>
                <p>Poetry, Singing And dancing have been common to all Ages And nations from
                        <placeName ref="pl2712">Terra del Fuego</placeName> in the South Untill you
                    come to the Eskimaux as well as <add place="above">on</add> the whole Length of
                    the Other Hemisphere And from before the days of <persName ref="pe1970">Moses</persName>, who Mentions former Songs, down to our own Times. The
                    most Savage Nations, the most Civilized, as well as the tame Insignificant
                    Inhabitants of <placeName ref="pl0737">St Kilda</placeName> compose, Sing &amp;
                    dance. These are Exercises which I take to be coeval with Society And as natural
                    to man as thought, Speech or Motion. We have a wonderful propensity to Analyse
                    And Simplify human Actions And reduce them to a primitive narrow principle. How
                    much have Phylosophers heated and fatigued themselves in deriving Virtue, some
                    from disinterested Benevolence, some from Self-Love, some from Feeling and
                    others from Reason, Without considering that the Mind As well As the Body is a
                    complex, much diversifyed peice of Workmanship, furnished out with Several
                    Facūlties, Passions &amp; feelings, to Any of Which Complexion &amp; Edúcation
                    may give an Ascendant over the Rest And Each of Which may give occasion in it's
                    turn to any of our Actions. In the same manner they have strained their
                    Immaginations to find out the Origine of Poetry. Many have imputed it to real
                    Inspiration, Some to the Aw, Love &amp; Gratitude struck into the Mind by the
                    presence of the Supreme Being in his Marvellous works. Had they not spoke more
                    Naturally? If they had said in the General, that Men of warm Immaginations,
                    Penetrated with a Lively Sense of External Objects <del rend="overstrike">and</del><add place="inline">or</add> accidents will Express themselves in
                    Terms of the greatest Energy And force And when Simple words come Short of the
                    forcible impressions they have received, they fly to the Use of tropes &amp;
                    figures and Even to the Abuse of the boldest Metaphors. When Plain Language
                    Sinks below them, that of bombast and Exaggeration fills it's place, Especially
                    among those who Labour Under the transports of Enthusiasm or whose passions Are
                    in the Natural Untamed State. In Every Language there are words &amp;
                    Expressions Suited to our Feelings, whether harsh, sweet or calm and came as
                    Easily out of the mouth of a Savage, as he finds his Gestures, Motions &amp;
                    Limbs obedient to his Internal Sentiments And Expressive of them, as well As
                    Language, A Man thus Susceptible of Lively impressions, whether Employed in the
                    Worship of his Maker or in describing the Heroic Actions of a Champion in
                            <pb/><fw>2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></fw> His Tribe or his own Escape
                    from danger or the remembrance of signal Benefits, the Beauties of a Mistress or
                    Whatsoever touched his heart to the quick, wou'd speak in the poetical stile And
                    at Last woud fit it to Feet, Number, Cadence, to help the Memory to preserve it,
                    to please the Ear in the Repetition And to be in full concert with the External
                    Motions of the body, particularly of the Head, hands and Feet, which go Under
                    the Name of dancing. The Odes, singing and dancing went Originally together —
                    Hence are derived these Terms in Poetry, a long foot, a short foot, Scaning,
                    measure, cadence: thus they were Jointly Employed in Public Worship, at Public
                    festivals, Even in going down to Batle And on Every Occasion when he was meant
                    to please or touch the heart.</p>
                <p>When or where Rimeing began is impossible to determine. It woud seem it was of a
                    very old standing in <placeName ref="pl1176">Europe</placeName>, for the poetry
                    among the barbarous Tribes was of that kind, tho, Often, something different
                    from the present Mode in the composition of English and French verses, for
                    sometimes a word in the Midle Answered to that in the End and Sometimes to that
                    in the Midle of the next Line. The Runic poems according to <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0677">Olaus wormius</title></bibl> never had
                    the final Syllables of One Sound, tho there were Rules to direct the Use of the
                    same Letters, of the vowels Especially in Other parts of the Couplet. I am apt
                    to believe that as their Religion, Laws &amp; History were comprehended in
                    Poems, which it was the Ambition of all to Masters of, And in which their
                    Learning consisted, that Rime was introduced As a help to the Memory, for the
                    Rime in the first Line of the Couplet woud naturally Lead them to the Second And
                    the Variety of the Rime depended on the Air to which the Poem was Sung — The
                    solemn Poems of <persName ref="pe0557">Ossien</persName> As well As <persName ref="pe1107">Homer</persName> &amp; <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="pe1971">Hesiod</title></bibl> were put to vocal &amp; Instrument
                    Music And I remember to have heard <persName ref="pe1107">Homer</persName> Often
                    sung to the tune of <hi rend="underline">Coir an Neasa</hi> a Highland Song.</p>
                <p>The Uncivilized Tribes were so Accustomed to hear the Works of their Bards And So
                    much delighted with them, that on Every Occasion they had some Song or Other in
                    their mouths. In the Western Isles we Remember the <hi rend="underline">Beanicha
                        Baird</hi>, i.e. the Bard's blessing at the Wedding, the <hi rend="underline">Coranich</hi>, that is, a Lamentation in dismal Shrieks,
                    which was an Extemporary Effusion in praise of the dead, in which a great Crowd
                    of women often Joined in Jarring discord, agreeable Enough to the Ears of those
                    Whose Relations were mentioned with Extravagant Encomiums — And indeed they
                    Often hit Upon Strong poetical figures, the Offspring of a Mechanical
                    Enthusiasm, for they were not sincere, tho Seemingly Serious &amp; very Much
                    Affected. <pb/><fw>p.3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi></fw> We remember Also their
                    foul and Abusive Satires. But the Poetical talent is now much Laid Aside, for
                    want of honour or Encouragement to support it. I know indeed that the Late
                        <persName ref="pe1867">Sir James Macdonald</persName> setled a Pension Upon
                    a Bard in <placeName ref="pl2473">Long Island</placeName> which he still
                    continues to draw. There are now Some shreds Only of the old Customs preserved.
                    Our Young Men And Women continue to dance to a Song, When they have no
                    Instrumental Music. They Sing Also to Amuse them at their work and to Enliven
                    their Spirits to the hasty performance of it. Our Rowers Sing at the Oar And
                    beat time to their own Music. One Man Sings the words And the whole of them Join
                    in the Chorūs — if they have a good Master, fair Weather And Some Usquebah to
                    drink, they Possess more Unmixed Joy, than the Slaves of <persName ref="pe1972">Cleopatra</persName> when rowing up the <placeName ref="pl2713">Cydnus</placeName> to the Music of flutes, Pipes and harps. This Song is
                    called the <hi rend="underline">Jorram</hi>.</p>
                <p>Our Women Sing After the same manner in time of Shearing down our Corn, And are
                    Surely more hearty &amp; Lively in their Progress than when Silent. The women
                    also sing when grinding their Corn at the hand Miln, as they do when <unclear reason="illegible">wakeing</unclear> their Cloaths on Flakes made of wicker:
                    At this Exercise they drive, with their hands &amp; Sometimes with their feet,
                    the Cloath, after it is sprinkled with a Nauseous decoction of their own
                    Makeing, from one Side of the Flake to the Other, keeping time to the Air of the
                    Song in all their Motions, their Sweet hearts often Looking on, admiring their
                    voice, their air and Every beauty about them.<note type="editorial">Pennant
                        gives an account of the Jorram in <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0008">A tour in Scotland and Voyage to the Hebrides 1772
                            (1774)</title></bibl>, p.334. A description of the songs sung by women
                        at work on the cloth (Luagh) and quern, accompanied by a plate, appears at
                        pp.327-329, <rs ref="ar0359">plate XXXIV</rs>.</note> These sort of Songs
                    were in Use among the Celtic Tribes, from beyond the reach of History and <del rend="overstrike">go</del>
                    <add place="above">went</add> in their Language Under the general name of <hi rend="underline">Litierses</hi> in <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0678">Athenæus</title></bibl> — <hi rend="underline">Laoi-do-herves</hi> i.e. a Song for Work.</p>
                <p>The Indian huts <note type="editorial">Probably a reference to shielings,
                        temporary dwellings used by herdsman. A Moses Griffith drawing of Sheilings
                        on Jura appears in Pennant <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0008">A tour
                                in Scotland and Voyage to the Hebrides 1772</title></bibl> (1774),
                            <rs ref="ar0363">plate XV</rs>, p.246.</note> are often found on
                        <placeName ref="pl2473">the Long Island</placeName> Shore — A few only Upon
                    our Coast which, I am told, are Generally Shūt up in the roots of Tangles. The
                    tangle seed which Nature hath provided with a clammy kind of Gum, to keep hold
                    of Any Solid body it touches, Lighting on <add place="above">or</add> rather
                    near the hut, may, I suppose, in the Progress of it's growth, stretch its roots
                    &amp; fibres over the hut And bring it along with it when pulled down by a
                    storm.</p>
                <p>The name of the Piper you dined with is <persName ref="pe1973">Donald
                        MacArthur</persName> — how Long his Ancestors have been Pipers in the Family
                    of Macdonald, no Man Alive can determine.<note type="editorial">Pennant
                        incorporates elements of MacQueen's history of the MacDonalds and their
                        pipers into <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0008">A tour in Scotland
                                and Voyage to the Hebrides 1772</title></bibl> (1774), pp.347-48,
                        although MacArthur himself is not named.</note> Tradition only informs Us
                    that <persName ref="pe1975">Angus Macdonald, Lord of the Isles</persName>,
                    father to <persName ref="pe1976">John</persName>
                    <pb/><fw>4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></fw> Who marryed <persName ref="pe1977">King Robert the 2<hi rend="superscript">ds</hi> daughter</persName> And
                    Grand father to <persName ref="pe1962">Donald Earl of Ross and Lord of the
                        Isles</persName>, who fought the battle of <placeName ref="pl2486">Harlaw</placeName>, he received in the thirteenth Century with <persName ref="pe1978">O Cane of the County of Colranis daughter</persName>, by way of
                    Dowry Sixty Gentlemen's Sons, when Men were more Esteemed than Money, of which
                    Number <persName ref="pe1974">MacArthur</persName> was one And it is supposed
                    that his grandson played the tempestuous Tune I formerly mentioned called <hi rend="underline">an Ca-gailich</hi>, whose posterity Served in the Office of
                    Piper all the time to this, Excepting when a Minority or Incapacity Might have
                    intervened. The Name of the Instrument in Erse is, <hi rend="underline">pibe-mhore</hi> ie the big pipes. The only person in the Island whom I
                    could trust with <unclear reason="illegible">noteing</unclear>Any Old tunes is
                    Factor to <persName ref="pe0447">the Knight of Macdonald</persName> And Just now
                    at <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinr</placeName></p>
                <p><persName ref="pe1950">Mackinnon's</persName> seat is at <placeName ref="pl2714">Kilmore</placeName>. <persName ref="pe1979">Mr Martin</persName> was a
                    native of this parish.</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe0446">MacLeod</persName> is now at <placeName ref="pl0665">Dunvegan</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl0715">Sky</placeName>, where he
                    Intends to reside till midsummer at Least</p>
                <p>The Birds of Passage which frequent <placeName ref="pl0715">Sky</placeName>,
                    appear much about the middle of October and go off about the Midle of March.
                    Their Motions in coming or going are not fixed to a day, if the month of October
                    is cold winter-like weather they cast Up the Earlyer And if it is a dry warm
                    March they decamp Sooner than Ordinary <add place="above">or vice versa</add>.
                    The woodcock is never Seen in the Parish but one at a time, if there is a pair
                    of them to me met with it is in the month of March. they are more numerous in
                    the woody parts of the Islands, tho I cannot Say there is plenty of them Even
                    there, And as they are not Observed to go or come in Flocks, the Hunter can only
                    Judge <del rend="overstrike"><gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" atLeast="2" atMost="4"/></del> of the time of their Arrival by their Appearance in
                    the woods And of their departure When he finds None there.</p>
                <p>I remember I writ in some former Scrawl, that our Priests seem to have been
                    Marryed And gave it As one of the Reasons for my thinking So, that their
                    Descendants preserve the names of the different orders they came of, Such as Mac
                    and Tagart, the Preist's Son Macpherson the Parson's Son &amp;c. There is an
                    Obvious Objection can be started to this Opinion; That these Ecclesiastics had a
                    dispensation <del rend="overstrike">for</del>
                    <pb/><fw>5<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></fw> For keeping Concubines And as
                    Particular appointments by the Pope of <placeName ref="pl1623">Rome</placeName>
                    put upon some of our Great men to provide certain Priests therein mentioned with
                    a Female Semel in uno quoque Mense ad purgund os re nes. When the begeting of
                    Children was Justifyed by so great And Infallible an Authority, the Fathers
                    needed not be ashamed of the Children, nor the Children of the Fathers. Whether
                    What I formerly writ Obviated this Objection I cannot now remember. But it is
                    certain the first Scots Clergy, the Culdees or Kelle dei, had wives &amp;
                    Children, that the distinguishing tenets of Popery made but a slow progress over
                    the Kingdom, that these primitive Ecclesiastics were not persecuted but allowed
                    to dy out where they were most discountenanced As in the Neighbourhood of a
                    powerful Bishop <add place="above">when that Order was Established among
                        them</add> And that some of them were provided for, even at <placeName ref="pl0371">Dunfermline</placeName>, Untill the End of the thirteenth or
                    the beginning of the fourteenth Century. This and the Neighbouring Isles being
                    at So great a distance from the Metropolis, secured <add place="above">them</add> from the fashions And Opinions Which prevailed in the more
                    Civilized Part of the nation, by seas high Mountains and Extensive Waste Mūirs
                    And withal asserting an Independancy on the Laws And on the Authority of the
                    Sovereign, may be supposed to have conformed very Slightly to the Edicts of the
                    holy Father And to have Litle dreaded the thunders of the Vatican. Further, the
                    Reformations me with no Opposition amongst Us And the Now Popish Island of
                        <placeName ref="pl2444">Barra</placeName>, was protestant As Early As Any,
                    but being an <unclear reason="illegible">Appendage</unclear> of the distant
                    Island of <placeName ref="pl0954">Harris</placeName>, Whose Minister happening
                    to Neglect that troublesome part of his Charge, left it Open to be perverted by
                    Itinerant Priests, who found themselves Uneasy Elsewhere. In Short, our
                    Tradition asserts that the Clergy were maryed And you see how far it is
                    countenanced by Appearances. If the Abbacy of <placeName ref="pl0651">Icolumkill</placeName> had not been often distressed And at Last destroyed
                    by <add place="above">the</add> Norwegian Rovers the Records of it would cast
                    full Light on this And on Several Other branches of Civil &amp; Ecclesiastical
                    History.</p>
                <p>In Mentioning <persName ref="pe1961">Nero</persName> As a player on the Bagpipe,
                    I misplaced the name of <placeName ref="pe1969">Galba</placeName>, which you
                    will Easyly Observe. <lb/>— turn over.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
                <p>I much approve of Your saying Nothing of Migration, tho it was going on when You
                    was here And I heartyly repent to have desired you to Speak to <persName ref="pe0109">Mr Archibald Macdonald</persName> on that head, tho it was on
                    the Encouragement of his writing Me that he woud Endeavour <hi rend="underline">Manibus Pedibus</hi> to stop the further progress of that work.<note type="editorial">See MacQueen's letter of <ref target="0409.xml">February 28
                            1773</ref>.</note></p>
                <p>If you Are pleased to Publish Any Part of the Scrapes I sent you, you will need
                    mend the Sense And the Language, Especially the Latter.</p>
                <p>you will permitt Me to Inform you, that I have a Son, <persName ref="pe1980">John
                        Macqueen</persName> a preacher, Who hath had the Benefit of Edūcation,
                    beyond you Men of his size, from this part of the Countrey, is possessed of a
                    tolerable genius And a good heart, to which Several besides Me woud bear
                    Testimony. When you have read this far, you will be Apt to Say, what is the
                    meaning of All this. — I will Explain that to you.</p>
                <p>I am Just now informed that <persName ref="pe0160">Mr John Maclean</persName>
                    Minister of <placeName ref="pl2656">Kintail</placeName>, on <persName ref="pe0155">Lord S<unclear reason="illegible">ea</unclear>fort's
                        Estate</persName>, close to the Neighbourhood of <placeName ref="pl0715">Sky</placeName> is no more. I wou'd be content to get my Son into this
                    Parish — <persName ref="pe0465">the King</persName> is patron of it, Yet My
                    Lord's Stewards have more to Say in Settling the vacancies on his Estate, than
                    his Majesty or his Lordship — they will, from Motives of their own, recommend a
                    young man to his Lordship and he procure the presentation. I have no Interest or
                    connection with these Men or tho I had, I woud be Loath to Ask a favour of them.
                    If you are acquainted with his Lordship could I ask you to speak to him or to
                    Employ a few minutes of Your Time, in bringing about the Setlement? Is it any
                    Recommendation that he, My Son, is descended of four Ministers Successively, who
                    served in this And the Neighbouring parish, of which My Lords Ancestors were
                    once Patrons And presented My Grand father and Great grand father to their
                    Liveings. It is Like this young man will be Less troublesome to the Heritor And
                    Parishioners, than Any of the Growth of that Estate, being Intent on his Studies
                    And not in absolute want. You Will be so good As to Acquaint me, in Course, What
                    part you will be disposed to Act in this Matter or Wether you shall take Any
                    Notice of it or not — Whatever turn it takes You may Ask me what further Queries
                    you please in your Letter, for You shall Always find Me,</p>
                <closer><salute>with much Esteem, Dear Sir, <lb/>Your Affectionate &amp; very
                        Obedient Servant</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0069">Don: Macqueen</persName></signed>
                    <dateline><placeName ref="pl0742">Kilmuir</placeName> february 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                        <lb/>1774.</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><address>
                        <addrLine>To</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Thomas Pennant Esqr,</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>of Downing in Flintshire.</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>South Brittain — </addrLine>
                    </address></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>