<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0415">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Donald MacQueen to Thomas Pennant</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP297</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>10</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <additional>
                        <p>Corrections and letter written continuously on one sheet.</p>
                    </additional>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0069">Donald MacQueen</persName>
                    <date when="1774-05-04"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Kilmuir</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct0416"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct0414"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gd">Gaelic</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="enclosed">
                <p>Corrigenda</p>
                <p>In stead of three page 295 Line the 11<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> read free.
                    Refer to <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0087">Torfæus</title> p.37</bibl>
                    rather than 36. <placeName ref="pl2720">Ugg</placeName> may, for ought I know,
                    have some connection with <persName ref="pe1983">Uggerūs</persName>, a poet of
                    whom there is no mention in the 193<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>p. of my coppy
                    of <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0087">Torfaeūs</title></bibl>.<note type="editorial">See Pennant <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0008">A
                                tour in Scotland and Voyage to the Hebrides 1772</title></bibl>
                        (1774), p.345. According to Pennant's note, 'Uggerus' is mentioned in Saxo
                        Grammaticus, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0086">Gesta
                                Danorum</title></bibl>.</note> In our Language however, <placeName ref="pl2720">Uig</placeName> is a dark hollow and <placeName ref="pl0181">Wick</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl0823">Suther Land</placeName> is of
                    the same <add place="above">name</add> And Situation. Page 303 Line 20<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> you are right in calling <placeName ref="pl0667">Dun-tuilm</placeName>, the Castle of the round Grassy Eminence, but you
                    might have Observed that it derived its name from the Rocky Island yoū mention
                        <sic>two Lines two Lines</sic> below, properly <placeName ref="pl0852">Holme</placeName>, which is an Island on the Sea <add place="above">near
                        the</add> Coast As well As in a River, of which there are Several Instances
                    in these Islands. If the old name of <placeName ref="pl0052">Durham</placeName>
                    which the Romans of Your Country Latinized, Musically Enough, into <placeName ref="pl0052">Dunelmūm</placeName> was to be pronounced in Erse it would be
                    no Other than <placeName ref="pl0052">Dun-tuilm</placeName>. Page 304 Line 2<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> instead of Chock read cnock.</p>
                <p>You will need review the third paragraph of the 306<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>p. The Number of Inhabitants within the bounds of the Presbytery of
                        <placeName ref="pl0715">Sky</placeName> may be something 'twixt twelve and
                    thirteen thousand souls: But the Smaller Islands of <placeName ref="pl0718">Rum</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl0653">Canna</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl2707">Egg</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl2708">Isle of
                        Muck</placeName> make Up one of the Parishes of that Presbytery, tho the
                    Minister draws more than a third of his stipend from <placeName ref="pl0715">Sky</placeName> And these Small Islands as they Are called may be supposed
                    to contain at Least two thousand of that Number. When Your Correspondent
                    mentioned <persName ref="pe1947">Captain Salts</persName> having got a List of
                    fifteen thousand Souls, he is apt to believe that the <placeName ref="pl0896">Island of Coll</placeName> was in the Number of the Small Isles which
                    Joined to <placeName ref="pl0715">Sky</placeName> contained that number of
                    Inhabitants. When he Also Spoke of the thousand's having crossed the <placeName ref="pl1084">Atlantic</placeName>, he coud not mean that they all went from
                        <placeName ref="pl0715">Sky</placeName>, for many of them came from the
                    Opposite Coast of the main Land And from the Neighbouring Islands. It is more
                    proper to be general in this thing than very Precise as to Numbers, for all the
                    Ministers have had public Orders, to make Up Lists of the Emigrants from their
                    Several Parishes And the Proprietors, at Least One of them, hath given Orders to
                    Make Up Lists Upon his Estate And if they Intend to be captious may contradict
                    Any the Smallest deviation from Truth. Page 308 Line the 14<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> the Sentence beginning with the words "the Use
                    of the first &amp;c is not Level to my Understanding. Page 312. Line the 8<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi>
                    <placeName ref="pl2721">Bordh-mor-mhicLeod</placeName> Shoud be called
                        <placeName ref="pl2721">Bordh-mor-mhicDhomnail or Macdonalds great
                        table</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
                <p>I made a return to your former Letter some weeks ago And the Last remained in the
                    Office for Some <add place="above">days</add> Longer than it ought Else you had
                    heard from Me Sooner. I cannot but congratulate with the Public, in your being
                    possessed of a Talent to work up Even small matters into Importance And dress
                    them in the mos agreeable colors — I wish with all my heart, you may Enjoy Long
                    Life &amp; health to do honor And give further Satisfaction to your
                    Countrey.</p>
                <closer><salute>I am with real Esteem Dr Sir <lb/>Your very Obedient And very humble
                        sevt,</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0069">Don: Macqueen</persName></signed>
                    <dateline><placeName ref="pl0742">Kilmuir</placeName> May the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                        <lb/>1774.</dateline></closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>An Anecdote.</p>
                    <p>If Tradition is to be credited this Prophecy was banged up And carefully
                        propagated on the Setlement of <persName ref="pe0066">Columba</persName> at
                        his favourite Island of <placeName ref="pl0651">Hi</placeName>, in order to
                        draw the Religious from Every Neighbourhood to Associate with him in it,
                        "That Seven years before the Conflagration; <placeName ref="pl1084">the
                            western Ocean</placeName> woud Overflow all Islands in one Nights time,
                        And that over the green And pleasant Isle, the <placeName ref="pl0651">Hi</placeName> of <persName ref="pe0066">Columb the Clerk</persName>,
                        would Swim on the surface of the Waters.<note type="editorial">See Pennant,
                                <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0008">A tour in Scotland and
                                    Voyage to the Hebrides 1772</title></bibl> (1774), p.284, and
                            John Stuart's letter of <ref target="0428.xml">December 31
                            1773</ref>.</note></p>
                    <p>This Prophecy which runs in metre soon made it's way And among an Ignorant
                        superstitious people, produced more than the desired Effect, for the Notion
                        Which was Spread of the distinguished Sanctity of the Island was Surely the
                        Cause why Kings, princes &amp; great men made choice of it for their Burial
                        place. It is not to be doubted that this Prophecy might work the better, the
                        Manufacturer of it brought the Conflagration close within View And gave out
                        that this great Catastrophe was to happen in that Generation or in the next;
                        Which is the Less Surprizing that in all Nations as far As our Histories
                        reach, it was a mighty Engine in the hands of Monks, Phylosophers &amp;
                        Poets to work their Purposes into the hearts of Men. The Monks put it So
                        close home to their Votaries, that in Several of the Charters granted to
                        them are these words — adventante Mundi Vespers — the Evening of the world
                        being at hand, I make over these Lands for the Salvation of my own Soul And
                        the Souls of My Relations And if it be so that the Dance called the
                        Conflagration Which I mentioned in my Last<note type="editorial">See MacQueen's letter of <ref target="0414.xml">April 11, 1774</ref>.</note> was Druidical there was a good Enough foundation in the
                        minds of the people of Every denomination for the Reception of the Above
                        Prophecy And it appears from the History of <persName ref="pe0066">Columba</persName> that his mind was well Enough turned for Useing
                        Every Art which tended to Produce the Reformation of Mankind.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><address>
                        <addrLine>To</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Thomas Pennant Esqre</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>of Downing in Flintshire.</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>South Brittain</addrLine>
                    </address></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>