<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0416">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Donald MacQueen to Thomas Pennant</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP297</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>11/1-2</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <additional>
                        <p>Corrections and letter written continuously on one sheet. Item 11/2
                            consists of a slip of paper bearing simple outlines of three irregularly
                            shaped stones (the 'gruagich-stones' mentioned by MacQueen) with a scale
                            indicating their size in feet.</p>
                    </additional>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="">Donald MacQueen</persName>
                    <date when="1774-08-18"/>
                    <placeName ref="">Kilmuir</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="0417"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="0415"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gd">Gaelic</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="fr">French</language>
                <language ident="grc">Ancient Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="enclosed">
                <p>Before the Arts of carving ingraving or the Statuary work were invented or in the
                    Countries into which they were not introduced, Representations of the Divinity,
                    whither high or Subordinate, were no other than the trunks of trees or rude
                    unformed stones.<note type="editorial">MacQueen's account of the Gruagich in
                        this letter is included in an appendix to Pennant,<bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0010"> A Tour in Scotland 1772, part
                            II</title></bibl> (1776), pp.434-38.</note> The Emblem of the Supreme
                    God at <placeName ref="pl2704">Dodona</placeName>, consecrated by the
                    Hyperboreans, was the trunk of an Oak And So it was in the <placeName ref="pl2722">Massilian Grove</placeName> ––––– simulacra que mistei Deorum
                    Arte carent, cosis que extant informia trūncis. The Emblem of <persName ref="pe1981">Apollo</persName> at <placeName ref="pl2723">Delphi</placeName>, set Up by the Pelasgi, the Primitive Inhabitants of
                        <placeName ref="pl2670">Greece</placeName>, was no Other than a pillar of
                    stone, Several Examples are mentioned by <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0679">Clemens Alexandrinus</title></bibl> as Also by <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0669">Eusebius</title></bibl>. As the Celtic
                    tribes worshiped Spiritual Gods, Whether the Supreme or Subordinate ones, they
                    well knew that Material Representations coud not be Expressive of them, tho the
                    trunk of a tree or a stone coud very well mark out the Place of Worship in a
                    grove or on the Summit of a mountain, Where the Small Societies in the
                    Neighbourhood might convene on Solemn Occasions or As the Necessity of A
                    Community might seem to require, in order to conciliate the favour and
                    Assistance of the Divinity whom the resorted to. Men of different religious
                    Principles have often been Unjust to One Another, in the common Charge of
                    Idolatry, which the Protestants Lay to the Account of Catholics, the Catholics
                    to the Account of Pagans of all denominations And which they all refúse, who
                    know best what they Are Employed About. They Surely Pray, Such of them As can
                    think, not to a stock or a stone, w<add place="above">h</add>ither in the state
                    of Nature or formed by Art into a statūe, but to the Divinity of which the One
                    or the Other is an Emblem. Among the variety of Subaltern Divinities, which the
                    Celtic tribes worshiped, the Spirit of the Sun was the foremost rank: the Sun
                    being the most chearful And the most Universally beneficent of all created And
                    visible beings. It brought Joy and gladness along with it to all the Animal
                    Creation, to Groves To fields and Meadows. The day of it's retūrn was celebrated
                    in Every district by a <hi rend="underline">feu de Joye</hi>, Whence May-day was
                    called in the Gaulic La-Beltein, the day of Bel's fire, <persName ref="pe1984">Belis</persName> being one of the names of the Sun in <placeName ref="pl2663">Gaul</placeName>. <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0680">Herodian</title><biblScope unit="volume">Lib. 8.</biblScope></bibl></p>
                <p>The Worship of the Sun was so frequent that Several mistook if for the Principal
                    Object of Adoration. The Inclosures called Granan or Granham, the house of the
                    Sun, are to be met with Every Where, in Which they offered their Sacrifices,
                    commonly horses, burnt up betwixt two Large fires. Whence is derived the Proverb
                    — he is betwixt two Beltein-fires — which is applyed to one in the hands of two
                    Artful persons, whose Intrigues he is not Able to Escape. From these inclosures
                    they Also received Oracular Responses.</p>
                <p>When the Elegant Arts were Invented the Celtic Deities appeared carved, ingraved
                    or painted in such forms As the Immagination of the workman Suggested to him as
                    the most Emblematic And Expressive of the common conceit they Entertained of the
                    Divinities they meant to point out. There they changed the rude Lumps into
                    figures resembling Living Creatūres, generaly into Men as bring the most
                    honourable forms. The Spirit of the Sun or the God who according to the Antient
                    Creed guided it in it's course, was figured out as a young Lively man with long
                    yellow dishevelled hair: Under this appearance <persName ref="pe1981">Apollo</persName> hath the Epithet of <unclear reason="illegible">Xευσο-κομoς</unclear>, the golden haired given him by <persName ref="pe1985">Euripides</persName> and of <unclear reason="illegible">aκερσε-κομος</unclear> the Unshaven by <persName ref="pe1107">Homer</persName> alluding to the beams of the Suns which Are Long And
                    Yellow. This Immaginary conceit of the Hyperborean <persName ref="pe1981">Apollo</persName> made its way to <placeName ref="pl0711">the Highlands of
                        Scotland</placeName>, where to this day he is called by the name of
                        <persName ref="pe1981">Gruagach</persName>, the fair-haired. The
                    Superstitious or warm Immagination of Ignorant People introduced him as a
                    Sportive Salutary guest into Several families, in which he played many
                    Entertaining tricks And then disappeared. It is Litle more than a Century ago
                    Since he hath been Supposed to have got an honest Man's daughter with Child at
                        <placeName ref="pl2724">Shulista</placeName>, near <placeName ref="pl0667">Duntulm</placeName> the Seat of the Family of Macdonald, tho it is more
                    probable that one of the Great man's retinue did that Bussyness for him.</p>
                <p>But tho' the Gruagich offers himself to Every One's fancy As a young handsome man
                    with fair tresses, his Emblems, Which Are almost in Every Village are no Other
                    than rude Unpolished Stones of different figures Just as they Seemed to cast Up
                    to the hand of the Druid who consecrated them. Carving was not introduced into
                        <placeName ref="pl0708">the Hebrides</placeName> And tho it had, Such of the
                    Unformed Images As were preserved, woud for their Antiquity be reverenced, in
                    preference of Any attempts in the Modern Arts.</p>
                <p>The Gruagich Stones, as far as Tradition can inform Us, were only honoured with
                    Libations of Milk from the hands of the Dairy, which were offered to <persName ref="pe1981">Gruagach</persName> Upon the Sund-day, for the preservation of
                    the Catle on the Ensuing week — from this Custom <persName ref="pe1981">Apollo</persName> seems to have derived the Epithet Galaxius. This was one
                    of the Sober offerings that well became a poor or a frugal people, who had
                    neither wine or oil to bestow, by which they recommended their only stock And
                    Subsistence to their favourite Divinity whom they always had in their Eye And
                    whose blessings they Enjoyed Every day. The Inscription <persName ref="pe1981">Apolini Granno</persName> (grianich, the Suny) was on a stone of this kind
                    dug up from the ruines of the Roman Pretenture in <persName ref="">King James
                        the 6<hi rend="superscript">th's</hi></persName> time. The Inscription in
                        <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0681">Gruter</title></bibl>, Apolini
                    Beleno, seems to have been on Such Another And the rock-idols of <placeName ref="">Cornwal</placeName> in <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0106">Dr
                            B-----</title></bibl> seem to be of the Same kind tho of different
                    forms, for it was not the Shape but the consecration that pointed out their
                    Uses, for tho they Are Numerous in this Island, you will Scarce meet Any two of
                    them of the <add place="above">same</add> Cast. The Only Idol-stones besides,
                    that remain with Us are oblong Square Altars of rough Stone that Ly within the
                    Druid's houses a we call them. Observe Also that the worship of the Sun seems to
                    have continued in <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> Untill <persName ref="pe1986">King Canut's</persName> time, by a Law of his Which Prohibits
                    that, with other Idolatrous practices.</p>

            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <opener><dateline><placeName ref="pl0742">Kilmuir</placeName> Augst the 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                        <lb/>1774</dateline>
                    <salute>Dr Sir</salute></opener>
                <p>Tho I had the honour of Your Letter of May the 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                    Long ago in my way to a Synod yet my time was So fully taken Up in the busyness
                    of my Calling And In attending on Some of my friends Who set out for the new
                    world that I had no Leasure at home till this week. I have Examined very
                    intelligent People who Are well Acquainted with the <placeName ref="pl0841">hills of Cūlin</placeName> who assure me that there are not the Smallest
                    traces of a Vulcano about them. On the East side of this Countrey the Land is
                    faced with a Steep rock of vast height towards the Sea. In a Particular part of
                    it the <placeName ref="pl2725">Giant's causeway</placeName> is to be seen in
                    Miniature — there is Also <placeName ref="pl2726">the kilted rock</placeName>,
                    As we call it, which is made Up of different rows of Pillars standing Upon One
                    Another but how far it resembles that at <placeName ref="pl0661">Talisker</placeName> I cannot Say, having never Seen the Later but I will
                    see it. I shall Enquire after the Trinkets you recommend but I wish you had
                    Spoke of them Last year having then been master of Some Uncommon things. Your
                    book, for which I return You most hearty thanks, comes home by Sea, which is an
                    Uncertain tedious conveyance. I hope You shall have as much honour by it As by
                    Your other Publication. I shall be glad to hear from You when You please As I
                    may be after this in the Way of making you a Speedier Return.</p>
                <closer><salute>I always am with Sincere Esteem, Dr Sir <lb/>Your most obedient
                        <lb/>and <lb/>Most humble Servant</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0069">Don: Macqueen</persName></signed></closer>

                <postscript>
                    <p>I inclose the out-lines of three of our gruagich-stones, which you may fling
                        into form When you have Occasion — they Are diminutive things if compared to
                        those you was pleased to Send me. There is no Inclosure about the gruagach
                        Stones, tho indeed they might have been in groves When the Countrey was
                        cover'd over with wood. I am apt to think they were the property of Every
                        body, Else how could the Dairies continue the Practice mentioned above? or
                        how coud Roman Souldiers pay their vows Upon them? which was the case in
                        Inscriptions referred to above.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><address>
                        <addrLine>To</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Thomas Pennant Esqre</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>of Downing in Flintshire.</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>South Brittain</addrLine>
                    </address></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>