<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0417">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Donald MacQueen to Thomas Pennant</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP297</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>12</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0069">Donald MacQueen</persName>
                    <date when="1775-03-15"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0742">Kilmuir</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="prev" target="0416"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
                <p>I had the pleasure of yours of the 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of January a
                    Long while ago. It is Idle to make an apology for being so Slow in Acknowledging
                    it — My time was Otherwise Necessarily taken Up, is Enough. I write you a
                    Suplement to the one you acknowledge the receipt of, which you would have had
                    before Yours reached me — it was addressed to <persName ref="pe0015">Roger
                        Mostin</persName>.</p>
                <p>The papper which is here Inclosed I submitt entirely to Your Judgement. If Any
                    one hath already Said that the Scots are but a branch of the Picts emerging from
                    Barbarity And have at Last turned out Conquerors of <placeName ref="pl0889">Irland</placeName> I know him not. How could it be Otherwise? They were
                    Caledonians who As well as the South Brittains painted their bodies. The Romans
                    found them first in Caledonia And Some time after that in <placeName ref="pl0889">Irland</placeName>. I could have gone a much greater Length but
                    as I believe it a new System I did not care to Encumber it with more Novelties.
                    I drew only the General Plan And Leave it to Any Other to confirm it confute it
                    or neglect it. I return you hearty thanks for the Torpedo Letter — I always
                    thought it a Mediterranian fish, And to Say the truth I knew Little about it,
                    having only some years ago read <add place="above">of</add> it with wonder. I
                    think it was in <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0682">Borielli de motu
                            Animalium</title></bibl>, who I believe knew As Litle of the Doctrine of
                    Electricity As <persName ref="pe1987">Claudian</persName>.</p>
                <p>I have not yet seen <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0095">Dr Johnson's
                            Journey</title></bibl>, but some Scrapes in a Magazine — I sent for the
                    book itself for tho he was pleased to make <add place="above">me</add> a Present
                    of Some Other Parts of his works he will not I suppose offer me this. I wish for
                    his own Sake he had not wrote it, for I Esteem the man on Account of his
                    Learning, and inflexible virtue if I mistake him not. He coud have Lost Nothing
                    by Looking to Your Manner of Writing. His prejudices Against <persName ref="pe0557">Ossian's</persName> poems he brought from <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> And brought them back Again because he met
                    with few who inclined to differ with him. He thought <persName ref="pe0558">Mr
                        Macpherson</persName> shoud have Left the original for the Inspection of the
                    Public — He coud find none that had Manuscripts of it in <placeName ref="pl0711">the Highlands</placeName> — Only Songs in the Mouths of rehearsers which
                        <add place="above">he</add> was informed were not Literally translated. I
                    believe nobody took much pains Upon him. <persName ref="pe0558">Mr
                        Macpherson</persName> Seems to be very angry at him.</p>
                <p>I Expect to have your book returned to me next week. In the mean time please know
                    that you have been MisInformed about <placeName ref="pl0653">Canna</placeName>.<note type="editorial">See Pennant, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0008">A tour in Scotland and Voyage to
                                the Hebrides 1772</title></bibl> (1774), p.314.</note>
                    <persName ref="pe1988">Mr Macdonald of Clanranald</persName> Set the Island on
                    to MacLeod And a Mackinnon — both these sublet their farms to small Tennants at
                    much higher rents than they payed the Proprietor which is a common care in
                        <placeName ref="pl0711">the Highlands</placeName>. In the mean time these
                    small tennants Are more at mercy in Narrow Islands than Any were Else and
                    therefore the proprietor should indeed take Every precaution to guard them
                    Against the Oppressions of the Principal Farmers.</p>
                <p>If I remember right You call <placeName ref="pl0647">orinsay</placeName> near
                        <placeName ref="pl0649">Colinsay</placeName> a Monastery. It is called a
                    priory in the antient Lists of the Priorees of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>. As I was never Upon the place I cannot positively Say
                    whether it is Really an Island or not; but I can say that there are Several
                    Islands called <placeName ref="pl0647">oransay</placeName>, that is, an Island
                    consecrated to <persName ref="pe1989">St Oran</persName>
                    <persName ref="pe0066">Columba's</persName> Fellow Labourer And that it is a
                    Circumstance Peculiar to Each of them that I know, that on time of full Sea they
                    are Islands but in time of Ebb the sands Are dry betwixt <add place="above">them</add> And the next Continent. Why Such Islands were chosen for
                        <placeName ref="pe1989">St Oran</placeName> I know not, but this peice of
                    Singularity Shoud not be forgotten.</p>
                <p>It will give me Pleasure to hear from You Soon for I will be Seeking health
                    abroad in Summer.</p>
                <closer><salute>I am with very great regard, Dr Sir, <lb/>Your very Obedient humble
                        Sevt</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0069">Don: Macqueen</persName></signed>
                    <dateline><placeName ref="pl0742">Kilmuir</placeName> March the 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                        <lb/>1775.</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="enclosed">
                <fw>P.1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi></fw>
                <opener>To <persName ref="pe0232">Mr Pennant.</persName>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
                <p>As a great Part of <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> hath had the good
                    Fortune to have been visited by you, a man whose Politeness is Equal to his
                    knowledge which is Extensive enough, by a man who is fully qualified to bring
                    the state of Past times in review before Us And to paint the present with
                    Justness And propriety; Litle disposed to disoblige, but Where Truth &amp;
                    Public Interest conjoined, guide the way; And As I find you are further in the
                    humour of travelling over that Part of our Countrey which you have not yet seen,
                    with Intention to favour the world with Other Curious And Useful discoveries, I
                    will presume to Lay before You a Conjecture which is not quite new And for Us
                    Obvious As it is, hath not yet been pursued for ought I know, to Any Extent,
                    about the first Inhabitants of a Countrey you pay So much attention to.<note type="editorial">The following treatise would later appear as 'Dr. Macqueen
                        on the Origin of the Picts and Scots' in <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0420">The Gentleman's Magazine</title></bibl>, LXIV
                        (1794).</note></p>
                <p>Our People of <placeName ref="pl0777">Brittain</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl0889">Irland</placeName>, like other Nations both Antient &amp;
                    modern, taking Advantage of the darkness of Antiquity, have not Only indulged
                    their credulous vanity in giving themselves an old Setlement in their Several
                    Countries but have fetched their Ancestors from a far, wherever their Pride
                    could be tickled by an honourable descent, bu a Similarity of Customs or perhaps
                    merely for the Sake of Going out of the common road And connecting themselves
                    with distant Strangers. Had it not saved our Friends, pen, Ink, time &amp;
                    passion to be Laid out on more Useful subjects, if they had from the beginning
                    contented themselves with the Usual course of things, peopled <placeName ref="pl0777">Brittain</placeName> from <placeName ref="pl2663">Gaul</placeName> the next Continent And <placeName ref="pl0889">Irland</placeName> from <placeName ref="pl0897">Kintire</placeName> And
                        <placeName ref="pl1624">Gallaway</placeName>. The Pruning knife of Criticism
                    is from Age to Age Lopping off the Extravagant Fictions of former times And will
                    at Length reduce them to a more natural appearance. The Emulation Which is
                    common in close Neighbourhoods <add place="above">determined the people of
                            <placeName ref="pl2003">South Brittain</placeName> to derive their
                        origine one way</add> — The Caledonians having been Split into two principal
                    branches, the Picts &amp; Scots, have gone differently to work. The Picts who
                    had no writers among them, must come from Any Countrey on the Continent Where
                    painting the body was fashionable And the Similarity betwixt the words Scot
                    &amp; Scythi hah been the Cause Why Some of our Countrey men thought them the
                    Same people, tho the Just have given themselves and the Scots a Spanish <add place="above">descent</add> As a more honourable origine, which
                            <pb/><fw>2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></fw> By falling under the
                    animadversion of the Learned is better known than Such trifles deserve.</p>
                <p>It is now my Intention to trace the Course of Population according to the Nature
                    of things, as Suggested to Us <del rend="overstrike">by</del>
                    <add place="above">in</add> the Lights cast <unclear reason="illegible">up</unclear> it by the first writers, who are the Only Sūre Guides: more
                    So, than the fancyful Unauthenticated reveries of Ignorant Ages, tho Afterwards
                    supported more Plausibly dressed out by their more Learned Sucessors.</p>
                <p>The Romans on their first Acquaintance with the Nations to the North of
                        <placeName ref="pl0833">the Friths of Clyde</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl0083">Forth</placeName> gave them the General title of Caledonians,
                    in process of time they Learned to distinguish them into tow Principal Tribes,
                    the Picts &amp; Scots And on a nearer view they found them Subdivided into
                    Smaller casts, on all of Whom they bestowed the general appellation of
                    Caledonians And <persName ref="bi0683">Isidore</persName> Even in the Seventh
                    Age, so Jumbles the Picts and Scots together that he Affirms the Later Also
                    painted various figures on their bodies, by pricking them with Iron bodkins And
                    rubbing them Over with Ink. Yet, out of Respect to men of Letters who, finding
                    that the Scots did not at all, or so commonly Paint as the Picts, woud fetch
                    from distant Countries, a further Deduction so became necessary to put the Truth
                    in a clearer point of view, tho Obvious Enough to Any Who considers it void of
                    the Prejudice which the Belief of Ages brings along with it.</p>
                <p>It is Universally agreed that all the Brittains painted in this manner — that
                    they struck the figūres or outlines of different Animals on their bodies When
                    they were Young, by Useing an Able Artist to prick them with a needle or bodkin
                    And rubbing the diminutive marks of the Iron with the Juice of a certain Herb,
                    which gave them a blue and Lasting Colour. The Unextinguishable Characters
                    Enlarging in the advance of Years looked in the Eyes of Civilized strangers, As
                    if the figures were immediately painted off, which was the reason Why the Romans
                    called them Picti, tho the word Puncti woud have been nearer the Fact, <del rend="overstrike">and</del> a Literal translation of the Gaulic word
                    Peaƈtigh and of the Greek word στίκτοί. The Nobless And the Commons were
                    distinguished here As well As the <placeName ref="pl2678">Thrace</placeName>, by
                    the figures of different animals And by the Largeness And Smallness of the
                    Characters As were Also the Several Tribes from One Another And that they might
                    not hide these marks of distinction, their breasts, backs And arms were Exposed
                    to view Especially in time of batle, when it was Necessary in the hurey of Arms
                    to find out the Friends or Relations with the glance of An Eye And to have
                    Witnesses of the Prowess or Cowardice of the Military man among his own
                    Acquaintances. In some parts of the world <pb/><fw>3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></fw> The Souldiers were marked with the Ensigns of their General
                    As were the Votaries of Certain false Deities with Something Peculiar to <hi rend="underline">their</hi> Service and <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="v">Tertūlian</title></bibl> affirms that the Brittains were
                    distinguished by their Stigmata As Other Nations by their Particular
                    Ensigns.</p>
                <p>An Unmixed People, who all from the highest to the Lowest, being bred &amp;
                    Educated in the very Same manner preserved the Same colour of hair, the same
                    whiteness of Skin, great Similarity in their features And in the proportion of
                    their Limbs, woud need these visible marks of distinction, Especially in the
                    first periods of Society when they went almost quite naked. For the same
                    Reasons, which Nature Suggested to all in Similar Circumstances, we find
                    Americans painted from one End of their Extensive Continent to the Other, some
                    in the Absolute want of Iron or Any Other Mettal pricking their flesh with a
                    pointed bone. It is true, that those who Live close to the Neighbourhood of the
                    European Colonies, by trading in furs, in Other Small branches of Commerce or by
                    Some Services have purchased Cloaths Which rendered their corporeal Ensigns
                    inviseable And consequently Unless, if they do not Sometimes mark their faces
                    And wear their hair in a Particular distinctive mode. Thus when <placeName ref="pl2003">South Brittain</placeName> became Subject to the Romans And the
                    debateable Lands betwixt the Walls were also converted into a Province Under the
                    Name of <placeName ref="pl2727">Valentia</placeName>, Such of the Natives As
                    dreaded Slavery most flew to the Forrests of <placeName ref="pl0705">Caledonia</placeName>. These fugitives from the Severity of Provincial
                    discipline And the Inhabitants of the Unconquered part of the Island had the
                    denomination of Picts given them by the Romans And by the South Brittains who
                    had Submitted to their Laws &amp; fashions. This name was appropriated to them
                    from about the End of the third And beginning of the fourth Century As the
                    Custom Expressed by it was Peculiar to them And Laid Aside by the Provincials
                    And at the same time the Name of Scots is bestowed by the Romans on the
                    Inhabitants of the Western Side of <placeName ref="pl0705">Caledonia</placeName>
                    by Which they woud Seem to Intimate that painting was not, at Least As Generally
                    practised among them As among their Neighbours.</p>
                <p>But how came it about that the Scots, a branch of the Old Caledonians As the
                    Romans allowed them to be quited this barbarous practice of striking their
                    bodies with the figūres of different Animals While their Eastern Neighbours
                    continued it And for Several Centuries were known by the Appellation of Picts is
                    a question of Some little Curiosity.</p>
                <p>The Picts, So called, being hemmed in betwixt <placeName ref="pl1107">the German
                        Ocean</placeName> And the vast Cluster of hills called <placeName ref="pl1166">the Grampians</placeName> which stretch themselves from
                        <placeName ref="pl0091">Strathern</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0193">Lochness</placeName> And further, had no outlet by which they might
                    intermix with Strangers, <pb/><fw>4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></fw> But by
                    the <placeName ref="pl0083">Passage of Bodotria</placeName> towards the Roman
                    Provinces And As it is Probable that <placeName ref="pl0705">Pictavia</placeName>, as well as <placeName ref="pl2003">South
                        Brittain</placeName> And Every Countrey, in the Original state of Barbarity,
                    was Split into many Independant Principalities, it is very Like that there woud
                    be Litle of the Spirit of Union among them, except when they saw a powerful
                    Enemy Close to their Gates, as in the case of <persName ref="pe1920">Agricola</persName> And <persName ref="pe1990">the Emperor
                        Severus</persName>; And thus Sequestered from Strangers, but when they
                    Sallyed out, some of them Only, upon a Plundering Party And returned quickly
                    when they got their hands full or were beaten back, they might continue Long
                    Enough in a State of the utmost Barbarity if they were not conquered by more
                    Polished People than themselves. But how came to Scots to be that People, when
                    they were, at almost the Same distance from the Schools of Civil<del rend="overstrike"><unclear reason="illegible">ity</unclear></del>
                    <add place="above">Life</add> And Originally Enured to the Same Customs And way
                    of Living?</p>
                <p>To the Scots &amp; Picts, men unatached to Any Land by houses, for they none but
                    the huts of a day's Labour, by Temples or by Agriculture, Every Soil woud be
                    Equal. The Necessity of Providing Subsistence for themselves And their Families
                    Ennobled the professions of Robbery And Arms And compelled them to a wandering
                    Itinerant Life, in quest of Game: they must have chosen to dy of Famine or to
                    Plunder &amp; fight. The Picts, possessing the Eastern Coast of Caledonia from
                    South to North, whom we Suppose <unclear reason="illegible">Minced</unclear>
                    into Many Independent States According As Rivers, Rocks, mountains And Arms of
                    the Sea bounded them, must have been in a state of war Among themselves, like
                    the Highland Clans in a Later Period, And confined to their favourite trade near
                    home: for the more Northern Tribes of them woud Scarce be permitted to march
                    Undisturbed, thro the States which Lay across their Way towards the Roman
                    Provinces.</p>
                <p>The Inhabitants of the western Coast made the Earlyer Progress in the Arts of
                    Good Order And Civility As being nearer the Roman Colonies, to which History
                    bears Testimony they made frequent Sallies together with Some of the Picts in
                    their Neighbourhood As they woud to Such of the Western Isles as Lay within
                    their view And Easyly Subdued them as being Severed from One Another, thinly
                    peopled and under Unsurmountable difficulty of Leagueing together for Mutual
                    defence. And tho the <add place="above">Scots</add> were at first but a Single
                    Tribe of the Picts, Unanimous therefore in all their Resolves, Separated from
                    the Rest by a Range of Unhospitable mountains they woud gather Strength And be
                    tempted by their Fortune in <placeName ref="pl0889">Irland</placeName>, a
                    Countrey favoured by Nature with very fine harbours which were better known And
                    more frequented by Strangers than those of <placeName ref="pl0777">Brittain</placeName>. <pb/>
                    <fw>5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></fw> Here, they woud see Civilised People
                        <add place="above">on the Coast</add> Exchange their furs, their Share of
                    the Roman booty, whatever Trinkets they had with the Merchants for the Cloathing
                    And ornaments which their Vanity demanded. At Length when the Plunder of the
                    Province and the Merchants tradeing to <placeName ref="pl0889">Irland</placeName> Supplyed them with Cloaths, they were Under a Necessity,
                    Like the South Brittains, of giving Up the Custom of Painting their bodies, at
                    which Period they offered themselves as a people quite different from the More
                    Barbarous Picts, which was the cause Why distant Progenitors were Sought out for
                    them with So much Assiduity.</p>
                <p>But still to preserve the distinctive marks of their Subordinate Divisions they
                    transposed the <del rend="overstrike">Animal</del>
                    <add place="above">Family</add> figures to their Shields. <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="pe1991">Seneca</title></bibl> I think says that the Scots
                    Painted their Shields And I find the Shield of <add place="above">a</add> Hero
                        <add place="above">thus</add> described in An Old Gaulic Poem, which it
                    seems Escaped <persName ref="pe0558">Mr Macpherson's</persName> Search — "He
                    fitted his red-tanned bossy Shield to his Left arm on which was drawn the
                    Picture of <add place="above">a</add> Lion, a Leopard, a Griphin And the biteing
                    Serpent. At Last the Colours, which might be Seen from a greater distance, with
                    the Animal drawn Upon <unclear reason="illegible">it</unclear>which
                    distinguished the Tribes was introduced a further Improvement In One of
                        <persName ref="pe0540">Fingal's</persName> batles, I find three or four Pair
                    of Colours displayed at Once, dazzling the Eye from afar with the Lustre of Best
                        <hi rend="underline">Ore</hi>: Which they Must have Learned from the Romans;
                    As we may Conclude from <persName ref="pe1107">Homers</persName> Silence that
                    they had no Standard in the Heroic times he describes tho his Greeks And <del rend="overstrike"><gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" atLeast="5" atMost="7"/></del><add place="above">Trojans</add> lived in a much more
                    Advanced Period of Society than the <sic>Cotemporary</sic>
                    <del rend="overstrike">Picts</del> Scots &amp; Picts we Speak of. Armoreal
                    bearings may very Justly be Supposed to ow their origine to this Practice And it
                    is not Unlike that when Patronimies gave place to Surnames which happened much
                    about the time the Picts ceased to be a distinct People, that those who have
                    taken Up the Name of Lion, wolf, Fox, Hawk, or of Any other Animal made choice
                    of that which distinguished their Tribe from the beginning, for in that quarter
                    of the Countrey where Patronimies are still Used no Such Surnames are to be Met
                    with.</p>
                <p>Here a very pertinent Question occurs — Could a Single Tribe from <placeName ref="pl0705">Caledonia</placeName> assisted by a few Islanders conquer
                        <placeName ref="pl0889">Irland</placeName> and give it their own name or
                    coud they in Any degree improve by the Company of Such Mortals As the Irish are
                    represented to have been? Woud not the Scots, pray, Learn the Art <pb/><fw>6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></fw> of War, from the Romans by an
                    apprenticeship of about three hundred Years And would not they Also Learn from
                    the folly of their Neighbours in <placeName ref="pl2003">South
                        Brittain</placeName> who never pursued any common Interest to form
                    themselves into indefeatable bands by the strictest treaties and Alliances? Thus
                    prevailing in power, policy and Numbers, <placeName ref="pl0889">Irland</placeName> whither the fertility of the Soil &amp; Mildness of the
                    Climate would tempt them to make frequent Visites, would become An Easy
                    Purchase, at Least in part, <placeName ref="pl0889">Irland</placeName> whose
                    Inhabitants have not yet been said to fight without their own Island, whose
                    habitations were common &amp; Uncircumscribed — far from being appropriated by
                    an Extensive Monarchy. If one Legion <add place="above">with a few
                        Auxiliaries</add> would Make an Intire conquest of in <persName ref="pe1992">Domitian's</persName> time What may not be Expected from Men of approved
                    valour Who made Such havock in <placeName ref="pl2003">South
                        Brittain?</placeName></p>
                <p>The frequent intercourse of the Scots with the Romans, the Brittains, the western
                    Islanders, the Irish And the merchants from different Countries who traded to
                    the Irish harbours, would as Iron polisheth Iron rub off something of their
                    barbarous rūst As a more Enlarged Experience would Also improve them in the Art
                    of War.</p>
                <p>Their conquests in <placeName ref="pl0889">Irland</placeName> however, would
                    produced but very Small Effects: it is agriculture Alone, an Art Unworthy of the
                    Military Men of that Age, that can fix attendance Upon Any Particular Spot of
                    Earth; And it was as well they did not apply to tillage, When the Lived among
                    Enemies who in one day woud Easyly destroy the fruits of a year's Industry. They
                    had Every thing to Seek by the Sword And to defend by the Sword: They woud be
                    skipping backwards And forwards to <placeName ref="pl0889">Irland</placeName>
                    And <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName> As Necessity, pleasure or
                    Amusement directed them — per diversa Vagantes <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0672">Amm. Marcell</title></bibl>: Thus <placeName ref="pl0889">Irland</placeName> As well as <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>
                    was the Scene of <persName ref="pe0540">Fingal's</persName> batles: People who
                    made war their Profession, <del rend="overstrike">could not be long <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" atLeast="5" atMost="6"/></del> As
                    being the Source of their Livelyhood, And reckoned that of their Glory could not
                    be Long at rest. The Brittains might properly Enough call them Schuits,
                    wanderers, As in <placeName ref="pl0708">the Western Isles</placeName> they call
                    the <placeName ref="pl0633">Campbelton</placeName> Vessels who go from Loch to
                    Loch, in quest of Herrings the black Schuits, which might be naturally Latinized
                    into Scoti. The Goths first came like a Swarm of Locusts to destroy the Roman
                    Empire. Can Historians or Geographers fix the seats of Such rapacious
                    Itinerants? they can Only point them out for the present time.</p>
                <p>However, it appears that the Scots made at Length a Setlement in that British
                    Island, for tho <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0672">Ammianus
                            Marcellinus</title></bibl> found them in <del rend="overstrike">Irland</del>
                    <add place="above"><placeName ref="pl0777">Brittain</placeName></add> about the
                    End of the third Age; And <persName ref="pe1993">Porphyry</persName> Somewhat
                    Earlyer <persName ref="pe1994">orosius</persName> met with them in <placeName ref="pl0889">Irland</placeName> about the beginning of the fifth, where they
                    raised themselves Up to Such Eminence As to give their own Name to the Island.
                        <persName ref="pe1995">St Laurence Archbishop of Canterbury</persName>, who
                    could not be Mistaken calls it Scotia, in a Letter addressed to it's own Bishops
                    about they year 605. <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0683">Isidore</title></bibl> And <pb/><fw>7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></fw>
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="pe1996">Adamnanus</title></bibl> in the same
                    Century bear Testimony to this Fact, tho at the Same time it appears Upon
                    Irrefragable Evidence that they kept Possession of their Dominions on the
                    Western coast of <placeName ref="pl0705">Caledonia</placeName>. Thus Stationed
                    in the different Countries, their best harvest lay towards the South. Their
                    Neighbours the Picts Joined them in their Attacks on <placeName ref="pl2727">Valentia</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl2003">South
                    Brittain</placeName>, the<del rend="overstrike">y</del> former of Which they
                    made An Intire conquest of, Upon withdrawing the Roman Legions; And it cannot be
                    doubted but the Irish woud also Support them from their Countrey Where they had
                    the Principal direction themselves. In the System I here Lay down, these
                    passages of <persName ref="pe1987">Claudian</persName> can be Easyly Understood
                    without passing them to the torture of Severe Criticism ––––– totam cum Scotus
                    Iërnen Movit, et in festo Spumavit remige Thetis. <del rend="overstrike">
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" atLeast="7" atMost="8"/>
                    </del> Scotorum cumulos flevit glacialis Hiberne ––––– As others may,
                    particularly from the Ecclesiastical writers, which have been often Squeesed to
                    Serve the Purposes of different <del rend="overstrike"><unclear reason="illegible">writers</unclear></del> Enterprizers.</p>
                <p>Thus Supported by their Friends in <placeName ref="pl0708">the Western
                        Isles</placeName>, by the Irish Scots and by continual Experience in Arms on
                    a more Enlarged Scene of Action, the Albin Scots would at Length become an over
                    match for the Eastern Picts.</p>
                <p>This Speculation might be caryed much further but I will conclude it with
                    observing that the Same Religion, the Same Customs, the Same Language proclaim
                    the antient Inhabitants of the <placeName ref="pl0777">British Isles</placeName>
                    the very Same People And it hath happened at Any time that a Tribe of Men
                    trusting themselves to the Uncertainties of wind And weather, from a distant
                    Part of the Continent, in the ill contrived vessels of former Ages, Should
                    Arrive in <placeName ref="pl0889">Irland</placeName> or <placeName ref="pl0731">Wales</placeName>, they woud bear So Small a proportion to the Natives, As
                    to be Soon <hi rend="underline">Assimilated</hi> to them. <persName ref="pe1997">Hanno the Carthaginian</persName>, by Order of Senate Planted thirty
                    thousand Men on the Western Coast of <placeName ref="pl1353">Africa</placeName>,
                    but, as they bore no proportion to the Natives, when deprived of the Support of
                    the Mother Countrey, they brutalized in the woods or were destroyed by Wild
                    beasts, for there were no Vestiges of them to be met with And the Same would be
                    the fate of a Small Parcell of Men who Setled in any Wild Countrey. They woud
                    presently find themselves oppressed with Every want which they would be Obliged
                    to Supply by violent means or by Very rough Expedients — a Spirit of Discord
                    would creep in among themselves And their Children for want of Care &amp;
                    Culture would become of a piece with the Natives. Old <placeName ref="pl0705">Caledonia</placeName> is distinguished in one respect from the most, if not
                    all the Kingdoms of <placeName ref="pl1176">Europe</placeName>; It's Situation
                    soil and the Military Spirit of it's Inhabitants were Ever impregnable
                    Securities Against the attempts of foreign Invaders. It is the race of the
                    Aboriginal Natives, with a Very few Exceptions, you meet with in the Countrey
                            <pb/><fw>8<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi></fw> You mean to adorn with
                    Curious <add place="above">&amp; Useful</add> Remarks And that you may Live Long
                    to promote the Happyness And Honour of the Human Species is the Sincere wish
                    of,</p>

                <closer><salute>Dr Sir <lb/><hi rend="underline">Your Most Obedient humble
                            Servant</hi></salute>
                    <dateline><placeName ref="pl0742">Kilmuir</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl0715">Sky</placeName> March the 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                        <lb/>1775.</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><address>
                        <addrLine>To</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Thomas Pennant Esqre,</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>of Downing, Flintshire.</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>S. Brittain.</addrLine>
                    </address></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>