<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0418">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Donald MacNicol to Thomas Pennant</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP297</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>13</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe1604">Donald MacNicol</persName>
                    <date when="1774-03-08"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0688">Lismore</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pe0232">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct01419"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gd">Gaelic</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <dateline><placeName ref="pl0688">Lismore</placeName> March 8<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> 1774</dateline>
                <opener><salute>Sir,</salute></opener>
                <p>I am ashamed I have been so long of Writing an Answer to your Letter which I
                    received from <persName ref="pe2000">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Campbell</persName> of <placeName ref="pl0685">Dunstaffnage</placeName> a
                    long Time ago; but Distress in my Family &amp; other Avocations prevented my
                    Complying with your Request till now, tho I must acknowledge a Man who did so
                    much Honour to our Country merited better Treatment; but <persName ref="pe0023">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Stewart</persName>, your Fellow
                    traveller, could so effectually satisfy you in all points as to leave me little
                    so say. as he frequently question'd me about every Thing that was singular in
                    this Place. —</p>
                <p>I am unhappy it was my Misfortune to miss you when here, as a few Hours
                    Conversation would be preferable to a Years Correspondence. —</p>
                <p>Tradition bears that this Island was originally a Forrest; a Number of Dear Horns
                    got in all the peat-mosses in the Country, besides the names of many places,
                    make me incline to the same Opinion. Hart Horns of an uncommon large Size were
                    found here some Years ago; If I do not forget, <persName ref="pe0451">Doctor
                        Walker</persName> of <placeName ref="pl0247">Moffat</placeName> brought one
                    of the Horns, or rather a part of one, to the Museum in <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName>. — The Scull of a Creature of the Cow Kind, of an
                    overgrown Size, was likewise found in this Island, in a deep Moss, some Years
                    ago, &amp; is still to be seen at <placeName ref="pl0987">Lochnell-house</placeName> in this Neighbourhood. — The Soil here is
                    reckon'd good, it seems to be Loam, a Mixture of Earth &amp; the Surface of the
                    Limestone Rock on which the Island stands, mouldered down together. Our Climate
                    here is bad, I mean wet, &amp; tho we have a flattering appearance of Corn early
                    in the Season, the great Falls of Rain in July &amp; August destroy all, &amp;
                    frequently make our Crops turn out to small Acc<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> in
                    the End. —</p>
                <p>We destroy our Ground by too frequent Tillage so that our Returns are seldom
                    equal to what might be expected. — Summer-fallowing is not practiced amongst us.
                    We have great Quantities of Rock &amp; Pit marl but we never burn Lime for Want
                    of Firing which is very scarce with us; Peats are our only Firing &amp; our Moss
                    has such a Mixture of Earth in it that it must be trampt with the Feet till its
                    brought to the Consistency of wrought Clay before it can be form'd into peats
                    which is done with the Hands; in no other Shape will our peats stick together. —
                    This method of making our peats is somewhat singular &amp; attended with much
                    Trouble — Corn &amp; Bear are the chief Produce of this Country; great
                    Quantities of the Latter are yearly made into Aqua Vitæ. — Our common Keal is
                    suppos'd to turn here into Cabbage, I am apt to believe that this holds true,
                    particularly after the 2<hi rend="superscript">nd.</hi> or 3<hi rend="superscript">rd.</hi> Years planting, but the first year it does not
                    hold; I am told its the same in the <placeName ref="pl0974">Island of
                        Tiree</placeName> &amp; in some parts of the <placeName ref="pl0701">Orkneys</placeName>. Savoys or German Greens are not so lyable to this
                    Metamorphosis, but even these incline to bow or close, &amp; a few of them
                    really do — We have three Water Lakes in the Island; two of them abound with
                    fine Trouts, many of them of a good Size; the third which lies nearest my House
                    has not Trouts in it, but has plenty of Eels in it; its call'd the <placeName ref="pl2728">Loch (Lake) of Balnagoun</placeName> which signifies the Lake
                    of Smith-town. Ducks of various Sorts frequent it in Winter &amp; Spring. The
                    Bottom of all our Lakes consists entirely of Marl —</p>
                <p>This was a Bishop's Residence; the Walls of the present Church are those of the
                    Choir of the old Cathedral roof'd anew — <persName ref="pe2001">S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Maluag</persName> is the first Religionist we
                    have any Acc<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> off that took Footing here; hence
                        <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="pe1012">Hector Boetius</title></bibl>
                    affirms he was buried in the North in the same Church with <persName ref="pe2002">S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Boniface</persName>, tho he
                    acknowledges the Argathelians<note type="editorial">MacNicol uses Argathelian
                        here to refer to the people of Argyll; the term was more commonly associated
                        with a pro-Hanover Scottish political faction of the early-to-mid-eighteenth
                        century that had been led by the second duke of Argyll.</note> claim a Right
                    to the Honour of his burial place in <placeName ref="pl0688">Lismore</placeName>. Mark that <persName ref="pe1012">Boetius</persName> was a
                        norland<note type="editorial">A reference to Hector Boece's identity as a
                        native of Aberdeen, and therefore potential bias against Argyll's claim to
                        the saints mentioned.</note> — In Consequence of a Vow made by <persName ref="pe1016">King Malcolm Ceanmore</persName>
                    <add place="above">to <persName ref="pe2001">S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi>
                            Maluag</persName></add> when engaged in Battle with the Danes, there was
                    a Church built in the North where the Bishops of <placeName ref="pl0128">Aberdeen</placeName> had their Residence till <persName ref="pe1459">David
                        the 1<hi rend="superscript">st.'s</hi></persName> Time —</p>
                <p>The Bishops were suppos'd of late years to have resided in the <placeName ref="pl2729">Castle of Achanduin</placeName> upon the west Side of this
                    Island fronting the small Garison of <placeName ref="pl0684">Duart</placeName>
                    on <placeName ref="pl0729">Mull</placeName>. There is a remarkable Echo near
                    this Castle; <persName ref="pe0451">Dr Walker</persName> &amp; I found that it
                    repeated distinctly five different Syllabels —</p>
                <p>When ravenous Beasts infested the Country the Inhabitants found it necessary to
                    lay something upon their Graves to prevent the Corps from being dug up; they
                    found large Logs of Timber answered this purpose &amp; these were us'd in the
                    ruder Ages before the Art of Hewing Stones was practiced or known; hence we find
                    that there is no Word in our old Galaic Books for a Grave Stone (Galaic Leichd
                    Lithidh) but Darag Lithidh, a Grave Tree or Log; Darag signifies a large, old
                    Oak Tree —<note type="editorial">MacNicol's account of log burials appears in
                        Pennant, <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0008">A tour in Scotland and
                                voyage to the Hebrides 1772</title></bibl>, part II (1774)
                        pp.414-15.</note> The better to secure their Graves from the Wild Beasts,
                    the old Highlanders, for the most part, buried their Dead on Islands; a practice
                    they would probably not have adopted because of <del unit="letters" atLeast="8" atMost="11"/> the Inconvenience that attended it, particularly in
                    tempestuous Weather, were it not to answer some particular purpose of this Kind.
                    I wish this long Letter may in any Shape answer your Expectations. </p>
                <closer><salute>I am <lb/>Sir <lb/>Your Very ob<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi>
                            Serv<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi></salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe1604">Donald M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Nicol</persName></signed></closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>