<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0540">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>George Paton to Thomas Pennant</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP326</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>8</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0228">George Paton</persName>
                    <date when="1779-10-13"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0696">Custom House, Edinburgh</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct0539"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
                <p>The unfortunate Lady was only daughter to <persName ref="pe2014">the ninth Earl
                        of Caithness</persName>, her name <persName ref="pe2015">Lady Dorothea
                        Sinclair</persName>,in the first period of life most promising but now by
                    barbarous treatment of <persName ref="pe0090">the dirty Lord</persName> rendered
                    a pity-able object , being under constant apprehension of resuffering similar
                    insults, she once bore from his hands or artifice; neglected tho' alimented by
                    her base husband she is unhappy &amp; may be often pinched with the extravagant
                    profusion of a thoughtful mother, that pryes upon her.</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe2013">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> John Clerk</persName> is a
                    fifth Son of <persName ref="pe0454">Sir John Clark Baro<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> of Penycuik</persName> one of the Late Barons of Exchequer,
                    &amp; Brother to <persName ref="pe2016">Sir James</persName> now of that Stile,
                    he is alive with a numerous family by <persName ref="pe2017">a Sister</persName>
                    of <persName ref="pe2018">John Adams</persName> the eminent adelphi schemer at
                        <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>, his house in the vicinity of
                        <placeName ref="pl2399">Lasswade</placeName>, named <placeName ref="pl2802"><hi rend="underline">Eldin</hi></placeName>, i.e. a vulgar word used in
                    this Country for Fire or the materials kindled or <hi rend="underline">Coal</hi>
                    <del unit="letters" atLeast="4" atMost="6"/>
                    <add place="above">he</add> having purchased the underground property, employs
                    many diggers for that vendable commodity.</p>
                <p>If you remember in our morning Jaunt passing <add place="above">South</add> to
                        <placeName ref="pl0385"><hi rend="underline">Hawthorden</hi></placeName> we
                    past thro' a small Kirk village which lyes low bordering on the <placeName ref="pl2803">North Esk</placeName> river, went <del>over</del>
                    <add place="above">along</add> the bridge, ascended a steep curvated road,
                    having gain'd this our Course was directly turn'd to the west up the river, we
                    reached <placeName ref="pl0385">Hawthorden</placeName> two <add place="above">miles</add> or somewhat more <del rend="overstrike">miles</del> of English
                    measure west of this Village, it is a Scots mile directly west of <placeName ref="pl0080">Dalkeith</placeName> on the same river which runs by its North
                    side as the <placeName ref="pl2804">South Esk</placeName> does <add place="above">on</add> the South Side of this country Town &amp; both Rivers
                    join in <persName ref="pe2019">his Grace of Buccleughs</persName> Parks or
                    Inclosures East of the Palace. <placeName ref="pl2399">Lasswade</placeName> is a
                    thoro'fare village for all passengers to <placeName ref="pl0398">Gala</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl0405">Melrose</placeName> &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi> five miles South of this: turn up <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0186"><hi rend="underline">Taylor &amp;
                                Skinners Book of roads</hi></title></bibl> South of <placeName ref="pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName> &amp; you must easily find it out a deep
                    valey between two risings — In this description I've been minutely tedious, as
                    we went out from this by the <placeName ref="pl2399">Lasswade</placeName> road
                    &amp; returned here again by the <placeName ref="pl0967">Roslin</placeName>
                    road, for the Chaise was ordered to go back by <placeName ref="pl2399">Lasswade</placeName> &amp; come up for us at <placeName ref="pl0967">Roslin</placeName> &amp; stopt on the way to examine <placeName ref="pl2805">the <hi rend="underline">Oily well</hi> at S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Kathrine's</placeName>.</p>
                <p>I take the Liberty of informing you that <persName ref="pe2016">Sir James
                        Clerk</persName>, his Brother <persName ref="pe0017">Geo. Clerk Maxwell
                            Esq<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi></persName> one of our Comissioners of
                    the Customs, <persName ref="pe2013">John of Eldin &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi></persName> and even all the daughters of the Family are very
                    remarkable for fine Geniuses in painting, sketching, music &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi> &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi> it gives me
                    great satisfaction that you relish the Etchings, many hundreds of sketches of
                    Views in England, Scotland &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi> he has by him
                    &amp; amuses himself at leisure hours in etching; will endeavour to get what
                    else he may publish to compleat your Collection for which reason he desired me
                    to stitch up the Book in the form sent you &amp; he pasted them on the paper
                    himself ––––– I know many of the Family who are now no more, every on had a
                    Taste peculiarly uncommon in the liberal Arts &amp; mechanicks, <persName ref="pe2013">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> John's</persName> children
                    promise to inherit these dispositions; <persName ref="pe2016">the
                        Knight</persName> has no Children but a Patron to every Young Artist, have
                    free access to copy from his fine Collection <add place="above">at <placeName ref="pl0726">Pennycuik</placeName></add>, many good Originals.</p>
                <p>Upon receipt of your Letter I wrote <persName ref="pe0190">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Donaldson</persName> to come Call at
                        <persName ref="pe0108">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Hixon</persName> for
                    a Set of <hi rend="underline"><persName ref="pe0058">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Cordiners</persName> Prints</hi>, received no answer from
                    him, but learn some Parcels for me <del rend="overstrike"><unclear reason="illegible">are</unclear></del> were put on board a Ship that
                    ought to have been here last Convoy, but thro' the avidity of the Master to get
                    a full Cargo evaded that opportunity, amongst these I hope the prints make one
                    parcel, all are packt up in <persName ref="pe0190">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Donaldson's</persName> Bale for his Shop here; these may
                    approach us shortly hence. I am happy that the M.S is advancing apace to you,
                    persuade myself the publication will be acceptable to the public, whenever you
                    can get it superintended.</p>
                <p>The late drubbing <persName ref="pe1589">P. Jones</persName> got on <placeName ref="pl2806">the Northumbrian Coast</placeName> &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi> as reports go (which to the discredit of the times are shamefully
                    double) all fears of such uncourtly visits from such barbarous fellows as him,
                    are now much vanished, yet the Money gatherers to dread the alarm, as our Shore
                    will not every where admit so comfortable a Security as you do in: for my own
                    part having nothing but the inclination &amp; ability to labour for a sustaining
                    pittance. I do the best to keep up my spirits as long as health permits, &amp;
                    expect no insult from the Pyrate, hoping such rough usage will not visit us in
                    my days. ––––– A more <sic>shoaking</sic> Scene happened t'other day amongst our
                    new raised Highland Regiment called <hi rend="underline">West Fencibles</hi>, of
                        <placeName ref="pl0818">Argyleshire</placeName> &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi> men which has brought an indelable slur on our Country in general
                        viz.<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> for sedition &amp; rebellion against
                    military discipline &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi> that must for the future
                    put a perpetual &amp; just refusal to the request of a <hi rend="underline">Scots Militia</hi>: this is the third insurrection in this place, within so
                    short a period: however real or imaginary the soldiers complaints may have been,
                    I am not able to determine (for our tales handed about are so vague no faith can
                    be given to them) yet must confess that these unhappy dissentions have taken
                    rise from the insidious arts &amp; practises of our low wretched principled
                    commonality upon these unhappy men, with numbers of these evil designing people
                    our place does abound &amp; I wish for the good of the Nation in general no
                    Highland Regiment should ever be quarter'd here again: nay from what I saw &amp;
                    suffered myself in 1745 I shall ever be delicate in <add place="above">the</add>
                    allowing Arms &amp; military stores to be too wantonly bestowed on these my wild
                    Countrymen to be used here; they will be under better subjection in foreign
                    parts than at home. It's said this commotion took rise from too high a price
                    demanded for some <add place="above">part</add> of their dress as Bonnet,
                    leather pouch or pocket with the hair &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi> or
                    some such <sic>triffles</sic>. — Such small matters blow the flame of
                    Insurrection too rapidly violent. — but hope it's now at an end after four of
                    the mutineers got discipline in presence of a number of the Corpse.</p>
                <p>I have scarce lookt into the new <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0294">History of Edinburgh</title></bibl>, <persName ref="pe2020"><hi rend="underline">Arnot</hi></persName> the Author, tho' am acquainted
                    with him, yet admired <add place="above">him</add> not, his principles do not
                    tally with mine, he is satyrical; profuse, of the reprobate &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi> cast; some praise &amp; others condemn the work;
                    it does not please generaly as he is bitter or sever where he wants an attack,
                    the price is unreasonably dear 25 Shillings for a moderate 4<hi rend="superscript">to.</hi> no plates but an indifferent view of the <hi rend="underline">Register Office</hi> &amp; a poor plan of the Town, either
                    the self same one done by <persName ref="pe2021">Armstrong</persName> the
                    wretched impostor of a Surveyor, or it's copied from him: if you desire a Copy I
                    beg acceptance of a copy, which shall send to you by the way of <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> recommended to any one's care you please: I
                    shall some time hence purchase one for myself when the price lowers, he reads
                    more pleasantly than the harsh <hi rend="underline">stonern</hi>
                    <persName ref="pe0161">Maitland</persName>, but the later is to be respected for
                    many of his <add place="above">old</add> collections which <add place="above">are</add> mostly faithfull, these are (am told) mostly overlookt by
                        <persName ref="pe2020">Arnot</persName></p>
                <p><persName ref="pe0039">M<hi rend="superscript">r. Bruce the Abbissinian
                            Traveller</hi></persName> seems of late to be in a torpid state, some of
                    his admirers say he is shut up in composition, others shrewdly tell <del unit="letters" quantity="3"/>
                    <add place="above">he is</add> an Imposture: I never had access to see any of
                    his drawing, which some admire &amp; others attest he cannot draw; I am at a
                    loss to inform you of his motions, but probably in a month or so I may meet with
                    one of his confidents, from which <add place="above">quarter</add> shall gain
                    some hints &amp; will write you. ––––– Should you not have <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0186"><hi rend="underline">Taylor &amp;
                                Skinner's Scot's Roads</hi></title></bibl> by you I shall send you a
                    Copy, but think <persName ref="pe0022">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                        Ramsay</persName> purposed this several years ago.</p>
                <closer><salute>I am <lb/> D. Sir <lb/>Your most obed<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>
                            Serv<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi></salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0228">GPaton</persName></signed>
                    <dateline><placeName ref="pl0696">Custom h<hi rend="superscript">o.</hi>
                            Edinburgh</placeName>
                        <lb/>13 Oct<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> 1779.</dateline></closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>P.S. A catalogue of <persName ref="pe0022">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                            Ramsay's</persName> Books will make part of a greater Collection for
                        Sale, the prices annexed (which will not be of the moderate line) to each
                        Book: this is preparing at present. it shall be sent in course when it goes
                        to press.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>