<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0542">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>George Paton to Thomas Pennant</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP326</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>12</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0228">George Paton</persName>
                    <date when="1774-01-20"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0696">Custom House Edinburgh</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct0150"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct0149"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="en">Gaelic</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
                <p>Three days ago I received yours of 11<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> Current,
                    &amp; have been in daylie Expectation of hearing from the West <placeName ref="pl0711">Highlands</placeName> with the Erse name for the Bagpipe but
                    this storm must retard a speedy Return.</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe0575">A particular Friend</persName> from <placeName ref="pl0821"><unclear reason="illegible">Athole's</unclear></placeName> who
                    understands that Language as spoken in the Dialect of that County informs me the
                    Word <hi rend="underline">Piohb</hi>, pronounces nearly pee<hi rend="underline">b</hi> is always <add place="above">used</add> to express that Instrument
                    of Musick with them, <hi rend="underline">Balg</hi> signifies <hi rend="underline">Bag</hi>. It is to be observed that there is no <hi rend="underline">term</hi> of Distinction known in <placeName ref="pl0711">the Highlands</placeName> for Bagpipe, Big Bagpipe or Irishpipes: these two
                    later are peculiar to the <placeName ref="pl1139">Low Country</placeName> &amp;
                    are used with Bellows instead of <hi rend="underline">Mouth-blow pipe</hi>,
                    practised by the genuine Highland pipers: so that the large pipe may have the
                    word <hi rend="underline">mohr</hi> or big added and for this smaller kind the
                    word <hi rend="underline">beg</hi>, <add place="above">small or little</add>
                    conjoin'd. — But of this more fully when I obtain the Answer from the West.
                    ––––– I am told that there was about 10 or 12 years ago a <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0584">Collection of Erse Poems</title></bibl> printed
                    amongst which there is a Poem on the <hi rend="underline">Bagpipe</hi>
                    containing (I presume a Discription as also) the Uses this Instrument was
                    applied to: pray let me know if you have not a Copy of these Poems, I will
                    endeavour to make Search for a Copy to send you in Course of the Post after
                    Receipt of your Answer to this.</p>
                <p>In the Course of Conversation with <sic>severals</sic> who understand the Erse, I
                    have been told the Highlanders have these three Distinctions for the Inhabitants
                    of <placeName ref="pl0777">Britain</placeName> 1. they call themselves <hi rend="underline">Gael.</hi> 2. the low Country people <hi rend="underline">Gald</hi> or as pronounced <hi rend="underline">Galt.</hi> 3. The English
                        <hi rend="underline">Sasonich</hi>, which is plainly according to <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0406">Cambden</title></bibl>
                    <hi rend="underline">Saxons.</hi> ––––– The Etymology of Gald is more difficult.
                    2. Whether this be a corruption of <hi rend="underline">Gothic</hi>? but to me
                    who does not understand the Erse appears harsh.</p>
                <p>I beg leave to inform you that ever since I had <unclear reason="illegible">the</unclear> pleasure of seeing you in this Country; it has been <unclear reason="illegible">my</unclear> earnest desire to trace out <persName ref="pe0161">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Maitland's</persName> (Author
                    of <unclear reason="illegible">the</unclear>
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0182">History of Scotland 2 Vol.
                            fol.</title></bibl> &amp; <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0299">of
                            Edinburgh</title></bibl>) <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0240">Manuscript Papers</title></bibl> which at last I have got Account of,
                    nay am promised the Use of them, a Gentleman whom I engaged in the Search &amp;
                    has at last found them, writes me there are amongst them <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0246">Collections relating to the Western
                        Islands</title></bibl>; but as they are too bulky to be transmitted in
                    parcels by Post; I have requested the Favour of their being sent me by the first
                    ship coming to <placeName ref="pl0077">Leith</placeName> from the North where
                    they are deposited at present: this I look for in a month or so hence. — I know
                    not <del rend="overstrike">in</del> what State they are in, neither can it be
                    ascertain'd whether he has inserted all these into his printed Books, which I
                    have by me &amp; will as accurately as I can compare together: but in the mean
                    time if you think of reaping any benefit therefrom, be so good as give me your
                    fullest Instructions, which shall be religiously attended to as far as lies in
                    my power.</p>
                <p>I hope the two Etchings will be come to hand by this Time, have seen by the same
                    hand an etched View of <placeName ref="pl0967"><hi rend="underline">Roslin
                            Castle</hi></placeName>, but the plate was destroyed, however if I can
                    by any means procure a loan of this, will put it in a Friends hand to copy it
                    for You: for it's a Doubt if any more remain but this single Copy: am told the
                    same Gentleman has many more Sketches of &amp; about <placeName ref="pl0967"><hi rend="underline">Roslin</hi></placeName>, of which shall make Inquiry
                    about and in due time inform you: as I perceive at present <placeName ref="pl0708">the Islands</placeName> attract your Attention: connected with
                    these I've this day got <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0229">the M.S.S
                            History of the Family of Maclean</title></bibl>, which is near 90 pages
                    folio very closly written, so wait your Call for Extracts.</p>
                <p>In hopes of hearing from you at Convenience</p>
                <closer><salute>I am <lb/>Dear Sir <lb/>Your most obed<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi>
                            Serv<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi></salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0228">GPaton</persName></signed>
                <dateline><placeName ref="pl0696">Custom house Edinburgh</placeName>
                    <lb/>20 January 1774.</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><address>
                        <addrLine>To</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Thomas Pennant Esq<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi></addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Downing</addrLine>
                    </address></p>
                <p><handShift/>Bagpipe <lb/>Maitland <lb/><hi rend="underline">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Paton</hi>
                    <lb/>Jan.20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1774.</p>
                <p><unclear reason="illegible">answered.</unclear></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>