<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1049">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Thomas Pennant to Richard Bull</title>
            <respStmt>                     <name>Transcribed by Ffion Mair Jones; edited by Ffion Mair Jones; encoded by Vivien Williams. (2019)</name>                 </respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                        <idno>5500C</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>no. 51</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <additions><hi rend="italic">On address sheet in Richard Bull's hand</hi>:
                            <p>Ritratto della Regina Catherine Cornar<del>a</del>o | from Palma Pinx – <persName ref="pe0402">Hollar</persName> Sculp: 1650.<note type="editorial">For 'Ritratto della Regina Catarina Cornara / Palma pinxit', engraved by 
                                Wenceslaus Hollar, 1650, see <ref type="http" target="https://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/2ca28a">here</ref> [accessed 15 May 2019]. Palma il Vecchio (?1480–1528) is identified as the artist.</note>
                                Starch<note type="editorial">See Bull's instruction to Pennant on the use of 'Starch instead of flour' for pasting prints, in <ref target="1052.xml">1052</ref>.</note></p>
                        </additions></physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <date when="1786-01-26"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0759">Stratton Street Piccadilly</placeName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage> <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><dateline><placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName> Jan- 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1786.</dateline><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
                <p>I acknowlege the receit of the bill which satisfies <persName ref="pe0014">moses</persName>
                    &amp; me. I spoke to him about the condition of some of the leaves; &amp; hope he will in future be more 
                    careful; but he ever sets less value on his own drawings than others do. I have a set or two on large paper 
                    left. if you chuse it, I will replace those leaves, &amp; reserve them for some one less in my esteem than 
                    yourself. I have heard from many quarters of the respect payed to me by the late <persName ref="pe0073">Doctor Johnson</persName>:
                    but have not yet seen the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0214">book</title></bibl>.<note type="editorial">For Johnson's warm commendation of Pennant as one who 'has greater variety of inquiry than almost any man', and (in answer to criticism of him) as 'a man six feet high, and you are angry because he is not seven', see James Boswell, The journal of a tour to the Hebrides, with Samuel Johnson, LL.D. By James Boswell, Esq., published on 1 October 1785, pp. 268–9.</note>
                    I flatter myself on the occasion; for I gave him a light lash in my <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0008">voyage to the Hebrides</title></bibl><note type="editorial">Pennant's only reference to Johnson in A tour in Scotland and voyage to the Hebrides 1772, appears to be in the pirated Dublin edition of 1775, where he writes that the 'the isle of Col, [is] still more celebrated for being the place where Doctor Samuel Johnson had long and woeful experience of oats being the food of men in Scotland, as they are of horses in England'. Pennant, A tour in Scotland and voyage to the Hebrides. MDCCLXXII (2 vols.; 4th edn., Dublin: A. Leathley, MDCCLXXV [1775]), II, p. 270. Johnson, in A Journey to the Western Islands of Scotland (London: 1775), p. 207, refers to a 'fit of simple credulity' of Pennant's and, less grudgingly, to the likely exactitude of the latter's measurements of two churches at p. 243. The likely publication date of the Dublin edition of Pennant's Tour makes it possible that there was interplay between the two men of the kind described in this letter.</note>
                    which he <del>again</del> repayed in <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0095"><hi rend="underline">his</hi> voyage</title></bibl>.
                    that done I rejoice to find he began a new score in the way of affection. Pray what gave rise to your remark on
                    <persName ref="pe0104">Gough</persName>. I have known him long: He is constitutionally peevish: no man more severe in the mistakes of others yet 
                    <hi rend="underline">no man living</hi> more liable to error than himself. I <del><gap unit="letters" quantity="2" reason="illegible"/></del>once 
                    suspecting him of forming a paper against me in the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0420">Gent. Mag:</title></bibl>
                    but I believe I wronged him so sent my excuses In that or some other paper is a foolish remark about the <hi rend="underline">Pax</hi> I mention p. 23 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0032">journey to London</title></bibl>. the critic w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>
                    have it than it ought to be <hi rend="underline">Pix</hi>.<note type="editorial">The critical comment on Pennant's use of the word 'pax' in The journey from Chester to London states: 'In p. 23, l. 11, for "pax" we surely should read "pix", the box in which the Romanists keep the consecrated host'. See Gentleman's Magazine, vol. LIII (1783), 408. The letter is signed 'Antiquarius', but Gough habitually signed himself 'D.H.' in his correspondence with the magazine, and Pennant had mistaken the identity of his critic.</note>
                    but to shew you that I was right I borrowed a <hi rend="underline">Pax</hi> from a romish Priest &amp; 
                    caused it to be drawn. it is a silver plate with a crucifixion engraven on the front which the Priest holds
                    up to the congregation just as he dismisses them. I put in several things not very interesting, but 
                    consider nature takes a long nap between <placeName ref="pl0002">Chester</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>.</p>
                <p>I hope to hear that you will soon date from <placeName ref="pl0759">y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> own house</placeName>.
                    for I do not like those <placeName ref="pl1020">isle of wight</placeName> excursions when I am in <placeName ref="pl0699">town</placeName>.
                    as to <persName ref="pe0780">M<hi rend="underline">r</hi> Luther</persName> he is the most complaisant of Husbands. I hold up the Pax to him.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>adieu
                    <lb/>Y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> most truely</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0232">T Pennant</persName>.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>In case I add any drawings to <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0012">welsh Tours</title></bibl> or
                        <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0032">journey to London</title></bibl> w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>
                    you like them on thin paper in order to paste them on y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> margins.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><stamp type="postmark">PENY POST PAYD <gap unit="letters" quantity="3" reason="illegible"/><note type="editorial">triangular stamp</note></stamp></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>