<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1052">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Richard Bull to Thomas Pennant</title>
            <respStmt>                     <name>Transcribed by Ffion Mair Jones; edited by Ffion Mair Jones; encoded by Vivien Williams. (2019)</name>                 </respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP189</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>2</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                    <date when="1786-02-21"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0759">Stratton Street Piccadilly</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage> <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><dateline><placeName ref="pl0759">Stratton Street</placeName>, Feb<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>. 21. 1786</dateline><salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener>
                <p>I should have written to you upon my first coming to <placeName ref="pl0699">town</placeName>, but for a reason
                    that I will give, before I send this letter.</p>
                <p>I will desire you to give <persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName> very many thanks for his most acceptable present of the
                    <rs type="art" ref="ar0253">Virgula Divinatoria</rs>, which I have been in vain hunting for a print of, and which I remember to have seen in some weekly publication. In case you add any drawings to the 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0015">welsh Tour</title></bibl>, or <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0032">journey to London</title></bibl>,
                    I shall be very desirous to have copies, on thin paper, to paste upon the Margins of my Books. I have talk'd with <persName ref="pe0332">Storer</persName>,
                    relative to <rs type="art" ref="ar0073">Catherine Cornaro</rs> being conceal'd under the name of La Bella Laura,
                    but he is not so clear and explanatory upon the subject, as he is upon most occasions.<note type="editorial">For the misidentification of Catherine Cornaro with Petrarch's Laura, see <ref target="1048.xml">1048</ref>.</note></p>
                <p>your cannot forget there is a print engrav’d by <persName ref="pe0402">Hollar</persName> in 1650, from a picture
                    of Palma, with the following inscription, vid<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. <rs type="art" ref="ar0254">Ritratto della Regïna Catharina Cornaro</rs>,
                    and which print I intend to place in my book untill I can procure a copy of <persName ref="pe0392">Lord Ossory</persName>'s
                    Picture, tho perhaps from no better authority than the print.</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe0431">Thane</persName> has been too much busied of late with the care of <persName ref="pe0781">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Blackburn</persName>'s
                    extensive <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0611">Catalogue of Prints and drawings</title></bibl>, just coming under
                    the hammer, and with his attendance upon <persName ref="pe0396">Gulston</persName>'s sale, to have had any leisure 
                    for other matters;<note type="editorial">Joseph Gulston's collection of prints and portraits was auctioned over a period of 38 nights from 16 January to 13 March 1786. <hi rend="italic">Gentleman's Magazine</hi>, LVI, part the second (1786), 622.</note> nor do I know any thing he has lately publish’d, except a neat <rs type="art" ref="ar0133">Print of the <persName ref="pe0782">Admiral Seymour</persName></rs>,
                    from a miniature of <persName ref="pe0434">Horace Walpoles</persName>, finely copied by <persName ref="pe0783">Lady Lucan</persName>
                    from an original picture <add place="above">by <persName ref="pe0401">Holbein</persName> now in the possession of the
                        <persName ref="pe0784">Marquis of Buckingham</persName></add> Apropos to <persName ref="pe0396">Gulstone</persName>
                    - half his sale is over, and tho’  the trash with which it abounds sells for little, such Lots as have either curiosity or Scarceness to recommend them rise
                    to prices beyond all manner of belief. a paltry print of <rs type="art" ref="ar0134"><persName ref="pe0785">Pendrel</persName>
                        in the oak</rs> not worth a shilling sold for £8: 15. 0., <rs type="art" ref="ar0135">Anthony Henley</rs>
                    for £8: 10. 0. – <rs type="art" ref="ar0136">Earl of Cumberland</rs> £5: 5. 0.
                    <rs type="art" ref="ar0137">Earl of Arundel</rs> £ 7: 7. 0 – <rs type="art" ref="ar0138">Humfry  LLoyd</rs>
                    £5: 14. 0. and a <rs type="art" ref="ar0139">little foolish scratch of <persName ref="pe0788">Hogarths</persName> engrav’d on a snuff box</rs>, of which few impressions were taken fetch’d £33: 0. 0. – it was intrinsically worth one penny, and no more.</p>
                <p>What Man could be so poor, or so tasteless as to return <persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName>'s most ingenious 
                    performances upon his hands?<note type="editorial">See <ref target="1051.xml">1051</ref>.</note> Why not bring the book to <placeName ref="pl0699">town</placeName>, and get it into the 
                    first auction of credit, it would probably find its own value, if not, it is only buying it in yourself, and the 
                    duty is sacred. I have recommended it to at least a dozen different Amateurs, and have shewn my <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0032">journey to London</title></bibl>
                    as a sample, but proffer’d service – you know what should follow. – Now a word or two as a reason for my not having answer’d 
                    your letter sooner, and I will worry you no longer. I return’d to town on account of the arrival of <persName ref="pe0413">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Morice</persName>'s
                    will from <placeName ref="pl0923">Naples</placeName>, and since it has been open’d, my whole time has been taken up in 
                    different businesses relative thereto, for my family hath a much larger interest therein than we had any reason to expect, 
                    indeed his whole property has fallen into our laps, to what extent we are yet to learn, but at all events, it must be very 
                    considerable. He has given me an annuity of £500 a year, and to my Daughters<note xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" type="editorial"><xi:include href="Bulls.xml"/></note>
                    an annuity of £100 per Ann<hi rend="superscript">m</hi>. - all the rest of his Estates, real and personal, whatsoever 
                    &amp; wheresoever, he has bequeath’d to <persName ref="pe0346">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Luther</persName> for her life,
                    and after her decease to <persName ref="pe0331 pe0336">my two Girls</persName> in equal proportions, <hi rend="underline">for ever,</hi>
                    and I must premise that in the manner we and <persName ref="pe0346">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Luther</persName>
                    have always liv’d together, it is just the same as <add place="above">if</add> we had immediate possession. He left 
                    <persName ref="pe0293">Burrell</persName>, his Executor, £1000. –</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe1373">Carter of <placeName ref="pl0776">Westminster</placeName></persName> has done a drawing for you
                    of the <rs type="art" ref="ar0140">Priory at <placeName ref="pl1335">Dunstable</placeName></rs>, &amp; I wish to know
                    whether you have any objection to his copying it for my <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0032">Journey to London</title></bibl>,
                    as he won’t do me one without your permission. The creases on the print enclosed, will all come out if you wet the print, 
                    <hi rend="underline">all over,</hi> and lay it flat in some book that is smooth, and for the future whenever you want paste remember to use
                    <hi rend="underline">Starch</hi> instead of <hi rend="underline">flour</hi>. I can’t yet find any method of being useful to 
                    <persName ref="pe0065">your son</persName> in his travels, but <persName ref="pe0797">a friend of mine</persName> is going,
                    the first week in June, to <placeName ref="pl1340">Lausanne</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1341">Geneva</placeName>,
                    and will take any parcell you wish to send.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I am my dear Sir, always yours, and always
                        <lb/>with truth &amp; sincerity, but always in haste</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0313">Rich<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>: Bull -</persName></signed>
                    <dateline><placeName ref=""/></dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>