<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1053">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Thomas Pennant to Richard Bull</title>
            <respStmt>                     <name>Transcribed by Ffion Mair Jones; edited by Ffion Mair Jones; encoded by Vivien Williams. (2019)</name>                 </respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                        <idno>5500C</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>no. 53</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <date when="1786-03-04"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage> <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><dateline><placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName> March 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1786.</dateline><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
                <p>I sincerely congratulate you, &amp; <persName ref="pe0346">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Luther</persName>
                    on the great acquisition of fortune.<note type="editorial">See <ref target="1052.xml">1052</ref>.</note> may health &amp; every other blessing give you the full relish of it. I hope no calls 
                    from bad health in any of your family will make another retreat from <placeName ref="pl0699">the Capital</placeName> necessary,
                    for I now find your presence there no small addition to my comfort whenever I happen to visit the place. But for the 
                    uncommon severe return of winter, we should have set out in about a weeks time: now our journey is uncertain, because we 
                    dare not venture our two little ones,<note type="editorial"><persName ref="pe0235">Sarah</persName> and <persName ref="pe0421">Thomas</persName> Pennant, junior.</note> who were to have visited town at the request 
                    of certain relations who appeared anxious to see them. Whenever I come I shall bring with me the Tours in Wales<note type="editorial">See <ref target="1051.xml">1051</ref>, n. 1, which identifies the edition being extra-illustrated at this time as <bibl><title ref="bi0015">A tour in Wales</title></bibl> (2nd edn., 1784)</note> &amp; <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0032">the journey to London</title></bibl> to be bound. since you had your sets
                    many additions are made which <persName ref="pe0014">moses</persName> will be happy to execute for you: He will have done near a dozen in 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0032">the journey</title></bibl> since yours reached you. The man with the <rs type="art" ref="ar0253">virgula divinatoria</rs> was taken from <persName ref="pe0798">Agricola</persName> <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0155">de re metallica</title></bibl>.
                    I thank you for <rs type="art" ref="ar0133"><persName ref="pe0782">Admiral Seymour</persName></rs>. Before I bind
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0032">the journey</title></bibl> I shall new-write the whole account of the 
                    pictures at <placeName ref="pl1342">Hatfield</placeName><note type="editorial">For Pennant's description of portraits at Hatfield, Hertfordshire, see <hi rend="italic">The journey from Chester to London</hi> ([1782]), pp. 403–11. It is noted on p. 411 that 'Since this account of these pictures was taken, they have been differently arranged'.</note>
                    according to the present arrangement. This shall be printed, &amp; the old leaves cancelled. let me honestly premise that I 
                    cannot bear every expence of collecting matter, printing these gratuitous affairs, &amp;c &amp;c. I shall expect those 
                    interested to go a small share &amp; that I think my friend will not refuse. Pray send me the name of some M. P. to whom I may inclose 
                    now <persName ref="pe0015">Sir R. M.</persName> is setting out. I will also bring up the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0025">Introduction to the arctic Zoology</title></bibl> in its half binding you will see what a rich volume I have made of it: but I know you will soon beat me so zealous, 
                    &amp; conversant are you in prints. I <del>am</del> have some where read that <persName ref="pe0799">Aristotle</persName>
                    lays it down as a certainty that no great attempts are wisely undertaken or successfully executed after our forty ninth year.<note type="editorial">Aristotle, <hi rend="italic">Rhetoric</hi>, part 14: 'The body is in its prime from thirty to five-and-thirty; the mind about forty-nine'.</note>
                    you will certainly brand me with foll<del><gap unit="letters" quantity="2" reason="illegible"/></del>y when I tell you I am going to
                    <hi rend="underline">finish</hi> my <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0037">Indian Zoology</title></bibl> on the plan of the 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0022 bi0023">arctic</title></bibl> at a period in which I want but 
                    <hi rend="underline">four months of sixty</hi>. I give up the pretensions to the wisdom, but will not to the success of the attempt, 
                    unless I meet with certain external obstructions which the successful are almost sure of 
                    m<del><gap unit="letters" quantity="2" reason="illegible"/></del>eeting.
                    I will anticipate your idea of the <persName ref="pe0809">archbishop of Grena<supplied>d</supplied>a</persName>
                    in <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0615">Gil Blas</title></bibl>: for I suspect that Idea 
                    wi<supplied>ll</supplied>
                    arise in your mind.<note type="editorial">Rash, vain and susceptible to flattery, the archbishop of Granada in Lesage's <hi rend="italic">Gil Blas</hi> suffers from 
                        diminished capacities following an apoplectic fit, producing a sermon which is no better than 'a vague discourse, the rhetoric of an old professor, 
                        a mere capucinade'. Alain René Lesage, <hi rend="italic">The Adventures of Gil Blas de Santillane</hi>, trans. Tobias Smollett (3 vols., London, 
                        1819), II, p. 221. For Pennant's fears of emulating the archbishop and his determination to 'hang up my pen in time' lest he should do so, see his 
                        comments in the Advertisement to <hi rend="italic">Of London</hi> (1790), p. v.<note type="editorial">
                    </note>
                    </note> But why <sic>may not the be</sic> a second spring in the animal man as well as the vegetable world. Do not you think it wise at lest
                    in <del><gap unit="letters" quantity="7" reason="illegible"/></del> one who is advanced in life to approach towards the sun,
                    &amp; to be invigorated with its rays in a region over which it shines with fuller power than in this frozen clime?<note type="editorial">Pennant describes the geographical foci of further volumes of his 'Outlines of the Globe'.</note> Think of being made attendant in my ideal voyage along the soft shores of 
                    <placeName ref="pl1202">Iberia</placeName>, till we reach the sultry <placeName ref="pl1352">Senegal</placeName>; sail along the 
                    barbarous coast of <placeName ref="pl1353">Africa</placeName>, double the cape, &amp; inhale the <placeName ref="pl1354">Sabæan</placeName>
                    odors of <placeName ref="pl1355">antient arabia</placeName>. be enraptured with <placeName ref="pl1024">India
                        &amp; its islands</placeName>; &amp; point out to you the novel beauties of the creation in all that that 
                    can be pleasing to Eye smell or taste, Happily the paper proves a ne plus,<note type="editorial">Short for 'ne plus ultra', translatable here as 'command to go no further'.</note>
                    but not to what <gap unit="letters" quantity="1" reason="illegible"/> will never cease that of subscribing myself</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Dear Sir
                    <lb/>most truely &amp; affect<hi rend="superscript">ly</hi> y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi></salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName></signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Remember me to <persName ref="pe0293">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Burrel</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe0332">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Storer</persName>.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>