<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1056">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Richard Bull to Thomas Pennant</title>
            <respStmt>                     <name>Transcribed by Ffion Mair Jones; edited by Ffion Mair Jones; encoded by Vivien Williams. (2019)</name>                 </respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP189</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>4</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                    <date when="1786-12-27"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0759">Stratton Street</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage> <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir.</salute><dateline><placeName ref="pl0759">Stratton Street</placeName> Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: 27. 1786.</dateline></opener>
                <p>I did not receive the favor of your letter, till I return'd again to <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>,
                    and the dear bought pleasures of this vile <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>, which <persName ref="pe0336">my poor daughter</persName>
                    begins to feel the Effects of already, tho in truth such weather as this, would make the teeth of a Laplander chatter.
                    I have not answer'd your <del>kind</del>Obliging letter, because nothing therein particularly requir'd it, except to ask when, and
                    <add place="above">to</add> whom I can pay the contents of the little account due to <persName ref="pe0014">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Griffith</persName>,
                    for the drawings you had the kindness to send enclos'd in your last. I much want a <rs type="art" ref="ar0142">view of Nanney House</rs>,
                    If <persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName> has ever taken it, and a <rs type="art" ref="ar0144">portrait of <persName ref="pe0823">David Gamm</persName></rs>,
                    and I don't recollect where I am to place <rs type="art" ref="ar0145"><persName ref="pe0810">Lord Donnegal</persName>'s Seat, call'd <placeName ref="pl1359">Fisherwyck</placeName></rs>,
                    or the <rs type="art" ref="ar0143">portrait of <persName ref="pe0113"><choice><abbr>Ch:</abbr><expan>Chief</expan></choice> Justice Glynn</persName></rs>.</p>
                <p>I have a friend in the custom House <add place="above">at <placeName ref="pl1372">Cowes</placeName></add> preparing an
                    e<del><gap unit="letters" quantity="2" reason="illegible"/></del>xact and faithful account of the exportation of Grain, and flower from the 
                    <placeName ref="pl1020">Island</placeName>, which is much encreas'd since the publication of <persName ref="pe0436">Sir Rich<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>: Worsley</persName>'s 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0290">book</title></bibl>, &amp; I have learn'd from an <del>old</del> old &amp; very
                    intelligent <add place="above"><gap unit="letters" quantity="1" reason="illegible"/></add> Tenant of my own, that Ground 
                    <hi rend="underline">well</hi> marl'd, will find the good effects of it for 20 years, but after it has once receiv'd  this 
                    measure, it answers no purpose to apply it a second time; experiments have been made after 25, and 30 years, and the only 
                    effect <supplied>produc'd</supplied> even at such a distance of time, has been to make a stiff Soil work rather more free: 
                    the quantity generally laid on, is 20 waggon loads to an Acre. I have been round the <placeName ref="pl1020">Island</placeName>,
                    and have observed nothing romantic or uncommon among the vast Cliffs, which surround the South and South West part of
                    <add place="above">it</add> <del><placeName ref="pl1020">the Island</placeName></del> except what has been already notic'd in 
                    <persName ref="pe0436">Sir Rich<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>: Worsley</persName>'s <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0290">publication</title></bibl>.
                    The high land of <placeName ref="pl1373">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Albans in Dorsetshire</placeName>, and 
                    <placeName ref="pl1375">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Catherine's Point in the Isle of Wight</placeName>, from a great
                    <add place="above"><gap unit="letters" quantity="1" reason="illegible"/></add> Bay, and in <hi rend="underline">blowing weather</hi>
                    with the wind to the South West, hardly any vessel, that gets within it, escapes without coming ashore; to prevent this the
                    <placeName ref="pl2119">Trinity House</placeName> a few years since erected at the expence of £7000, two light houses, one upon <placeName ref="pl1375">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Catherine's hill</placeName>,
                    and one upon the <placeName ref="pl2118">high downs just above the needle Rocks</placeName>, and a third upon 
                    <placeName ref="pl1377">Hurst: beach</placeName>; the two last were lighted for the first time the 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.
                    of last September, but the former has never yet been illuminated. a Toll or duty of one shilling, for every coasting vessel 
                    passing the lights is collected by the <placeName ref="pl2119">Trinity House</placeName>. British vessels bound on foreign
                    pay ½ per ton, Foreigners double. Sailors doubt whether the lights upon the two <placeName ref="pl2118">high Points of the needles</placeName>,
                    and <placeName ref="pl1375">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Catherine</placeName>'s will answer any good purpose; they say 
                    they had been better seen upon the beach, than where they are, because in bad weather, when most wanted, those high hills 
                    are almost always envelop'd in clouds, and of course the lanthorns invisible <add place="above">at</add> any little distance,
                    and that for some time to come, they will be liable to be mistaken for the <placeName ref="pl1378">Portland lights</placeName>;
                    one fatal instance of which, has already <sic>happend</sic>, for the night before we left <placeName ref="pl1020">the Island</placeName>
                    a <placeName ref="pl1228">Dutch</placeName> Frigate of 36 Guns and 250 men came bump ashore, (mistaking the lights) and was beat to pieces, 
                    &amp; tho most of the crew were sav'd at last, the surf ran so high, it was one night, and two days before they could be brought off.<note type="editorial">This refers to the Dutch frigate 'Juno' (36 guns) which came aground in Freshwater Bay on the Isle of Wight on 20 December 1786. See <hi rend="italic">Chelmsford Chronicle</hi>, 15 December 1786, quoting a letter of 12 December 1786 which corroborates Bull's account of the difficulty of the rescue operation; and <ref target="https://tinyurl.com/ydcsgxgm" type="http">here</ref> [accessed 9 August 2018].</note>
                    I saw myself, for four hours together, the Captains wife, and other women, waving their handkerchiefs, and shewing every sign of 
                    distress, and I make myself believe I was the means of saving eight men by bribing a desparate Smugler to go off to them in his boat.<note type="editorial">The following section is bracketed to the end of the paragraph.</note> The Fishermen who <del>have</del>
                    <add place="above">used to</add> get a miserable livelyhood on the back of the <placeName ref="pl1020">Island</placeName> 
                    are ruin'd by the vigilance of the Government cutters, and by the tea act, for tho' fishing was the pretence,
                    Smugling was their trade. they tell me the tide is not <sic>particilarly</sic> affected by Storms, and that 
                    <add place="above"><gap unit="letters" quantity="1" reason="illegible"/></add> at Spring tides it seldom 
                    rises above 8 feet, and (what seem'd to me very extraordinary) that it flow'd there 9 hours out of the 12. –––––</p>
                <p>I have not seen <persName ref="pe0379">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Chiswell</persName>, to lament the downfall of 
                    my book<note type="editorial">It is not clear to which book Bull refers here nor what its connection with Chiswell might be; but on a later offer for Bull to have Chiswell's Ingleby drawings for <hi rend="italic">A tour in Wales</hi> copied by Moses Griffith, see <ref target="1065.xml">1065</ref>.</note>
                    - <persName ref="pe0332">Storer</persName> is still at <placeName ref="pl1023">Paris</placeName>, where he went to make a
                    bow at the <persName ref="pe0824">King</persName> for his picture. the rest of <del>di</del> Our friends are dispersed, 
                    but I hope we shall all meet in the Spring. I shall be glad to hear all your family enjoy their healths, and that 
                    your usual chearfulness and agreeable spirits do not forsake you – valeat Possessor!<note type="editorial">Bull quotes from Horace, <hi rend="italic">Epistles</hi>, I, II, l. 49: 'valeat possessor oportet' ('may the owner thrive').</note>
                    as for me I am old, quite deaf, and almost blind, and of course my family ought to kill me and eat me, as I 
                    have read the children of some parts in <placeName ref="pl1353">Africa</placeName>, do their parents, when they grow old, and good for nothing like,</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>my Dear Sir,
                    <lb/>Yours very sincerely</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0313">Rich<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>: Bull</persName></signed>
                    <dateline><placeName ref=""/></dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>