<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1062">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Thomas Pennant to Richard Bull</title>
            <respStmt>                     <name>Transcribed by Ffion Mair Jones; edited by Ffion Mair Jones; encoded by Vivien Williams. (2019)</name>                 </respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                        <idno>5500C</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>no. 29</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <date when="1786-07-11"><note type="editorial">1786 is suggested because of the apparent link between questions asked here and information provided in <ref target="1056.xml">1056</ref>. Pennant's claim that he has 'personally visited' every part of the journey from London to the Scilly Isles probably rests on his juvenile travels rather than on his 1787 tour of this territory alongside his son David. See Evans, 'The life and work of Thomas Pennant', pp. 443–5; Pennant, <hi rend="italic">From London to Dover</hi> (1801), p. 77; <hi rend="italic">From Dover to the Isle of Wight</hi> (1801), pp. 148–54.</note></date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage> <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="fr">French</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
                <p>I am happy in a friend who so instantly apprehends the intents of my questions &amp; answers them in so very a
                    satisfactory a manner. my plan ought to be unfolded to you, as you take so kind a part in my labors. I have 
                    already written a view of <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> in its antient state, but drop it soon 
                    after the conquest.<note type="editorial">This appears to refer to the beginnings of Pennant's <hi rend="italic">Of London</hi>, published in 1790.</note>
                    I still wish to give a state of its increase in population, &amp; of the Customs to the present time. any
                    hints on that head will be of use. is there any account of the increase of the latter: suppose it to be by 
                    æras of twenty years.</p>
                <p>I take my departure from <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>: &amp; give as good an account as I can of the 
                    <placeName ref="pl1389">Thames</placeName> as <del>I <gap unit="letters" quantity="7" reason="illegible"/></del> far As its 
                    mouth, then proceed coastways to <placeName ref="pl1020">y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> <hi rend="underline">Fortunate island</hi></placeName>;
                        &amp; thence in the same manner to the <placeName ref="pl1390">Scilly isles</placeName>. 
                    This suffices for the present. every part of this tract I have personally visited except <placeName ref="pl0922">Sussex</placeName>.
                    If you can point out &amp; describe anything curious on the back of the <placeName ref="pl1020">isle of Wight</placeName>
                    or that may be seen from sea you will not fail to embellish my labors greatly. are there any <hi rend="underline">autres dire</hi><note type="editorial">'other things worthy of mention'.</note> &amp;c &amp;c to be mentioned, beneath the 
                    stupendous cliffs of fresh water bay, or any other wonders worthy to be attended to? I have <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0290"><persName ref="pe0436">Worsley</persName></title></bibl>
                    but he is useful only in the historic part.  I have numbers of views of headlands &amp;c on the foreign coasts of my plan,
                    but am rather deficient in those of <placeName ref="pl0777">Britain</placeName>. I think you need not trouble yourself any 
                    further about the queries except answering that relative to the quantity of salt exported. perhaps that of corn may give an 
                    idea of the fertil<del>y</del>ity of the <placeName ref="pl1020">isle of W</placeName>.</p>
                <p>I <del>am</del> was not a little irritated when I wrote last by a fresh piece of injustice done to poor <persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName>
                    by another Welsh man of fortune who bespoke an illuminated copy &amp; gave repeated orders about the manner of doing it 
                    <add place="above">after being made acquainted with his terms.</add> but when finished expected to have about forty 
                    eight pounds of work <del>of</del> for eight pounds.<note type="editorial">This man has not been identified.</note>
                    To a poor man this is cruel usage, who expected to lay up something against old age: happily for him I have made
                    him in some measure partaker of my authorial gains &amp; have saved for him no inconsiderable sum. This misfortune 
                    involves us in it. for I am above six months behind hand in work, which likewise affect you, which I truely lament. 
                    But in future you alone shall share the fruits of his pencil. He gratefully acknowleges his obligations to you.</p>
                <p>I am at present at <placeName ref="pl1391">Parkgate</placeName> for the sake of bulking <persName ref="pe0235 pe0421">my two little ones</persName>.
                    I return home next week. Our friend <persName ref="pe0284">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hunt</persName> who presents 
                    his Compliments to you frees this to you.<note type="editorial">Pennant appears to have sent an enclosure from Hunt, possibly a duplicate print or engraving for Bull's benefit.</note></p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>every good wish attend you &amp; yours.
                    <lb/>I am Dear Sir
                    <lb/>most truely y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi></salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0232">T Pennant</persName>.</signed>
                    <dateline>July 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1783 but Q.<note type="editorial">The year is added in Richard Bull's hand.</note></dateline>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>I was yesterday at <placeName ref="pl0723">Liverpool</placeName>. to shew the abundance of wealth in that great town, 
                        the Corporation are laying out 200 000<hi rend="superscript">£</hi> in pulling down whole streets, purchasing houses &amp;c
                        in order to rebuild them with the utmost splendor &amp; regularity</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>