<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1064">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Richard Bull to Thomas Pennant</title>
            <respStmt>                     <name>Transcribed by Ffion Mair Jones; edited by Ffion Mair Jones; encoded by Vivien Williams. (2019)</name>                 </respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/ TP 189</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>6</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                    <date when="1787-08-14"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl1013">Northcourt, Isle of Wight</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage> <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
                <p>I have receivd the pleasure of your letters, one dated June 16. the other July 29.<note type="editorial">See <ref target="1061.xml">1061</ref> and <ref target="1063.xml">1063</ref>.</note> inclosing Drawings from
                    <persName ref="pe0014">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Griffith</persName> corresponding with the account remitted therewith, 
                    and which I much wish to know where to pay, that He and I, may continue good friends. I hold myself highly oblig’d to you 
                    for Sparing me so much of his time, and shall set it down on the Debtor side of my book, amongst the many marks of attention 
                    you have honor’d me with, and which I mean to pay whenever I am able, in the mean time think of me often, and esteem me as 
                    much as you can. <persName ref="pe0837">Our only M. P.</persName> arriv'd in the <placeName ref="pl1020">Island</placeName>
                    two days ago, and I have procur’d a frank as soon as possible, without which, and without having any particular business to 
                    write about, I should have thought myself unpardonable in troubling you.</p>
                <p>In my last to <persName ref="pe0293">Burrell</persName>, I gave him a wrap on the knuckles, respecting his unusual silence 
                    to your requests, and I did it the more willingly, hoping to find it a mistake, because I have ever experienc’d his punctuality 
                    upon all occasions.<note type="editorial">For Pennant's complaints about Burrell, see <ref target="1063.xml">1063</ref>.</note> poor fellow! I hardly think he could read my jobations, which must have reach’d his hands, just at the time 
                    when the heaviest of all misfortunes fell upon him, whilst sleeping by the side of <persName ref="pe0838">his wife</persName>,
                    who was in hourly expectation of being brought to bed, and who has since been deliver’d, and is wonderfully well. If you have 
                    not already heard it, I must be the unwilling newsman to you, and inform you, that he has been attack’d with a very severe 
                    paraletic stroke, and has quite lost the use of one side, from his face downwards, and his friends apprehend a second stroke, 
                    perhaps at no great distance, will be the consummation devoutly to be wish’d, at least so I should think. I have known him 
                    almost as long as memory can look back, and the earliest circumstances I can recollect, are kindnesses received from him, no 
                    wonder therefore, this mellancholy event affects me extremely.</p>
                <p>I have been frequently to <placeName ref="pl1392">Appuldurcombe</placeName>, and dont ] find many pictures worth your recording, the chief are
                    <lb/><rs type="art" ref="ar1050"><persName ref="pe0629">Henry VIII</persName></rs>. said to be a true picture of <persName ref="pe0401">Holbein</persName>
                    <lb/><rs type="art" ref="ar1049"><persName ref="pe0829">Edward VI</persName></rs>. a child, formerly in the <placeName ref="pl0699">royal collection</placeName>, by <persName ref="pe0401"><choice><abbr>D<hi rend="superscript">o</hi></abbr><expan>Ditto</expan></choice></persName><note type="editorial">Hans Holbein, the younger.</note>. 
                    <rs type="art" ref="ar1051"><persName ref="pe0830">Frances Howard Countess of Somerset</persName></rs>. the picture from which <persName ref="pe0840">Simon Pass</persName>,
                engrav'd the Print.
                    <lb/><rs type="art" ref="ar1052"><persName ref="pe0831">Robert Earl of Essex</persName></rs>. 1572. by no means handsome.
                    <lb/><rs type="art" ref="ar1054"><persName ref="pe0835">Isabella Clara Eugenia</persName></rs>, in a vast ruff. Engraved.
                    <lb/><rs type="art" ref="ar1053"><persName ref="pe0832">Lady Worsley</persName></rs>, wife to <persName ref="pe1421">Sir Rich<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>: daughter of <persName ref="pe0833">Sir Henry Neville</persName></persName>. - a good 
                    picture by <persName ref="pe0834">Cornelius Jansen</persName>.
                    <lb/><rs type="art" ref="ar1055">2 very Capital Landscapes</rs>, by <persName ref="pe0836">Zucharelli</persName>. ---
                    <lb/>I ask'd <persName ref="pe0093">Emondson</persName>'s <persName ref="pe0841">Son</persName> for the <rs type="art" ref="ar1056">Print of the House of Yvory</rs>,
                    at the corners of which are the <rs type="art" ref="ar1057">little Prints of Enmore</rs>; He has none struck off, nor does he know
                    where the plate is, but has promiss’d me one when it comes to hand. What you call the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0618">actual Survey of the Sussex Coast</title></bibl>,
                    I apprehend to be <persName ref="pe0844">Avery</persName>'s <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0618">Plan <del>of</del> and Chart of the Sea Coasts from the head land of
                        S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Albans to Beachy head in Suss<del><gap unit="letters" quantity="2" reason="illegible"/></del>ex</title></bibl>, 
                    with the Soundings, and distances.<note type="editorial">This 'Plan and Chart' has not been identified.</note> This map <persName ref="pe0293">Burrell</persName> could never get, and I never saw more than one, which is at a tradesman’s in this
                    <placeName ref="pl1020">Island</placeName>, and I have been long trying to coax him out of it for <persName ref="pe0293">Burrell</persName>,
                    who I doubt will <hi rend="underline">now</hi> have little occasion for it, so if I succeed it will be for you.</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName> sent me a shell with the Drawings, but being little of a naturalist, I don’t know how to name it, or where to place it.<note type="editorial">Pennant names this shell and its intended location in <hi rend="italic">The journey from Chester to London</hi> (1782) in <ref target="1065.xml">1065</ref>.</note></p>
                <p>I desire my compliments to your pleasant young friend, as well as near Relation 
                    <persName ref="pe0065">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Pennant</persName>, and my Daughters<note xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" type="editorial"><xi:include href="Bulls.xml"/></note>
                    beg their remembrances to you both.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I am Dear Sir
                    <lb/>Yours very Sincerely</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0313">Rich<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>: Bull</persName></signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>