<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1078">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Richard Bull to Thomas Pennant</title>
            <respStmt>                     <name>Transcribed by Ffion Mair Jones; edited by Ffion Mair Jones; encoded by Vivien Williams. (2019)</name>                 </respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/ TP 189</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>13</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                    <date when="1788-07-06"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl1013">Northcourt, Isle of Wight</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage> <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="fr">French</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute> <dateline><placeName ref="pl1013">Northcourt, Isle of Wight</placeName>, July 6. 1788</dateline></opener>
                <p>Having lost my old Housekeeper, who liv’d with me forty years, and having left a new Servant behind me in 
                    <placeName ref="pl0699">town</placeName>, who sent my letters into <placeName ref="pl1388">Essex</placeName>, instead of
                    <placeName ref="pl1471">Hampshire</placeName>, I have been depriv’d of the pleasure of yours till within these few days..</p>
                <p>Forgive my stupidity If I don’t construe your letter right; am I to return the letter press of 
                    England and orkney,<note type="editorial">Sections of '<bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0025">Introduction of the Arctic World</title></bibl>' undergoing extra-illustration by both Pennant and Bull. See <ref target="1077.xml">1077</ref>, where Pennant also mentions 'a forgotten treasure of drawings relative to [Orkney]'.</note>
                    or the drawings you last sent me? I shall obey your commands in either, but I know not how to get at them, being lock’d up in 
                    my Bureau in <placeName ref="pl0759">Stratton Street</placeName>, till I go next to <placeName ref="pl0699">town</placeName>,
                    which will hardly be sooner than Michaelmas, when business will call me there for a few days.</p>
                <p>I naturally supposed they were intended for <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0025">my book</title></bibl>,
                    (<hi rend="underline">the drawings I mean</hi>) and have rang’d them therein, but luckily had no time to paste them in their 
                    proper places, so, if you desire it, you shall most certainly have them return’d, malgré moi,<note type="editorial">'in spite of myself'.</note>
                    and when <persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName> has leisure to copy them, I shall rejoice to have them back again, for my 
                    own use and benefit. I am au desespoir<note type="editorial">'in despair'.</note> respecting a good binder; I quarrel with 
                    <persName ref="pe0435">Wingrave</persName> eternally, and go to others who use me worse; <persName ref="pe0889">Lord Sandys</persName>
                    recommended me one <persName ref="pe0890">Walther</persName>, a German, who does well, but his prices are enormous, and his lettering not even.</p>
                <p>I know little and care less, what is doing in <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>, but I have a good 
                    <persName ref="pe0891">french correspondent</persName>, who tells me the Storm in <placeName ref="pl0925">that Country</placeName>
                    encreases, tant mieux pour nous.<note type="editorial">'so much the better for us'.</note> it is very probable the
                    Etats Generaux<note type="editorial">On 19 November 1787 Louis XVI agreed to the convocation of the 'Estates-General' before 1792. The first meeting in fact took place on 5 May 1789.</note>
                    will be conven’d e’er long, the clergy having made a remonstrance tending to hasten such a convention. all their troubles take their rise from the 
                    American war; the day of retribution is come. <persName ref="pe0892">Mons<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Necker</persName>
                    borrow’d money, and while the Bill was not brought in, the War was popular, its aim being to distress <placeName ref="pl0777">Great Britain</placeName>.
                    now pay day is come. – the <persName ref="pe0824">monarch</persName>, &amp; the nation find the war cost money. – the nation dislikes parting with money, and the 
                    <persName ref="pe0824">monarch</persName> wishes to retain his power.</p>
                <p>The <persName ref="pe0893">Emperor</persName> seems to be making a bad figure against the Turks.<note type="editorial">Austria entered an ongoing war between Russia and Turkey on 9 February 1788 and continued at war with Turkey until 1791.</note>
                    the <persName ref="pe0894">Empress</persName> is Stop’d in her career, because <persName ref="pe0895">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thornton</persName>
                    will not supply her with transports. this gives one a poor opinion of <placeName ref="pl1474">Russian</placeName> Force,
                    when we see a transport monger, stopping the mighty armaments of her Hyperborean Majesty. The report is that 
                    <placeName ref="pl1475">Sweden</placeName> has got together her fleet by having the money advanc’d by <placeName ref="pl0777">G. B.</placeName><note type="editorial">The Russo-Swedish War of 1788–1790 began as the Swedish open sea fleet put out to sea on 9 June 1788. Western powers, including Great Britain, lobbied for a war in the north as a means of diverting Catherine II of Russia from her successful campaign against Turkey.</note>
                    - tis true money don’t abound in that country, and as it could not come from <placeName ref="pl0925">France</placeName>,
                    it is naturally supposed it is issued by the good city of <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>. 
                    Foreign nations consider this country as a perfect Fortunatus’s Cap;<note type="editorial">In the German tale of Fortunatus, popular in fifteenth- and sixteenth-century Europe, Fortunatus is given a purse containing a boundless fortune by the goddess Fortune, and steals from a sultan a hat able to transport its wearer wherever he wishes.</note>
                    put in your hand and you are sure to find an everlasting treasure. If I live to return to <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>,
                    I will write again, and tell you the news of the day, in the mean time receive my thanks, for <sic>claring</sic> 
                    up every doubt respecting the Patagonians.<note type="editorial">A reference to Pennant, <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0033">Of the Patagonians</title></bibl>.</note> we are very gay here, Sailing matches, music meetings, ship wrecks, and 
                    <persName ref="pe0896">Wilkes</persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe0897">his daughter</persName>, who are become our neighbors. – I hope you are all well – 
                    Stet Fortuna Domus.<note type="editorial">'Let the good fortune of the house endure'.</note> I, and mine are well, and what is better, contented and happy.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I am Dear Sir, yours very truly</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0313">Rich<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>: Bull</persName></signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>we have no members of Parliament here – pray respect me, for I am become a <hi rend="underline">Great Grand</hi> father
                        by the birth of <persName ref="pe0898">Sir John Swinburne</persName>'s boy. -</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><stamp type="postmark">JY 8 88</stamp></p>
                <p><address>
                    <addrLine><persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName> Esqr. | <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing | <hi rend="underline">Flintshire</hi></placeName></addrLine>
                    </address></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>