<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1095">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Richard Bull to Thomas Pennant</title>
            <respStmt>                     <name>Transcribed by Ffion Mair Jones; edited by Ffion Mair Jones; encoded by Vivien Williams. (2019)</name>                 </respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/ TP 189</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>21</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                    <date when="1790-01-02"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0759">Stratton Street</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage> <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir.</salute> <dateline><placeName ref="pl0759">Stratton Street</placeName>, Jan<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>. 2. 1790</dateline></opener>
                <p>I don’t know from what original <persName ref="pe0014">Moses Griffyth</persName>, has taken the 
                    <rs type="art" ref="ar0041">drawing of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Pitt</rs>, which he sent me at the End of your 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0025">Introduction to the Arctic Zoology</title></bibl>, but it has a Stronger likeness,
                    and more of character, and spirit, than any Picture, or print, I have yet seen of that wonderful young man. I mean this, by way 
                    of preface, before I ask you whether you have any objection to my getting it engraved <add place="above">for sale</add> it shall 
                    be done well, or not at all, and I will reserve half a dozen Impressions for you, and myself. pray give me your answer and I beg 
                    you to understand, that it is not a matter, I make a point of, if you have any objections that do not occur to me. – now I 
                    <add place="above">am</add> upon the subject of Prints, let me ask you, whether you have got the <rs type="art" ref="ar0158">four Apostles</rs>
                    <del>who</del> by <persName ref="pe0675">Rousellet</persName>, the originals of which you mention to be in <placeName ref="pl0951">Broad lane House</placeName>.
                    
                    if not, I can give you a Set. the Arms <persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName> has sent me, with the Barons Coronet, and a royal Coronet annex’d, are, I apprehend the 
                    <rs type="art" ref="ar0156">Arms of Lutterel</rs>, and that thereby hangs a tale, but what the Story is, or where I am to place the drawing I know not; pray have the 
                    goodness to inform me.</p>
                <p>If there is any news, I am not in the way of hearing it. – It is said the <persName ref="pe0393">Prince of Wales</persName>,
                    has got again into debt to a vast amount, and that he has lately borrow’d 300,000, on post obit’s,<note type="editorial">'A bond given by a borrower, securing to the lender a sum of money to be 
                        paid on the death of a specified person from whom the borrower expects to inherit.' <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>.</note>
                    which his <persName ref="pe0949 pe0959">two next brothers</persName> have guarantee’d, &amp; the payment to be made by either brother who may come 
                    to the Crown.<note type="editorial">The brothers in question were Frederick, duke of York (1763–1827), and William, duke of Clarence, later 
                        William IV (1765–1837).</note> The 
                    <persName ref="pe0418">Duke of Orleans</persName> is little respected here, it is generally believ’d that he meant to have assasinated his 
                    <persName ref="pe0824">King</persName>, and that <persName ref="pe0979">La Fayette</persName> knew it, and told him he had his head in his 
                    pocket, if he chose to take the forfeit, but He advis’d him to get a passport, and <del><gap unit="letters" quantity="1" reason="illegible"/></del>away 
                    to <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>, as fast as he could.<note type="editorial">For an account of the relations of Orléans and Lafayette 
                        following the events of 5–6 October 1789, when crowds marched to Versalles to vent their anger against the monarch, see Tom Ambrose, 
                        <hi rend="italic">Godfather of the Revolution: The Life of Phillippe Égalité, Duc D'Orléans</hi> (London: Peter Owen, 2008), pp. 169–70.</note> My <persName ref="pe0336">daughter</persName> 
                    is better, but does not gain strength, indeed she was never a Giantess. I hope you, and your house, enjoy your healths.
                    – Employ me, if you want such <gap unit="letters" quantity="4" reason="illegible"/> trifling services as I have to offer you, </p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>&amp; believe me, Dear Sir,
                        <lb/>Yours always.</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0313">R: B -</persName></signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>P.S. while I was sealing my letter, I receiv’d yours,<note type="editorial">See <ref target="1094.xml">1094</ref>.</note> – ––– <del><gap unit="letters" quantity="4" reason="illegible"/></del> 
                        I am expecting company every moment to dine, so can only say, I will go to <persName ref="pe0387">Edwards</persName>,
                        on monday morning, and as soon as I gain the intelligence you wish for, I will trouble you with another letter, as bad 
                        written as this is, which I could write better, if I would, and so could you, but neither of us think it worth while. –</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>