<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1110">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Richard Bull to Thomas Pennant</title>
            <respStmt>                     <name>Transcribed by Ffion Mair Jones; edited by Ffion Mair Jones; encoded by Vivien Williams. (2019)</name>                 </respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/ TP 189</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>23</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <additions><p><hi rend="italic">Endorsement in Thomas Pennant’s hand</hi>: <hi rend="underline">answ<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></hi></p>
                        </additions>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                    <date when="1790-08-25"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl1013">North Court</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage> <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="fr">French</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir.</salute> <dateline><placeName ref="pl1013">North Court House, Isle of Wight</placeName>
                <lb/>August 25. 1790</dateline></opener>
                <p>I send you a few very hasty lines, because you desir’d a return of the enclos’d,<note type="editorial">The enclosure is no longer present with the manuscript letter.</note>
                    and because I just now happen to have a franker in the house. – I thank you much for the private engravings, and at the same moment 
                    <add place="above">that</add> I feel myself oblig’d to you for the deep secret (which shall be buried in my breast, till you call it to resurrection) of the 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0271">new Edition of London</title></bibl>, I am almost ready to wish you every thing but 
                    <hi rend="underline">ill</hi>, for stopping me in my carrier of finishing <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0039">that work</title></bibl>.
                    I am an old man, and am fully satisfied with your <persName ref="pe0998">old secretary</persName>; at 68 one has no loose years to throw away upon expectation; 
                    Expedition is better by half to me, than even perfection to be waited for. I wish you would have the goodness to direct 
                    <persName ref="pe0111">m<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: Hugh's</persName> to send a porter, with your 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0041">litterary life</title></bibl>, <hi rend="underline">safely pack’d</hi>, and directed to me at 
                    <persName ref="pe0346">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Luthers</persName>, <placeName ref="pl1649">Lower Grosvenor Street</placeName>
                    where it will be taken care of, till my return, which may not be the case, if I direct it to be sent to <placeName ref="pl0759">my own house</placeName>,
                    because it is under a full repair, and no place lock’d up.</p>
                <p>––– I have been used very ill by <persName ref="pe0428">Smith</persName> the Engraver, with respect to the <rs type="art" ref="ar0041">little head of Pitt</rs>,
                    - the story is not worth troubling you with, tending only to prove, what you know already, that Artists, (in general I mean,) are all 
                    interested wretches, without a grain of liberality in their disposition. The Fleet lately at <placeName ref="pl1637">Spithead</placeName>
                    has made this <placeName ref="pl1020">Island</placeName> very gay,, rather too much, for me, or for my pocket, for every acquaintance 
                    calls himself ones friend, when he is upon his travels, and has no better house to go to eat his toast and butter at, than 
                    yours. since the beginning of July, I have seldom had less than ten at table every day in the parlor, and so it seems likely to 
                    continue; when they write me word of their intentions to come to view the fleet, and, <hi rend="underline">par bricole</hi><note type="editorial">'tinkering; messing around; toying'.</note> only, to visit me, in vain I answer
                    <lb/>– atria longa patent, sed nec cænantibus usquam
                    <lb/>nec somno locus est<note type="editorial">'halls stretch at length, but there is nowhere a place to dine or to sleep'. Bull quotes from Martial, Epigram L, 'In Habentem Amœnas Ædes' ('On having a charming dwelling').</note> 
                    ––– – they come for all that, and as far as my homely way of living will satisfie them, they are heartily welcome, but I put myself out of my way for no man. I think with you, that
                    <placeName ref="pl0925">France</placeName> is sinking below contempt and infamy, but how <placeName ref="pl0777">this Country</placeName>
                    has risen since its unpromissing situation a very few years back, and how good Fortune has seconded the good Intentions of our good 
                    <persName ref="pe0500">Minister</persName>?</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>You and yours have the best <hi rend="underline">good</hi> wishes, of me and mine and I am always, Dear Sir,
                        <lb/>Yours with much truth</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0313">Rich<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>: Bull</persName></signed>
                    <dateline><placeName ref=""/></dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>