<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1117">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Richard Bull to Thomas Pennant</title>
            <respStmt>                     <name>Transcribed by Ffion Mair Jones; edited by Ffion Mair Jones; encoded by Vivien Williams. (2019)</name>                 </respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/ TP 189</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>26</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <additions><p><hi rend="italic">Endorsement on top of first page in Thomas Pennant's hand</hi>: <hi rend="underline">Answ<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></hi></p></additions>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                    <date when="1791-01-21"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0759">Stratton Street</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage> <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute> <dateline><placeName ref="pl0759">Stratton Street</placeName>, <del>Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></del> Jan<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>: 21.1791</dateline></opener>
                <p>My Rheumatic hand, I hope, will serve me to tell you, that I have sent the Set of Shipping<note type="editorial">See <ref target="1116.xml">1116</ref>, n. 2.</note> to <persName ref="pe0328">Faulder</persName>'s,
                    who says he has a parcell to remit to you, with a Specimen of a very elegant work, now in course of publication, tending to illustrate
                    your <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0039">history of London</title></bibl>, and which, if my wretched Ears did not deceive me, I understood 
                    the Editors mean to present you with a copy of, upon large paper.<note type="editorial">This may refer 
                        to <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0114">The environs of London</title></bibl>. It was edited 
                        by <persName ref="pe1533">Daniel Lysons</persName>, while his brother 
                        <persName ref="pe1534">Samuel</persName> contributed many of the illustrations, as both artist and etcher. The 
                        first of four volumes appeared in 1792, but it is quite possible that this had initially been published in parts, as indicated 
                        here.<hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi>.</note> one number only is yet publish’d and proposed to be continued at 5 shillings 
                    each number, on small paper, which I shall prefer for my own use, because it is just the size of your London,<note type="editorial">Bull probably refers here to the 
                        <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0271">second edition</title></bibl> of Pennant's work on London, which Pennant had been advocating for the purposes of extra-illustration at the expense 
                        of the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0039">first edition</title></bibl> for some time. See <ref target="1109.xml">1109</ref>, <ref target="1110.xml">1110</ref>, <ref target="1111.xml">1111</ref>, <ref target="1114.xml">1114</ref>.</note>
                    and I shall bind them together. but perhaps I am talking to you, about what you know much better than I do, who am just risen from the dead, in a manner, 
                    and am ignorant of every thing that has passed for the last six weeks. – the weather makes much against an invalid, and this is the second day I have been 
                    sufficiently well to go out, even in my Carriage, else I should have procur’d the ships I promiss’d You, before now.</p>
                <p>I shall be very glad of <persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName>'s pencil, to proceed in ornamenting the margins of <del>my</del> the Zoological part of my 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0022">Arctic Zoology</title></bibl>, with Birds, beasts, fishes, &amp; all kind of animals, in which line I think he
                    shines with particular elegance, and a peculiar manner of his own, and unrival’d by any body. If he has any views to add, he will insert them of course in
                    their proper places. I will beg you to remember to inform me soon, whether I shall send <persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName> my copy of the 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0022">Arctic Zoology</title></bibl> to proceed upon accordingly, and how send it, and how direct it to him, whether 
                    at <placeName ref="pl0001">your house</placeName>, or his own. I am very sorry to find He can do nothing towards illuminating <hi rend="underline">my</hi>
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0268"><add place="above">Journey from</add> London <add place="above">to Dover.</add></title></bibl> - - - I shall
                    miss his pencil in every page. I have got your <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0041">Litterary Life</title></bibl>, for which I am desirous of 
                    thanking you as well as I am able, but I hope you will allow me to pay the <persName ref="pe0404">transcriber</persName>. Many a mawkish hour of sickness 
                    has of late been alleviated by the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0012">welch tour</title></bibl>, and <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0032">journey to London</title></bibl>,
                    which at last are <hi rend="underline">ready</hi> for the binder, I had better have said <hi rend="underline">unready</hi> for there are many desiderata to 
                    come, but I have turned the Volumes over so often, that they are daub’d sadly; and I wish to get them safely cover’d at any rate. Can you tell me, where I 
                    can possibly procure <hi rend="underline">two title plates</hi> of your <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0032">journey from Chester to London</title></bibl>,
                    because I make three Volumes of that work. I should wish for them upon large paper, but can make a good shift with small.</p>
                <p>You gave me, sometime last spring, two neat etchings, one the <rs type="art" ref="ar0175">Church of S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Margarets near Lincoln Cathadral</rs>,
                    the other <rs type="art" ref="ar0176">Mapleton Church near Ashbourn Derbyshire</rs>. pray remember in your next to say whether they are private etchings, 
                    and if so, by whom, and I also wish to know whether they have reference to any work of yours.</p>
                <p>pray have the goodness to ask <persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName>, if he has any drawings of any kind, which refer to any part of your 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0012">tour in Wales</title></bibl>, or <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0032">journey to Lond</title></bibl>,
                    which are not <hi rend="underline">too large to paste onto the Margins of my Volumes, and which I have not already had</hi>, 
                    and if he can find any, that I shall be very glad to have copies upon thin paper. He <del>knows</del> knows, most likely, what I have already had, if not I can send him a list, without much trouble. 
                    <persName ref="pe0328">Faulder</persName> says, the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0271">2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Edition of London</title></bibl>
                    goes off, as well as the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0039">first</title></bibl>. it is in every bodies hands, and extremely well spoken of. I write 
                    with pain, and I am afraid illegibly.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I am always yours, my worthy friend, and always
                        <lb/>with truth – </salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0313">R. B. -</persName></signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>There is a talk to day, that the <persName ref="pe1048">Chancellor</persName> is to resign, with a large pension,
                        and that <persName ref="pe1049">Baron Eyre</persName> is to be a peer, and Chancellor, but not to be speaker of the 
                        House of Lords, which is to be given to <persName ref="pe1050">Lord Grenville</persName>.<note type="editorial">Grenville's likely appointment as Speaker of the Lords was, bewilderingly, reported in the <hi rend="italic">Chelmsford Chronicle</hi> on 3 December 1790, immediately beneath the report that Sir James Eyre was spoken of for the same title.</note>
                        – I don’t give it you as truth. –</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>