<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1123">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Richard Bull to Thomas Pennant</title>
            <respStmt>                     <name>Transcribed by Ffion Mair Jones; edited by Ffion Mair Jones; encoded by Vivien Williams. (2019)</name>                 </respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/ TP 189</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>29</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                    <date when="1791-02-21"/>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage> <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute><dateline>21 Feb<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>. 1791</dateline></opener>
                <p>I send you <persName ref="pe0412">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Minchins</persName> account of the <placeName ref="pl1582">Forest of Bere</placeName>,
                    which you saw from <placeName ref="pl1703">Port-down</placeName>, and I will pledge myself that it is a true one. You must have seen 
                    <placeName ref="pl1705">Southwick</placeName> at the same time, of which I know not where to find any account proper for your insertion, 
                    but I will endeavour to get information. As soon as I get the <rs type="art" ref="ar0168">Drawing of Lord Fanhope</rs>
                    from Carter,<note type="editorial">For the identity of Carter, see <ref target="1122.xml">1122</ref>, n. 1.</note> I will send it to <persName ref="pe0143">Mazel</persName>, with what prints I can pick up of your list. I should be 
                    glad to have any Drawings for the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0269">Dover M.S</title></bibl> that <persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName>
                    can furnish me with, particularly of Birds, beast’s, fishes, and other parts of natural history, and I wish to 
                    know your opinion whether I had not better return the M.S. itself; that the drawings may be done there on, instead of having them on detach’d pieces of 
                    paper. at any time when you want to write to me, enclose your letter, to <persName ref="pe0422">Lieu<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>: General Rainsford</persName>,
                    <placeName ref="pl1988">Soho Square</placeName>, and he will send it to me regularly, and with exactness. You’ll thank me for what 
                    <del>is not worth</del> is not worth a thought, but ’tis <del><gap unit="letters" quantity="5" reason="illegible"/></del> I,
                    who am the oblig’d person, and I am sure I think so.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I am Dear Sir, as always
                        <lb/>Sincerely yours.</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0313">R.B.</persName> -</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>P.S. if you have time, turn to page 24. of the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0269">Dover M.S.</title></bibl>
                        &amp; you will see the mistake, (which is mine and not yours) respecting the <persName ref="pe1241">Earl of <placeName ref="pl1351">Northampton</placeName></persName>,
                        was a natural one. – After speaking of the <del>latter</del> <persName ref="pe1242">Earl of <placeName ref="pl1385">Arundel</placeName></persName> 
                        the virtuoso Lord, you proceed and say “<hi rend="underline">He</hi> had the honor of founding two others at clun &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>.
                        and <hi rend="underline">He</hi> seem’d to rest his character on a few good works &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>. &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>. - -<note type="editorial">See <hi rend="italic">From London to Dover</hi> (1801), p. 21, where the ambiguity to which Bull draws attention here has been corrected. ('Northampton had the honour of founding to others, at Clun in Shropshire, and at Castle-rising in Norfolk. He seemed to rest entirely on a few good works...'.)</note>
                        to an unattentive reader the <hi rend="underline">He</hi> seems to refer to the latter, and not the former, whose name perhaps requires to be repeated after the break in the sentence. 
                        their characters indeed were not <sic>simalar</sic>, but that may not be known to the generality of readers. –</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>