<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1146">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Richard Bull to Thomas Pennant</title>
            <respStmt>                     <name>Transcribed by Ffion Mair Jones; edited by Ffion Mair Jones; encoded by Vivien Williams. (2019)</name>                 </respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/ TP 189</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>39</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                    <date when="1792-01-20"/>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage> <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="fr">French</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="it">Italian</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute><dateline>Jan<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>. 20. 1792</dateline></opener>
                <p>I give you this trouble merely to answer a question of yours in a former letter, which I had no opportunity of 
                    doing sooner, altho' I had enquir’d of every Nabob that came in my way, and of all the Booksellers I knew.</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe0422">Rainsford</persName>, upon asking him the same question, this minute informs me, that he 
                    <hi rend="underline">had</hi> the book, but lent it to a friend, who has never return’d it. the title is 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0522">Zendavesta</title> <add place="above">in English the lighter of the sacred fire,</add></bibl>
                    written by <persName ref="pe1537">Anquetel de Perron</persName>, and having therein, (unless he is extremely mistaken), the 
                    journey from Goa, to Poonah.</p>
                <p>I am sorry to find your <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> journey is not likely to take place soon, and more so, for the occasion of its being postpon’d. I am glad 
                    <persName ref="pe0065">your Son</persName> deserves so well, and that your worthy <persName ref="pe0237">Sister</persName> has the
                    means, as well as the Heart, to behave so much en Princesse;<note type="editorial">'like a princess'.</note> to make a young man quite happy, 
                    He must have a little less time, and a little more money than He absolutely has occasion for; and so 
                    <hi rend="underline">She</hi> seems to think. Don’t send <persName ref="pe0421">your son</persName>
                    to <placeName ref="pl2548">Westminster</placeName>, experto crede,<note type="editorial">'trust one who knows'.</note>
                    I was there seven years; a Boy may learn there, if he pleases, or may let it alone, if he likes better to be idle, no particular attention is 
                    paid to any body, except to the Sons of ministers, or other great men, by whose interest the masters, and Ushers expect to rise in 
                    the world, as in general they do: thus it was forty years ago, and I don’t hear of any alteration, except that vices of every sort, are 
                    more abundant, and less restraint laid upon them. I know a <placeName ref="pl2548">Westminster</placeName> Boy, who is a Debauché at 16, 
                    and whom I have heard at Eleven o’clock at night, complaining he did not know any clever place to spend the Evening at.</p>
                <p>The Character which the present <placeName ref="pl1899">Eton Seminary</placeName> bears, is still more discouraging, and for 
                    reasons which a decent pen ought not to write. a particular friend of mine, the celebrated <persName ref="pe0388">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Erskine</persName>
                    speaks highly of <placeName ref="pl2550">Winchester School</placeName>, and the manners of <persName ref="pe1670">his son</persName>
                    who is now there, seem to authorise his predilection for it.</p>
                <p>
                    Private Schools have their disadvantages certainly, and very material ones, nor can I tell where good ones are now to be found. one at 
                    <placeName ref="pl2483">Kensington</placeName><note type="editorial">On various schools at Kensington during the eighteenth century, see 'Private Education from the Sixteenth Century: Developments from the 16th to the early 19th century', in <hi rend="italic">A History of the County of Middlesex: Volume 1, Physique, Archaeology, Domesday, Ecclesiastical Organization, the Jews, Religious Houses, Education of Working Classes To 1870, Private Education From Sixteenth Century</hi>, ed. J. S. Cockburn, H. P. F. King and K. G. T. McDonnell (London, 1969), pp. 241–55. See <ref type="http" target="http://www.british-history.ac.uk/vch/middx/vol1/pp241-255">here</ref>.</note>
                    is well spoken of, and another at <placeName ref="pl1746">Sa<supplied>li</supplied>bury</placeName>,<note type="editorial">This may refer to the grammar school at Salisbury cathedral in Wiltshire. 'The cathedral of Salisbury: Eighteenth to twentieth centuries', in R. B. Pugh and Elizabeth Crittall (eds.), <hi rend="italic">A History of the County of Wiltshire: Volume 3</hi> (London: Victoria County History, 1956), pp. 197–210. See <ref type="http" target="http://www.british-history.ac.uk/vch/wilts/vol3/pp197-210">here</ref>.</note>
                    but I know not enough of either to recommend them. I am <add place="above">myself</add> at this minute very anxious about this matter, because the 
                    friend of my heart <add place="above"><persName ref="pe0382">Lady Clarges</persName>?</add><note type="editorial">The name 'Lady Clarges?' is added in pencil, neither in Richard Bull nor in Pennant's hand.</note>
                    has a <persName ref="pe1671">Son</persName> ready to send to school, and She depends upon me to make those enquiries, 
                    which a woman cannot, and ought not to do.</p>
                <p>
                    I have return’d your Volume of <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0038">Indian Zoology</title></bibl> to <persName ref="pe0328">Faulder</persName>,
                    not without feeling very much oblig’d to you for permitting me to ask for it, but in truth I am so little of a naturalist, that 
                    <hi rend="underline">unless it is somehow connected with your <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0022">artic Zoology</title></bibl></hi>,
                    (the only part of your natural history I am possess’d of) I should act contrary to my fix’d intention, in never depriving 
                    any body of a Print, or a book, that I do not immediately stand in need of. – The news of the day <add place="above">which may be alter’d to morrow</add>
                    is, that the <persName ref="pe0465">King</persName>, and the <persName ref="pe0393">Prince of Wales</persName>, are upon the best terms again, 
                    that the former is to dine with the latter shortly, and that Parliament will be apply’d to, <del><gap unit="letters" quantity="2" reason="illegible"/></del>to
                    add £40,000 a year to his income, upon the condition of the <persName ref="pe0465">King</persName>'s taking his debts upon himself, which are 
                    said to amount to 800,000£. perhaps the intended addition to the <persName ref="pe0949">Duke of Yorks</persName> establishment may make the 
                    <persName ref="pe0393">Elder Brothers</persName> hopes appear less unreasonable. but alas! one Brother would lose a world at Play, if he had it, and the other 
                    would fool away a world in race<del>s</del><add place="above">horses</add> and hunters, and unworthy connections. they say 
                    <persName ref="pe1672">her Grace of York</persName> is very unhappy, both at the late hours, and the manners of a 
                    <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> fashionable life, as well upon the Account, of <persName ref="pe0949">her Sposo</persName>’s unabating propensity
                    to play. I saw her at the tragedy of the Gamester (where <persName ref="pe1139">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Siddons</persName>
                    play’d Mrs Beverly) weeping and wailing with such seeming feeling, that I really felt for her myself.<note type="editorial">Sarah Siddons (née Kemble) (1755–1831) and her brother, John Philip Kemble, first played the parts of Mr and Mrs Kemble in Moore's <hi rend="italic">The Gamester</hi> on 22 November 1783. <hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi>.</note></p>
                <p>
                    The Report is, that <persName ref="pe1065">Lord Salisbury</persName> is to lose his high office, for having given 
                    <persName ref="pe1676">Martindale the Faro Dealer</persName>, one of the most efficent, and respectable employments, 
                    be<del><gap unit="letters" quantity="3" reason="illegible"/></del>longing to him as L<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>
                    Chamberl<del><gap unit="letters" quantity="3" reason="illegible"/></del>ain.<note type="editorial">For a contemporary report of this appointment, see <hi rend="italic">Hampshire Chronicle</hi>, 20 February 1792, which notes the significance of the promotion: 'It is to this officer that all the writs on the election of member of Parliament are delivered from the crown-office; and, on a general election, it is a place of very particular consequence.'</note></p>
                <p>
                    It is said too that the <persName ref="pe0393">Prince of Wales</persName> has made the <persName ref="pe1677">Duke of Queensberry</persName>'s
                    peace at <placeName ref="pl1105">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. James's</placeName>,<note type="editorial">In 1789, during the regency crisis, George, Prince of Wales, was backed by William Douglas, fourth duke of Queensberry (1725–1810), in a vote against William Pitt. Contrary to Bull's account here, this led to Douglas's dismissal from the favour of the king after the latter's return to health. <hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi>.</note>
                    and that he is to have some good department at Court. What has a very rich, a very old, and a very deaf man to do with places at Court, 
                    or, having quarrelled with an indulgent Master at 65, what business had he with a reconciliation at 70? – It seems agreed, 
                    <hi rend="underline">on all sides</hi>, that no Chancellor of the Exquequer ever open’d his budget, with such very amazing abilities, both as to matter, 
                    <del><gap unit="letters" quantity="2" reason="illegible"/></del>and manner, as <persName ref="pe0500">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Pitt</persName>
                    did his, last week.<note type="editorial">The <hi rend="italic">Northampton Mercury</hi>, 21 January 1792, predicted that 'Mr. Pitt will, in the approaching Session of Parliament be enabled to open his Budget with an eclat beyond that of any preceding period, which must considerably add to the reputation he has already acquired from his abilities as a financier. In addition to the annual million, there is stated to be a surplus of no less than eight hundred thousand pounds above the ordinary expenditure'.</note></p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>– give our best remembrances to your family, and believe me, my Dear Sir, 
                        <lb/>Yours very sincerely</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0313">Rich<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>: Bull</persName></signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>