<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1147">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Richard Bull to Thomas Pennant</title>
            <respStmt>                     <name>Transcribed by Ffion Mair Jones; edited by Ffion Mair Jones; encoded by Vivien Williams. (2019)</name>                 </respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/ TP 189</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>40</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <additions>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Endorsement on top of the letter, in Thomas Pennant’s hand</hi>: <hi rend="underline">Answd</hi></p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Printed newspaper extract, glued in beneath address at top of page</hi>: <persName ref="pe0232">Mr. PENNANT</persName> - His seasonable admonition on the Burials at 
                                <placeName ref="pl2494">St. Giles</placeName>, has already produced a reform in almost all the Parishes of <placeName ref="pl0776">Westminster</placeName><note type="editorial">See <ref target="1148.xml">1148</ref> for Pennant's reference to his having 'workd among the burial grounds'.</note>.
                            </p>
                        </additions>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                    <date when="1792-01-21"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0759">Stratton Street</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage> <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="it">Italian</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute> <dateline><placeName ref="pl0759">Stratton Street</placeName>. January 21. 1792</dateline></opener>
                <p>Illness, and not Idleness has prevented my writing, to acknowledge the receit of your last. Alas! I have no 
                    Glastonbury thorns<note type="editorial">A variety of hawthorn. See <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> s.v. Glastonbury.</note> in my nursery, for we never bloom in the winter. I have enclos’d 
                    <rs type="art" ref="ar0311">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Cecilia</rs>, which seems to have little more merit than being horridly like, but the Print has had a very rapid sale, for all that.</p>
                <p>
                    You mention a <rs type="art" ref="ar0333">small Q<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> print of yourself</rs>, a new one, as I understand,
                    and ask whether <persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName> may ornament one for me, and paste it <hi rend="underline">neatly</hi>
                    on large paper<add place="above">for the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0023">Arctic Zoology.</title></bibl></add> - to be
                    sure he may, and I shall readily pay him for it, and thank him into the Bargain, as I shall You, for furnishing him with the means of doing it. I am just now set in, with your 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0268">Dover journey</title></bibl>, and <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0041">litterary life</title></bibl>,
                    both which will bear good adornings but I must request <persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName> to furnish me with an ornamented Title page of some sort, for the 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0686">litterary life</title></bibl>, upon a <add place="above">1/2</add> sheet of Pretty stout paper of this size<note type="editorial">A diagram follows, representing the title page mentioned, with the measurements '15 Inches / <del><gap unit="letters" quantity="2" reason="illegible"/></del> 1¾.'</note></p>
                <p>
                    I have been loth to worry <hi rend="underline">him</hi>, or to torment you, but I am in dispair about <rs type="art" ref="ar0306">Lusty Packington</rs>,
                    of whom you promiss’d to let me have a copy taken, for <placeName ref="pl1986">Greenwich</placeName>.<note type="editorial">Bull refers to the section on Greenwich in Pennant's <hi rend="italic">From London to Dover</hi> (1801), with John Packington mentioned on pp. 12–13.</note> now we are upon 
                    <persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName>'s subject, ask him if he can do me a small <rs type="art" ref="ar0334">drawing of the whiff Flounder</rs>,
                    upon thin paper for the margin of <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0015">my Book</title></bibl>,<note type="editorial">The whiff ('A name for various flat-fishes or flounders', <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>) is illustrated in Pennant, <hi rend="italic">A tour in Wales</hi> (2nd edn., 1784), plate III, following a description of the fish most plentiful in the estuary of the River Dee, on ibid., p. 20. This makes it likely that Bull is here writing of his extra-illustration of the Welsh tour.</note>
                    the print being not sufficiently explanatory, or else mine is a bad impression. I thank you, con spirito,<note type="editorial">'with spirit'.</note>
                    for all your kind intentions, respecting the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0023"><sic>Artic</sic> Zoology</title></bibl>. I won’t say to 
                    <persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName> upon this occasion, what <persName ref="pe0922">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Radcliffe</persName>
                    did to <persName ref="pe1072">Sir Godfrey Kneller</persName>, about a door the latter <del><gap unit="letters" quantity="1" reason="illegible"/></del>
                    wanted to be moved in the Garden of the former – tell <del>him</del><add place="above">your master</add> (says the D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. to the messenger)
                    he may do any thing to the door, so he don’t paint it;<note type="editorial">This anecdote relating to the physician John Radcliffe (bap. 1650, d. 1714) and Sir Godfrey Keller (1646–1723), history and portrait painter, is related in Thomas Joseph Pettigrew, <hi rend="italic">Medical portrait gallery: biographical memoirs of the most celebrated physicians, surgeons, etc. etc. who have contributed to the advancement of medical science</hi> (4 vols., London: Fisher, Son, &amp; Co., n.d.), I, 'John Radcliffe, M.D.', p. 5.</note>
                    on the contrary, I desire he may paint my book as much as he pleases. I congratulate you upon getting safe from abroad, 
                    all your articles of virtú, and curiosity;<note type="editorial">On the return of a German and Italian collection shipped home by David Pennant from the continent, see <ref target="1145.xml">1145</ref>.</note> and very much I felicitate You upon the return of <persName ref="pe0065">your Son</persName>,
                    safe and sound, I hope and trust, in health, principles, and pocket, and not too much, nor too little foreignized. the more he resembles 
                    his worthy and respectable Parent, the better it will be for his friends, his Country, and himself.</p>
                <p>
                    If you want news you must enquire at the Faro tables, which are abused, and visited, by all the fashion of the town; 
                    <persName ref="pe1676">Martindale</persName> finds it worth while to pay the Ladies, where they are weekly establish’d, forty Guineas a night, for the use of their Houses.
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I am, Dear Sir, with my usual good wishes to You, and your family, 
                        <lb/>Your very oblig'd hum: Serv<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0313">Rich<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>: Bull</persName></signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>