<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1150">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Thomas Pennant to Richard Bull</title>
            <respStmt>                     <name>Transcribed by Ffion Mair Jones; edited by Ffion Mair Jones; encoded by Vivien Williams. (2019)</name>                 </respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                        <idno>5500C</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>no. 103</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <date when="1792-02-11"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage> <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute><dateline><placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName> Febr 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1792.</dateline></opener>
                <p><persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName> shall do all that is necessary: but he &amp; I are such bunglers at pasting that we did not dare to undertake it, so gave you the trouble. Many thanks for 
                    <rs type="art" ref="ar0335">Lord Cowper</rs>: the price is most acceptable though I risque the punishment of a postumous libeller, I must say it will perpetuate his insignificancy.</p>
                <p>
                    I am at this time a good deal deranged in my plans by the long continuance of my good <persName ref="pe0237">sister</persName>'s 
                    illness. such is her hospitality &amp; her munificence: that I know we shall add to her weight of pain by being in 
                    <placeName ref="pl0699">town</placeName>; &amp; she incapable of receiving &amp; seeing us as she was wont to do. I cannot but in gratitude mention her kindness to 
                    <persName ref="pe0065">my son</persName> on his return in october. She <del><gap unit="letters" quantity="3" reason="illegible"/></del>
                    presented him with a new chaise: &amp; settled on him by way of pocket money 400<hi rend="superscript">£</hi> a year. These are such rare instances that they merit record. almost weekly my motives to visit 
                    <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> lessen. the Lady just mentiond is one. the enquiry after another school for my 
                    <persName ref="pe0421">little son Tom</persName> a second: I abjure <placeName ref="pl1899">Eton</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl2548">West<del>c</del>minster</placeName>:
                    but a larger than that he is at at present must be found. let me not be thought <del>if</del>a flatterer if I say <persName ref="pe0313">m<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bull</persName>
                    is no small motive. to my journey. my friends fall off apace. one died last sunday: another is struck with a palsy &amp;
                    equally dead to the world. These things sink deep into me: and <sic>make wish</sic> my retreat as permanent as human duration will admit. I have all that conduces to ease. 
                    domestic happiness, increasing fortune; a disposition to contribute part at lest to the public good. <del>Sir R</del> To divert the subject:
                    <persName ref="pe0015">Sir R.M.</persName> leaves the country next week: so how shall I convey double letters to you: if such I have occasion to see. one of 
                    <persName ref="pe0015">Sir Roger</persName>'s businesses is to marry his <persName ref="pe1663">second daughter</persName> a <del><gap unit="letters" quantity="2" reason="illegible"/></del>
                    beautiful giantess to little <persName ref="pe1682">m<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Champnes</persName> son of a <persName ref="pe1683">Baronet</persName>
                    a fugitive for debt in foreign parts. <persName ref="pe0015">Sir R.</persName> is a prudent man so I dare say the lover has <sic>goo</sic> reversions. but to us it seems a comical affair.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Adieu
                        <lb/>Y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> most faithfully</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0232">Tho. Pennant</persName></signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Pray what is become of our friend <persName ref="pe0332">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Storer</persName>.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>