<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1157">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Richard Bull to Thomas Pennant</title>
            <respStmt>                     <name>Transcribed by Ffion Mair Jones; edited by Ffion Mair Jones; encoded by Vivien Williams. (2019)</name>                 </respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/ TP 189</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>43</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <additions>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Endorsement at the bottom of the page, in Thomas Pennant's hand</hi>:</p>
                        <p><hi rend="underline">Answ<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></hi></p></additions></physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                    <date when="1792-09-23"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl1013">Northcourt</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage> <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="fr">French</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute> <dateline><placeName ref="pl1013">Northcourt</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1020">Isle of Wight</placeName>. September 23. 1792</dateline></opener>
                <p>Altho’ I do not plume myself upon being a good correspondent, or even a punctual one, I think it incumbent upon me, to give an answer of some sort, and immediately, to your 
                    very kind, and as usual, very friendly letter. It reach’d my hands last night only, having been as great a rambler as myself, for I have been in 
                    <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> several times since my first Journey hither. – no wonder your letter could not find me 
                    <add place="above">at</add> <placeName ref="pl1608">Brighthelmstone</placeName>, for we left the place a week before it's arrival, and that town is growing like 
                    <add place="above">a little</add> <placeName ref="pl0796">Bath</placeName> for magnitude, so that such an unimportant Individual as myself, had a little chance of being remember’d.</p>
                <p>
                    We hope now to be stationary here, till the middle or end of November, having little other pleasure to look forward to in <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>,
                    than the hopes of finding a good deal of <persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName>'s <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0023">Arctic Zoology</title></bibl>
                    there, upon our return, and perhaps some few Drawings relative to <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0271">your London</title></bibl>. 
                    As you seem so amazingly deep, in <placeName ref="pl2515">China</placeName>,<note type="editorial">For Pennant's engrossment in work on China for his 'Outlines of the Globe', see <ref target="1155.xml">1155</ref>.</note> I ought not to omit telling you, that 
                    <persName ref="pe0437">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Penruddock Wyndham</persName>, an exotic Inhabitant of <placeName ref="pl1020">this Island</placeName>,
                    like myself, and <hi rend="underline">now</hi> amongst my visitors at <placeName ref="pl1013">Northcourt</placeName>, has brought for our inspection, and amusements, two 
                    <hi rend="underline">very large</hi> Plans, one of <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0478">Canton</title></bibl>, the other of <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0701">Peking</title></bibl>,
                    laid down with extreme precision, and taking in the vast suburbs of both Cities, the latter of which is said to be thirty miles round, within the Walls. 
                    They seem to me, to be drawings in Indian Ink, but in very high preservation, and every street <add place="above">and temple</add>
                    seems to have its peculiar discription, for there <add place="above">are</add> abundant references upon the margin of each Plan, in chinese characters.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName ref="pe0437">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: Wyndham</persName> told us, He became possess’d of them, by inheritance from the late 
                    <persName ref="pe1697">Lord Melcombe</persName>, in whose family they had been (I think I dont lie) for near an hundred years back. 
                    As you and your labors are never out of my mind upon these occasions, I could not help expressing a wish that <persName ref="pe0389">Faden</persName>
                    might be allow’d to copy them for <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0462">your book</title></bibl>, tho I doubt the expense would 
                    <del><gap unit="letters" quantity="several" reason="illegible"/></del> amount to a world of money, if finish’d like the originals. 
                    <persName ref="pe0437">Wyndham</persName> is a very sensible, liberal minded Man, &amp; I dare believe would not object to it, unless 
                    <persName ref="pe0411">Lord <add place="above">+</add> Macartney</persName> takes them along with him to <placeName ref="pl2515">china</placeName>,
                    for whose use they <del>are</del><add place="above">were</add> brought hither by <persName ref="pe0437">Wyndham</persName>,
                    that <persName ref="pe0411">his</persName><add place="above">+</add> Interpreters might inspect them, before they sail’d from 
                    <placeName ref="pl1637">Spithead</placeName>, where the Lion Man of War, and an India-Man have been at anchor some time, in readiness for a three years expedition to 
                    <placeName ref="pl2515">china</placeName> - &amp; <placeName ref="pl1024">India</placeName>. <persName ref="pe0411">Lord Macartney</persName>
                    takes his passage in the latter, with every convenience, and accommodation on board, that human invention could contrive. The Lion is painted in a very peculiar manner, red 
                    &amp; brown, like a chinese Junk, and intended to look as unlike a man of war as possible, for fear of offending the natives.</p>
                <p>
                    You tell me, I can’t live out of a gay tempest;<note type="editorial">See <ref target="1155.xml">1155</ref>.</note> it is very much malgré moi,<note type="editorial">'in spite of myself'.</note>
                    if I do so, and very unbecoming a deaf old man of 71, but the truth is, that half the world have taken it into their noddles to visit the 
                    <placeName ref="pl1020">Isle of wight</placeName>, and who ever we know, or whoever we don’t know in their kindness, and in their Idleness, 
                    call upon us for want of having something better to do, and I might almost as well keep the Bull’s head at once. during the last week we have had nineteen beds occupied, every night.</p>
                <p>
                    Do you imagine the present storms in <placeName ref="pl1176">Europe</placeName> can ever subside again? it is my opinion that another age of Barbarism is at hand, and that another Race, not of Goths, and 
                    Vandals, but of Russians, will overwhelm all arts and Sciences, and that 500 years hence, they will begin to rise again: <placeName ref="pl0925">France</placeName>
                    has reach’d the Summit of her Elegance, her Luxury, and irreligion, and will fall first,; <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName>,
                    her rival in each will sink under her prodigious Vices next, and so on with the rest of <placeName ref="pl1176">Europe</placeName>. – We talk of the Savages in 
                    <placeName ref="pl0710">America</placeName>, but their Hatchets, and Tomahawks, are Instruments of Mercy, compared to the Pikes in the hands of a french Barbarian: 
                    many People are content to become Scholars to the Devil, but the Jacobins are fit to be his masters. —–</p>
                <p>
                    It is said, and believ’d here, that the <placeName ref="pl2516">Palace of winchester</placeName> is to be fitted up, so as to contain some thousands of the miserable Emigrants from 
                    <placeName ref="pl0925">France</placeName>, but what is to become of the rest, who have no money, and won’t starve? <placeName ref="pl1357">Portsmouth</placeName>
                    and <placeName ref="pl1073">Southampton</placeName>, I <hi rend="underline">know</hi>, swarm with them, and I believe it is the same all over the Sea Coasts. 
                    <persName ref="pe0422">Rainsford</persName> writes me word that a rough Calculation was made, (by order of Council, a fortnight ago,) 
                    of the numbers in, and about <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>, and that they <hi rend="underline">then</hi>
                    amounted to about 50,000. and are now supposed to be doubled.<note type="editorial">The numbers of refugees arriving from Revolutionary France accelerated during the final months of 1792, with daily arrivals of men, women and children throughout September and October. Kirsty Carpenter, <hi rend="italic">Refugees of the French Revolution: Émigrés in London, 1789–1802</hi> (Basingstoke: Macmillan, 1999), pp. 29–48.</note>
                    Some of them are respectable persons, and bring wealth along with them, but many are such wretched objects, not of Charity but of fear, that 
                    <placeName ref="pl1629">Newgate</placeName> would bar her doors against them.</p>
                <p>I have been very well all the Summer, as it is called, but not felt, and my good Daughters,<note xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" type="editorial"><xi:include href="Bulls.xml"/></note>
                    the comforts of my fast declining life, have been equally so. we all join in our best remembrances, and in all manner of 
                    good wishes to you, and all the House of <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>, and I hope you will think of me, as I am,</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Dear Sir, yours faithfully, and 
                        <lb/>affectionately.</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0313">Rich<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>: Bull</persName></signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>