<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1162">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Richard Bull to Thomas Pennant</title>
            <respStmt>                     <name>Transcribed by Ffion Mair Jones; edited by Ffion Mair Jones; encoded by Vivien Williams. (2019)</name>                 </respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/ TP 189</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>44</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <additions>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Endorsement on top of the page, in Thomas Pennant’s hand</hi>:</p>
                            <p>Answ<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></p>
                        </additions>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                    <date when="1793-01-25"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0759">Stratton Street</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage> <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="fr">French</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute> <dateline><placeName ref="pl0759">Stratton Street</placeName>. January 25. 1793.</dateline></opener>
                <p>Your last letter requiring no particular answer, and having been neither in health or spirits of late, I have 
                    ceased troubling you. the death of a very near Relation has not made me better, one indeed, with whom I have
                    had little intercourse for many years past, tho' I trust I have been more sin’d against, than sinning; But 
                    Death puts an end to all controversy, and <add place="above">one</add> must be unfeeling indeed not to be Counsell 
                    on the side of a departed Relation. I have not as yet bought your <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0272">new Edition of the London</title></bibl>,
                    being desirous of knowing from yourself, before I begin to unmake my <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0271">last Edition</title></bibl>,
                    whether the addenda can be had seperate, or whether they are so interwoven with the text, as to render it impossible to copy them into my book,
                    except in Manuscript, which I would willingly do rather than pull my fine hott press’d Book to pieces, with hundreds of prints 
                    &amp;c already inserted therein. are the Additions numerous? I wish to have your opinion in this matter e’er long, because there are but few 
                    of the large paper copies remaining unsold, &amp; I may be left upon the Pavé,<note type="editorial">'pavement'.</note>
                    should I want one.</p>
                <p>
                    ’Tis in vain to begin upon Politics, in the hurry of a short letter. one object alone occupies the mind and opinion of every body.<note type="editorial">Bull refers to the news of the execution of Louis XVI on 21 January 1793.</note>
                    I enclose the news paper, which is said to be best inform’d in respect to the affairs of <placeName ref="pl0925">France</placeName>,
                    but other Prints have a contradictory account, tho all agree in one thing, that <persName ref="pe0418">Mons<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Egalité</persName>,
                    (who seems to have improv'd upon Satan himself in wickedness,) has a strong party, backed by <persName ref="pe1710">Dumourier</persName>,
                    ready to declare him head of the Empire, by some name, or other.</p>
                <p>Our Royal family (I am told) are much affected, and I know the <persName ref="pe1143">Queen</persName> was particularly so, 
                    because she left the Drawing room yesterday seemingly very ill. –’twas  a good trait in John Bull’s character, that the whole audience of the play House, 
                    refused to hear any farce play’d the night the news arriv’d.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName ref="pe0418">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Egalité</persName>'s brothers are in 
                    <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName><note type="editorial">It is not clear who is meant by Louis Philippe's brothers. He had two sisters, one of whom married Louis Henri, Prince of Condé (1756-1830). Condé did not live in exile in England until 1801, however. See Jones, <hi rend="italic">Longman Companion to the French Revolution</hi>, pp. 334-5; Carpenter, <hi rend="italic">Refugees of the French Revolution</hi>, pp. 178, 212 n. 39.</note>
                    and live a good deal with some of the <hi rend="underline">highest ra</hi>nk here, <hi rend="underline">next to the <persName ref="pe0465">King</persName></hi>.</p>
                <p>
                    The Stocks fell considerably upon this news arriving, and a war is now look’d upon as inevitable; I am sorry the <persName ref="pe0894">Empress <add place="above">of</add> Russia</persName>
                    is likely to be our ally upon this occasion, she is a worse Savage than <persName ref="pe1461">Marat</persName> himself, and enough to damn any cause</p>
                <p>
                    It is really a piteous sight to <del>see</del><add place="above">behold</add> and hear some of the Emigrants complaints, I mean those of high rank. We pass’d the 
                    Evening with four of them a short time since – Vid<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. the <persName ref="pe1712">Duke of Luxemborgh</persName>,
                    <persName ref="pe1713">Mons<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. de Montmorenci</persName>, and the <persName ref="pe1714">Prince and princess de Leon</persName>,
                    the latter of whom were possess’d of £12,000 sterling per ann<hi rend="superscript">m</hi>, &amp; I suppose the
                    <persName ref="pe1712">Duke of L.</persName> of twice as much. they all went <del>to their</del> away together in a hackney coach to their wretched Hotel near 
                    <placeName ref="pl2494">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Giles</placeName>. the <persName ref="pe1715">Princess de Leon</persName>,
                    being as pretty a creature as you can form an Idea of, did not make our feelings the less. She said, unless, some remittances arriv’d soon, they must 
                    litterally beg their daily bread, and declar’d She meant to set up a milliners shop, and make up Caps &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>
                    for any body, who would be charitable enough to send them the materials, but with all this, they will not accept of any thing from the Subscription's
                    raise'd for peaceable Aliens, which seems very contradictory to people, who talk’d of being starv’d. I have seen some of the 
                    Lodgings of those of the highest rank, in places you would not put your stable boys in.</p>
                <p>
                    My daughters<note xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" type="editorial"><xi:include href="Bulls.xml"/></note> are well, and beg their best remembrances to you, and yours. after such a long 
                    <del>Scroll</del> Scrawl, it will seem inconsistent to say, I am in a hurry, but so it is. ––--</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I am yours however, at all times 
                    <lb/>very truly</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0313">Rich<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. Bull</persName></signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>P.S.  I saw upon many doors and walls, this morning written very nicely in the same hand</p>
                    <p>no war with <placeName ref="pl0925">France</placeName>.<note type="authorial">Bull wrote these words in a distinctive script.</note></p>
                    <p>I doubt we have bad subjects amongst us, and I believe we have French assassins too, at least there are strange reports –</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>