<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1174">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Richard Bull to Thomas Pennant</title>
            <respStmt>                     <name>Transcribed by Ffion Mair Jones; edited by Ffion Mair Jones; encoded by Vivien Williams. (2019)</name>                 </respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/ TP 189</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>51</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>Condition: slight tear to paper on third page of MS, caused by ripping of the seal.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                    <date when="1794-01-05"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0759">Stratton Street</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage> <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute> <dateline><placeName ref="pl0759">Stratton Street</placeName> Jan<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>. 5. 1794</dateline></opener>
                <p>On my return to <placeName ref="pl0699">town</placeName>, not many days ago, I found your <hi rend="underline">Epistola objurgatoria</hi>
                    <note type="editorial">'objurgatory letter'. See <ref target="1173.xml">1173</ref>.</note> <add place="above">of November 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></add>
                    which being directed to me in <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>, <persName ref="pe0319">my servant</persName> there had laid by 
                    so very carefully, that she forgot to send it at all.</p>
                <p>
                    I very sincerely congratulate you, upon the nuptials of your amiable <persName ref="pe0065">Son</persName>, and desire to wish him, and his Relations, 
                    all the happiness they may want, and a continuance of all the happiness they are in possession of already.</p>
                <p>
                    It was not in my power to obey your commands <hi rend="underline">personally</hi>, respecting the monuments in <placeName ref="pl2536">Godshill Church</placeName>;
                    at the time you desir’d me to visit them, I was unwell, and not able to ride, and the roads were then unsafe for a carriage. 
                    I was not however unmindful of your wishes, but desired a younger, and a wiser man than myself, to go thither immediately in order to review the tombs, and to
                    report to you the condition he found them in. This little commission, I dare believe <persName ref="pe0383">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Clarke</persName>
                    has fulfill’d with accuracy, as He is kind enough, to be diligently usefull to me, upon every occasion that concerns my pleasures, or my profits. I hope you 
                    likewise receiv'd from him the <rs type="art" ref="ar0340">two drawings of the Princess Elizabeth’s Coffin</rs>, and the vault in which it stands, which, as 
                    soon as discover’d, I beg’d him to employ a young man at <placeName ref="pl1479">Newport</placeName> to make Sketches of, on my account, and to send one of each to you.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName ref="pe0014">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: M. Griffith</persName> has the letter press of that part of my <sic>large<hi rend="superscript">ts</hi>:</sic>
                    paper Copy of the <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0023">Arctic Zoology</title></bibl>, which relates to the Quadrupeds, 
                    which He was to illustrate on my account, when he could be spared from the business, you wrote me word, He was then engag’d in for you. 
                    And He has also, the title page, and the list of birds belonging to the <bibl type="editorial"><title ref="bi0023">same volume</title></bibl>.
                    as I know not where to direct to him, may I take the liberty, without risk of giving offence, to request you to enquire of him whether he has been able to do any thing for me in this 
                    re<supplied>spect</supplied><note type="editorial">The paper is torn at this point.</note> and if He has, that he would send the sheets to me here, by some safe conveyance, 
                    together with the account for the same, and he may depend upon receiving the amount thereof, by the next post, after I know what I am in his debt.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I am, as I have ever been, Dear Sir, always ready to acknowledge myself, your grateful, and very oblig’d &amp;<hi rend="superscript">a</hi></salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0313">Rich<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>: Bull</persName></signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>
                    <stamp type="postmark">O. JA. 6 94; Single<note type="editorial">The word 'Single' is written by hand.</note></stamp>
                </p>
                <p>
                   <address>
                    <addrLine><persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName> Esq<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> | <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName> | <placeName ref="pl0702">Flintshire</placeName> | <placeName ref="pl1221">N. Wales</placeName></addrLine>
                    </address></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>