<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1186">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Thomas Pennant to Richard Bull</title>
            <respStmt>                     <name>Transcribed by Ffion Mair Jones; edited by Ffion Mair Jones; encoded by Vivien Williams. (2019)</name>                 </respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                        <idno>5500C</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>no. 124</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <date when="1795-09-14"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage> <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute> <dateline><placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName> sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1795</dateline></opener>
                <p>I remained anxious for hearing from you. fearful that you was ill; &amp; odd to say fearful that you was well. I bear ill the neglect of friends: therefore 
                    almost wished to find some excuse for you. Yet I must say that it gave me much concern that you had so substantial a one. I hope it is entirely removed, and that you
                    gave so speedy a proof that I still have a place in your memory. When I wrote last I had just taken to my bed on account of my knee pan. I lay recumbent six weeks 
                    &amp; five days in possession of patience, spirits &amp; my full faculties. I pursued my studies as usual &amp; part of the inclosed is a proof of my ease of mind. It is the last leaves of a 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0034">history of Whiteford</title></bibl> my native parish; that of the adjacent <placeName ref="pl1251">Holy well</placeName>
                    goes to the press next week &amp; both form a largish book. I disposed of the copy to <persName ref="pe2024">White</persName> at (as usual a low price. 
                    He has acted with much liberality about the plates &amp; spares no cost. I shall send you a print very soon as a proof. he is a very different man from 
                    <persName ref="pe0026">his father</persName> &amp; reconciles me to the shop. He made me or rather my <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0475">out lines of the Globe</title></bibl>
                    a visit this summer. We made a verbal agreement for <del><gap unit="letters" quantity="1" reason="illegible"/></del> copies of them when better 
                    times arrive.<note type="editorial">Only two volumes of Pennant's manuscript 'Outlines of the Globe' were published by Benjamin White &amp; Son. Both 
                        <hi rend="italic">The View of India Extra Gangem, China, and Japan. Vol. III</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The View of the Malayan Isles, New Holland, and the Spicy Islands. Vol. IV</hi> 
                        were edited by David Pennant and published posthumously by John White in 1800. It is not clear whether the arrangement with the White firm at this 
                        stage stipulated that these were to be the published sections of the work; the reference in this letter to an arrangement which prevents Pennant 
                        from allowing a copy of the section on the Isle of Wight to be made for Bull suggests that the Whites may have had plans to publish a substantial 
                        part of the manuscript, if not the whole.</note> This agreement will I fear 
                    make him think that no part sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be parted with. This will prevent me from communicating the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0657">copy</title></bibl> You wish,
                    as I otherwise w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> chearfully have done.</p>
                <p>
                    To return to my knee pan. I am restored to the blessing of the use of my limbs, can walk two or three miles without fatigue &amp;
                    ride tolerably. &amp; this in less than five months. How many have I heard limping for life: or confined for almost as many years! I am truely thankful for this favor of Providence, for enabling me to pass with comfort the remnant of my days</p>
                <p>
                    I have now about me my whole stock, <persName ref="pe0234">daughter</persName> two sons<note type="editorial">Pennant refers to <persName ref="pe0065">David</persName> 
                        and <persName ref="pe0421">Thomas Pennant, junior</persName>.</note> &amp;
                    a most amiable <persName ref="pe0814">daughter in law</persName> in a fair way to make me a grandfather. All unite in best Compliments 
                    &amp; wishes to <persName ref="pe0313">m<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bull</persName> &amp; his two daughters.<note xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" type="editorial"><xi:include href="Bulls.xml"/></note>
                    my best wishes are closely united.</p>
                <p>
                    As to <persName ref="pe0014">moses</persName> he has for sometime past given himself to miniature painting. His portraits are exquisite but he loses so much time that I fear he never will get what he ought. He 
                    sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> stick to his old branches &amp; then w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be able to lay up a little money. He promises to do all you wish when winter comes on. His 
                    <persName ref="pe0345">son</persName> promises to be a genius in music as well as painting.</p>
                <p>
                    As to franks <persName ref="pe0015">Sir R. M.</persName> lives on one side of me &amp; the <persName ref="pe0365">Bishop</persName> the other. You may inclose to the former if you please at <placeName ref="pl0695">Mostyn</placeName> <placeName ref="pl0702">Flintshire</placeName>.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Adieu, Dear Sir,
                    <lb/>Y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> most affect<hi rend="superscript">ly</hi></salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0232">Tho. Pennant</persName>.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>P.S. <persName ref="pe0379">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Chiswell</persName> &amp;c were with me 3 or 4 days &amp; went away much content with the place.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>