<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1188">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Richard Bull to Thomas Pennant</title>
            <respStmt>                     <name>Transcribed by Ffion Mair Jones; edited by Ffion Mair Jones; encoded by Vivien Williams. (2019)</name>                 </respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/ TP 189</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>55</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                    <date when="1795-09-29"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl1013">Northcourt</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage> <!-- delete as appropriate -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="fr">French</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute> <dateline><placeName ref="pl1013">Northcourt</placeName>. <placeName ref="pl1020">I. W.</placeName> September 29. 1795</dateline></opener>
                <p>With a Franker at my elbow, and with a mind possess’d of your kind Attentions to me, it would be strange indeed, if I did not thank you as well as I am able, for your last two letters, and their contents; – with the specimens of Engravings I am delighted, and I should have known the Extracts from some treatise on Husbandry, were of your Pen, had I found them in any part of the Globe. The 
                    Book itself I hope and trust will appear soon.<note type="editorial">This may refer to the lengthy section on husbandry included as the closing section of the 'History of Whiteford Parish' 
                        in <hi rend="italic">HPWaH</hi>, pp. 157–71.</note> We very much rejoice to hear you are happily restor’d from any bad Effects which we had apprehended from such a fall as yours. I must confess that 
                    <persName ref="pe0026">White le Pere</persName>, never appear’d in my eyes as a liberal minded man, but <persName ref="pe2024">the young man</persName> has the best character with those that know him best, the surest sign of merit. circumstanc’d as you now are with him, I am not so wrong headed, as to expect a 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0657">copy of what relates to our Island</title></bibl>, but, unlike the Fox in the fable, I think the Grapes the sweeter, for being out of my reach. You seem to me a very happy old cock with all your chickens playing round you; long, very long, may you enjoy one another. Stet fortuna domus.<note type="editorial">'Let the fortune of the house stand'.</note> – I shall have a good account of <placeName ref="pl0001">your place</placeName> from <persName ref="pe0379">Chiswell</persName>, and if <hi rend="underline">He</hi> liked it, it must be desirable indeed. We breathe nothing here but War, every town fill’d with Soldiers, and all the Sea cover’d with transports, and Ships of War. 
                    there is an encampment near <placeName ref="pl1073">Southampton</placeName> consisting of 20,000 troops, most of whom are destin’d to yellow fevers in the <placeName ref="pl0704">West Indies</placeName>, and expected to Sail in three days. the Commerce de Marseilles<note type="editorial">A French ship captured 
                        at the Siege of Toulon and added to the Royal Navy on 29 August 1793. See <ref type="http" target="http://collections.rmg.co.uk/collections/objects/110188.html">here</ref> [accessed 8 January 2019]; and see the report in the <hi rend="italic">Hereford Journal</hi>, 14 October 1795: 'His Majesty's ships Commerce de Marseilles, with 1000 troops on board, besides 500 seamen, and a great quantity of war-like stores and baggage, is sailed with the Alcmene frigate, and several transports for the West Indies'.</note>
                    is fitted out as a Storeship to attend this Expedition, and with only 400 men, a circumstance which makes the knowing ones unwilling to think such a vast vessel secure. The <persName ref="pe0465">King</persName>,
                    the <persName ref="pe0393">Prince of Wales</persName>, and the <persName ref="pe0949">Duke of York</persName> have been to review their Army, and <persName ref="pe0425">Lord Spencer</persName> is now at <placeName ref="pl1357">Portsmouth</placeName>,
                    attending the equipment of the Fleet. We have had, in common with all <placeName ref="pl0775">England</placeName> a most Plentiful harvest, notwithstanding which, grain of every sort, more especially horse provander keeps its last summers price in our <placeName ref="pl1020">Island</placeName>.
                    Hay is at £7. 12. 0 a load. Straw at £2 .6. 0.. Oats £1: 17. 0 a Quarter, I speak of Prime sorts of each. My <persName ref="pe0336">youngest daughter</persName> is quite otherwise than well; her usual spasmodic complaints having return’d with encreased violence. Quant à moi,<note type="editorial">'As for me'.</note>
                    I am patch’d up for the present, and may continue so, till the cold weather comes. for these last ten weeks we have hardly seen a cloud.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Our best of wishes attend you all at <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>, and
                        <lb/>I am, Dear Sir, yours with sincerity, &amp; truth</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0313">Rich<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>: Bull</persName></signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>