<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1300">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Daniel Lysons to Thomas Pennant, May 1764</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>Warwickshire County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>CR 2017/TP294/1</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0408">Daniel Lysons</persName>
                    <date>May 1764</date>
                    <placeName ref="pl1276">Gloucester</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref=""/>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct1301"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct1299"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><dateline><placeName ref="pl1276">Glocester</placeName> May 1764.
                </dateline><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
                
                <p>I am once more return’d to <placeName ref="pl1276">Glocester</placeName> my Health being greatly improved by the 
                    <placeName ref="pl0796">Bath</placeName> waters. I left your Sisters<note type="editorial">Lysons refers to Pennant's twin sisters,
                        <persName ref="pe0807">Sarah</persName> and <persName ref="pe0237">Catherine Pennant.</persName></note> there very well on Monday 
                    last. and from them I had the Pleasure to hear of <persName ref="pe2025">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Pennants</persName>  Recovery of which I give you Joy.
                    Since I came here I have seen the <persName ref="pe2068">Printer</persName> who says that the Prices of printing a Work in 
                    8<hi rend="superscript">vo</hi>. are regulated by the Size of the Letter and the Dimensions of the Page. Thus a Sheet of what he calls
                    Pica Letter, (of which you have a Sample marked No. i)<note type="editorial">Neither this nor other samples or enclosures mentioned
                        have been preserved with the manuscript letter.</note>
                    containing 38 Letters in a Line, and 35 Lines in a Page comes to 17.S. per Sheet for printing. A Sheet of the same Pica Letter containing 42 
                    letters in a Line and 39 Lines in a Page, comes to <hi rend="superscript">£</hi>1:1:0 <del>for</del>per Sheet for printing.
                </p>
                <p>Upon a Letter one Size larger than the above Specimen the Charge for printing will be from 14. S. to 18. or 19 S. per Sheet.</p>
                <p>You will receive a Specimen of a Letter one Size larger than Pica marked N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 2. This Letter is the 
                    same with that used in the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0693">History of Kamtschatka</title></bibl>,  &amp; the Price is
                    17.S. per Sheet This Letter I think better than the Pica which he says is a new Letter. The Pica is indeed neatest but it fatigues
                    the Eye in reading.</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe2068">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Raikes</persName> says he can send no better proposals than the above
                    without seeing the Copy. But if he was permitted to see the <del>Copy</del> <add place="above">Manuscript</add> he would then
                    print off a Page or two by way of specimen. This I shall not allow, or let him know what the Work is except I receive a 
                    Commission from you for that Purpose. The above Calculation is made for 500 Copies. but if more are wanting the additional Paper
                    will be the Chief if not the only additional Expence.</p>
                <p><persName ref="pe2068">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Raikes</persName> has sent the enclosed Specimens of Paper. One at 17.S. 6.d.
                    per Ream the other at 15-<hi rend="superscript">S</hi>. and he has some of Inferior Quality at 13.S.</p>
                <p>Upon my Return home I find myself in full Employment. the Infirmary very full, &amp; much other Business leaves me very little 
                    at Leisure. However I shall be glad to serve you in whatever I can.</p>
                <p>The <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0700"/>British Zoology part the 2d.</bibl> &amp; another Copy for <persName ref="pe2069">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Tindale</persName>
                    I have received. 
                    The figures are in general well done, but two very common Birds are so very ill executed that I fear it will bring a Discredit 
                    on the whole. These are the wood Pigeon or Ring Dove, &amp; the Bull finch.<note type="editorial">For references to plates of the
                        birds which Lysons notes are a cause for concern in this letter, see <hi rend="italic">British zoology</hi> (2nd edn., 1768–70). Vol.
                        I,
                        p. 216, includes Dove, or Wood Pigeon in a list of 
                        names under the general title Common Pigeon, referring in a note to 'Br zool. 88. plate 88'. Ibid., vol. II, p. 307, mentions
                        under 'The Brambling', 'Br. Zool. 108. plate V. f. 4'; and p. 321 under 'The Greater Brambling'
                        refers to 'Br. Zool. 112. plate [gap] f. 6.'</note>  They are not at all 
                    proportioned to the size of the 
                    natural Birds. The Wood Pigeon I thought a bird of Prey by its attitude, &amp; could by no means guess what it was on account of 
                    its bulk. You will excuse my censuring freely what I think wrong in the work as I wish it well.</p>
                <p>Possibly <persName ref="pe2025">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Pennant</persName> may be advised to a water drinking Place for the 
                    more perfect establishment of her health.<note type="editorial">Pennant's first wife, Elizabeth (née Falconer) was to die in June 1764.</note>
                    If she is <placeName ref="pl2881">Malvern</placeName>, or <placeName ref="pl1302">Bristol</placeName> may probably be recommended,
                    &amp; then I shall in either case hope to see You &amp; her. I beg my Compliments to her &amp; am</p>
                <closer><salute>Your most faithful
                    <lb/>humble Servant</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0408">D. Lysons.</persName></signed>
                    <dateline/></closer>
                <postscript><p/></postscript>
            </div>
            <div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>