<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1302">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Daniel Lysons to Thomas Pennant, 26 September 1767</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>Warwickshire County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>CR 2017/TP294/3</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <additions>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Endorsement (in Thomas Pennant's hand)</hi>: answ<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> 
                                oct<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</p>
                  
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Marginalia in <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>'s hand</hi>: <persName ref="pe2071">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Farrington</persName> 
                                has seen shads weigh 15lb.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">in pencil, in the hand of <persName ref="pe2070">Cecilia, Countess of Denbigh</persName></hi>: Found in <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0694"/>Tessin's Nat Hist</bibl></p>
                        </additions>
                    </physDesc>
                    
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0408">Daniel Lysons</persName>
                    <date when="1767-09-26">26 September 1767</date>
                    <placeName ref="pl1276">Gloucester</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct1303"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct1301"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><dateline><placeName ref="pl0796">Bath</placeName> Sept: 26 1767
                </dateline><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
                
                <p>In my last I gave you an account of the Salmon, I shall now proceed with the other Inhabitants of the <placeName ref="pl1226">Severn</placeName>.</p>
                
                <p><add place="margin">2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>.</add> The Shad is taken in the <placeName ref="pl1226">Severn</placeName>
                    in the same manner as the Salmon. It makes its entrance into the <placeName ref="pl1226">Severn</placeName> 
                    <add place="above">&amp; is taken</add> in the months of may &amp; June. A Shad never weighs more than 8 pounds, and rarely
                    exceeds seven. Its most common size is 4 or 5<hi rend="superscript">lb</hi> but many weigh no more than two. The Shad makes its appearance in the 
                    <placeName ref="pl1226">Severn</placeName> sooner or later as the weather is warm or cold, so that it sometimes comes in april, 
                    &amp; is often retarded for some weeks in may.x <add place="margin">x At <placeName ref="pl1276">Glocester</placeName> a Shad 
                        is reckoned 
                    a very good fish &amp; usually sells dearer than Salmon.</add> As the shad leaves us it is succeeded by another in shape, &amp;
                    appearance very like it, but less. This is calld a Twaite.</p>
                
                <p><add place="margin">3.</add> The Twaites weigh from two pounds to half a pound, and are taken in great numbers in the months of
                    June and July. A large twaite differs from a small shad only in one or more round black spots on the sides. If there is only 
                    one of these spots it is always near the gill, but there are commonly three or four of them one under another,<note type="editorial">
                        The material in this paragraph up to this point is used almost verbatim in <hi rend="italic">British zoology</hi> 
                        (2nd edn., 1768–70), III, p. 299. A note at the foot of the page acknowledges the debt to 'Doctor Lysons, of Gloucester, 
                        for his communications relating to this fish, as well as to several other articles relating to those of the Severn'.
                    </note>  whereas the
                    Shad has more. This fish is taken in the <placeName ref="pl1389">Thames</placeName> about the same time of the year, &amp;
                    calld at <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> a shad; but I believe the true shad is never taken in the 
                    <placeName ref="pl1389">Thames</placeName>. The Twaite is a bad fish, the flesh being dry, &amp; not in any degree equal in flavour
                    to a shad. But the Twaites being at <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> called Shads the Londoners have 
                    <add place="above">a</add> bad opinion of the true shad, &amp; being in appearance so like the Twaite they can not think it a 
                    different fish.<note type="editorial">Ibid., p. 298, discusses the 'Thames shad' and 'the variety called near Gloucester the Twaite', 
                        clearly using the information provided by Lysons in this letter.</note> </p>
                <p>It is by no means a settled point whether the Shads or Twaites come into the <placeName ref="pl1226">severn</placeName> to spawn.
                    That the Salmon spawns upon the sands beyond <placeName ref="pl0740">shrewsbury</placeName> is certain from the accounts I have 
                    received from people of that country who have seen them making their beds upon the shoals, as well as from the great number of 
                    <sic>Samblets</sic> which come down the river in the month of March. But then the old ones are taken in their return after spawning, 
                    greatly emaciated, and call’d old fish in opposition to those in Season which are calld new fish. The Shad is also in spawn when it 
                    enters the River, &amp; in the month of July we have great numbers of Bleak, some of which are nearly as big as a 
                    small <sic>hering</sic>. Many people think these fish the spawn of the Shad because they are taken about 
                    <placeName ref="pl1276">Glocester</placeName> only in the Months of July and august, &amp; if I am not mistaken they come down, &amp;
                    not up the <placeName ref="pl1226">Severn</placeName>. But on the other hand none of the old emaciated fish are taken in their return, 
                    which one should think would be the case did they spawn towards the head of the River.</p>
                <p><add place="margin">4.</add> The Lamprey weighs about three pounds, &amp; is taken <add place="above">chiefly</add> in the months
                    of March, April, &amp; may. The sooner they are taken in the year the better they are, being much wasted &amp; flabby as the warm 
                    weather approaches. They are taken in long nets in the same manner as the Salmon, &amp; Shad, &amp; together with them, &amp; also in
                    wheels laid in the bottom <add place="above"><del>or sides</del></add> of the river. The Lamprey does not breed in the 
                    <placeName ref="pl1226">Severn</placeName>, neither is there more than one Species of them.</p>
                <p><add place="margin">5</add> The Lampern is in shape like a Lamprey, but of the colour of an Eel, having a black back, and white
                    belly, whereas the Lamprey is yellow, or brown, variegated with black lines upon the back. The Lamperns appear in January, <del>and</del>
                    and continue untill the weather becomes warm, when they <add place="above">waste &amp;</add> leave the River. They are all when in 
                    season about the size of a small Eel, weighing ab<add place="above">o</add>ut two ounces, &amp; about 7 Inches long. They are never 
                    taken in nets, but in wheels fixed to the sides of the banks before the tide comes in. They are potted in the same manner as Lampreys, 
                    &amp; by some people preferrd to them as being milder.</p>
                <p>There is a fish in the <placeName ref="pl1389">Thames</placeName> resembling the two last mentioned 
                    <add place="above">in shape &amp; figure</add>, but different from both in colour, &amp; size. It is about the bigness of a 
                    goose quill <del>but differing</del> and of a green colour. It is found in shallow water about <placeName ref="pl1347">oxford</placeName> 
                    under stones, and is I think calld a stone Eel, though of quite a different Species from an Eel. I am told that great 
                    quantities of Lamperns are taken about <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>, but that few are eat there, being chiefly 
                    bought up for baits in the Cod fishery.</p>
                <p><add place="margin">6</add> Elvers are certainly the spawn of Eels, &amp; with great reason supposed to come from the great 
                    conger Eel, which is often found in the salt water of the <placeName ref="pl1226">Severn</placeName> upon the Sands weighing 
                    50lb. These elvers come from the salt water up the <placeName ref="pl1226">Severn</placeName> in prodigious numbers, and are 
                    taken in a kind of <sic>seive</sic> made of hair cloth, &amp; fixed to a long pole. A man standing on the bank, &amp; drawing 
                    his net in the water by the side of the bank as far <sic>is</sic> he can reach, whilst the tide is in, takes some at every 
                    sweep, untill at last he shall, in the space of one tide, take as many as will fill a bushel. The Elvers usually preceed the 
                    Shad, &amp; it is supposed that the Shads come up the River to prey upon them.</p>
                <p>I have now given you the best answers I can to your enquiries, &amp; hope they will be satisfactory. The waters agree with me
                    very well, &amp; I doubt not but I shall be perfectly well if I can possibly stay here a month. My Disorder is a constant 
                    purging which reduced me very much I was something better than I have been before I came here which was three days ago, &amp; 
                    am still better since I have been here. There is not a great deal of Company here yet but indeed the Season is not begun 
                    the music comes to the pump Room on Monday next. <persName ref="pe2072">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Derrick</persName> has 
                    had great opposition but has overcome it &amp; remains M. C. upon the same footing as formerly.  Pray are the 
                    Miss Pennants<note type="editorial"><persName ref="pe0237">Catherine</persName> and <persName ref="pe0807">Sarah Pennant</persName>.</note> 
                    with you at <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName> or in attendance at <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>. If with you 
                    I beg my Compliments to them and am</p>
                <closer><salute>Yours sincerely</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0408">D. Lysons.</persName></signed>
                    <dateline/></closer>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>
                    <stamp type="handstamp"><placeName ref="pl0796">BATH</placeName></stamp>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <address><addrLine>To <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant Esq<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName> at 
                        <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName> near <placeName ref="pl1251">Holywell</placeName> 
                        <placeName ref="pl0702">Flintshire</placeName></addrLine></address>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>