<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1303">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Daniel Lysons to Thomas Pennant, 13 November 1767</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>Warwickshire County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>CR 2017/TP294/5</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0408">Daniel Lysons</persName>
                    <date when="1767-11-13">13 November 1767</date>
                    <placeName ref="pl1276">Gloucester</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct1304"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct1302"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><dateline><placeName ref="pl1276">Glocester</placeName> Nov: 13 1767
                </dateline><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
                
                <p>Yours I rec<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. in <placeName ref="pl1347">oxford</placeName> where I was attending our College 
                    Election, &amp; return’d home on friday last. If you desire me to go on from N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 6 you must tell 
                    me what fish N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 6 are as I made no rough draught of what I wrote, but I think they must be Salmon, 
                    shad twaite Lamprey, Lamperns, Elvers. Pray did I say nothing about Sturgeon?</p>
                
                <p>We have certainly two species of Eels in the <placeName ref="pl1226">Severn</placeName>. One, which I take to be the Conger, 
                    has a remarkably broad head, &amp; mouth, and its body is thicker in proportion to its length than the common Eel. It is also 
                    different in colour, its back being of a yellowish green, &amp; its belly very white, whence it is here calld a silver 
                    Eel.<note type="editorial">See <hi rend="italic">British zoology</hi> (2nd edn., 1768–70), III, pp. 115–18, on the 'Conger' 
                        variety of eel, for information about which Pennant acknowledges his debt to Doctor Borlase. The large numbers of conger fry 
                        which come up the river Severn in April are noted on p. 116.</note> 
                    The common Eel has a pointed snout, a narrow head, a black back, and a white, or dirty yellow colourd billy. If the silver Eel 
                    is put into a fresh water pond it will live, &amp; grow to about 2 or 3 pounds weight, but not larger, and I never saw any of 
                    them larger that were taken in the fresh water of the <placeName ref="pl1226">Severn</placeName>. But in the salt water I have 
                    frequently seen the Conger Eel (which agrees with the silver Eel in shape) of many pounds weight I have seen them more than 
                    12, &amp; I am told it is no uncommon thing to have them 40, 50, or 60. If you will come to me next Summer we will enquire 
                    more particularly into this Species of fish.</p>
                
                <p>The Lampreys certainly return to the Sea. And it is as certain that the City of <placeName ref="pl1276">Glocester</placeName> 
                    sends annually a present of Lampreys to the King. They are sent in a large raised pye at Christmass. If possible the 
                    Corporation sends fresh fish, &amp; for that purpose always give a guinea a piece for them.<note type="editorial">The Gloucester 
                        custom of presenting the king with a 'lamprey pye, covered with a large raised crust' in spite of the difficulty of acquiring 
                        the fish at that time of year is mentioned in <hi rend="italic">British zoology</hi> (2nd edn., 1768–70), III, p. 59. Pennant 
                        also mentions the prevalence of the lamprey in the Severn and the discovery of a large, 3lb lamprey in the Esk. See ibid., p. 58.
                        
                    </note>  But it is so very rare a thing 
                    to get fresh fish at that time of the year that they <del>commonly</del> <add place="above">are frequently oblig’d to</add>
                    send some <add place="above">of last years</add> that has been preserved. I will make enquiry whence this custom took its rise and 
                    let you know.</p>
                
                <p><persName ref="pe2073">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Charleton</persName>, at
                    whose request I wrote to you about the ascent of minerals into the veins of
                    plants, is of your opinion that minerals cannot enter the [<del>...</del>] juices
                    of plants in such a manner as to impregnate their fruit with their respective
                    qualities. But he does <del>not</del> think that the acidum vagum fossile may,
                    &amp; that the colics, &amp; palsies attending the <placeName ref="pl0780">Devonshire</placeName> colic may proceed from this cause.<note type="editorial">Rice Charleton discusses cases of cholic related to the
                        consumption of cyder in <hi rend="italic">Three tracts on Bath water</hi>
                        (Bath: R. Cruttwell for W. Taylor, 1774), pp. 72–80, and the work of George
                        Baker on the Devonshire cholic in ibid., pp.
                        78–9. See further n. 4, below.</note> He asserts (what I much doubt) that the Drinkers of Cyder made
                    in <placeName ref="pl1653">Herefordshie</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl1284">Worcestershire</placeName> have no such colics, or palsies as
                    the rest of the Cyder counties are subject to. And he supposes that where ever
                    minerals abound there the acidum vag abounds also, &amp; thus he accounts for
                    the 2 counties above mention’d being free from this colic, but not the others
                    where minerals &amp; consequently the acidum vagum fossile abound. I have no
                    doubt but that the different qualities of the juices of plants depend
                        <sic>cheefly</sic> upon the soil they grow in. But how far the acid. vag.
                    fossil may in this manner contribute to the colics &amp; palsies or what you
                    think of its allways attending minerals he desires me to ask your opinion. There
                    is an answer to <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0695"/>D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Baker</bibl> published by <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0696"/>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.
                        Geach</bibl> Surgeon at <placeName ref="pl0778">exeter</placeName> in which
                    he seems justly to attribute the Colic to Cyder made from unripe fruit, or not
                    properly fermented. And with as much appearance of reason supposes that the lead
                    found in 18 bottles of <placeName ref="pl0780">Devonshire</placeName> cyder
                    proceeded from shot left in the bottles, as <persName ref="pe2074">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Baker</persName> does that it proceeded from
                    the lead with which the cramps of the cyder mill <del>was</del>
                    <add place="above">were</add> fastened.<note type="editorial">On the dispute
                        between George Baker and <persName ref="pe2075">Francis Geach</persName>
                        regarding the causes of colic, see letter from Devo at Exeter to Mr Urban,
                        April 14 [1798], <hi rend="italic">Gentleman's Magazine</hi>, vol. 183
                        (April 1798), 305: 'Dr. Baker ascribed the colic to the leaden pounds in
                        which the cider ... is pressed; Mr. Geach to the shot left in the
                        bottles'.</note>
                </p>
                <p>I am obliged to you for your enquiry after my health, &amp; have the pleasure to acquaint you that I 
                    rec<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. as much benefit from the <placeName ref="pl0796">Bath</placeName> waters as I could expect 
                    or hope for, &amp; the ride to <placeName ref="pl1347">oxford</placeName> after, by which I was absent six weeks in the whole, 
                    has so far established my health that I find my self in better health and spirits than I have known for a long time. 
                    I hope therefore that you will make me a visit next summer, and we will then make our enquiries into the natural productions 
                    of this part of the world together. I wish you all health and happiness and am</p>
                
                <closer><salute>Yours sincerely</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0408">D. Lysons.</persName></signed>
                    <dateline/></closer>
                <postscript><p>P.S. My <persName ref="pe2076">Sister Reeves</persName> husband being lately dead I shall probably be obliged to go 
                    to <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> sometime in the Spring, pray when shall you be there.</p></postscript>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <p>
                    <stamp type="handstamp"><placeName ref="pl1276"><unclear>GL</unclear>OUCESTER</placeName></stamp>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <address><addrLine>To <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant Esq<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName> at 
                        <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName> near <placeName ref="pl1251">Holywell</placeName> 
                        <placeName ref="pl0702">Flintshire</placeName></addrLine></address>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>