<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1306">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Treadway Russell Nash to Thomas Pennant, 3 November 1777</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                        <idno>15423C</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent"><persName ref="pe0416">Treadway Russell Nash</persName>
                    <date when="1777-11-03">3 November 1777</date>
                    <placeName ref="pl1290">Bevere</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">[Thomas Pennant]</persName>
                    
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct1307"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct1305"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
                
                <p>I beg pardon for thus long delaying my answer to your obliging letter, but I did it in hopes of getting better Information: 
                    Indeed several Days have been fixed for my attending to the Spot a Gentleman in that Neighbourhood who is very conversant in 
                    these Enquiries, but bad Weather, or one untoward Accident or other have always prevented us, and as the rainy Season is now 
                    set in I dispair of being able to go this Winter, &amp; therefore must content myself with giving you the best Information I 
                    can from the report of others. ––––– The facts then are thus, &amp; you must draw your own Inferences.</p>
                
                <p><placeName ref="pl1288">Wobury Hill</placeName> is about 9 miles N.W. of <placeName ref="pl0806">Worcester</placeName> &amp; 
                    <del>is in Extent</del> contains 26.<hi rend="superscript">A</hi> 2.<hi rend="superscript">R</hi> 27<hi rend="superscript">P</hi> within 
                    the Trench: if the Ditch be measured (for it is a single one) it will be two Acres more.<note type="editorial">
                        See Treadway Russell Nash, <hi rend="italic">Collections for the history of Worcestershire</hi> 
                        (2 vols., London: John Nichols, 1781–2), II, p. 465. Pennant reproduces some of this detail (the 27 acres contained 
                        within the camp and the fact that it had 'a single foss' only) in <hi rend="italic">A tour in Wales 1770 [1773]</hi> 
                        (1778), I, p. 351.
                    </note> It is distant from <placeName ref="pl1282">Wasal Camp</placeName> in the Parish of 
                    <placeName ref="pl1285">Kederminster</placeName> about 8 miles &amp; from <placeName ref="pl1283">Kinvar <add place="above">edge</add></placeName> 
                    (Ken-vawr in British a great bank) about 11 miles the latter <placeName ref="pl1283">Camp</placeName> is mentioned in 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0602">Plots Staffordshire</title></bibl> p. 413, &amp; contains about 12 Acres, is situated at 
                    equal distances from the small Station or Camp at <placeName ref="pl1282">Wassall hill</placeName>, &amp; from an other small 
                    Camp on <placeName ref="pl1297">Witchberry Hill</placeName> to the East: Probably these two small Camps were out posts to the larger 
                    Camp at <placeName ref="pl1283">Kinvar</placeName>: Signals given at any one of them would be visible at them all: they lye in the Road 
                    from <placeName ref="pl0740">Shrewsbury</placeName> to <placeName ref="pl0806">Worcester</placeName>.</p>
                
                <p>You will consider whether the Distance be not too great for <persName ref="pe0667">Henrys</persName> Army to be supposed to 
                    occupy these Camps, – if they did occupy <add place="above">them</add>, part of the Army must be supposed to have crossed the 
                    <placeName ref="pl1226">Severn</placeName>, &amp; to have taken possession of <placeName ref="pl1298">Abberley hills</placeName>,
                    &amp; the other hills adjoining, which directly face <placeName ref="pl1288">Wobery Hill</placeName>, where 
                    <persName ref="pe0495">Glendwr</persName>'s camp was: these hills I intended to have searched for Camps, tho the face of them is very 
                    much altered by a great quantity of Limestone which has constantly been dug away both for the roads &amp; for Lime.</p>
                
                <p>I wish you could have obliged me by riding over them with me, when perhaps your
                    sagacious Eye might have discovered more than I can describe, but I live in
                    hopes of that pleasure an other Year.<note type="editorial">Nash mentions that
                        he had 'the pleasure of viewing the ground', apparently of the camp at
                        Woodbury Hill, with Pennant, in <hi rend="italic">Collections for the
                            history of Worcestershire</hi>, II, p. 465. Pennant, in his description
                        of Woodbury hill in the 1778 edition of <hi rend="italic">A tour in Wales
                            1770 [1773]</hi>, p. 351, writes that 'I never had an opportunity of
                        examining the nature of the ground, and how far it suits the description
                        given by Monstrelet' and refers his readers to the forthcoming work of Nash.
                        By the second edition, however, he was able to note that 'I surveyed the
                        spot in company with my friend DOCTOR NASH, and found it answered precisely
                        to the account given by Monstrelet'. <hi rend="italic">A tour in Wales</hi>
                        (2nd edn., 1784), I, p. 376.</note> Pray how do you dispose of yourself this
                        Winter[<del>:</del>]? I wish you would make <placeName ref="pl1284">Worcestershire</placeName> your road to <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>, <persName ref="pe0729">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                        Nash</persName> would be very happy to pay her respects to <persName ref="pe0238">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Pennant</persName> at
                        <placeName ref="pl1290">Bevere</placeName>.</p>
                
                <p>Pray tell me with truth that your <persName ref="pe0065">Son</persName> is perfectly 
                    well<note type="editorial">For Nash's anxiety regarding David Pennant, see <ref target="1305.xml">1305</ref>.</note> &amp; believe me to be, 
                    Dear S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>, Your most obedient &amp;</p>
                
                <closer><salute>obliged humble Servant </salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0416">T. Nash</persName></signed>
                   
                    <dateline><placeName ref="pl1290">Bevere</placeName><lb/>
                        Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 3. 1777.</dateline></closer>
                <postscript><p>If Miss Pennant<note type="editorial">This probably refers to Pennant's daughter, 
                    <persName ref="pe0234">Arabella</persName>, who would have been of a similar age to Treadway Russell Nash's daughter, Margaret, rather than to one of 
                    Pennant's unmarried twin sisters.</note> is with you, [<del>...</del>]my <persName ref="pe0729">wife</persName> 
                    &amp; <persName ref="pe0730">Daughter</persName> desire their Compliments</p></postscript>
                
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>