<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1311">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Hugh Davies to Thomas Pennant, 14 March 1782</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                        <idno>2594E, Caernarvonshire folder</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc><additions><p><hi rend="italic">Endorsement in Thomas Pennant's hand</hi>: Arms of <persName ref="pe0945">Ednyfed fychan</persName></p></additions></physDesc>
                    
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent"><persName ref="pe0903">Hugh Davies</persName>
                    <date when="1782-03-14">14 March 1782</date>
                    <placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumaris</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001"/>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct1312"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct1310"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
             
                <p>In the month of March 1776 walking along the seacoast between <placeName ref="pl1594">Criccieth</placeName> and 
                    <placeName ref="pl1524">traeth-mawr</placeName> I observed the beach for miles together covered with dead seafowl, particularly 
                    those which visit our rocks and islands in summer to breed, viz. the <hi rend="underline">Puffin</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Razorbill</hi>, 
                    <hi rend="underline">Guillemot</hi>, and <hi rend="underline">Kittiwake</hi>, of which there were many-many thousands; there were several other 
                    kinds in great quantities, I noted the <hi rend="underline">Tarrock</hi>, more numerous than any of the following, the <hi rend="underline">Gannet</hi>, 
                    <hi rend="underline">wild <del>g</del>Goose</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Barnacle</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Brentgoose</hi> <hi rend="underline">Scoter</hi> 
                    and <hi rend="underline">tufted Ducks</hi>, common <hi rend="underline">Sea Mew</hi> &amp;c &amp;c</p>
                
                <p>I have not a doubt of their having perished by the remarkably severe frost which commenced on the 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. of January preceding and 
                    continued till the 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. of February.<note type="editorial">Pennant mentions this account of Hugh Davies's in <hi rend="italic">A tour in Wales 1770 [1773]</hi> (1778), II, p. 191.</note></p>
                
                <p>Will this circumstance assist to cast any new light on the Natural history of these our annual visitants? If they migrate, they must then 
                    have been on their passage, but it seems to me to have been too early in the year for them to have arrived at their summer residence I 
                    would therefore conclude that they pass their winter some distance at sea in our own climate –</p>
                
                <p>I observed a remarkable difference in the bills of the Puffins, which seem’d to indicate the age of the bird till 
                    <del><gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="1"/></del>three years old; the bill of the youngest was narrow, blunt, 
                    and wanted those transverse <hi rend="underline"><unclear>sulei</unclear></hi> and color which are observable in the old birds; the next 
                    class which seem to me to be two years old have the bill in form and color between the last described and those fully formed, the transverse 
                    <hi rend="underline"><unclear>sulei</unclear></hi> and color in these are faint – As I have at different times had opportunities of seeing vast 
                    numbers of these birds on <placeName ref="pl1959">Priestholm Island</placeName>, and never observed the difference now noticed, I am led to 
                    conclude that these birds do not approach the land to breed till they are at least three years old. I observed the same difference in the bills 
                    of the <hi rend="underline">Razor-bill</hi> – There were among the wreck great quantities of the bone of the <hi rend="underline">Sepin</hi> 
                    <hi rend="underline">officinalis</hi>. I likewise found the upper Jaw of a Dolphin. –</p>
                
                
                <closer>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0903">H: D.</persName> –</signed>
                   
                    <dateline><placeName ref="pl1486">Beaumares</placeName>, March the 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1782.</dateline></closer>
                
                
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>