<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1354">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Philip Yorke to Thomas Pennant, 13 November 1778</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>Warwickshire County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>CR 2017/TP 401/2/1</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc/>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0243">Philip Yorke</persName>
                    <date when="1778-11-13"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl1250">Netherhall</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct1359"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct1358"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener>
                    <salute>Dear Sir.</salute><dateline><placeName ref="pl1250">Netherhall</placeName> Nov: 13. 1778</dateline></opener>
                
                <p><persName ref="pe0683">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Senhouse</persName> is so kind to sit near me, and from his dictating, I 
                    make you the following Communication of such things as have been found in and near the Camps since you were in this 
                    Country.<note type="editorial">Yorke refers to Pennant's visit to Senhouse at the town of Maryport and the latter's seat, 
                        Netherhall, Cumbria, on his journey to Scotland in 1772. Pennant observed the remains of a Roman station square, a 
                        tumulus, and 'several antiquities that had been long preserved in [the] house and gardens', and provided plates showing 
                        some of the latter. He also reported that Senhouse had since provided him with 'an account of other discoveries'. This 
                        letter suggests that yet further material was uncovered during the second half of the 1770s. 
                        <hi rend="italic">A tour in Scotland 1772</hi>, part I (1774), pp. 59–64. Further on the discovery of Roman remains at 
                        Maryport
                        from the sixteenth century to the present day, see Kirstie Kinghorn,
                        'Maryport Roman settlement: unearthing a Roman civilian's past', <ref type="http" target="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-cumbria-26558713">here</ref> [accessed 13 August 2017].
                    </note></p>
                <p>
                    <table>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <list>
                                    <item>1.</item>
                                    <item>VIRTVTI</item>
                                    <item>AVGVSTAE</item>
                                    <item>--------------</item>
                                    <item>QVINTIFILIA</item>
                                    <item>HERMIONAE</item>
                                    <item>VSLLM</item>
                                </list>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <list>
                                    <item>2</item>
                                    <item>I O M</item>
                                    <item>ACILIANVS</item>
                                    <item>PRAEFECTVS</item>
                                    <item>P</item>
                                </list>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <list>
                                    <item>3.</item>
                                    <item>VEXIL LEG II AV<add place="above">G</add></item>
                                    <item>ET XX VV</item>
                                    <item>FECERVNT</item>
                                </list>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </p>
                <p>No: 1, and 2, are Altars like those you saw here before; the first has only half the Cup, being but the section of the Altar, 
                    and the front face of it; the Second is remarkable for having no Cup at all. Note, there is a line lost in the first (as scratched) 
                    by the Fracture of <add place="above">the</add> Stone, which was the name of the woman; the three last letters of the lost name, 
                    were clearly <del>X</del>AN<del>X</del>A – without the stroke in the A –––––</p>
                <p>No: 3. appears to have been a facing Stone in some building, and found in the Camp. In the Quarry near the Camp about 3 Years 
                    since was found a Stone bearded head – The Sculpture is bold, and you may suppose it <persName ref="pe2102">Jupiter</persName> if you will. The neck is broken 
                    from the Body and it had fallen from <del>the Camp</del>the ––––– Brow near the Camp into the Quarry. You will note that the 
                    letters of the Inscriptions herein sent are not exactly in the Sit<del>t</del>uation they are in on the Stone, that is, the 
                    <sic>the</sic> number of Letters in each line are preserved, but they do not <del>unders</del>, stand under one another, 
                    exactly as they do on the Stone. One <sic>compleat</sic> Pair of Millstones have been found; an odd one, which is extremely 
                    neat, <unclear>to</unclear> several Fragments their diameter (that is the Dia: of the Pair, are twenty Inches, the odd one is 
                    seventeen. They are supposed to have been worked by the hand. There has been a Stone female Image found, but the Limbs and head are 
                    gone; the Barbarians seem to have made a whetstone of the back. There is a Fragment of a broad Stone, which appears to have been a 
                    facing in a wall, on which the following Fragment is very fairly Inscribed in larger letters than com[m]on<lb/>
                    C O H <unclear>I</unclear><lb/>
                    and by the tops of the letters in the next line <persName ref="pe0683">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Senhouse</persName> 
                    thinks it is <sic>Hispanoric</sic>.
                </p>
                <p>Several <sic>peices</sic> of unground Glass painted &amp; plain, have been dug up <gap unit="letters" quantity="several" reason="authorial"/> 
                    They are understood to be as well cast as Any of the same Kind now done: but neither ground of polished. With 
                    <persName ref="pe0683">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Senhouse</persName>'s best Resp<hi rend="superscript">cts</hi> to you, </p>
                <closer><salute>
                    I am Dear Sir Your very<lb/>
                        Faithfull Friend
                    <lb/>
                    </salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0243">Ph: Yorke</persName></signed>
                    </closer></div>
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>