<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1355">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Philip Yorke to Thomas Pennant, 3 December 1776</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>Warwickshire County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP 22/5/3</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc><additions>
                        <hi rend="italic">Endorsement, in Thomas Pennant's hand</hi>: <persName ref="pe0243">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Yorke</persName>'s Letter.</additions>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0243">Philip Yorke</persName>
                    <date when="1776-12-03"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl1244">Erthig</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref=""/>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct1356"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct1353"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><dateline><placeName ref="pl1244">Erthig</placeName>, Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. <gap unit="letters" quantity="2"/>3:<add place="above"><del>th</del>d</add> 1776.</dateline>
                    <salute>Dear Sir.</salute></opener>
                
                <p>I took my Route from <placeName ref="pl1244">Erthig</placeName> on the 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. of August 
                    1766<note type="editorial">For Yorke's account of this journey, see <ref target="0024.xml">0024</ref>.</note> in a party with 
                    <persName ref="pe0623">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Cust</persName>, <persName ref="pe0624">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Brownlow Cust</persName>, 
                    and <persName ref="pe0625">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Kent</persName>, the descendant, and opulent Heir of our first 
                    Modern <persName ref="pe2101">Gardiner</persName>, of that name, and Passed in primo limine,<note type="editorial">'first of all'.</note> the inscrutable 
                    Remains of <placeName ref="pl1206">Watt's-dyke</placeName><note type="authorial">I have not been able with any Precision to 
                        determine the Extent (from North to South) of <placeName ref="pl1206">Watt's dyke</placeName>, but 
                        <persName ref="pe0663">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Evans</persName> who is at this time engaged on a Map of <placeName ref="pl1221">north Wales</placeName>, 
                        means to do it.<note type="editorial">Pennant refers to John Evans's 'actual survey of North Wales' and his intention to publish a large map of that area in a note 
                            in <hi rend="italic">A tour in Wales 1770 [1773]</hi> (1778), I, p. 21, noting that the work is 
                            'extremely worthy of public encouragement'.</note></note>; Our Tradition is, for we have no written Memorial, that it was a Cotemporary 
                    Work, with <placeName ref="pl1207">Offa's dyke</placeName>, which for a considerable way, runs parallel with it, at unequal distances, but here, 
                    within two miles; The intermediate Country is supposed to have been neutral Ground, set apart for Treaty, and Traffick, and it was a Law to each 
                    Nation, that if a Saxon was taken armed, on the Western side of <placeName ref="pl1207">Offa</placeName>, or a Welchman to the East of 
                    <placeName ref="pl1206">Watt</placeName>, he forfeited the loss of a Member:<note type="editorial">Citing the <hi rend="italic">Polycraticon</hi> of John of Salisbury (Sarisburiensis) as his 
                    authority, Camden notes 'that Harald establish'd a Law, that whatever Welshman should be found arm'd on this side the limit he had set them, to 
                    wit, Offa's-Dike, his right-hand should be cut off by the King's Officers'. See Camden, <hi rend="italic">Britannia</hi> (2nd edn., rev. Gibson, 1722), II, p. 698.</note> Hence, passing <placeName ref="pl1207">Offa's dyke</placeName><note type="authorial">I conceive 
                            Dyke to mean the Rampire, and not the Ditch and so it is understood in <placeName ref="pl1228">Holland</placeName> and is the Fence against 
                            the Sea.</note> at <placeName ref="pl1208">Adwy-ar y <sic>Claudd</sic></placeName><note type="authorial">Anglice, 
                                <placeName ref="pl1208">the Gap in the Ditch</placeName>–</note> and leaving the broken Extremity of the <placeName ref="pl1209">Brendaeg Hills</placeName>, 
                    and the <placeName ref="pl1210">Minera lead mines</placeName>, (once the anxious object of Roman, as since of British 
                    Adventurers,<note type="editorial">For Pennant's comments on the mineral vein of Minera, which he describes as part of 'a rich mineral tract', see 
                        <hi rend="italic">A tour in Wales</hi> 
                        (2nd edn., 1784), I, pp. 316, 447.</note> (on our left, We departed out of <placeName ref="pl1213">Bromfeild</placeName>, and entered the 
                    Hilly <placeName ref="pl1211">Hundred of Yale</placeName>, at <placeName ref="pl1212">Abber Croes Newydd</placeName>: The former fine 
                    <placeName ref="pl1213">Lordship</placeName>, (in which, is my Paternal House,) in the Tripartite Partition of all Wales, by 
                    <persName ref="pe0626">Rodoricus Magnus</persName>, circiter annum 870. was a Comot<note type="authorial">by the name<add place="above">:</add> of 
                        <placeName ref="pl1213">Maelor Cumraec, Welch maelor</placeName></note> of the 
                    <placeName ref="pl1214">Kingdom of Mathrafal or Powys Land</placeName>,<note type="authorial">The other two Kingdoms, were 
                        <placeName ref="pl1222">Gwynedh or North-Wales</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1223">Deheubarth</placeName>, <add place="above">(the left Hand)</add> 
                            or <placeName ref="pl1223">South-Wales</placeName> – Our six Counties of <placeName ref="pl1221">NWales</placeName>, are comprehended 
                            in <placeName ref="pl1270">Gwynedh</placeName>, 
                        and <placeName ref="pl1224">Powys</placeName>.</note> in the <placeName ref="pl1217"><sic>Cantred</sic> Uchnant</placeName>, which, was a 
                    Subdivision of <placeName ref="pl1215">Powysfadoc</placeName>,<note type="authorial">The other Division, was 
                        <placeName ref="pl1225">Powys - Wenwynwyn</placeName>.</note> one of the two Greater divisions: The Mercian Saxons, under the 
                    Auspices of their Prince <persName ref="pe0627">Offa</persName>, extended their Conquests over this Country, (tho in part 
                    Recovered afterwards by the Welch,<note type="authorial">The Town of <placeName ref="pl0740">Shrewsbury</placeName>, Wall:<hi rend="superscript">ce</hi> <placeName ref="pl0740">Pengwerne</placeName>, 
                        and the plain Country on the Banks of <placeName ref="pl1226">Severn</placeName> 
                        to <placeName ref="pl1227">Wye</placeName>, and <del><gap unit="letters" quantity="several" reason="illegible"/></del>that to the East of the 
                        <placeName ref="pl1138">Dee</placeName>, was never Reunited to the <placeName ref="pl0731">Principality</placeName>.</note>) and probably gave 
                    to this <placeName ref="pl1213">Hundred</placeName>, the name it now bears; a Saxon Compound of the Plant Broom, and the Field, or Seat of 
                    <sic>it's</sic> Growth, and I observe in many parts, there is yet much to be found of it; A <note type="authorial">H<gap unit="words" quantity="several" reason="illegible"/> Plantæ –</note>Shrub 
                    indeed! of no ordinary fame, for besides giving title to this fine Country, it marked with <sic>it's</sic> name the 
                    <persName ref="pe0628">Angevin Family</persName>, the magnanimous Race of the 
                    <persName ref="pe0628">Plantagenets</persName>,<note type="authorial">Planta Genista –<note type="editorial">'Common broom', used by the Plantagenet kings 
                        as an emblem.</note></note> who are said to have been so called, from the use of weaving in their Helm<unclear>ets</unclear>,  a sprig of this 
                    Plant. By the Act of Union, the 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. of 
                    <persName ref="pe0629">Henry 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</persName><note type="editorial">What became known as the Act 
                        of Union of 1536 was represented by clause 26 of the legislation passed in the twenty-seventh year of the reign of Henry VIII. 
                        Among its provisions were the formation of new counties, including the division of the March into the counties of Denbigh, Montgomery, 
                        Radnor, Brecon and Monmouth; the abolishment of legal distinctions between the Welsh and the English; representation to the Welsh in 
                        the English parliament; and stipulation that English was to be the only language of the courts of Wales. Davies, 
                        <hi rend="italic">A History of Wales</hi>, pp. 231–8.</note><note type="authorial">This wise and beneficial Statute 
                            (and in bad times), as I have been well informed, supplied my <persName ref="pe0664">Lord Somers</persName>, 
                            with many useful Hints in the (splicing) Act he drew of Union with <placeName ref="pl0705">Scotland</placeName>.<note type="editorial">Both 
                                John Davies and Geraint H. Jenkins note the fundamental difference between the act unifying Wales with England in 1536 and those which 
                                united Scotland with England in 1707 and Ireland with Britain in 1800. Whereas the parliaments of Scotland and Ireland voted for their 
                                own abolition, the English parliament (which contained no Welsh members) passed the legislation to unite England and Wales without Welsh 
                                acquiescence. Furthermore, the preamble to the statues claimed that an union already existed between the two lands. Yorke's comment that 
                                the Welsh example furnished John Somers with ideas on how to achieve the union of Scotland and England is worthy of notice. It may perhaps 
                                relate to the deception and trickery which Davies accredits to the promoters of the unions with Scotland and Ireland in their efforts to 
                                persuade the parliaments of the latter countries to agree to their own abolition. Davies, <hi rend="italic">A History of Wales</hi>, p. 232; 
                                Jenkins, ' "Taphy-land historians" and the Union of England and Wales 1536–2007', 1–27, esp. 3.</note></note>  This <placeName ref="pl1213">Lordship</placeName> 
                    was made Parcel of <placeName ref="pl1216">Denbighshire</placeName>, then first <unclear>Exxted</unclear>  into a 
                    County:<note type="authorial">Three other additional Welch Counties were at the same time erected, composed of the ancient <sic>Independant</sic> Baronies, 
                        and the Lordships Marchers, Petty Feudal Tyrannies w<add place="above">h</add>ere, in some Cases, the King's Writts did not Run: 
                        <placeName ref="pl1229">Monmouthshire</placeName> by the same Act was made a County composed as the rest, and annexed to the English Circuit, 
                        The Ancient Welch-Shires were: <placeName ref="pl1230">Glamorgan</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1231">Caermarthen</placeName>, 
                        <placeName ref="pl1232">Pembroke</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1233">Cardigan</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl0702">Flint</placeName>, 
                        <placeName ref="pl1234">Caernarvon</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1235">Merioneth</placeName>.</note> 
                    In the Earlier times, as I have before observed, it was a Comot of the Kingdom of <placeName ref="pl1214">Mathrafal</placeName>, by the name of 
                    <placeName ref="pl1213">Maelor Cymraec</placeName>, and as a Portion of it Passed by the Bounty of <persName ref="pe0626">Rodoricus Magnus</persName>, 
                    to his youngest Son <persName ref="pe0630">Merfyn</persName>, in whose Posterity this Principality remained Entire, till the death of 
                    <persName ref="pe0618">Blethyn ap <sic>Confyn</sic></persName>; That Potentate, (who was also Prince of <placeName ref="pl1222">North Wales</placeName>) 
                    divided it between his Sons <persName ref="pe0631">Meredith</persName>, and <persName ref="pe0632">Cadwgan</persName>; nevertheless it returned 
                    whole and entire to the Possession of <persName ref="pe0631">Meredith ap Blethyn</persName>; He, once more dissevered it, and it fell between 
                    his two Sons <persName ref="pe0633">Madawc</persName>, &amp; <persName ref="pe0634">Gr<del>i</del>uffydh</persName>; <persName ref="pe0633">Madawc</persName> 
                    the Elder, married <persName ref="pe0635">Susannah</persName>, the Daughter of <persName ref="pe0636">Gruffydh ap Conan</persName>, 
                    Prince of <placeName ref="pl1222">North Wales</placeName>: 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>.<note type="authorial">1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0592">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. David Powell</title></bibl> 
                        from whom I have extracted the descent of <placeName ref="pl1214">Powys Land</placeName>, particularly that Division of it, called 
                        <placeName ref="pl1215">Powys Fadoc</placeName>, derives that Moiety to <persName ref="pe0633">Madawc</persName> the Eldest son of 
                        <persName ref="pe0631">Meredith ap Blethyn</persName> from his marriage with <persName ref="pe0635">Susannah</persName> - the Daughter of 
                        <persName ref="pe0636">Gruffydh ap Conan</persName>; whereas it should rather seem that he (<persName ref="pe0633">Madawc</persName>) in the 
                        partition, inherited it from his Father <persName ref="pe0631">Meredith ap Blethyn</persName>, who Possessed all <placeName ref="pl1214">Powys</placeName>, 
                        in descent from <persName ref="pe0618">Blethyn ap Confyn</persName><sic>;:</sic> who was the immediate Descendant of 
                        <persName ref="pe0630">Merfyn</persName> the youngest Son of <persName ref="pe0626">Roderick the Great</persName>: Moreover it was not probable it 
                        should come by any Connection with <persName ref="pe0636">Gruffydh ap Conan</persName>, who does not appear ever to have had it in Possession, 
                        and who left 5 Children: 3 Sons &amp; two Daughters.</note> This Moiety<note type="authorial">viz <placeName ref="pl1215">Powys-Fadoc</placeName> –</note> 
                    after his death<note type="authorial"><persName ref="pe0633">Madawc</persName> –</note>, (which happened at <placeName ref="pl1280">Winchester</placeName>,) 
                    underwent a Tripartition, and was divided between his Sons <persName ref="pe0637">Gruffydh Maelor</persName>, <persName ref="pe0638">Owen ap Madawc</persName>, 
                    and <persName ref="pe0639">Owen <sic>Brogynton</sic></persName>; <persName ref="pe0637">Gruffydh Maelor</persName> had to his share Both the 
                    Maelors,<note type="editorial">Yorke refers to Bromfield, or <placeName ref="pl1213">Maelor Gymraeg</placeName>, and 
                        <placeName ref="pl1218">Maelor Saesneg</placeName>.</note> with <placeName ref="pl1219">Llanrhaidr Mochnant</placeName>; He 
                    married <persName ref="pe0640">Angharad</persName> the Daughter of <persName ref="pe0641">Owen Gwynedh</persName> Prince of 
                    <placeName ref="pl1222">North Wales</placeName>, and by her had Issue one son <persName ref="pe0642">Madawc</persName>, who held his 
                    <persName ref="pe0637">Father</persName>'s Inheritance Entire, and left it to his only son <persName ref="pe0643">Gruffydh</persName>; He married 
                    <persName ref="pe0644">Emma</persName> the daughter of James Lord Audley, and by her had Issue: <persName ref="pe0645">Madawc</persName>, 
                    <persName ref="pe0646">Llewellyn</persName>, <persName ref="pe0647">Gruffydh</persName>, and <persName ref="pe0648">Owen</persName>; 
                    <persName ref="pe0643">Gruffydh</persName>, the Father, being a warm Partizan of <persName ref="pe0649">Henry 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>.</persName> 
                    and <persName ref="pe0650">Edward 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>.</persName> and therefore very obnoxious to his own Countrymen, in fear of their 
                    just Resentments, kept himself close shut up in his impregnable <placeName ref="pl0794">Castle of Dinas-Bran</placeName>;<note type="editorial">The account given by Yorke in 
                        his <ref target="0024.xml">1766 tour</ref> of Castell Dinas Brân focuses on its Galfridian association with the figure of Brennus and on traditional lore about a 
                        concealed treasure within the ruins. No mention is made of the medieval dynastic considerations discussed in this letter.</note> Our Welch 
                    Historians assert: that <persName ref="pe0650">Edward 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi></persName>– with great Ingratitude, made 
                    away <add place="above">privately</add> with two of his Children, and bestowed the Wardship of <persName ref="pe0645">Madawc the Eldest Son</persName> 
                    (who by his <persName ref="pe0643">Father</persName>'s Will inherited the Lordships of <placeName ref="pl1213">Bromfeild</placeName>, and 
                    <placeName ref="pl1211">Yale</placeName>) on <persName ref="pe0651">John Earl Warren</persName>, who soon secured to himself this fine Possession, 
                    and began the <placeName ref="pl1220">Castle of Holt</placeName>, the Capital of his <sic>ill-atchieved</sic> Lordship; It was finished by his 
                    Son <persName ref="pe0652">William</persName>; In this great Baronial House it continued for three descents, and then passed by <persName ref="pe0653">Alice</persName> 
                    (the Sister and Heir of the last <persName ref="pe0654">John Earl Warren</persName>) to <persName ref="pe0655">Edmond Fitzallan Earl of Arundel</persName> 
                    her Husband, in which line it also Remained for three Descents. <persName ref="pe0656">Richard</persName> the son of <persName ref="pe0655">Edmond</persName>, 
                    <persName ref="pe0657">Richard</persName>, his Son, and <persName ref="pe0658">Thomas Earl of Arundel</persName>; For want of Issue to this last 
                    <persName ref="pe0658">Thomas Earl of Arundel and Warren</persName>, <gap quantity="several"/>His <sic>Unintailed</sic> 
                    <add place="above">Estates</add> fell to two of his Sisters,<note type="authorial"><persName ref="pe0658">His</persName> three Sisters were 
                        his Heirs General –</note> <persName ref="pe0659">Elizabeth</persName>, married to <persName ref="pe0661">Henry Mowbray Duke of Norfolk</persName>, 
                    and <persName ref="pe0660">Joan</persName>, to 
                    <persName ref="pe0662">William Beauchamp Lord of Abergavenny</persName>.<note type="authorial"><bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0702">Camden</title></bibl> 
                        takes notice of a <persName ref="pe0665">third Sister</persName> <add place="above">&amp; Coheir</add>, of <persName ref="pe0658">Thomas Earl of Arundel</persName>, 
                        who married <persName ref="pe0666">Sir Rowland Lenthall</persName>, Master of the Wardrobe to <persName ref="pe0667">King Henry 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></persName>. 
                        He built that handsome and venerable Pile of <placeName ref="pl1271">Hampton Court</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl1653">Herefordshire</placeName>, which I have 
                        heard often mistakenly attributed to <persName ref="pe0667">Henry 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</persName> whilst he was 
                        Earl of Hereford.<note type="editorial">'... the <hi rend="italic">Lug</hi> hastens to the <hi rend="italic">Wye</hi>, first, by <hi rend="italic">Hampton</hi>, 
                            where Rowland Lenthall, Master of the Wardrobe to King Henry the fourth, who married one of the heirs of <hi rend="italic">Thomas</hi> Earl of <hi rend="italic">Arundel</hi>, 
                            built a very fine House ...'. Camden, <hi rend="italic">Britannia</hi> (2nd edn., rev. Gibson, 1722), I, p. 690.</note></note></p> 
                <closer><salute>I am<lb/>
                    Dear Sir<lb/>
                    Your affect: Humble<lb/>
                    Servant<lb/>
                    </salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0243">Ph: Yorke</persName> –</signed>
                    </closer>
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>