<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1356">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Philip Yorke to Thomas Pennant, 10 April 1777</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                        <idno>15423C</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc/>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0243">Philip Yorke</persName>
                    <date when="1777-04-10"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl1238">Conduit street</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl1243">Great George st:</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct1357"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct1355"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener>
                    <salute>Dear Sir.</salute></opener>
                
                <p>Impatient to Receive another of your most Entertaining Volumes,<note type="editorial">Yorke evidently refers to a draft or proof of the volume (or a part of the volume) published 
                    the following year as Pennant's <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0012">A tour in Wales 1770 [1773]</title></bibl> (1778).</note>  I return you this, which I have gone through with the greatest 
                    pleasure to myself, but I fear without any use to you. - I <gap quantity="1"/>can pay you but with thanks, the poor man's 
                    Excheques. If <del><gap quantity="1"/></del><del>you</del> this finds you at home, pray send me another book.</p> 
                <closer><salute>
                    Dear Sir<lb/>
                    Y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Faithful Friend<lb/>
                    &amp; Servant<lb/>
                    </salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0243">Ph: Yorke</persName> –</signed>
                    </closer>
                <postscript><p>I will attend you to the <placeName ref="pl1237">Paper office</placeName>, and <placeName ref="pl1236">Museum</placeName> 
                    tomorrow if agreeable to you. –</p>
                    <p><placeName ref="pl1238">Cond<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>: st:</placeName> Apr: 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1777<lb/>
                        Thursday night. –
                    </p>
                    <p>Page 1st Line 1st –<lb/>
                        the Motto is excellently chosen; I had thought of one, inferior = Antiquam exquirere matrem.<note type="editorial">'Seek out our ancient mother[land]'.</note><lb/> 
                        P: 8 – L: 10 = &amp; supported by the Friends and Partizans of his Uncle <persName ref="pe0668">Jasper Earl of Pembroke</persName>, created by 
                        himself (after he was <persName ref="pe0670">King</persName>, Duke of Bedford: there remained till of very late Years at 
                        <placeName ref="pl1239">Corsygydol</placeName>, the seat of the ancient Family of Vechan or <persName ref="pe0669">Vaughan</persName> in 
                        <placeName ref="pl1235">Merionethshire</placeName>, a very dilapidated part of the House, in which was a Chamber called the King's, wherein 
                        <persName ref="pe0670">Henry</persName> occasionally lived, and was concealed  by the <persName ref="pe0671">Possessor of that day</persName>, 
                        who had a Command in a South Welsh castle (I think <placeName ref="pl1998">Aberystwith</placeName> in the <placeName ref="pl1241">bay of Cardigan</placeName>) 
                        under the aforesaid <persName ref="pe0668">Jasper</persName>.<note type="editorial">Pennant does not appear to have made use of this information 
                            in <hi rend="italic">A tour in Wales</hi>. Philip Yorke may have been aware of the account of the Corsygedol family given by Robert Vaughan, 
                            Hengwrt. Vaughan noted that Gruffudd Vaughan 'was in great credit w<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Jasper Earle of <sic>Pembrok</sic>, who lay in his house at Corsygedol 
                            when he fled to France in y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> tyme of Ed: 4, and as some report, Harry the Earle of Richmont w<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 
                            him, who afterwards was King of England'. Dwnn, <hi rend="italic">Heraldic visitations of Wales and part of the marches</hi>, II, p. 219 n. 19.</note> 
                            P. 19. L: 21. the word Castle, is improperly repeated.<lb/>
                        P: 20, L 15. The <placeName ref="pl1207">Dyke</placeName> Itself I apprehend, was clearly a boundary, and not a work of defence, yet there 
                        are near upon it large Entrenchments seemingly to command it It is the same with <placeName ref="pl1206">Watt's dyke</placeName>: To sport 
                        a conjecture; might not the Dyke, <add place="above">or Rampire</add> (properly speaking) of this Foss, which was clear amidst a 
                        surrounding Country of Wood, act as a Road or Communication Pr.<note type="editorial">'Pr.' may be an abbreviation for 'proceeding'.</note> 
                        North to South, &amp; be cast to a double use.<lb/>
                                P: 30. L: 17. Is not this part of the <hi rend="underline">Maid</hi>'s story, too funny and gay for a grave &amp; instructive 
                        Work.<note type="editorial">Yorke's pagination and his reference to the 'Maid' suggest that he may be referring to the section of Pennant's first volume 
                            <hi rend="italic">A tour in Wales</hi> which relates to Saint Wenefrede. Pennant provides a humorous account of the miraculous 
                            story of the decapitation and restoration of Wenefrede's head by Beuno, apparently to Yorke's discomfiture at the change 
                            of tone displayed. <hi rend="italic">A tour in Wales 1770 [1773]</hi> (1778), I, pp. 32–3.</note><lb/>
                                Leaf opposite to P: 32. The following pretty Monkish distich, was found engraven on an ancient Bell –<lb/>
                                = Dum cano busta, mori; dum pulpita, vivere disce;<lb/>
                        = Disce mori nostro, vivere, disec, sono.<note type="editorial">Pennant notes an inscription on one bell 
                            consecrated to St Wenefrede in <hi rend="italic">A tour in Wales 1770 [1773]</hi> (1778), I, p. 35.</note><lb/> 
                                P: 33. L 17. On the groundwork of which Heathen Story (as hath been usual with the Monks) is built this Miraculous History.<lb/>
                        P 37. L: 15. <placeName ref="pl1216">Denbighshire</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1242">Montgomeryshire</placeName> being taken from 
                        the Baronies Marchers, were added to these 4 anc<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Shires of <placeName ref="pl1221">N-Wales</placeName>, 
                        by the incorporating Act of <persName ref="pe0629">H: 8</persName> –––––<note type="editorial">Denbighshire and Montgomeryshire 
                            were among the seven new counties fashioned from the Marcher lordships by the Acts of Union of 1536 and 1543, and added to the other 
                            six shires of Wales, which had been established through the 1284 Statute of Wales. In the north, these shires consisted of Anglesey, 
                            Caernarfonshire, Merioneth and Flintshire. Davies, <hi rend="italic">A History of Wales</hi>, pp. 232–3; 
                            Jenkins, ' "Taphy-land historians" and the Union of England and Wales 1536–2007', 4; and see <ref target="1355.xml">1355</ref>.</note><lb/> 
                        P: 41. L 6. I think Majesty was first applied to the Person &amp; Character of <persName ref="pe0672">James 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi></persName>. –––––
                    </p></postscript></div>
                <div><p><address>
                    <addrLine><persName ref="pe0232">Tho<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>. Pennant Esq<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.</persName></addrLine>
                    <addrLine><placeName ref="pl1243">Great George st:</placeName> –</addrLine>
                </address></p></div>
            
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>