<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1357">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Philip Yorke to Thomas Pennant, 17 November 1777</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>Warwickshire County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017 /TP23/4</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc><p><hi rend="italic">Condition</hi>: slight damage to the manuscript</p></physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0243">Philip Yorke</persName>
                    <date when="1777-11-17"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl1244">Erthig</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref=""/>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct1358"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct1356"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener>
                    <salute>Dear Sir;</salute><dateline><placeName ref="pl1244">Erthig</placeName>, 
                        Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1777–</dateline></opener>
                
                <p>I received with great pleasure your Commands by our friend <persName ref="pe0691">Owen Wynne</persName>;<note type="editorial">Owen 
                    Wynne has not been identified.</note>  I divided the Contents between two Covers, for I found that the large single <sic>Pacquet</sic>, 
                    which brought them enclosed to me, weighed considerably above two Ounces. <persName ref="pe0692">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Newcome</persName> 
                    dined with me last Thursday, and he encourages me to dislodge that <hi rend="underline">ancient</hi> <hi rend="underline">Briton</hi> from his 
                    snug Situation under the Wall of his Church:<note type="editorial">This may refer to <placeName ref="pl1257">Gresford Church</placeName>, 
                        which featured a statue sometimes described as representing Henry VII. Cf. also a note by Trevor Parkins in the 1883
                    edition of Pennant's <hi rend="italic">A tour in Wales</hi>, which mentions the discovery of a tombstone upon the demolition of wall at the old mansion of Pantiocyn near Gresford. On the stone, there was 'a shield with a lion rampant on it, and the inscription, 
                        <hi rend="italic">Hic jacet Griffri</hi>'. Parkins noted that the stone had subsequently been taken to Gresford Church, whence he believed it had come originally.<hi rend="italic">Tours in Wales by Thomas Pennant, Esq</hi> ed. by John Rhys (3 vols., Caernarvon: H. Humphreys, 1883), I, p. 388.</note> My Mason (who is a <gap quantity="1"/>careful Person, and like his 
                    Master, having a due veneration for Antiquities) will go over with me for that purpose, and we will serve <persName ref="pe0693">Wilkinson</persName> 
                    the Herald with notice, if he should be at <sic>liesure</sic> to attend us in the Course of the next week. By the marginal note in 
                    <persName ref="pe0333">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lloyd</persName>'s <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0592"/>Powell</bibl>, 
                    this Monument should be given to <persName ref="pe0700">Madoc ap Llewellin ap Griffri</persName>, who was buried (according to our Antiquary) 
                    in the <placeName ref="pl1257">Church of Gresford</placeName>, circiter Annum 1330, the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. of <persName ref="pe0695">Edw<gap quantity="2"/>ard 
                        the 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></persName>. If the Inscription be <sic>decypherable</sic>, and shall square with <persName ref="pe0333">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lloyds</persName> 
                    Intelligence, there seems no difficulty in pointing out the Person –<note type="editorial">Yorke mistakenly identifies Madog 
                        ap Llywelyn ap Griffri, who died in 1331, with Madog ap Gruffudd Fychan (Madog Grupul; c.1275–1304/6). See further n. 5, below.</note> 
                    He was the Son of <persName ref="pe0647">Gruffith y Barwyn Gwyn (or the White Baron) Lord of Glyn dyfy<gap quantity="1"/>rdwy</persName>, 
                    and succeeded his Father, and died possessed of that L<gap quantity="1"/>ordship; He is called by the Welsh Heralds and Historians: 
                    <persName ref="pe0694">Madoc Grupul</persName>, and was the Great-Great Grandfather of <persName ref="pe0495">owen Glyndyfyrdwy</persName>, 
                    who inherited that Estate in Succession from him. This <persName ref="pe0647">Baron Gwyn</persName> (the Father of 
                    <persName ref="pe0694">Grupul</persName>) was the third of the four unfortunate Sons of <persName ref="pe0643">Griffith Lord of Dinas-Bran</persName>, 
                    Temp: <persName ref="pe0649">Hen: 3d</persName>. The two Elder (<persName ref="pe0645">Madoc</persName>, &amp; <persName ref="pe0646">Llewellin</persName>,) 
                    inherited f<hi rend="superscript">m</hi>. their <persName ref="pe0643">Father</persName> in Gavel, the two 
                    Bromfeilds,<note type="editorial">Yorke refers to <placeName ref="pl1213">Maelor Gymraeg</placeName> and 
                        <placeName ref="pl1218">Maelor Saesneg</placeName>, both also known by the name 'Bromfield'.</note> and the Lordships of <placeName ref="pl1211">Yale</placeName>, 
                    and <placeName ref="pl1259">Nanthewdwy</placeName>; They were wards. (as you well know) to <persName ref="pe0651">Earl Warren</persName> &amp; 
                    <persName ref="pe0697">Roger Mortimer</persName>; by whom, they were dispossess'd, and dispatched privately:<note type="editorial">Yorke here apparently 
                        draws on Davies, <hi rend="italic">A display of herauldry</hi>, pp. 19–20. The story of the two sons being 'dispatched privately', is recounted in 
                        <hi rend="italic">A tour in Wales 1770 [1773]</hi> (1778), I, p. 210, where Pennant also wrongly identifies them as the elder sons of Gruffudd ap 
                        Madog (Gruffudd of Bromfield). Modern scholarship records the death of Gruffudd and Llywelyn, the young sons of Madog ap Gruffudd, grandsons to 
                        Gruffudd ap Madog, noting the tradition that they were drowned in the river Dee at Holt on the orders of John de Warenne and Roger Mortimer and 
                        on the instructions of Edward I. <hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi> s.n. Madog ap Gruffudd.</note>  When, the 
                    <persName ref="pe0648">4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Son</persName> of <persName ref="pe0643">Gruffith Lord of Dinas</persName>, had the Moiety 
                    of <gap quantity="1"/><placeName ref="pl1281">Cynllaeth</placeName>; He was intended for the Church, but died young, and his Patrimony 
                    Devolved to his Brother <persName ref="pe0647">Griffith</persName>, and thro' him, was continued <gap quantity="several"/> 
                    <persName ref="pe0495">Glyn dyfrydwy</persName>, the legal Representative of the <persName ref="pe0701">House of Powys Fadoc</persName> 
                    (before it was dismembered,) and the lineal descendant of <persName ref="pe0630">Merfyn</persName> the third Son of 
                    <persName ref="pe0626">Rodericus Magnus</persName>, Princeps tertius Walliæ.<note type="editorial">'the third prince of Wales'.</note> 
                </p>
                <p>It seems particular that <persName ref="pe0694">Madoc Grupul</persName>, should bear the Addition :ap <sic>LLewellin</sic>, 
                    <sic>seing</sic> that neither his <persName ref="pe0647">Father</persName>
                    or <persName ref="pe0643">Grandfather</persName>, had that appellation;  His Uncle had :<persName ref="pe0702">ap Griffri</persName> 
                    is very Intelligible; his <persName ref="pe0698">Mother</persName>
                    being the Daughter of <persName ref="pe0699">Cadwgan ap Griffri</persName> – It does not appear, that any of the Princes of the 
                    <persName ref="pe0701">House of Powys Fadoc</persName>, or of its Gavelled Divisions, had sepulchure at <placeName ref="pl1257">Gresford</placeName>.</p>
                <closer><salute>
                    I am Dear Sir,<lb/>
                    Your affect: Friend<lb/>
                    &amp; Faithful Serv<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>.
                    <lb/>
                    
                    </salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0243">Ph: Yorke</persName> –</signed>
                    </closer></div>
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>