<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1361">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Philip Yorke to Thomas Pennant, 19 July 1791</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>Warwickshire County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>CR 2017/TP401/5</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc/>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0243">Philip Yorke</persName>
                    <date when="1791-07-19"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl1203">Abergele</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct1362"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct1360"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,</salute></opener>
                
                <p>I don't know that you will relish being troubled on the score of the Welsh tribes; You once thought of doing something with 
                    them, yourself: <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0593">Vaughan of Hengwrt's account</title></bibl> is dry, short, and 
                    unsatisfactory;  their numerous descendants will furnish anecdote, and some, should enliven so dry a subject: perhaps, you 
                    will let your <persName ref="pe0404">writer</persName>, copy answers, to a few Queries; In Barrington's 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0591"><sic>Gwedi</sic> History</title></bibl> is the relationship as it stands, between the 
                    present <persName ref="pe0326">Sir W: W. Wynne</persName>, and <persName ref="pe0607">Sir John of Wynnstay</persName>; If I 
                    conceive it right, <persName ref="pe0608">Sir W. Williams</persName>, the son of the <persName ref="pe0609">speaker</persName> 
                    married the daughter, and <persName ref="pe0610">heiress</persName> of <persName ref="pe0611">Edw. Thelwal</persName> of 
                    <placeName ref="pl1204">Plas y ward</placeName>; Her <persName ref="pe0680">Mother</persName> was a <sic>Grandaughter</sic> of old 
                    <persName ref="pe0321">Sir John</persName>, the Historian, &amp; Sir Watkin to whom Sir J: left his 
                    Estate,<note type="editorial">The relations outlined here are complex, and may be confused. The Sir J: to whom Yorke refers is unlikely 
                        to be Sir John Wynn, first baronet, whose Gwydir estate was bequeathed to Robert Bertie, first duke of Ancaster. It may, rather, 
                        be a reference to Sir John Wynn, fifth baronet (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>.1628–1719), of Rhiwgoch, Merionethshire, and Wynnstay, 
                        Denbighshire. He bequeathed the Wynnstay estate to Jane (née Thelwall), through whom it came to <persName ref="pe0608">Sir William Williams</persName>, second baronet 
                        (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>.1665–1740), her husband, and their son Sir Watkin Williams Wynn, third baronet (?1693–1749), of 
                        Wynnstay, Denbighshire. <hi rend="italic">Hist P</hi>.</note> was of course his first Cousin's <add place="above">grand-</add>son, 
                    and his great-<hi rend="underline">Welsh nephew</hi>: Pray, <hi rend="underline">what length of time did the late 
                    <persName ref="pe0612">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Wynne of Bodyscallan</persName> set for the <placeName ref="pl1247">Carnarvonshire Boroughs</placeName>, 
                    and what year did he dye: When did <persName ref="pe0613">Billy Bodvel</persName> dye, and how long did he set for that 
                    <placeName ref="pl1234">County</placeName>: When did <persName ref="pe0681">Lady Prendergast</persName> dye: 
                    <persName ref="pe0614">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Gabriel Goodman</persName>, Dean of <placeName ref="pl0776">Westminster</placeName></hi>, and 
                    the Founder of <placeName ref="pl3068">Ruthin school</placeName>, <persName ref="pe0375">Camden</persName>'s patron, was <hi rend="underline">he not a Welshman? and 
                        the Father of <persName ref="pe0615">Bishop Goodman</persName>?<note type="editorial">Yorke appears to have confused the generational 
                        order of the Goodman family as well as the identity of its members. Gabriel Goodman was uncle to Godfrey Goodman, bishop of Gloucester.</note>  of what See?</hi> I  know your books  will answer these Questions in an instant, if 
                    I could get over to them; As I cannot at present determine that time, so I wish this information by letter, for I stop for want of it: It will be 
                    well if it pleases you to send me some sense on the general matter, but I rather guess you are in another world, and will despise this, at present.<note type="editorial">Yorke 
                        may be referring to Pennant's preoccupation with his <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0475">'Outlines of the Globe'</title></bibl> at this time. See, for example, <ref target="1136.xml">1136</ref> and <ref target="1142.xml">1142</ref>.</note> 
                    <persName ref="pe0333">Bloddy</persName> will only write from his pate, and good memory, and will <add place="above">not</add> set on a Chair, 
                    and Consult Books, otherwise, I had not troubled you, as above. I shall take great care of <unclear>y<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></unclear>. 
                    Pedigree, till I have a safe opportunity of sending it over: <persName ref="pe0333">Bloddy</persName> has promised me <persName ref="pe0616">Powell</persName>'s 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0590">latin verses, on the Tribes</title></bibl>, He was of <placeName ref="pl1198">Ednop</placeName>, in 
                    <placeName ref="pl1245">South-Wales</placeName>; I wish I knew more of him, as well as of his namesake, our <persName ref="pe0617">Historian, of Ruabon</persName>. 
                    Anecdotes, and Characters of Great men, are exhausted; some thing might still be had from those of a second rate: You have gathered the Welsh 
                    Harvest of History, so close, that there is scarce any. thing to Glean after you, especially in greater matters. 
                    <gap unit="letters" quantity="several" reason="authorial"/> Shall I say something of this sort, of <persName ref="pe0333">Bloddy</persName>:<lb/>
                    To the <persName ref="pl1200">House of Kymbychan</persName> of this tribe, (<persName ref="pe0618">Bleddyn ap Cynfyn</persName>) we are 
                    indebted for a worthy man, and excellent Welsh Genealogist, the <persName ref="pe0333">reverend John Lloyd</persName> Rector 
                    of <placeName ref="pl1201">Caerwis</placeName>; He is a liberal and living light to all who pry into pedigree: that loose 
                    fellow <persName ref="pe0682">Foote</persName> ridiculed, and with some success, our natural love of Ancestry, but <placeName ref="pl1202">Spain</placeName> 
                    was, not ultimately obliged to <persName ref="pe0619">Cervantes</persName>; his ingenuity tis true, was an honour to his Country, but in removing 
                    the speck, he injured the Eye itself, of her national Gallantry, and the Spanish Infantry has been no longer distinguished as the 
                    first in Europe. <gap unit="letters" quantity="several"/> But of this Enough, and I remain always, Dear Sir,</p> 
                <closer><salute>
                    Your affect:<hi rend="superscript">te</hi> Servant,
                    </salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0243">Ph: Yorke</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                <dateline><placeName ref="pl1203">Abergele</placeName>, July 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>: 1791.</dateline>
            
                <postscript><p>If I should put a Motto –<lb/>
                    <sic>ridentem</sic> dicere verum<lb/>
                    Quid vetat –<note type="editorial">'Ridente dicere verum quid vetat': 'What prevents me from telling the truth while smiling?' 
                        Horace, <hi rend="italic">Satires</hi>, book I, satire 1, line 24.</note> 
                    
                    </p></postscript></div>
                
            
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>