<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1363">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>To Thomas Pennant, of Downing, Esq., 20 April 1795</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Wrexham</settlement>
                        <repository>Philip Yorke, Tracts of Powys (1795)</repository>
                        <idno>dedicatory letter</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0243">Philip Yorke</persName>
                    <date when="1795-04-20"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl1244">Erthig</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct1364"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct1362"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,</salute></opener>
                
                <p>I attempted with some pains and to little purpose, the several pedigrees of the different descendants of
                    <persName ref="pe0618">Bleddyn ap Cynfyn</persName>, the founder of our third Royal Tribe, but communications failing me, the design, 
                    hath ended, for the present at least, in this slight Memoir of the Princes and Lords of <placeName ref="pl1224">Powys</placeName>, 
                    only.<note type="editorial">This dedicatory letter, addressed to Pennant in recognition of Yorke's sense of the latter's huge contribution 
                        to the field of Welsh antiquarianism (see <ref target="1361.xml">1361</ref>), prefaces Yorke's 1795 publication, <hi rend="italic">The Tracts of Powys</hi>. 
                    The work focused on the descendants of Bleddyn ap Cynfyn, provided notes on the crown lordships of Powys, and argued against the anti-Galfridian view of the 
                    origins of the ancient Britons expressed by Polydore Virgil. The <hi rend="italic">Tracts</hi> were expanded 
                        in <hi rend="italic">The Royal Tribes of Wales</hi>, published in 1799. See <hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi>; <hi rend="italic">DWB</hi>.</note> Such as it is then,
                    permit me to present it you, as to one, by whom 
                our Antiquities have been best understood, and best illustrated. I have added the names of all the families I can find descended 
                from this, as from the nineteen other Tribes: from that source alone, the information necessary must be sought; what we have abroad, 
                is without anecdote, imperfect and uninteresting, and I detach this
                with great submission among them, on a service of better intelligence: If with success, 
                I would report progress; for I am free to think the race of <persName ref="pe2108">Cadwalader</persName>, more glorious 
                    than the breed of <persName ref="pe2109">Gimcrack</persName>, and a Welsh Card, than a <placeName ref="pl3015">Newmarket</placeName> Calendar.</p>
                  
                <closer><salute>I am, Dear Sir, with great esteem,<lb/>
                    
                    Your very faithful and obedient Servant
                </salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0243">Ph. Yorke.</persName></signed>
                    <dateline><placeName ref="pl1244">Erthig</placeName>, April 20th. 1795.</dateline></closer>
                
                
            </div>
            <div><p><address><persName ref="pe0232">Tho<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>: Pennant Esq<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName><lb/>
                <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing –</placeName><lb/>
                
                </address></p></div>
               
            
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>