<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1378">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>John Lloyd, Caerwys, to [Thomas Pennant], <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.1777</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                        <idno>NLW 2594E, Merionethshire folder</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent"><persName ref="pe0333">John Lloyd</persName>
                    <date>c.1777</date>
                    <placeName ref=""/>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">[Thomas Pennant]</persName>
                    <placeName ref=""/>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct1379"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct1377"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><dateline/><salute>D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sir</salute></opener>
                
                <p>All that this Volume contains relative to <persName ref="pe0495">Owen Glyndwr</persName>, is a kind of a Welsh 
                    Inden<del>d</del>ture (as it is call<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>) or rather a Compact enter,<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> 
                    into voluntarily by several districts therein mentioned in order to make some <add place="above">kind</add> of reparation 
                    to individuals, for damages suffer,<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> before &amp; after the war. – It seems to consist of two parts,
                    but the language is so very bad that in many parts it is not intelligible. – I will endeavour to extract the most material &amp;
                    intelligible articles. The first part begins thus. ––—– “This Indenture was made by <placeName ref="pl1607">Llan Ondras</placeName>, 
                    <placeName ref="pl1601">Gwarth-Rymmon</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl2443">Mostyn</placeName> &amp; the three Commots of 
                    <placeName ref="pl1602">Deuddwr</placeName>, near <placeName ref="pl1606">Pont Gammarch</placeName>, six years after
                    <persName ref="pe0495">Owen</persName>’s wars” The purport of which is: “That every one had a Right to his demands from the other 
                    before &amp; after the war, but not during the war; &amp; that every one should have his lands restored without lawsuit[<del>...</del>];
                    whoever refused, not only forfeited the Benefit of the Compact, but the goods so retained &amp;c should be deemed as Thefts, &amp;
                    he deprived from the power of selling them, &amp; if his Lord sold them, he was fined ten pounds, &amp; the goods or their value 
                    to the owners. If the refractory person was Hanged or died a natural death, the <sic>clain</sic> lay good against his wife, 
                    Heirs [<del>...</del>]or Executors &amp;c. But if she or they denied the demand, the plaintiff must procure his Compurgators, viz Six 
                    persons to swear with him to the right of his claim &amp;c <add place="above">The defendant had a right to object to one of the Six, 
                        and another must be provided &amp;c</add>” By the Fragment left of the next clause it seems that the dead [<del>...</del>]Defendant 
                    had a right to his Compurgators. ––––– After this there follow several laws for the quieting &amp; good government of the Country 
                    in general, such as those relative to waives &amp; Estrays, vagrants &amp;c &amp; those relative to <add place="above">Bail &amp;</add>
                    the recovery of Debts, of manslaughter &amp;c of Thefts, the Duty of officers &amp;c. – This Indenture or rather Code concludes with 
                    the Valuation of the Several goods &amp; chattels for which Satisfaction was to be made. – A Horse <add place="above">or mare</add>
                    upon the oath of the Owner &amp; two neighbours might be valued at 0<hi rend="superscript">£</hi>: 10<hi rend="superscript">S</hi>- 
                    0<hi rend="superscript">D</hi>. A foal at 20 pence an ox at a mark, a Cow at twelve 
                    <add place="above">ten</add> Shillings &amp;c &amp;c The Hire of the Ox and the milk of the Cow are also valued &amp;c – An ewe at 
                    16<hi rend="superscript">D</hi>,
                    her wool at at 4<hi rend="superscript">D</hi>, her milk at 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>, her Lamb at 
                    8<hi rend="superscript">D</hi>. &amp;c- [<del>...</del>]&amp;c
                </p> 
                <p>A two handed sword upon the oath of the Owner might be valued at 10<hi rend="superscript">S</hi> a one Handed Sword at 
                    6<hi rend="superscript">S</hi>: 8<hi rend="superscript">D</hi>, a steel Buckler, 2<hi rend="superscript">S</hi>: 
                    8<hi rend="superscript">D</hi>: A Bow 16<hi rend="superscript">D</hi> an arrow 6<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></p>
                <p>It is further ordained, that for all goods, upon which no set value is fixed, such as Cloth, Fustian, <sic>Cloathes</sic>, 
                    Brass, Copper, Flesh, che<del>s</del>ese, meal &amp;c their value is to be <sic>assertained</sic> by the Oath of the Owner</p>
                <p>It may be observed that this seems to be a good Code of Laws voluntarily enacted by the men <add place="above">of</add> the above
                    districts, at that Critical Time; They certainly wanted the Sa[<del>...</del>]nction of Legal authority, &amp; there is no penalty
                    annexed for the Breach of them, But the Forfeiting of the Benefit of the Compact, excepting in one case, where the delinquent is
                    to be fettered with Iron &amp; cast into Prison, and if his keeper shews him any Favour, he is to make good his delinquency &amp;
                    both loose the Benefit of the Compact. This relates to some Judgements confessed before the making of this Compact, &amp; as the
                    passage stands in this manuscript, is totally unintelligible. – I must further observe that <add place="above">this</add> is a 
                    Transcript from <add place="above">some</add> ancient M:S: that was not entire; which is the reason of <sic>it’s</sic> being 
                    s[<del>...</del>]o imperfect. – Most of the Districts mentioned, I believe, are in <placeName ref="pl1242">Montgomeryshire</placeName>
                    . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . – ––––––</p>
                <p>The [<del>...</del>]other Part is a general Compact entered into by the Several parts of the three Principalities. It sets forth to the
                    Following Purport. “Here is a memorandum of the first Compact made, after the Time of <persName ref="pe0495">Owen ap Gryffydd</persName>;
                    Between <placeName ref="pl1222">Gwyned.</placeName> (<placeName ref="pl1221">N: wales</placeName>) and <placeName ref="pl1224">Powys</placeName>,
                    at <placeName ref="pl1597">Bwlch Oerddyrws</placeName>; Between <placeName ref="pl1245">Southwales</placeName> &amp;
                    <placeName ref="pl1224">Powys</placeName>, at <placeName ref="pl1598">Eisteddfa Guric</placeName>; Between <placeName ref="pl1224">Powys</placeName>, 
                        <placeName ref="pl1599">Elvel</placeName>, &amp; <placeName ref="pl1600">Buell</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1601">Gwarth-rymmon</placeName>
                        &amp; the Commot of <placeName ref="pl1602">Deuddwr</placeName>, at <placeName ref="pl1603">Aber Diwlas</placeName>; Between 
                    <placeName ref="pl1224">Powys</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="pl1604">Melionydd</placeName>, at a place call,<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> 
                    <placeName ref="pl1605">Rhuddwr</placeName>.” 
                        This likewise allows the right of of all demands before &amp; after the wars of <placeName ref="pe0495">Owen ap Gryff: (ałs Glyndwr)</placeName>
                        excepting, during the war, and proceeds to a Regular Method of Recovering them &amp;c Here in some cases imprisonment &amp; the Stocks take place. 
                        Both in this and the preceding, Officers are punish,<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> for neglect of Duty &amp;c Here like 
                        <add place="above">wise</add> 
                        the Highest value that the Owner of any cattle &amp;c was allow, <hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to Swear to is fix<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>; 
                        But differs <add place="above">very</add> <del>a</del> little from the former. <del>the prices being generally Higher in that, 
                            but the difference is very Trifling</del> &amp;c All these causes &amp;c were to be tried &amp; Settled in the Courts of the Lords of 
                        the Several districts.. – </p>
                <p>As Justice &amp; <add place="above">the</add> good Regulation of the Country seems to be the only Object of these Compacts, I cant help commending our
                    ancestors highly upon that score, especially if they adhered to the observation of them. They seem to be the associations of all the great men of 
                    the Principality, in order to enforce the observation of Justice, by their Own weight &amp; power, without any other Legal Sanction, &amp; to have
                    arose from those merciless laws enacted against them by <persName ref="pe0667">Henry 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></persName>, where Justice itself
                    (as <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0592"/>Powel</bibl> observes) was <sic>meer</sic> injury &amp; cruelty. – I suppose they were 
                    subsequent to those laws, as the first of these Compacts is mentioned to be made Six years after <persName ref="pe0495">Owen</persName>’s 
                    wars; The last as it comprehends the whole <placeName ref="pl0731">Principality</placeName>, probably arose, from the observation of the utility of
                    the Former in these few districts which entered into it. – – You may probably think it worth your while to dress up a Handsome paragraph upon 
                    this Subject, which will do very well to be inserted after the close of <persName ref="pe0495">Owen</persName>’s 
                    life &amp;c<note type="editorial">Pennant disregarded John Lloyd's advice on the location of this material, including it instead in 
                        <hi rend="italic">A tour in Wales 1770 [1773]</hi> (1778), II, pp. 85–6, following a section on Bwlch yr Oerddrws, which he says ‘is noted for 
                        being one of the three places, in which were assembled, six years after the wars of <hi rend="italic">Glyndwr</hi>, all the great men of certain 
                        districts, in order to enforce the observation of justice by their own weight, without any other legal sanction’.</note></p>
                <closer><salute/>
                    <signed/>
                    <dateline/></closer>
            </div>
            <div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>