<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1379">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>John Lloyd, Caerwys, to Thomas Pennant, 13 June 1777</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Hawarden</settlement>
                        <repository>Flintshire County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>D/DM/120/3</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <additions><p><hi rend="italic">on top of first page in unidentified hand</hi>: P. 58</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Condition</hi>: bottom of first page cut very close to final line of text</p></additions>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0333">John Lloyd</persName>
                    <date when="1777-06-13"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl1201">Caerwys</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref=""/>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct1380"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct1378"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><dateline/><salute>Dr
                        Sir</salute></opener>
                
                <p>I am very glad to find that you are so happily situated at 
                    <placeName ref="pl0692">Harrowgate</placeName><note type="editorial">For Pennant's visit to Harrowgate in May 1777
                        see <ref target="1305.xml">1305</ref> (Treadway Russell Nash to Thomas Pennant, 25 July 1777).</note> with your Family, 
                    [<del>...</del>]friends &amp;c and hope that may be an Inducement for you to stay there a 
                    little longer; 
                    I heard some Rumour that you intend coming home towards the latter end of next week, which I 
                    is not true; The reason of this extraordinary wish is that I am rather Backward in my Task; 
                    I am rather Idle &amp; indolent by nature, and what little time for activity these qualities 
                    would 
                    afford me, was thrown away upon Farming schemes, besides what employment fell to my Lot by the 
                    absence of two or three of my neighbouring Clergy men. – However I made a shift to pay a visit 
                    to <placeName ref="pl1303">Corwen</placeName> &amp; its Vicinity last week, but met with nothing 
                    material relative to <persName ref="pe0495">Owen Glyn 
                        dwr</persName>; - <persName ref="pe0737"><sic>Mr Vaghan</sic> Pughe</persName> was not 
                    at home, where he seldom is. – The Curate 
                    of <placeName ref="pl1303"/> was like wise absent, and I was Informed that his church 
                    the sunday before, 
                    was unserved in the morning, owing to a love visit he had made the preceding week to a lovely 
                    maid, viz, <persName ref="pe0738">miss Small</persName> of <placeName ref="pl1251">Holywell</placeName><unclear>.</unclear>
                    whether it was the cruelty of the Fair maid,
                    or the Influence of the pleasant Draughts administered by the <placeName ref="pl0702">Flintshire</placeName> 
                    corps, were the
                    occasion of it, must be left to time to discover. I visited 
                    <placeName ref="pl1304">Owen Glyndwr’s Prison</placeName>, part 
                    of it is intire &amp; consists of very strong heart of Oak wooden Building, &amp; carries the signs
                    of being coæval with <persName ref="pe0495">Owen</persName>; from what is remaining the whole may be
                    restored by the Pencil of <persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName>. and I think a drawing of it would
                    not be improper to follow his life. – I think besides that there is a paragraph or two that ought to
                    be alter’d, from a cursory view I made of 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0604">“vita Ricardi 2di</title></bibl> at 
                    <placeName ref="pl0695">Mostyn</placeName>.<note type="editorial">Pennant acknowledges 
                        'Vita Ricardi II. 178' as a source for his account of the capture of Lord Grey by Owain Glyndŵr 
                        in 1402, and 'Vita Ricardi, 178' as his source for ascribing the barbaric treatment of the bodies
                        of English soldiers following Glyndwr's victory at Bryn Glas in the same year to a single follower 
                        rather than to a mob of Welshwomen as stated by Holinshed. See <hi rend="italic">A tour in Wales 1770 [1773]</hi>
                        (1778), I, pp. 322, 328–9; and Johnston, 'Shaping a heroic life: Thomas Pennant on Owen Glyndwr', 
                        in Mary-Ann Constantine and Nigel Leask (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Enlightenment travel 
                            and British identities</hi>, pp. 105–121, esp. 171, n. 58.</note>
                    – Next week I intend to dedicate to your Library at <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName> 
                    &amp;c, provided I am not interrupted by Election Business, which I had no reason to expect, till I
                    found <persName ref="pe0739">S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Walden Hanmer</persName>’s 
                    <persName ref="pe0740">son</persName> in the heart of our City,  this morning, Busily canvassing for
                    Votes;  He did not get one here, and by the Dismal appearance of his visage, I guess he met with a 
                    Similar success at <placeName ref="pl1305">Rhuddlan</placeName> from whence he came here. – I wrote
                    Immediately to <sic>aquaint</sic> <persName ref="pe0015">S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Roger Mostyn</persName>
                    with his appearance, &amp; sent off a messenger upon the same occasion to 
                    M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Williams at <placeName ref="pl1021">Salop</placeName>, 
                    and I have Just now receiv,<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> a note from 
                    <persName ref="pe0015">S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Roger</persName> acquainting <add>me</add>
                    that <persName ref="pe0740">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hanmer</persName> was with him yesterday
                    upon the same fruitless Errand. – I hope these Discouraging Circumstances will make him drop his
                    pretensions, and Leave the honest Burghers live in quiet. Contested <add>Elections</add> are not to 
                    be coveted, unless their very object be, to get Rid of some Capital Rogue. – I won’t trouble you with
                    any account of the good family at <placeName ref="pl0695">Mostyn</placeName> as I know my 
                    <persName ref="pe0741">Lady</persName> wrote to 
                    <persName ref="pe0238">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Pennant</persName> by last post, &amp; 
                    I dare say some of you will <sic>here</sic> from thence by this. – I have all along entertain’d
                    hopes that <persName ref="pe0742">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Wynne</persName><note type="editorial">Roger Mostyn's 
                        mother in law was Catherine (née Vaughan),
                        wife of Hugh Wynn of Bodysgallen. It is possible that she may be the Mrs Wynne 
                        mentioned here.</note> will get the 
                    better of her Disorder, but our hopes are often vainly guided by our wishes, and that I should 
                    wish her to live is no strange matter, since I have always found her a Solid Sincere Friend, you 
                    are Philosopher <add>enough</add> to know, that the world does not produce a great many 
                    such. – Pray my Best Respects to <persName ref="pe0238">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Pennant</persName>,
                    <persName ref="pe0743">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName> &amp; 
                    <persName ref="pe0744">Miss Francis Mostyn</persName>, 
                    <persName ref="pe0065">M<del>x</del><hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName> &amp; 
                    <persName ref="pe0234">Miss Pennant</persName>, &amp; believe me to be</p> 
                <closer><salute>your most obedient Humble Servt<lb/></salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0333">John Lloyd</persName></signed>
                    <dateline><placeName ref="pl1201">caerwys</placeName> June: 13:1777</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>