<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1385">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>John Lloyd, Caerwys, to [Thomas Pennant], 27 January 1778</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                        <idno>2594E</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
        
                        <additions><p><hi rend="italic">Endorsement in Thomas Pennant's hand</hi>: <lb/>Datceiniad<lb/>
                        </p></additions>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0333">John Lloyd</persName>
                    <date when="1778-01-27"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl1201">Caerwys</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">[Thomas Pennant]</persName>
                    <placeName ref=""/>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct1386"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct1384"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><dateline/><salute/></opener>
                
                <p>The Datceiniad, or he that accompanied any <add place="margin">Datceiniad</add> musical Instrument with his voice, 
                    tho he was inferior to both Bard
                    &amp; musician, yet he must be possessd. of a Considerable degree of Knowledge of both the Sciences, he must be able 
                    to Tune the Harp &amp; Crwth,<note type="editorial">'crowd'.</note> to understand the Gamut, to shew his skill in playing several notes &amp; Keys, &amp;
                    be perfectly conversant, in that they calld<sic>,,</sic> the 24 measures of Instrumental song, &amp; be able to sing
                    with Judgment, Melody &amp; propriety. – He must likewise be master of reading welsh Justly &amp; writing it Correctly, 
                    to <add place="above">&amp; he must not only</add> understand the 24 common modes of <sic>Mertrical</sic> Compositions, 
                    but <sic>exibit</sic> sp<del>p</del>ecimens of his own at least in three of them. – If he met with any 
                    o[<del>...</del>]<del>ly</del>ld 
                    song faultily transcribed, he was required to be able to rectify it. – He was further required not only to be a handy waiter at
                    Table, but an expert Carver of every Species of Fowl. – In the Weddings of any of the Royal Family, his office was to wait at the 
                    Table of the Bride +<add place="margin">Datceiniad Pen pastwn</add><note type="authorial">+He was also to carry about him a Harp or 
                        Crwth<note type="editorial">'crowd'.</note> covered with a White Case.</note> The most inferior of the musical Tribe was the 
                    <hi rend="underline">Datceiniad Pen Pastwn</hi>, or he that sung to the Harmony of his club or staff, having no skill in any other 
                    musical Instrument; when this Gentleman was suffered to be introduced, he was obliged to stand in the middle of the Hall &amp;
                    sing his Cywydd<note type="editorial">A strict-metre poem consisting of rhyming couplets.</note> or 
                    Owdl,<note type="editorial">'ode'.</note>  beating time &amp; playing the Symphony with his Pastwn.<note type="editorial">'staff'.</note> 
                    But if there was a Professor of Music present, his leave must be first obtain,<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> before he presumed to 
                    entertain the Company with this Species of Melody. Wherever he came he must act as a menial Servant to the Bard or Musician.
                </p> 
                <p>[<del>...</del>]Notwithstanding our Eisteddfods held by Royal Authority have long since 
                    ceas’d,<note type="editorial">Lloyd refers to the eisteddfodau held at Caerwys in 1523 and 1567. See Hywel Teifi Edwards, 
                        <hi rend="italic">The Eisteddfod</hi> (Cardiff, 1990), pp. 4–10.</note>  yet our Bards have at all times &amp; do still hold such 
                    Congresses, tho’ they don’t confer degrees as formerly, save in [<del>...</del>]one case, where the Victor is chaired. The 
                    Modern Eisteddfod, 
                    generally consists of a Contest for Superiority between the Bards of two different districts, as of two Counties &amp;c They meet at 
                    a particular place previously agreed upon, <del>sometimes</del> <add place="above">generally</add> at a publick house, &amp; sometimes
                    sub dio.<note type="editorial">'in the open air, under the open sky'.</note>  A Judge is always appointed who decides upon the 
                    merit of the performers, and proclaims the Victor who is always chaired upon the occasion, &amp; <del>always</del> afterwards 
                    held in estimation
                    as a Bard. I have frequently seen[<del>...</del>] poems composed at some of these Eisteddfods, they were upon different 
                    <add place="above">given</add> Subjects, upon each of which, [<del>...</del>]every <sic>Cadidate</sic> must deliver 
                    [<del>...</del>]his composition. The <sic>Sujects</sic> are generally given by the Judge.</p>
                <p>As to the <hi rend="underline">Datceiniaid</hi> or Vocal Performers, tho’ not at present tied by the Ancient Regulations, yet they are
                    very numerous &amp; very excellent in their way, particularly in the Counties of <placeName ref="pl1235">Meirionydd</placeName>
                    <placeName ref="pl1234">Caernarvon</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName> &amp; 
                    <placeName ref="pl1216">Denbigh</placeName>. It forms a great part of their Amusements at Festivals, wakes Fairs, Weddings, Dancings
                    &amp; all opportunities of Festivity. Both Sexes equally excel in it. They often <add place="above">meet</add> entirely for that 
                    purpose, but it <sic>oftner</sic> takes place at the Conclusion or middle of a Dance, when the parties are disposed to a little Rest.
                    Here they all sit down and the Musician plays any tune at his option, especially if it becomes a matter of Contest, for then no person 
                    is allow,<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> to call for a Tune. One begins &amp; sings the Tune once Through, when he has done the next to him takes it <add place="above">up</add>
                    &amp; so on till the whole of the Singers have Sung over it once, Sometimes the Same tune is Continued for Several Rounds, 
                    especially if the Company is small. Whenever &amp; how often <sic>soever</sic> the T[<del>...</del>]une is changed the 
                    <add place="above">same</add> rotation is observ<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> &amp; every one sings in his Turn, unless, as often Happens, some of 
                    <add place="above">the</add> less skilful are flung out, when a Tune is played that they are not acquainted with. 
                    – Some veteran proficients will hold out for whole nights together, without scarce ever<del>y</del> Singing the same Stanza or Same Tune twice over. 
                    Their excellency Consists as well in the Harmony of their Voices, as in the great variety of Tunes &amp; Stanzas they can Sing. 
                    Some Hundreds of the latter, of different lengths &amp; metres are Treasured up in their memories, which they daily sing whilst
                    attending their flocks, or <add place="above">are</add> occupied in any other rural employment. In winter nights every house in those 
                    Countries affords a Concert of vocal music. – As these Pennylls or Stanzas admit of great variety in length &amp; Structure, not a one 
                    of our Tunes can be played, but a Skilful Singer can adapt numbers of his Stock of Pennylls to it, at pleasure. – These Stanzas are 
                    detached pieces upon <add place="above">all</add> the variety of Subjects, some Grave <del>some</del> some Serious, some adapted to 
                    <persName ref="pe0765">Venus</persName> some to <persName ref="pe0766">Bacchus</persName> &amp;c &amp;c many of these sung to this day
                    are suppos,<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> as old as the Times of the Druids, others have been composed in every age since, 
                    - no wonder therefore that we are so rich in old <add place="above">stock</add> besides numbers that are continually 
                    Compos<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> upon some 
                    Occasion or other, <add place="above">all</add> these Pennylls they generally learn from one another without being scarce ever Committed
                    to paper. A singer that is well Stocked is sure to sing one a propos to that sung before. – They often likewise adapt part of a Cywydd
                    or any other song to the Tune – In a Singing Contest between two Counties held some years ago in <placeName ref="pl0760">Gwedir Park</placeName>,
                    A woman appeared there who Sung variety of verses to 140 different Tunes.</p>
                <p>I beg leave further to add that you had better leave this Subject alone till you come to <placeName ref="pl1235">Meirionydd</placeName>
                    or <placeName ref="pl1234"><sic>Caernavonshire</sic></placeName> or some musical Country, especially as your present volume will be
                    large <sic>enought</sic> without it. – As to our Interludes I think they may as well be dropped for the present for the same reason, 
                    You may in some of your next excursions attend the representation of one, then your account will come in 
                    a propos<note type="editorial">Pennant used this material in 
                        <hi rend="italic">A tour in Wales 1770 [1773]</hi> (1778), I, pp. 445–6. See R. Paul Evans, 'Reverend John Lloyd of Caerwys (1733–93)', 
                        <hi rend="italic">Flintshire Historical Society Journal</hi>, 31 (1983/4), 109–124, esp. 118. For a discussion of this episode as a 
                        classic example of layering material and of John Lloyd's influence on Pennant, see Mary-Ann Constantine, 
                        ' "To trace the country's glories to their source": Dangerous History in Thomas Pennant's <hi rend="italic">Tour in Wales</hi>', 
                        in Porscha Fermanis and John Regan (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Rethinking British Romantic History, 1770–1845</hi> 
                        (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2014), pp. 121–143, esp. pp. 136–7.</note></p>
                <p>My back is very Stiff &amp; the day cold, otherwise I should have waited of you <del>today</del></p>
                <p>My best respects to <persName ref="pe0238">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi></persName> &amp; <persName ref="pe0234">Miss Pennant</persName></p>
                <closer><salute>Your very Humble Ser<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> &amp;c</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0333">John Lloyd</persName></signed>
                    <dateline><placeName ref="pl1201">Caerwys</placeName><lb/>Jan<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>. 27: 1778 –</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            <div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>