<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1404">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>William Morris to Thomas Pennant, 28 July 1757</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                        <idno>21558E</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc><additions><p>In Thomas Pennant's hand:
                        <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell><list><item>Plane</item>
                                <item>Sugar maple</item>
                                <item>Flowering maple</item>
                                <item>Chestnut oake</item>
                                <item>Canada Poplar</item>
                                <item/>
                                <item/></list></cell>
                                <cell><list><item>
                                    Carolina Ash</item>
                                <item>virg. Ash</item>
                                <item>Montpelier maple</item>
                                <item>N. England Scarlet maple</item>
                                <item>virg. D<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>.</item>
                                <item>Long Leaved alder</item>
                                <item>cherry Plumb.</item></list></cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </p></additions>
                    </physDesc><additional><p>A pencil note in an archivist's hand reads: 'Found in 
                        <bibl type="authorial">
                            <title ref="bi0732"/>
                            "Hortus Cliffortianus"
                        </bibl>
                        <persName ref="pe0162">George Clifford</persName>.'</p></additional>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0031">William Morris</persName>
                    <date when="1757-07-28">28 July 1757</date>
                    <placeName ref="pl1018">Holyhead</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct1405"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct1403"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener><dateline><placeName ref="pl1018">Holyhead</placeName>, 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. July 1757 –</dateline>
                    <salute>Good Sir,</salute></opener>
                
                <p><persName ref="pe0037">Doctor Ellis</persName> and my self arrived safe at this our <placeName ref="pl1018">Castrum</placeName>
                    abo<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. 3 Days ago, where we found all well,<note type="editorial">William Morris had been absent from 
                    home for a fortnight on a fossil-hunting expedition, travelling through four Welsh counties and visiting Thomas Pennant at Downing.
                    See his letter of 24 July 1757 to his brother Lewis, where he writes that he reached home the previous 
                    evening. <hi rend="italic">ML</hi>, II, p. 494.</note> the Day after our return a ship Arrived here from 
                    <placeName ref="pl3325">Barbado<del>e</del>s</placeName> to discharge Sugar it was lucky that she did not come in my 
                    Absence.<note type="editorial">As deputy comptroller of the customs at Holyhead, William Morris would have needed
                    to maintain a presence when ships returning from distant and lucrative voyages such as the one named here docked. See his reference to
                    weighing a load of more than two hundred tons from a sugar ship which came into the port in August 1754, and his wistful comment on the
                    difficulties of gaining any material benefit from this work because of a rivalry with the other Anglesey port of 
                    Beaumares. William to Richard, 23 August 1754, in <hi rend="italic">ML</hi>, I, p. 305.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Your conjecture abo<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. <placeName ref="pl3326">Maen Chwyfan</placeName> being a Cross set up by Christians
                    on some religious occasion is Confirm'd by Two Pillars much resembling it in <placeName ref="pl3327">Disert Church</placeName> yard.<note type="editorial">Pennant closes
                    his discussion of Maen Achwyfan in <hi rend="italic">A tour in Wales</hi> (2nd edn., 1784), p. 13, noting that it is like 'other pillars
                    of antient date in several parts of Great Britain' 'evidently a Christian monument'. For images of two Celtic crosses now housed in the interior 
                    of the Parish Church of St Bridget,
                    Dyserth, but formerly placed in the churchyard, 
                    see <ref type="http" target="https://www.megalithic.co.uk/article.php?sid=16833">here</ref> [accessed 15 July 2020].</note> One of them stands 
                    endwise in a reclining posture &amp; call'd by the Natives y Groes (ie) the Cross; is abo<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. 5 feet out
                    of the Ground wrought all over w<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. embellishments but no Figures of Animals or Letters that i could perceive.
                    The Other lying Edgewise in the Church yard wall &amp; made use of for a Stile embelishe like the Other. the Cross on the Top in each Juts 
                    out a little at the Ends, &amp; each imbossd at the Centre like your Maen.
                </p>
                <p>I observ'd that the House where <persName ref="pe0038">m<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Elli</persName>s of 
                    <placeName ref="pl0361">Disert</placeName> lives is built of a Limestone in which are stratas of Flinty matter resembling that
                    mention'd by <persName ref="pe0042">Woodward</persName><note type="editorial">William Morris refers to the work of John Woodward, 
                        <bibl type="authorial">An attempt towards a natural history of the fossils of England<title ref="bi0047"/></bibl> (1729),
                        which contains several references to Arkendale.
                    </note> to be at <placeName ref="pl3328">Arkendale</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl0770">Yorkshire</placeName>, Time w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>.
                    admit of my Going to Examine the Quarry where it was dug.</p>
                <p>I proposed going to <placeName ref="pl3329">Llan Dydno</placeName> <add place="above">in my return</add> in search of some of the many 
                    Curiosities mention'd by <persName ref="pe0044">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lhwyd</persName>, but the time failed the Jubilee at <placeName ref="pl1049">Conway</placeName> 
                    likewise prevented my having the pleasure of seeing <persName ref="pe0046">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Holand</persName> to 
                    deliver your Message &amp;c</p>
                <p>Having met with some recent Alcyoniums<note type="editorial">The application of the word 'alcyonium' to denote a genus of coral dates from work by Linnaeus
                in 1758 and thus post-dates this letter. The meaning here therefore relates to sessile marine invertebrates, in particular 
                soft corals and sponges. See <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>.</note> betwixt <placeName ref="pl3170">Penman Rhôs</placeName> and 
                    <placeName ref="pl3330">Rhôs Fynach</placeName>. I took hold of the first Opportunity of Coneying them you, in hopes you would
                    receive them before they were emaciated. they were the Alc. ramoso-digitatum molle &amp;c of Ray's <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bi0082">Syn.</title></bibl> Pa. 31.<note type="editorial">As indicated here, Ray refers to the 'Alcyonium ramoso-digitatum molle' 
                            on p. 31 of his <hi rend="italic">Synopsis methodica stirpium 
                    Britannicarum</hi> (1690; 3rd edn., London: Gulielmi &amp; Joannis Innys Regiae Societatis Typographorum, 1724).</note> – Had 
                    y<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. seen <add place="above">one of</add> them when first ta'en out of the Sea, you certainly 
                    w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. have concluded them to <add place="above">be</add> the Originals of 
                    M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lhwyd's Cartilago Mamillaris sive 
                    u<del><gap unit="letters" quantity="1" reason="authorial"/></del>ber vaccinum &amp;c of which he hath given an 
                    Icon –<note type="editorial">William Morris refers to Edward Lhuyd's 
                        <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0085">Lithophylacii Britannici ichnographia</title> (1699). The 'Cartilago mamillaris, 
                            sive uber vaccinum referens' is listed as no. 1522 on p. 78, with an icon in Table 18.
                    </bibl></note></p>
                <p>The Plant calld by your Gardiner Bladder Flatmina,<note type="editorial">The reading of 'Flatmina' is clear, but cf. 'Ketmia' below and the 
                examples of 'bladder ketmia' cited in <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> s.v. flower, n., goodnight, n., int., and adj., and modesty. The quotations including
                this form equate the 'Bladder Ketmia' with the 'Hibiscus Trionum', 'Trionum annuum', and the English name 'flower of an hour'.</note> w<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi>. I took <add place="above">at first</add> to be
                    the Corchorus. I find is the Alcea Peregrina of <persName ref="pe0150">Gerard</persName>, or Venice Mallow of 
                    w<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi>. he gave a bad Icon.<note type="editorial">See John Gerard, <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bi0104">The herball or Generall historie of plantes</title></bibl> (1633 edn.), p. 936, for a description and an icon 
                        of the Alcea Peregrina or Venice Mallow.
                    </note> And is the Alcea Peregrina Sive vesicaria of Parkinson's Parad. who gives a good Icon and a description that exactly
                    Answers in all respects.<note type="editorial">For the 'Alcea peregrina sive vesicaria' in John Parkinson's <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bi0107">Paradisi in sole paradisus terrestris, or, A Garden of All Sorts of Pleasant Flowers ... 
                            with a Kitchen Garden ... and an Orchard</title> </bibl>, see pp. 368, 370, and for an 
                    icon entitled 'Alcea Veneta. The Venice Mallow', ibid. p. 367, no. 2. Parkinson notes several Latin names, concluding that 'The most
                    usuall english name is Venice Mallow'.</note> <persName ref="pe0150">Gerard</persName> is mistaken in the time the Flower
                    shuts, which is as soon as it feels the heat of the Sun, &amp; not at noon.<note type="editorial">See Gerard, <hi rend="italic">The herball 
                        or Generall historie of plantes</hi> (London, 1633),
                        p. 937: 'it openeth it selfe about eight of the clocke, and shutteth vp againe at noone, about twelue a clock when it hath receiued 
                        the beams of the Sun, for two or three houres, whereon it should seeme to reioice to look, and for whose departure, being then vpon the 
                        point of declension, it seemes to grieue, and so shuts vp the floures that were open, and neuer opens them againe'.</note> You'll find
                    it in Miller under the name of <hi rend="underline">Ketmia</hi> (Vessicaria). 19<note type="editorial">This is a reference to Joseph Miller,
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0109">The gardener's dictionary</title></bibl> (1731). The name 'Ketmia vesicaria vulgaris'
                appears as no. 19 under the entries for 'Hibiscus', with the names 'Common Bladder Ketmia, called Venice Mallow, or Flower of an hour' also given.
                See ibid. (8th edn., London, 1768), unpaginated.</note>  should be glad of some 
                    of the Seed for this important discovery.</p>
                <p>I have sorted the Few Fossils &amp;c bro<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. with me, &amp; now begin to Long for the Arrival of the 
                    Grand Cargo.<note type="editorial">William Morris had evidently sent material gathered on his journey to Flintshire back to his home in Holyhead
                        by sea.</note> Here are no Vessels as yet bound to your Parts. — I hope 
                    <placeName ref="pl3332"><hi rend="underline">Morva Rhuddlan</hi></placeName> is daily improving, the Few men that were employd there the 
                    22<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Inst. were a Burlesque upon Roadmaking, and if an Estimate was to be made from their performance it must be a
                    Dear Jobb indeed ––– May the <placeName ref="pl1216">Counties of Denbigh</placeName>, <placeName ref="pl1234">Carnarvon</placeName> &amp; 
                    <placeName ref="pl1093">Anglesey</placeName> follow your Laudable Example that <placeName ref="pl1221">North-wales</placeName> may be no 
                    more A terror to Travelers. –<note type="editorial">The responsibility for road maintenance at this time lay in the hands of local parishes,
                        operating through the High Constable and the Quarter Sessions. See Bryn Ellis, 
                    'Flintshire Quarter Sessions Rolls 1752–1830', <hi rend="italic">Flintshire Historical
                        Society Journal</hi>, 36 (2003), 96–113. The work in question here, however, may be linked to a parliamentary act. 'An Act for amending, widening, and keeping in Repair, the Roads from the Town of <hi rend="italic">Wrexham</hi> ... 
                    to <hi rend="italic">Pentre Bridge</hi> in the County of <hi rend="italic">Flint</hi>, and from the Town of <hi rend="italic">Mold</hi> to 
                        <hi rend="italic">Northop</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Holywell</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Rhuddlan</hi>, in the same County, and from thence to <hi rend="italic">The
                    Ferryhouse</hi> opposite the Town of <hi rend="italic">Conway</hi> in the County of <hi rend="italic">Carnarvon</hi>, and from 
                        <hi rend="italic">Ruthin</hi> to the said Town of <hi rend="italic">Mold</hi>' was among a series of Bills presented to be passed before the House
                        of Lords on 28 June 1757. See <hi rend="italic">Journals of the House of Lords (1688–1834)</hi>, vol. 6, p. 188, 
                        <ref type="http" target="https://parlipapers.proquest.com/parlipapers/result/pqpdocumentview?accountid=12799&amp;groupid=100095&amp;pgId=bfb4a13a-271e-494d-90b7-5cf9b7dddc75&amp;rsId=172CD111EC8#0">here</ref> 
                    [accessed 19 July 2020].</note> <persName ref="pe0037">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Ellis</persName> Joins with me in humble
                    respects to your Worthy <persName ref="pe0341">Father</persName> &amp; Sisters<note type="editorial">Pennant's twin sisters, 
                        <persName ref="pe0341">Sarah</persName> and <persName ref="pe0237">Catherine</persName>.</note> and Compliments to your good Self we shall
                    always retain the warmest gratitude for all Civilities receiv'd at <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName> –</p>
                <closer><salute>I am
                    <lb/>D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Sir
                    <lb/>your most obliged humble Serv<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>.</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0232">W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> Morris
                    </persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>