<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1406">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>William Morris to Thomas Pennant, 5 February 1760</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                        <idno>21558E</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0031">William Morris</persName>
                    <date when="1760-02-05">5 February 1760</date>
                    <placeName ref="pl1018">Holyhead</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct1408"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct1405"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="enclosed">
                <p>Supine<note type="editorial">This word labels a diagram of a fish, showing it lying on its back.</note><lb/>
                    Prone<note type="editorial">This labels the same fish viewed lying on its belly. Note that in mentioning parts
                    of the body in the text, William Morris refers to specific points in the diagram, with letter labels, given here as 'P', 'a', 'B'. See
                    further below for Morris's own key to the diagrams.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Of this Size.<note type="editorial">The words refer to the diagram.</note></p>
                <p>Taken in a Herring Net at<lb/>
                    <placeName ref="pl1018">Holyh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>.</placeName> 7 December 1759. –<lb/>
                of a Dark yellowish Colour<lb/>
                    with Brownish irregular Spots<lb/>
                interspersd with beautiful<lb/>
                streaks of light blue &amp; yellow<lb/>
                the Body from the Anus to the<lb/>
                    Tail all Transparent. the Vent<unclear unit="letters">2</unclear><add place="above">P</add><lb/>
                perfectly white thence downward<lb/>
                of a Dull white. the formost back fin<lb/>
                whose membrane was yellow, <hi rend="underline">was</hi> most<lb/>
                beautifully streakd with light blue –<lb/>
                the Pupil of the Eye was perectly b<del>x</del>lack<lb/>
                &amp; the Iris of a whitish Green with swelld<lb/>
                or <del><gap reason="illegible" unit="letters" quantity="several"/></del><add place="above">vesicled</add> lids. blowing
                in the foramens <add place="above">a</add><lb/>
                would Swell the Gills.<add place="above">B</add> In the Ventricle<lb/>
                was found pieces of the Rays of Stella lacert;<add place="above">a</add><note type="editorial">The 'Stella lacert' 
                has not been identified. It seems unlikely that it is connected with the 'lacerta stellio', a lizard. See <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> s.v.
                starry lizard.</note><lb/>
                It had a large milt or Oil Vessel of a yellow<lb/>
                    white Colour. It had no Scales &amp; was<lb/>
                    Slippery. the fish when boild was firm<lb/>
                   <del> &amp;</del> hard and Delicious –––––<lb/>
                    It was Exactly of this Size &amp; Dimensions<lb/>
                    x the Anus. t the Penis. none of the Fins prickly
                </p>
                <p>The Length of this Fish was 19½ f<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. is drawn by a Scale of 16 to an Inch 
                    (= 1<unclear unit="letters" quantity="several"/> of the Cartilaginous kind<lb/>
                    The Skin of a Sooty (Cloudy) Colur. extream rough against the Grain resembling in some things 
                    Dr. Grew's river whale
                    in having <add place="above">small <del unit="letters" quantity="2"/> "Teeth</add><lb/>
                    innumerable <del unit="letters" quantity="several"/> ^ standing like those in a Card. Gills descending almost from the Top of his
                    <add place="above">Head</add> meet under his throat."<note type="editorial">William Morris quotes from Nehemiah Grew,
                        <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0112"><hi rend="italic">Musæum regalis societatis; or, A catalogue &amp; description of the natural and artificial rarities 
                            belonging to the Royal Society and preserved at Gresham Colledge</hi></title></bibl>, p. 103. Grew's text refers to 'an innumerable
                    company of prickly Teeth, standing like those in a <hi rend="italic">Card</hi> wherewith Women Comb Wool'. Morris adds an icon for the 
                        teeth (given here as '^').</note> No Teeth<lb/>
                    from x to x only a Socket like other whales, at <hi rend="italic">x</hi> a Small vent hole w<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi>. go downward
                    to <sic>the roof the mouth</sic><add place="above">Qu Ears.</add> The mouth by reason of the Gills<lb/>
                    being so long w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. open to a Surprizing wideness so that a child of 5 or 6 year Old might sit therein. The Bach 
                    Fin p<note type="editorial">The letter 'p' here refers to a label in the drawing of the fish.</note>
                    &amp;  part of the<lb/>
                    Tail always appear above water <del>when the Fish</del> when the Fish Bask<del>ing</del> on the Surface which they
                    do in great number on<lb/>
                    a Sun Shiny day in Sum~er, are not Seen in winter. ––– One taken at <placeName ref="pl3336">Rhoscoly</placeName>n in Sept. 1759. 27 foot long
                    <add place="above">i.e. 27</add><lb/>
                    yeelded 190 odd Gallons of Oil. The male have 2 Penis's and the Female 2 Apertures answerable thereto. –––<lb/>
                    It hath but one Gut. no Ventricle distinguishable. The <add place="above">2</add> Oil Vessels or Liver Surprizing large, no Blubber.
                </p>
                <p>x And a hollow for them in the Body of the Fish. the Edges<lb/>
                of the Tail &amp; Fins of that some<add place="above">what</add> Jagg'd. The Two hind<lb/>
                    Fins in that Opposite, The Fins nigh the Anus Small<lb/>
                    x The Oil Vessel or liver very small.
                </p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">In Thomas Pennant's hand</hi>:] Does the vent Hole at <hi rend="italic">x</hi> go thro' into<lb/>
                the mouth. [<hi rend="italic">in William Morris's hand</hi>:] it goeth downward that way. –</p>
                
                <p><persName ref="pe0163">Smith</persName> in His <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0113">Nat Hist. of Cork</title></bibl> calls this<lb/>
                "the Mola Sale. the Sun Fish but not the<lb/>
                Mola Salviani w<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi>. Willoughby names the<lb/>
                Sun Fish" –<note type="editorial">For the quotation, see Charles Smith, 
                    <hi rend="italic">The antient and present state of the county and city of Cork</hi> (Dublin, 1750), p. 299; and for the naming of the Mola Salviani as 'The Sun-fish', see
                Francis Willughby, <hi rend="italic">De historia piscium libri quatuor</hi> (Oxford, 1686), p. 151.</note> The Irish call it Herring 
                    Hog.<note type="editorial">For citations of the name 'herring-hog', described as a dialect word meaning 'the grampus', see <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> s.v. herring.</note><lb/>
                Some, Bottle Noses –––––</p>
                <p>It differs from the Shark in many respects the teeth<lb/>
                of the Shark <del unit="letters" quantity="2"/><add place="above">are</add> large &amp; three pointed &amp; in three rows<lb/>
                    these here are not ¼ Inch long, round &amp; bent. the Gills<lb/>
                of that reach not much above half way to the back<lb/>
                these almost quite up, that <hi rend="underline">broad</hi><add place="above"><unclear unit="letters" quantity="several"/></add>
                from the Small fins<lb/>
                to the Tail, this almost round, that w<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. a Sharp Snout<lb/>
                this with a blunt round one. the Penis's much larger in that. x</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <opener><dateline><placeName ref="pl1018">Holyh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></placeName>, February 
                    5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Feb<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>. 1760–</dateline>
                    <salute>Good Sir.</salute></opener>
                
                <p>I Blush to see your kind Lre lying before me unanswer'd owing to my not having time to Copy the New Fish, and now
                    <sic>its</sic> done have Comitted a blunder by putting the Description on the Same paper which I beg 
                    y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> will Excuse.<note type="editorial">For this material, see the enclosure to this letter.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In Answer to your Queries concerning the Large Fish, am to aquaint that they begin to Appear in the <placeName ref="pl1108">Irish Chanel</placeName>
                    betwixt this &amp; <placeName ref="pl1673">Dublin</placeName> in the Sum~er months, July &amp; <del>August</del> June but dont come
                    into the Bays till August &amp; Continue till about the beginning <del>or middle</del> of November when they Disap~ear. their Size from 
                    18 f<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. to 28 or 30, The large ones produce 190 odd Gallons of oil the Small ones 60 or 80 
                    gall<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>. the Eye is Small in the Largest not much bigger than an Ox's but the Exact Size is exhibited in the 
                    Figure.<note type="editorial">Note that William Morris sent
                        a drawing of a fish judged by Pennant to be a nondescript – quite possibly the same as the one enclosed with this letter of the same date 
                        to Pennant – with a letter of 5 February 1760 to his brother Lewis, asking for it to be returned
                        as soon as possible, with its name on the back. See William Morris to Lewis Morris, 5 February 1760, in <hi rend="italic">ML</hi>, II, p. 171.
                        For other occasions on which Lewis sent responses to queries by William about fish, see [Dafydd Wyn Wiliam], 'Wiliam Morris at Thomas Pennant 
                        – Tri Llythyr: III', in <hi rend="italic">Tlysau'r Hen Oesoedd</hi>, no. 20 ([October] 2006), 5 n. 2; Lewis Morris to William Morris, 18 September 1757, 
                        in <hi rend="italic">ML</hi>, II, pp. 15–16; Lewis Morris to 
                    William Morris, 24 September 1757, in ibid., p. 21; and Lewis Morris to William Morris, 5 October 1757, in ibid., p. 24, where Lewis mentions that he 
                    has completed a drawing of a large fish and written a dissertation about it to be read before the Cymmrodorion Society.</note>
                    No food in the Stomach but a kind of thick Slimy matter. they dont seem to pursue The Herrings or any other Fish. The teeth are Set in 
                    an irreg<del>l</del>ular mañer and not in Rows. As to the Fin<note type="editorial">A mark in the text here may have been intended to represent the fin
                    under discussion.</note> I am in doubt about it, whether it should not be underneath. Pray examine 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0055">Willughby</title></bibl>, if any other fish hath such on their Sides it must be right. 
                    <persName ref="pe0163">Smith</persName> in his 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0066">Nat. Hist<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. Waterford</title></bibl> says that instead of Teeth 
                    <del>it</del>this Fish is furnishd in the roof of the Mouth
                    with horney bearded Laminæ, and seem in this respect to be somewhat of the Species which afford the Wholebone tho' unlike in other 
                    respects –<note type="editorial">William Morris quotes from Charles Smith, <hi rend="italic">The antient and present state of the county and city
                    of Waterford</hi>, p. 271, where two examples of 'Sun-fish' caught on the coast of Waterford in 1743 and 1744 are discussed: 'This fish instead of teeth is furnished
                    in the roof of the mouth with several rows of horney bearded <hi rend="italic">Laminæ</hi>, and seem in this respect to be somewhat of the species which 
                    affords the whalebone, though unlike it in other particulars.'</note><lb/>
                    Vide Phil<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. Trans. N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 406 p. 243 for Jan. 40 where mention is made of one of these Fish 
                    being brot. into Ply<hi rend="superscript">mo</hi>. June 29. 1734.–<note type="editorial">William Morris refers to 'A Paper concerning the Mola SALU.
                    or Sun-fish, and a Glue made of it; communicated by the Rev. Mr. William Barlow to the President of the Royal Society', dated from 'Stoke-Dock near Plymouth,
                    Devon, June 29. 1734', in <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Transactions</hi>, vol. 41 (1739–1741), 343–5, 
                    see <ref type="http" target=" https://www.jstor.org/stable/104284">here</ref>.</note></p>
                
                <p>I am proud to find that the other is like to turn out a Non descript. How could I know whether it was good without eating of 
                    it? –<note type="editorial">This comment is elucidated by William Morris's remarks to his brother Lewis regarding a fish which he 
                        and his daughter ate, to the great consternation
                        of Pennant. See [Wiliam], 'Wiliam Morris at Thomas Pennant – Tri Llythyr: III', 5 n. 4; and William Morris to Lewis Morris, 
                        17 March 1760, in <hi rend="italic">ML</hi>, II, p. 184: 'Nid pysgodyn pigog gwenwynig oedd fy 'sgodyn i [Mine 
                    was not a stinging poisonous fish]; all his fins
                    were soft and pliable. Oni ddarfu i fy merch a minnau ei fwyta fo, er bod y Bennant agos a dymunaw na busai asgwrn yn glynu yn fy ngwddwg am 
                    Esu Nondescript [Didn't my daughter and I eat it, although Pennant was almost wishing that a bone would stick in my throat 
                    for [?eating] a nondescript]'.</note> I receivd the Two Books Safe and Sound &amp; shall return them anon in the Same Condition with 
                    thanks<note type="editorial">The borrowed books cannot be identified; but for a reference to Pennant's lending of books to William Morris, see
                        <ref target="1405.xml">1405</ref>, n. 4.</note> a Sight of <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0069">Artedi</title></bibl> will 
                    be Acceptable. am Sorry to find your Friend Linnæus is a Changeling. –<note type="editorial">William Morris, a keen botanist, may be referring to the 
                    increasing attention given by Linnaeus to the animal kingdom in the tenth edition of <hi rend="italic">Systema Naturae</hi> (1758). </note>
                </p>
                <p>I am extream glad to hear that there is a Prospect of your having a Sucking Virtuoso,<note type="editorial">This refers to the 
                    <persName ref="pe0164">firstborn</persName> of 
                Thomas Pennant and his first wife, Elizabeth (née Falconer), who had already been born when William Morris wrote this letter.</note> the Sight would be extreamly 
                    agreeable <add place="above">to</add> your humble Serv<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. but I must not flatter my self with so great a 
                happiness.<note type="editorial">William Morris's wife Jane (née Hughes) had died during 1750 and he remained single after that, although father 
                    to two children from his marriage to her. See Dafydd Wyn Wiliam, <hi rend="italic">Cofiant William Morris (1705–63)</hi> (Llangefni: 
                    Yr Awdur, 1995), pp. 96, 100–101, 102.</note> May you &amp; your <persName ref="pe0219">Lovely Spouse</persName> be blessd with it, 
                    is the hearty wish of Good Sir</p> 
                <closer><salute>Your most obliged &amp; most Obedient<lb/>humble Serv<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. &amp; Pupil
                    </salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0232">Will Morris
                    </persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                <postscript><p>PS. I am at a loss for a Frank Have none of yours, I returnd one in Lieu of it. – Yonder is 
                    <persName ref="pe0592">Ellis the Coralinist</persName> gone to rack &amp; ruin
                    I tho<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Virtuosii were made of tougher matter, than it seems some of them are.<note type="editorial">John Ellis
                    was bankrupted during 1759. <hi rend="italic">ODNB</hi>.</note><lb/>I must Hazzard this Pacq<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. 
                w<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. a Guide for want of a Frank.–</p></postscript>
                
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>