<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1416">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>William Owen [Pughe] to Thomas Pennant, 22 April 1789</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                        <repository>NLW</repository>
                        <idno>13231B</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>pp. 67–71</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <additional><p>This letter is a copy. See manuscript 
                        description, <ref type="http" target="https://archives.library.wales/index.php/amrywiaethau">here</ref> 
                        [accessed 4 September 2019].</p></additional>
                    
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe2111">William Owen [Pughe]</persName>
                    <date when="1789-04-22"/>
                    
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                   
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct1423"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct1415"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div><opener><salute>Sir,</salute></opener>
                
                <p>I went to examine <placeName ref="pl3018">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Saviour’s Dock</placeName><note type="editorial">Much of the 
                    material in the opening four paragraphs of this letter appears, some of it verbatim, in Pennant's <hi rend="italic">Of London</hi> 
                    (1790), pp. 55, 283, 252.</note> – It is the receptacle that receives several rivulets from the low grounds about <placeName ref="pl3025">Bermondsey</placeName> 
                    &amp; <placeName ref="pl3029">S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. George’s Fields</placeName>. The warehouses on it are all old erections – the inlet 
                    which forms it existed before it was made a regular dock – I could get no information as to the time when it was made, though I met with a person 
                    that belonged to it thirty years and upwards. Its length is about 400 yards, and its mean breadth about 30 feet. It is solely appropriated for barges; 
                    which land there various articles; as it is not for any particular branch of trade, though <sic>calls</sic> may be placed at the head, copperas 
                    from <placeName ref="pl3019">Writtlesea</placeName> in <placeName ref="pl1388">Essex</placeName> is landed here, Pipeclay from <placeName ref="pl3030">Poole</placeName> 
                    in <placeName ref="pl3031">Dorsetshire</placeName>, and Corn, &amp;c &amp;c.</p>
                
                <p><placeName ref="pl3020">Limehouse New Cut</placeName>,<lb/>
                    was begun about 20 years ago – runs by <placeName ref="pl3027">Bromley</placeName>, and joins the <placeName ref="pl3022">river Lea</placeName> near 
                    <placeName ref="pl3021">Bow</placeName>, where barges enter from one to the other by means of a Lock, called Bow Lock. Both these navigations convey 
                    to the <placeName ref="pl1389">Thames</placeName> the produce of the great Distilleries near <placeName ref="pl3021">Bow</placeName>, and return with 
                    commodities for the use of those works; which is the principal traffick on those waters as far as <placeName ref="pl3021">Bow</placeName>. The principal 
                    articles of general trade are coals, corn, malt and Flour. The new cut has not annihilated the navigation of the <placeName ref="pl3022">river Lea</placeName> 
                    from its mouth, but barges go by either just as conveniency occurs in respect to the place the articles are to be conveyed to; or as the tides answer. 
                    But when they are not influenced by either of those events, the barges will enter the mouth of the <placeName ref="pl3022">river Lea</placeName> to 
                    save the navigation charges that must be paid in going by the <placeName ref="pl3020">New cut</placeName>.
                </p>
                
                <p>A new <sic>Bason</sic> is intended to be made at <placeName ref="pl3023">Blackwall</placeName> for the use of the East India Co’s ships.</p>
                
                
                <p>On the site of the <placeName ref="pl3043">Old Navy-office</placeName> the East India company has raised what one may venture to call a magnificent erection – It is a regular 
                    oblong square building of about 250 feet by 160 feet, enclosing a court of 150 feet by 60, entered by an arched gateway – It is a Tea-Warehouse.</p>
              
                <p>Cold-Bath-fields<lb/>
                    Is the spot where the Prison, you mentioned, is erecting.<note type="editorial">Pennant does not appear to have used the material in this paragraph 
                        in <hi rend="italic">Of London</hi> (1790).</note> Sir, if <del>ever</del>you ever walked by <placeName ref="pl3032">Bagnidge Wells</placeName> 
                    you might have observed south of that spot, at the distance of near 200 Yards, a high hill, of factitious earth, probably formed by the rubbish 
                    brought from the ruins caused by the great fire. This hill is levelling; the work was begun about two years ago, and the foundation is partly 
                    laid; upwards of 40 feet below the summit of the hill. So far advanced it is a great work, by reason of an insecure foundation they have been 
                    obliged to sink piles, and lay frames, and prodigious brick-works. – The lease of <placeName ref="pl3033">Clerkenwell Bridewell</placeName> will 
                    expire in about seven years, and the owners of the ground will want it at that time for their own purposes; in consequence of which the <placeName ref="pl3034">county of 
                    Middlesex</placeName> erects this Prison to be ready against that period. It is to be a Penitentiary House as well as a Bridewell: the convicts lodged here 
                    will be doomed to solitude, as its plan is for a separate lodgement for each convict. The dimensions of the building will be 241 feet by 187 feet 
                    in a square area within a wall of 440 feet by 400 f<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>, The west wall will have a little irregularity, as it follows the 
                    <sic>cours</sic> of the <placeName ref="pl3035">river <hi rend="underline">Fleet</hi></placeName>.
                </p>
                <p>Extract from p. <del>1</del>53 of MS. Lond.<lb/>
                    “There is no mention of his striking the chief Justice, or of his commitment,” &amp;c<note type="editorial">For the episode involving the striking of a 
                        judge by the young prince of Wales, later Henry V, see <ref target="1415.xml">1415</ref>, n. 3.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Care shall be taken in arranging the corrections you have transmitted.</p>
                <p>The approaching Festival for the Recovery of <persName ref="pe0465">his Majesty</persName><note type="editorial">George III was severely ill during late 1788, but was convalescing by the middle 
                    of February 1789.</note> attracts the attention of the people to a degree that one not on the spot can hardly form an idea. – I wished that the 
                    <placeName ref="pl0731">principality of Wales</placeName> should not pass unobserved in the Celebrity; and with that view took the liberty of hinting to a Nobleman, native of that 
                    country, that it were <sic>desireable</sic> that a characteristic Medal should be struck for the Principality.<note type="editorial">For a commemorative 
                        medal on the occasion of George III's recovery, dated 23 April 1789, see 'Medal commemorating George III's recovery of health, visit to St Pauls 1789' 
                        at the Royal Museums Greenwich, <ref type="http" target="https://collections.rmg.co.uk/collections/objects/40434.html">here</ref> [accessed 5 September 2019].</note> 
                    The obverse of which should be descriptive of the event; and the reverse might have the genius of <placeName ref="pl0731">Cambria</placeName> in the attitude of Adoration 
                    to heaven; and a suitable inscription in <add place="above">the</add> Welsh language, The expence would not have exceeded what some individual 
                    Welshmen will expend on the occasion in the blaze of a moment, and that would have shone to future ages.</p>
               
                <p>I hope you and Family are in perfect health – And remain respectfully,</p>
                
                <closer><salute>Sir,<lb/>
                    Your most humble Servant
                </salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe2111">William Owen</persName></signed>
                    <dateline>April 22. 1789.</dateline></closer>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                
                <p><address><addrLine>To <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant Esq<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.</persName>
                    </addrLine></address></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>