<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1425">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>John Jones to Thomas Pennant, 7 November 1776</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR 2017 /TP169</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>item 2</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0322">John Jones</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl1347">Oxford</placeName>
                    <date when="1776-11-07">7 November 1776</date>
                    
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    
                    
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct1426"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct1423"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div><opener><salute>Sir</salute>
                <dateline><placeName ref="pl1347">Oxford</placeName> Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: 7 1776</dateline></opener>
                <p>On my Return here last Tuesday I received your Favor, for which I have taken the first Opportunity to return you my sincere thanks 
                    as well as for the Trouble which you have so obligingly taken respecting the M.S. I delivered your Compliments to 
                    <persName ref="pe2126">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Price</persName> and also communicated to him the Particulars of 
                    <persName ref="pe0216">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Morris</persName>'s Letter. <persName ref="pe2126">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Price</persName> 
                    is extremely sorry to find that the M.S. is not yet returned, and the more concerned for the Delay as he was the Cause of <sic>it's</sic> being first 
                    parted with. He purposes to write immediately to <persName ref="pe0326">S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Watkin Williams</persName> on the Subject to reques<gap reason="page torn" unit="letters" quantity="1                         "/> it may be return'd immediately.<note type="editorial">The identity of the manuscript in question is uncertain. The reference to Richard Morris may suggest that it was 
                            the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0707">Robert ap Huw manuscript</title></bibl>, since Morris had possession of this compilation of Welsh music in tablature 
                            form at this time and is known to have lent it to others in an attempt to find a satisfactory interpretation of its contents. Watkin Williams Wynn's harpist,
                            John Parry, had already seen the manuscript in 1771, as had John Jones the previous year. Note, however, that Jones gives the impression of having 
                        newly acquired the manuscript (or acquired it anew) in letter <ref target="1427.xml">1427</ref>, dated 23 April 1777. See further Stephen P. Rees
                        and Sally Harper, 'Aspects of the Palaeography and History of the Robert ap Huw Manuscript', in <hi rend="italic">eadem</hi> (ed.), 
                            <hi rend="italic">Welsh Music History 3: Robert ap Huw Studies</hi> (Cardiff: University of Wales Press, 1999), pp. 54–65.</note></p>
                
                <p>I have lately perused that <add place="above">part</add> of the Appendix to <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0706">Dr Davies's Grammar</title></bibl> 
                    which treats of Welch Music. I find therein the Names of 104 Pieces of Music, and of the Keys they are to be played in. I do not 
                    find any Account of the three first Pieces in <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0707">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Morris's Book</title></bibl>, 
                    but there are several by <persName ref="pe2127">David Athro</persName> the Author of the first Piece.<note type="editorial">Dafydd Athro 
                        is named as the author of the 'Gosteg' which opens the Robert ap Huw manuscript (B.M. Add. 14905).</note> It appears by this <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0707">Book</title></bibl> 
                    that the Britains divided their Musicians into eight Classes. – The four first are called graduate Classes all the Members of them being 
                    Graduates. In the first Class were the Bards who<del><gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="2"/></del> were further subdivided into three Classes. 
                    – In the 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Class<del>es</del> were those who were professed Players upon the Harp. In the third Class those that were 
                    profes<gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="1"/>sed Players on the <sic>Crooth</sic>.<note type="editorial">'crowd'.</note> The Vocal 
                    performers made up the fourth Class. These were required to understand Welch perfectly, and to write it correctly; the four and twenty Measures of 
                    vocal Song, the Different metres used in Poetry. They were also required to be Masters of tuning the Harp or Crwth<note type="editorial">'crowd'.</note> 
                    and to be able to play all the Accompanyments of "vocal song". On the Marriage of any of the royal Family they were to wait on the Bride at Dinner. 
                    The four other Classes were called the inferior Classes.<note type="editorial">The information on the required accomplishments of the class described by
                        Jones as 'the Vocal performers' is echoed by Pennant in his discussion of the 'datceiniad'. See <hi rend="italic">A tour in Wales 1770 [1773]</hi> (2nd edn., 1784), pp. 475–6.</note><lb/>
                    Of the first Class were those who played upon the different Sorts of Pipes as Bagpipe &amp;c. I am not clear what the second Class consisted 
                    <add place="above">of</add>, but I am inclined to think they were the vocal Performers of these Classes who sung to the Pipe, &amp;c.<lb/>
                    the third Class consisted of those <add place="above">who</add> played upon the Tabor.<lb/>
                    The fourth class contained the Fiddlers i:e: those that played upon the three stringed <sic>Crooth</sic>. –<note type="editorial">'crowd'.</note></p>
                
                <p>I have taken the Liberty to send you the above Account of the British Musicians, presuming that upon this Occasion it would not prove unacceptable 
                    and am with <persName ref="pe2126">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Price</persName>'s Compliments with the profoundest Respect</p>
                <closer><salute>Sir<lb/>
                    your much obliged humble Servant
                </salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0322">Jno Jones</persName></signed></closer>
                
            </div>
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>