<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1429">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>John Jones to Thomas Pennant, 25 September 1777</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>WCRO</repository>
                        <idno>CR 2017 /TP169</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus>item 6</locus></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc><additions><p><hi rend="italic">Endorsement (in Thomas Pennant's hand)</hi>: 
                        <persName ref="pe0322">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Jones</persName>.</p>
                        </additions></physDesc>
                    
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0322">John Jones</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl1553">Bodleian Library</placeName>
                    <date when="1777-09-25">25 September 1777</date>
                    
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    
                    
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct1431"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct1477"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div><opener><salute>Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                
                <p>I am ashamed to have deferred answering your Letter so long, and sending my acknowledgments of your obliging Favour of a drawing of 
                    the <rs type="art" ref="ar0459">Silver Harp</rs>. I wrote to <persName ref="pe0216">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Morris</persName> immediately upon the receipt 
                    of yours to enquire of him whether he had any Poems rehearsed at <placeName ref="pl1201">Caerwys</placeName>, worth communicating to 
                    you, but I have received no Answer; from whence I conclude that he is not in <placeName ref="pl0699">Town</placeName>. The only 
                    Poem that I know of produced there, is in <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0610">J. D. Rhys's Grammar</title></bibl> pag: 242 which 
                    is the more remarkable as containing in it the 24 Measures. I intended sending you a Translation of the "Constituta sui Edicta antiquitus 
                    in usum Bardorum Musicorum Præscripta"<note type="editorial">'Rules established from ancient times for the purpose prescribed for the use of bardic musicians'.</note> in the Grammar above mentioned, (pag 295) but for want of more knowledge of the old British Musick, 
                    and of corresponding Terms in English, I am under the Necessity of dropping my Design. The 
                    <del><gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/></del><add place="above">Sorts</add> of Musicians as related 
                    by <persName ref="pe2144">J. D. Rhys</persName> are eight, of which four are called graduates viz. Bards. Harpers. Crowders, &amp; vocal Performers. 
                    The other four O<add place="above">r</add>ders contain the inferior Performers, such as played upon all sorts of Wind Instruments, Taborers, Fidlers, 
                    or those who played upon the three stringed Crwth,<note type="editorial">'crowd'.</note> and vocal Performers, who were to play all manner of 
                    Tricks, much in the style of our modern merry Andrews. <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0610">J. D. Rhys. Gram:</title></bibl> p 303 
                    <persName ref="pe2137">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Warton</persName> in a Letter to <persName ref="pe2126">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Price</persName> 
                    acknowledges the receipt of your Favour, and says that he will give you ample Satisfaction respecting the 
                    <placeName ref="pl0002">Chester</placeName> Plays &amp;. <persName ref="pe2126">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Price</persName> desires his best 
                    Compliments to you, and has sent you the inclosed Description of <placeName ref="pl1788">Raglan Castle</placeName>, which he requests may be put with 
                    the rest of his Papers in your Hands when you have done with it –<note type="editorial">This enclosure has not survived with the manuscript, and there 
                    is no mention of Raglan Castle in Pennant's work.</note>
                </p>
               
                
                <p>In persuing <persName ref="pe0216">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Morris</persName>'s 
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0707">MS of ancient British Music</title></bibl>, I found a piece with 
                    this account of it. "The End of the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0712">Prelude of the Salt</title></bibl> <hi rend="underline">which was wont to be</hi> played before <persName ref="pe1645">Arthur</persName>'s Knights when the 
                    <sic>Saltseller</sic> was placed upon the Table."<note type="editorial">Pennant reproduces this information in his discussion of the 
                    eisteddfod, which he introduces with the words 'I find that a tune ...', footnoting his reference to 'Mr. Morris's MSS. of British music'.
                    <hi rend="italic">A tour in Wales 1770 [1773]</hi> (2nd edn., 1784), I, p. 459.</note>
                </p>
                <p>I am much obliged to you for your kind promise of a <rs type="art"><ref target="ar0459">Drawing of the Silver Harp</ref></rs>. 
                    I gave M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Edwards<note type="editorial">Mr Edwards has not been identified.</note> a rude drawing of it, which I 
                begged of him to compare with the original, in order to know whether there is a remarkable Protuberance near the upper Extremity 
                of the Belly of the Harp as represented in <persName ref="pe0216">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Morris</persName>'s Drawing of 
                    it. As <persName ref="pe0015">Sir Roger Mostyn</persName> is in Possession of this Medal by an hereditary Right he may possibly be able to give an 
                account of the Bards Medals which the chief Bards wore upon their Shoulders. These were both of gold and Silver. on them were 
                presented a Chair, or they were in the Shape of 
                a Chair but which I cannot as yet make out. <del><gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="1"/></del> I am afraid that none of them 
                are extant, and that little or no Account can by given of them at this Period.<note type="editorial">Pennant writes of the 'Penbardd or Pencerdd' (the 
                chief bard) that he 'received the badge of the silver-harp; or that of a golden or silver chair, which he wore upon his shoulder'. See 
                <hi rend="italic">A tour in Wales 1770 [1773]</hi> (2nd edn., 1784), I, p. 471.</note> I am with great Respect</p>
                <closer><salute>Sir<lb/>
                    your most obedient humble Servant
                </salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0322">Jno Jones</persName>.</signed>
                    <dateline><placeName ref="pl1553">Bodleian Library</placeName><lb/> 25 Sept 1777</dateline></closer>
                
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><address><addrLine><persName ref="pe0232">T. Pennant Esq<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName></addrLine></address></p></div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>