<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1432">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>John Jones to Thomas Pennant, 20 April 1782</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                        <idno>15422C</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab><locus/></ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc/>
                    
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0322">John Jones</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl1553">Bodleian Library</placeName>
                    <date when="1782-04-20">20 April 1782</date>
                    
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    
                    
                </correspAction>
                <correspContext>
                    <ref type="next" target="ct1433"/>
                    <ref type="prev" target="ct1478"/>
                </correspContext>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div><opener><salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                <dateline><placeName ref="pl1553">Bodleyan Libr.</placeName> Apr. 20. 1782</dateline></opener>
                
                <p>I receiv'd your Note last night and agreeably to your Request I have sent you a
                    few Extracts from Du fresne's 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>
                    <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0717">Dissertation sur l'histoire de S.
                            Louis</title></bibl>. The Title of the Dissertation is. <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0717"><sic>De</sic> Cottes D'Armes &amp; par
                            occasion de l origine des Couleurs &amp; des Metaux dans les
                            Armoiries</title></bibl>. pag 127. The Title of the Book is <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0716">Histoire de S. Louys IX du nom, roy de
                            France</title></bibl>. f<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 1668. Du fresne
                    seems to be of Opinion that <sic>Ermrae</sic> &amp; other <del><gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="several"/></del>
                    <add place="above">rich</add> Furs. were first us'd by the French to adorn a
                    Garment or mantle that was peculiar to the Gauls of which Martial makes mention
                    lib. 1. Epigr. 97 &amp; which they calld sagum.<note type="editorial"><hi rend="italic">Histoire de S. Louys IX. du nom roy de France</hi> (Paris,
                        1668), p. 127.</note> In process of Time this Garment increasd in Dimensions
                    till it reachd down to the heels. He quotes a passage from Albert chanoine
                    d'Aix-la chapelle Lib. 2 cha 16. where he describes the habit of <hi rend="underline">Godfrey of Bouillon &amp;</hi>
                    <add place="above">of</add> other french Barons who came to present themselves
                    before the Emperor Alexis Comnene,*<note type="authorial">*before the Crusade in
                        1097</note> that they apppeard. "In splendore &amp; ornatu pretiosarum
                    Vestium tam ex Ostro quam aurifragio &amp; in niveo Opere harmellino, &amp; ex
                    Mardrino Grisioque &amp; vario, quibus principes Gallorum præcipuè utuntur.<note type="editorial">'in the splendour and ornateness of precious vestments as
                        much out of purple as of gold and in snowy ermine work and from marten pelts
                        ... grey [pelts] and various [others] which the leaders of the Gauls
                        principally used'. See ibid., p. 128. Pennant uses a section from this
                        quotation in <hi rend="italic">Arctic zoology</hi> (1784), I, p. 81, where
                        he writes of the impression made upon the emperor Alexis Comnene by 'the
                        richness of [the] dresses' of Godfrey of Boulogne and his followers when
                        they appeared before him on their way to the Holy Land.</note> And also
                    where mentioning a Defeat of the French, he says that the Infidels acquired a
                    great Booty &amp; that they carried off "molles vestes, pelliceos varios,
                    Grisios, harmellinos, Mardrinos, ostra in numerabilia auro texta, miri decoris
                    operis &amp; coloris.<note type="editorial">'soft garments, various items made
                        from pelts, grey, ermine, marten, innumerable purple items, woven with gold,
                        of wonderful decorative and coloured work'. See <hi rend="italic">Histoire
                            de S. Louys IX. du nom roy de France</hi>, p. 128.</note> Eguinard in
                    his <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0072">History of
                        Charlemagne</title></bibl> says <sic>that that</sic> Monarch "vestitu patrio
                    hoc est Francio utebatur, &amp; during Winter, ex pellibus lutrinis thorace
                    confecto houmeros &amp; pectus tegebat.<note type="editorial">'this as the
                        traditional vestment Francis would use, [and during Winter,] he would cover
                        his shoulders and chest with a doublet made from otter skins. Ibid., p.
                        129.</note> Du fresne concludes from this that the French se servoient de
                    Fourrures dans leur vetem<del>a</del>ens commes les autres Peuples
                        septentrionaux.<note type="editorial">'Used furs as garments like other
                        northern races.' Ibid.</note> About 1190 he says the wearing of Ermine &amp;
                    other rich furrs as well as of Scarlet &amp; such luxurious Articles of Dress
                    were prohibited &amp; quotes Gul. Neubr. lib 3. C 22. Quod nullux vario, vel
                    grisio, vel Sabellinis, vel escarletis utatur.<note type="editorial">'that
                        no-one should use a variety [of pelts], neither grey, nor sable nor
                        scarlet'. Ibid., p. 128.</note> He quotes also a Passage from Geoffroy
                    Prieur de Vigeois's <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0073">Chronicle</title></bibl> to shew that the Barons of old were contented with
                    furs of <del><gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="1"/></del>far less
                    value &amp; Esteem than Ermine. "Barones prisco tempore munifi<add place="above">ci</add> largitores vilibus utebantur Pannis, adea ut Eustorgius Episcopus,
                    vicecomes Lemovicensis, &amp; vicecomes Combornensis arieti<del><gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="1"/></del>nis ac vulpinis
                    Pellibus aliquoties uterentur, &amp; adds quas post illos, mediocres deferre
                        erubescunt.<note type="editorial">'Barons of former times, benevolent
                        patrons, would use common round shields, just as Eustorgius Viscount Bishop
                        of Lemovicensis, and Viscount of Comborn would at different times have used
                        the pelt of rams and foxes [and adds] to which after them not insignificant
                        persons are ashamed to refer.' Ibid., p. 130.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Du Fresne does not pretend to give an Account of toutes les riches Fourrures dont <sic>le grand</sic> Seign<del><gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="1"/></del>neurs 
                    se revetoient,<note type="editorial">'all the rich furs with which the noblemen dressed themselves'. Ibid.</note> but confines himself to Ermine &amp; 
                vaire. He enters pretty minutely into both these Subjects. The Ermine he says was known to the Greeks &amp; Romans. &amp; quotes Plin. lib. 8 c. 37. 
                Ælian lib. 6 c. 40. 41 de anim. lib 1 Cap. II. var hist.<note type="editorial">Jones's references are as given in the margin 
                    of <hi rend="italic">Histoire de S. Louys IX. du nom roy de 
                        France</hi>, p. 130.</note> The name 
                he says is deriv'd from Armenia, the People of that Country according to Julius Pollux (lib. 7 c. 13) having a Garment tout particulier calld by the Greeks
                μυωτος. Ἀρμενίων δε ὁ μυωτος, κ’ εκ μυῶν των πάρ’ ἀυτοις συνυφασμένος
                    <note type="editorial">'made of mouse skin. The Armenian skins were woven by them out of these mice.'</note> The original name he says was 
                    mures Pontici but that the French anciently calld them Peaux des Hermins, or d.'Hermins whence the name, &amp; 
                adds that the spaniards call them Arminos.<note type="editorial">See ibid., pp. 131–2.</note></p>
                
                <p>I cannot find any Traces of the precise Time when this &amp; other fur<del><gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="1"/></del>s commenc'd
                    Articles of luxurious Dress, as this in particular seems to have been known to
                    the Ancients as such very early. Necessity no Doubt soon taught the northern
                    Nations the use of them, &amp; their more southern neighbours, struck with the
                    Elegance of the Ermine might soon adopt it <gap reason="page torn" unit="letters" quantity="1"/>s an article of their Dress.<note type="editorial">Pennant's discussion of the use of furs by the Greeks and
                        Romans and its introduction 'by the northern conquerors' into Europe appears
                        to draw on these observations. He observes 'I cannot find that the Greeks or
                        old Romans ever made use of furs', but that sable skins were transmitted to
                        Rome in the sixth century as a prelude to the use of furs as luxury items by
                        medieval princes. See <hi rend="italic">Arctic zoology</hi> (1784), I, p.
                        81.</note> Just. lib. 2. says that the <gap reason="damage" unit="letters" quantity="several"/>d them. Lanæ iis usus &amp; vestium ignotus &amp;
                        quamqua<gap reason="damage" unit="letters" quantity="1"/>
                    <supplied>frigor</supplied>ibus continuis urantur, pellibus tamen ferinis &amp;
                        mur<supplied>inis</supplied> vestiuntur.<note type="editorial">The text is
                        obscure here due to the seal. The second section of the quotation may be
                        translated as 'yet they are dressed in wild animal [and mouse?] skins'. <hi rend="italic">Histoire de S. Louys IX. du nom roy de France</hi>, p.
                        132.</note> Amm. Marcellinus l. 31. spealing of the Huns says Indumentis
                    operiuntur linteis, vel ex pellibus siluestrium murium consrcinatis.<note type="editorial">'they devoted themselves to making garments from linen, or
                        from the pelts of various forest mice'. Ibid., p. 132.</note> The
                    Babylonians from their vicinity to Armenia might be the first who adopted the
                    Ermine, &amp; Ælian in l. 17. C. 17 de Anim says that the Babylonian Furrs were
                        <sic>Peau</sic> de rats as Dufresne expresses it.<note type="editorial">'rats' skins'. Ibid. The reference given is from the margin to this
                        page.</note> The Modern Greeks according to him <del><gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="1"/></del>call it Ermine, Ποντίκ[ιν] sans
                    ajouter l'espece de l Animal &amp; non seulement les Hermines, mais encore
                    toutes sortes des rats indifferement.<note type="editorial">'from the area of
                        Pontus (around the Black Sea)'; 'without adding which type of animal, and
                        not only ermines but also all sorts of rats indifferently'. Ibid.</note>
                </p>
                <p>This is the substance of what I find in the <bibl type="authorial"><title ref="bi0717">Dissertation</title></bibl> concerning the subject of your Enquiry, &amp; I hope it will yield to you 
                    some Satisfaction. I have bu<del><gap reason="authorial" unit="letters" quantity="1"/></del>t just Room to inclose 
                    <persName ref="pe0065">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Pennant</persName>'s duty to you and am</p>
                <closer><salute>Dear Sir<lb/>
                    your obligd humble Serv<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>
                </salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="pe0322">J. Jones</persName></signed></closer>
                
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><address><addrLine><persName ref="pe0232">Th Pennant Esq<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.</persName></addrLine></address></p></div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>